Part I Fundamental Elements of Cooking

Chapter I Fonds de Cuisine

Before undertaking the description of the different kinds of dishes whose recipes I purpose giving in this work, it will be necessary to reveal the groundwork whereon these recipes are built. And, although this has already been done again and again, and is wearisome in the extreme, a text-book on cooking that did not include it would be not only incomplete, but in many cases incomprehensible.

Notwithstanding the fact that it is the usual procedure, in matters culinary, to insist upon the importance of the part played by stock, I feel compelled to refer to it at the outset of this work, and to lay even further stress upon what has already been written on the subject.

Indeed, stock is everything in cooking, at least in French cooking. Without it, nothing can be done. If one’s stock is good, what remains of the work is easy; if, on the other hand, it is bad or merely mediocre, it is quite hopeless to expect anything approaching a satisfactory result.

The workman mindful of success, therefore, will naturally direct his attention to the faultless preparation of his stock, and, in order to achieve this result, he will find it necessary not merely to make use of the freshest and finest goods, but also to exercise the most scrupulous care in their preparation, for, in cooking, care is half the battle. Unfortunately, no theories, no formulæ, and no recipes, however well written, can take the place of practical experience in the acquisition of a full knowledge concerning this part of the work—the most important, the most essential, and certainly the most difficult part.

In the matter of stock it is, above all, necessary to have a sufficient quantity of the finest materials at one’s disposal. The master or mistress of a house who stints in this respect thereby deliberately forfeits his or her right to make any remark whatsoever to the chef concerning his work, for, let the talent or merits of the latter be what they may, they are crippled by insufficient or inferior material. It is just as absurd to exact excellent cooking from a chef whom one provides with defective or scanty goods, as to hope to obtain wine from a bottled decoction of logwood.

The Principal Kinds of Fonds de Cuisine (Foundation Sauces and Stocks)

The principal kinds of fonds de cuisine are:

Ordinary and clarified consommés.
The brown stock or “estouffade”, game stocks, the bases of thickened gravies and of brown sauces.
White stock, basis of white sauces.
Fish stock.
The various essences of poultry, game, fish, &c., the complements of small sauces.
The various glazes: for meat, game, and poultry.
The basic sauces: Espagnole, Velouté, Béchamel, Tomato, and Hollandaise.
The savoury jellies or aspics of old-fashioned cooking.

To these kinds of stock, which, in short, represent the buttresses of the culinary edifice, must now be added the following preparations, which are, in a measure, the auxiliaries of the above:

The roux, the cohering element in sauces.
The “Mirepoix” and “Matignon” aromatic and flavouring elements.
The “Court-Bouillon” and the “Blancs”.
The various stuffings.
The marinades.
The various garnishes for soups, for relevés, for entrées, &c. (“Duxelle”, “Duchesse”, “Dauphine”, Pâte à choux, frying batters, various Salpicons, Profiteroles, Royales Œufs filés, Diablotins, Pastes, &c.).

Ordinary or White Consommé

Quantities for making Four Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Shin of beef | 3 | lbs.
Lean beef | 3 | lbs.
Fowls’ carcases | 1½ | lbs.
Carrots | 1 | lb.
Turnips | ½ | lb.
Leeks | ¾ | lb.
Celery | 1 | Stick
Parsnips | ¼ | lb.
Medium-sized onion with a clove stuck in it | 1

Preparation

Put the meat into a stock-pot of suitable dimensions, after having previously strung it together; add the poultry carcass, five quarts of water, and one-half oz. of grey salt. Place the stock-pot on a moderate fire in such a manner that it may not boil too quickly, and remember to stir the meat from time to time. Under the influence of the heat, the water gradually reaches the interior of the meat, where, after having dissolved the liquid portions, it duly combines with them. These liquid portions contain a large proportion of albumen, and as the temperature of the water rises this substance has a tendency to coagulate. It also increases in volume, and, by virtue of its lightness, escapes from the water and accumulates on the surface in the form of scum. Carefully remove this scum as it forms, and occasionally add a little cold water before the boil is reached in order that, the latter being retarded, a complete expulsion of the scum may be effected. The clearness of the consommé largely depends upon the manner in which this skimming has been carried out. Then the vegetable garnishing is added. The scum from these is removed as in the previous case, and the edge of the stock-pot should be carefully wiped to the level of the fluid, so as to free it from the deposit which has been formed there. The stock-pot is then moved to a corner of the fire where it may continue cooking slowly for four or five hours. At the end of this time it should be taken right away from the fire, and, after half a pint of cold water has been added to its contents, it should be left to rest a few minutes with a view to allowing the grease to accumulate on the surface of the liquid, whence it must be carefully removed before the consommé is strained. This last operation is effected by means of a very fine strainer, placed on the top of a white tureen (clean and wide), which should then be placed in a draught to hasten the cooling of the consommé. The tureen should not on any account be covered, and this more particularly in summer, when rapid cooling is a precautionary measure against fermentation.

Remarks upon the Different Causes which Combine to Influence the Quality of a Consommé

It will be seen that I have not made any mention in the above formula of the meat and the vegetables which have helped to make the consommé, my reason being that it is preferable to remove them from the stock-pot only after the broth has been strained, so as not to run the risk of disturbing the latter.

The quality of the meat goes a long way towards settling the quality of the consommé. In order that the latter be perfect, it is essential that the meat used should be that of comparatively old animals whose flesh is well set and rich in flavour. This is a sine quâ non, and the lack of meat coming from old animals in England accounts for the difficulty attaching to the making of a good consommé and savoury sauces in this country. Cattle in England are killed at an age varying from three to four years at the most; the meat thus obtained has no equal for the purpose of roasts and grills, and anything approaching it is rarely met with on the Continent. But when this same meat is used for boiling or braising, it does not contain enough juice or flavour to yield a satisfactory result.

This shortcoming is furthermore aggravated by a fault that many commit who are employed in the making of consommés and stock. The fault in question consists in cooking the bones simultaneously with the meat. Now to extract that gelatinous element from bone which produces the mellowness characteristic of all good consommés, it is necessary that the gelatigenous bodies should be cooked for twelve hours at least, and even after that time has elapsed they are still not entirely spent. On the Continent the quality of the meat easily compensates for this technical error, but such is certainly not the case in England, where five hours’ stewing only results in a flat and insipid consommé.

I therefore believe that, in the case of either consommé or stock, the formulæ of which I shall give later, it would be advisable for the bones to stew at least twelve hours, and this only after they have been well broken up, while the quantity of water used should be so calculated as to suffice exactly for the immersion of the meat that must follow. The contents of this first stock-pot should include half of the vegetables mentioned, and the consommé thus obtained, after having been strained and cooled, will take the place of the water in the recipe, in accordance with the directions I have given above.

The Uses of White Consommé

White consommé is used in the preparation of clarified consommés, in which case it undergoes a process of clarifying, the directions for which will be given later. It also serves as the liquor for thick soups, poached fowls, &c. It must be limpid, as colourless as possible, and very slightly salted, for, whatever the use may be for which it is intended, it has to undergo a process of concentration.

The Preparation of Clarified Consommé for Clear Soups

Quantities for making four quarts

Five quarts of ordinary consommé, one and one-half lbs. of very lean beef, the white of an egg, one fowl’s carcass (roasted if possible). First, mince the beef and pound it in a mortar with the fowl’s carcass and the white of egg, adding a little cold white consommé. Put the whole into a tall, narrow, and thick-bottomed stewpan then gradually add the cold, white broth, from which all grease has been removed, that the whole may be well mixed. Then the stewpan may be put on the fire, and its contents thoroughly stirred, for fear of their burning at the bottom. When boiling-point is reached, move the stewpan to a corner of the fire, so that the soup may only simmer, for anything approaching the boil would disturb the contents. A good hour should be enough to properly finish the consommé, and any longer time on the fire would be rather prejudicial than the reverse, as it would probably impair the flavour of the preparation. Now carefully remove what little grease may have collected on the surface of the consommé, and strain the latter through muslin into another clean stewpan. It is now ready for the addition of the garnishes that are to form part of it, which I shall enumerate in due course.

Remarks upon Clarifications

For clarified consommés, even more than for the ordinary kind, it is eminently advisable that the meat should be that of old animals. Indeed, it is safe to say that one lb. of meat coming from an animal of eight years will yield much better consommé than two lbs. would, coming from a fattened animal of about three or four years. The consommé will be stronger, mellower, and certainly more tasty, as the flesh of young animals has absolutely no richness of flavour.

It will be seen that I do not refer to any vegetable for the clarification. If the white consommé has been well carried out, it should be able to dispense with all supplementary flavouring, and, the customary error of cooks being rather to overdo the quantity of vegetables—even to the extent of disguising the natural aroma of the consommé—I preferred to entirely abandon the idea of vegetable garnishes in clarifications, and thus avoid a common stumbling-block.

Chicken Consommé

White chicken consommé is prepared in exactly the same way as ordinary white consommé. There need only be added to the meat, the quantity of which may be lessened, an old hen or a cock, slightly coloured on the spit or in the oven.

For the clarification, the quantity of roast fowl-carcasses used may be increased, provided the latter be not too fat. The process, however, is the same as in the clarification of ordinary consommés.

The colour of chicken consommé should be lighter than that of the ordinary kind—namely, a light, amber yellow, limpid and warm.

Fish Consommé

These consommés are rarely used, for Lenten soups with a fish basis are generally thick soups, for the preparation of which the fish fumet whereof I shall give the formula later (Formula №11) should avail. Whenever there is no definite reason for the use of an absolutely Lenten consommé, it would be advisable to resort to one of the ordinary kind, and to finish off the same by means of a good fish essence extracted from the bones of a sole or whiting. An excellent consommé is thus obtained, more palatable and less flat than the plain fish consommé.

If, however, one were obliged to make a plain fish consommé, the following procedure should be adopted:

Clarification of Fish Consommé

Quantities for making Four Quarts

Four and one-half quarts of ordinary fish fumet having a decided taste; one-half lb. of good fresh caviare, or pressed caviare.

Mode of Procedure

Pound the caviare and mix the resulting pulp with the cold fish fumet. Put the whole into a saucepan, place it on the open fire, and stir with a spatula until the contents reach the boil. Then move the saucepan to a corner of the fire, and let the consommé simmer gently for twenty minutes, after which strain it through muslin with great caution, and keep it well covered and in the warmth, so as to prevent the formation of a gelatinous film on the surface.

Fish consommés are greatly improved by the addition of such aromatics as saffron or curry, both of which considerably add to their quality.

Game Consommé

The necks, breasts, and shoulders of venison and of hare, old wild rabbits, old pheasants, and old partridges may be used in the production of game consommés. An ordinary consommé may likewise be made, in which half the beef can be replaced by veal, and to which may be added, while clarifying, a succulent game essence. This last method is even preferable when dealing with feathered game, but in either case it is essential that the meat used should be half-roasted beforehand, in order to strengthen the fumet.

The formula that I give below must therefore only be looked upon as a model, necessarily alterable according to the resources at one’s disposal, the circumstances, and the end in view.

Quantities for making Four Quarts of Plain Game Consommé

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Neck, shoulder, or breast of venison | 3 | lbs.
Hare-trimmings | 1½ | lbs.
Old pheasant or partridges | 1 or 2
Sliced carrots, browned in butter | 4 | oz.
Mushrooms, likewise browned in butter | ½ | lb.
Leeks | 1 | Medium sized
Celery | 2 | sticks
Bunch of herbs with extra thyme and bay leaves | ¼ | lb.
Onion, oven-browned, with 2 cloves stuck into it | 1

Liquor

Five and one-half quarts of water.

Seasoning

One oz. of salt and a few peppercorns, these to be added ten minutes previous to straining the consommé.

Time allowed for cooking

Three hours.

Mode of Procedure

Proceed in exactly the same way as for ordinary consommés, taking care only to half-roast the meat, as I pointed out above, before putting it in the stewpan.

The Clarification of Game Consommés

The constituents of the clarification of game consommés vary according to the kind of consommé desired. If it is to have a partridge flavour, one partridge should be allowed for each quart of the consommé, whereas if its flavour is to be that of the pheasant, half an old pheasant will be required per each quart of the liquid. Lastly, in the case of plain game consommés, one lb. of lean venison, hare, or wild rabbit should be allowed for each quart of the required consommé.

Mode of Procedure

Whatever be the kind of game used, the latter must be thoroughly boned and the meat well pounded, together with the white of an egg per four quarts of consommé.

About two oz. per quart of dried mushrooms should now be added if they can be procured, while the bones and the remains or carcases of game should be browned in the oven and completely drained of all grease. The whole can now be mixed with the cold game consommé. The clarification is then put over an open fire (stirring incessantly the while), and as soon as the boil is reached the saucepan must be moved to a corner of the fire, where its contents may gently boil for three-quarters of an hour. The fat should then be removed, and the consommé strained through muslin, after which cover up until wanted.

Special Consommés for Suppers

The consommés whose formulæ I have just given are intended more particularly for dinners. They are always finished off by some kind of garnish, which, besides lending them an additional touch of flavour, gives them their special and definite character when they are served up in the diner’s plate.

But the case is otherwise with the consommés served for suppers. These, being only served in cups, either hot or cold, do not allow of any garnishing, since they are to be drunk at table. They must therefore be perfect in themselves, delicate, and quite clear.

These special consommés are made in a similar manner to the others, though it is needful to slightly increase the quantity of meat used for the clarification, and to add to that clarification the particular flavour mentioned on the menu—to wit, a few stalks of celery, if the consommé is a celery one; a small quantity of curry, if the consommé is given as “à l’Indienne”; or a few old roast partridges if it is to be termed “Consommé au fumet de perdreau”; and so on.

The means by which one may vary the aroma of consommés are legion, but it is highly important, what aroma soever be used, that the latter be not too pronounced. It ought only to lend a distinctive and, at the same time, subtle finish to the consommé, which, besides sharpening the latter, should increase its succulence.

When the consommé is served cold it ought to have the qualities of an extremely light and easily-melting jelly, barely firm; but when it is too liquid, it rarely gives that sensation of perfection and succulence to the palate of the consumer which the latter expects. When too firm and too gelatinous it is positively disagreeable; therefore, if it is to be relished, it should be just right in respect of consistency.

Brown Stock or “Estouffade”

Quantities for making Four Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Shin of beef (flesh and bone) | 4 | lbs.
Shin of veal (flesh and bone) | 4 | lbs.
Lean, raw ham | ½ | lb.
Fresh pork rind, rinsed in tepid water | ½ | lb.
Mushrooms, likewise browned in butter | ½ | lb.
Minced carrots, browned in butter | ¾ | medium sized
Minced onions, browned in butter | ¾ | sticks
Faggot, containing a little parsley, a stick of celery, a small sprig of thyme, and a bay leaf | 1

Preparation

Bone and string the meat, and keep it in readiness for the morrow. Break the bones as finely as possible, and, after having besprinkled them with a little stock-fat, brown them in an oven; also stir them repeatedly. When they are slightly browned, put them in a conveniently large sauce-pan with the carrots, the onions, and the faggot. Add five quarts of cold water, and put the saucepan on an open fire to boil. As soon as the boil is reached skim carefully; wipe the edge of the saucepan put the lid half on, and allow the stock to cook gently for twelve hours; then roughly remove the fat; pass the liquid through a sieve, and let it cool.

This being done, put the meat in a saucepan just large enough to hold it. Brown it a little in some stock-fat, and clear it entirely of the latter. Add half a pint of the prepared stock, cover the saucepan, and let the meat simmer on the side of the fire until the stock is almost entirely reduced. Meanwhile the meat should have been repeatedly turned, that it may be equally affected throughout. Now pour the remainder of the stock, prepared from bones, into the saucepan, bring the whole to the boil, and then move the saucepan to a corner of the fire for the boiling to continue very slowly and regularly with the lid off. As soon as the meat is well cooked the fat should be removed from the stock, and the latter should be strained or rubbed through a sieve, after which it should be put aside to be used when required.

Remarks Relative to the Making of Brown Stock

Instead of stringing the meat after having boned it, if time presses, it may be cut into large cubes before browning. In this case one hour and a half would suffice to cook it and to extract all its juice.

Whether brown or white, stock should never be salted, because it is never served in its original state. It is either reduced in order to make glazes or sauces—in which case the concentration answers the purpose of seasoning—or else it is used to cook meat which must be salted before being cooked, and which, therefore, imparts the necessary salt to its surrounding liquor.

Brown stock ought to be the colour of fine burnt amber, and it must be transparent. It is used in making meat-glazes after reduction, also to moisten meat for braising and to prepare brown sauces.

Brown Game Stock

There is no difference between the game consommés and game stock, or, otherwise stated, ordinary game consommé and brown game stock are one and the same thing. The distinction lies in the ultimate use of this preparation; it is clarified, as we have shown (Formula №5), if it be intended for a clear soup, and it is used in its original state if it is to be used for a thick game soup, for a sauce, or for reducing.

Brown Veal Stock

Brown veal stock requires the same quantities of shin and trimmings of veal as white veal stock (Formula №10). The time allowed for cooking is, however, a little shorter, and this operation may be completed within eight hours. This stock is mostly used as the liquor for poultry and poëled game, while it may also serve in the preparation of thickened veal stock. Being quite neutral in taste, it lends itself to all purposes, and readily takes up the aroma of the meat with which it may happen to be combined. It is admirably suited to the poaching of quails, and nothing can supplant it in this particular.

White Stock, Veal and Poultry Stock

Quantities for making Four Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Shin of veal, or lean and fresh veal trimmings | 8 | lbs.
Fowls’ carcases, raw if they are handy | 1 or 2 | lbs.
Carrots | 12 | oz.
Onions stuck with a clove | 6 | oz.
Cold water | 5½ | quarts
Leeks strung with a stock of celery | 4 | oz.
Minced onions, browned in butter | ¾ | sticks
Faggot, including 1 oz. of parsley, 1 bayleaf, and a small sprig of thyme. | 1

Preparation

Bone the shins, string the meat, break up the bones as small as possible, and put them in a stewpan with the water. Place on an open fire, allow to boil, skim carefully, and then move to a side of the fire to cook very gently for five hours. At the end of this time put the stock into another stewpan, add the meat and the vegetables, add water, if necessary, to keep the quantity of liquid at five quarts, let it boil, and allow it to cook slowly for another three hours, after which remove all grease from the stock, pass the latter through a fine strainer or a colander, and put it aside until wanted.

Remarks upon White Stock

One should contrive to make this stock as gelatinous as possible. It is therefore an indispensable measure that the bones be well broken up and cooked for at least eight hours. Veal never yields such clear stock as beef; nevertheless, the consommé obtained from veal should not be turbid. It must, on the contrary, be kept as clear and as white as possible.

Poultry Stock is made by adding two old fowls to the above veal stock, and these should be put into the liquor with the meat.

Fish Stock

White Fish Stock

Quantities for making Four Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Trimmings and bones of sole or whiting | 4 | lbs.
Sliced, blanched onions. | ½ | lbs.
Parsley, root or stalks | 2 | oz.
White wine | ½ | bottle

Preparation

Butter the bottom of a thick, tall stewpan, put in the blanched onions and the parsley-stalks, and upon these aromatics lay the fish remains. Add the juice of a lemon, cover the stewpan, put it on the fire, and allow the fish to exude its essence, jerking the pan at intervals. Moisten, in the first place, with the white wine; then, with the lid off, reduce the liquid to about half. Now add four quarts of cold water, bring to the boil, skim, and. then leave to cook for twenty minutes, only, on a moderate fire. The time allowed is ample for the purpose of extracting the aromatic and gelatinous properties contained in the bones, and a more protracted stewing would only impair the savour of the stock.

Remarks upon White Fish Stock

The formula which I give above diverges considerably from that commonly used, for, as a rule, fish stock is diluted far too much, and is stewed for much too long a time. I have observed that fish stock may be greatly improved by rapid cooking, and it was this consideration that led me to dilute it scantily, so as to avoid prolonged reduction.

It is likewise necessary to remember that in order to make perfect fish-stock, only the sole or whiting should be used. In a case of emergency, however, i.e., if the supply of the latter were to run short, a quarter of their weight of brill bones might be added to them. But all other kinds of fish should be avoided in the preparation.

Fish Stock with Red Wine

This stock is comparatively rarely used, because, in practice, it is naturally obtained in the cooking of the fish itself, as, for instance, in the case of the “Matelotes”. Be this as it may, with the recent incursion of a custom which seems to demand, ever more and more, the serving of fish without bones, the following formula will be worthy of interest, as it is likely that its need will henceforth be felt with increasing urgency.

Fish fumet with red wine may be prepared from all freshwater fish, as well as from the remains of sole, whiting, chicken-turbot, and brill. It is generally better, however, to have recourse to the bones and remains of that fish which happens to be constituting the dish—that is to say, the bones and trimmings of sole in a stock for fillet of sole, the bones and trimmings of a chicken-turbot in a fumet for a chicken-turbot, and so on. The preparatory formula remains the same, whatever the kind of fish used may be.

Quantities for making Four Quarts of Fumet with Red Wine

Four lbs. of bones, heads, and trimmings of the fish to be served; three-quarters lb. of minced white onions; three oz. of parsley stalks, two bay leaves, four small sprigs of thyme, and four cloves of garlic; two bottles of red wine and five pints of water.

Mode of Procedure

Put all the above-mentioned ingredients in a thick and tall stewpan, boil, skim carefully, and allow to cook twenty to thirty minutes on a moderate fire; then strain the stock through a colander into a tureen, to be used when required.

Remarks upon Fish Stock with Red Wine

This stock stands reduction far better than white fish stock. Nevertheless, I urge the advisability of trying to obtain the required quantity without reduction. In its preparation, one may use some mushroom parings, as in the case of white stock, if these are handy, and they will be found to lend an agreeable flavour to the fish fumet.

Various Essences

As their name implies, essences are stock which hold a large proportion of a substance’s aroma in a concentrated form. They are, in fact, ordinary stock, only less diluted, with the idea of intensifying the flavour of the treated ingredients; hence their utility is nil if the stock which they are intended to finish has been reasonably and judiciously treated. It is infinitely simpler ta make savoury and succulent stock in the first place than to produce a mediocre stock, and finally complete it by a specially prepared essence. The result in the first instance is better, and there is economy of time and material.

The most one can do is to recommend, in certain circumstances, the use of essences extracted from particularly well-flavoured products, as, for instance, mushrooms, truffles, morels, and celery. But it would be well to remember that, nine times out of ten, it is preferable to add the product itself to the stock during the preparation of the same than to prepare essences.

For this reason I do not think it necessary to dilate upon the subject of essences, the need of which should not be felt in good cooking.

Various Glazes

The various glazes of meat, fowl, game, and fish are merely stock reduced to the point of viscosity. Their uses are legion. Occasionally they serve in decking dishes with a brilliant and unctuous coating which makes them sightly; at other times they may help to strengthen the consistence of a sauce or other culinary preparation, while again they may be used as sauces proper after they have been correctly creamed or buttered.

Glazes are distinguished from essences by the fact that the latter are only prepared with the object of extracting all the flavour of the product under treatment, whereas the former are, on the contrary, constituted by the whole base of the substance itself. They therefore have not only its savour, but also its succulence and mellowness, whereby they are superior to the essences, and cooking can but be improved by substituting them for the latter. Nevertheless, many chefs of the old school do not permit the use of glazes in culinary preparations, or, rather, they are of opinion that each cooking operation should produce them on its own account, and thus be sufficient unto itself. Certainly, the theory is correct when neither time nor cost is limited. But nowadays the establishments are scarce where these theories may be applied, and, indeed, if one does not make an abuse of glazes, and if they be prepared with care, their use gives excellent results, while they lend themselves admirably to the very complex demands of modern customs.

Meat Glaze

Meat glaze is made by reducing brown stock (Formula №7) in a large stewpan upon an open fire. As often as the stock is appreciably reduced, during ebullition, it may be transferred to smaller stewpans, taking care to strain it through muslin at each change of stewpan. The glaze may be considered sufficiently reduced when it evenly veneers a withdrawn spoon. The fire used for reducing should gradually wane as the concentration progresses, and the last phase must be effected slowly and on a moderate fire.

When it is necessary to obtain a lighter and clearer glaze, the brown veal stock (Formula №9) should be reduced instead of the “Estouffade”.

Poultry Glaze

Reduce the poultry base indicated in Formula №10, and proceed in exactly the same way as for meat glaze (Formula №15).

Game Glaze

Use the game base (Formula №8), and proceed as for meat glaze (Formula №9).

Fish Glaze

This glaze is used less often than the preceding ones. As it is only used to intensify the savour of sauces, it is sufficient for this purpose to prepare a white fish stock (Formula №11), which may be diluted with the stock already prepared, and which may be reduced according to the requirements. The name of fish fumet or fish essence is given to this preparation; its flavour is more delicate than that of fish glaze, which it replaces with advantage.

Chapter III The Small Compound Sauces

Remarks

In order that the classification of the small sauces should be clear and methodical, I divide them into three parts.

The first part includes the small brown sauces; the second deals with the small white sauces and those suited to this part of the classification; while the third is concerned with the English sauces.

The Small Brown Sauces

Sauce Bigarrade

This sauce is principally used to accompany braised and poëled ducklings. In the first case, the duckling’s braising stock, being thickened, constitutes a sauce. In the second case, the stock is clear, and the procedure in both cases is as follows:

After having strained the braising stock, completely remove its grease, and reduce until it is very dense. Strain it once more through muslin, twisting the latter; then, in order to bring the sauce to its normal consistence, add the juice of six oranges and one lemon per quart of sauce. Finish with a small piece of lemon and orange rind cut regularly and finely. Julienne-fashion, and scalded for five minutes.
Strain the poëling stock, for duck or ducks, through linen; entirely remove the grease, and add four pieces of caramel sugar dissolved in one tablespoonful of vinegar per one-half pint of stock, the juice of the oranges and the lemon and the Julienne of rinds, as for the braised-ducklings sauce indicated above.

Sauce Bordelaise

Put into a vegetable-pan two oz. of very finely minced shallots, one-half pint of good red wine, a pinch of mignonette pepper, and bits of thyme and bay. Reduce the wine by three-quarters, and add one-half pint of half glaze. Keep the sauce simmering for half an hour; despumate it from time to time, and strain it through linen or a sieve. When dishing it up, finish it with two tablespoonfuls of dissolved meat glaze, a few drops of lemon-juice, and four oz. of beef-marrow, cut into slices or cubes and poached in slightly salted boiling water. This sauce may be buttered to the extent of about three oz. per pint, which makes it smoother, but less clear. It is especially suitable for grilled butcher’s meat.

Chasseur Sauce (Escoffier’s Method)

Peel and mince six medium-sized mushrooms. Heat one-half oz. of butter and as much olive oil in a vegetable-pan; put in the mushrooms, and fry the latter quickly until they are slightly browned. Now add a coffee spoonful of minced shallots, and immediately remove half the butter; pour one-half; pint of white wine and one glass of liqueur brandy into the stewpan; reduce this liquid to half, and finish the sauce with: one-half pint of half glaze, one-quarter pint of tomato sauce, and one tablespoonful of meat-glaze. Set to boil for five minutes more, and complete with a teaspoonful of chopped parsley.

Brown Chaud-froid Sauce

Put one quart of half glaze into a sauté-pan with one-fifth pint of truffle essence. Put the pan on an open fire, and reduce its contents; while making same absorb one and one-half pints of jelly—the latter being added to the sauce in small quantities.

The degree of reduction in this sauce is a good third, but, to be quite certain, a test of its consistence may be made by allowing it to cool a little. After the reduction, carefully taste, and rectify the seasoning if necessary; mix a little Madeira or Port with the sauce, away from the fire, and strain through muslin or, preferably, through a Venetian-hair sieve. Stir the sauce now and then while it cools, until it is sufficiently liquid, and at the same time consistent enough to coat immersed solids evenly with a film of sauce. Its use will be explained among the formulæ of the different kinds of Chaud-froids.

Varieties of the Chaud-froid Sauce

For Ducks

Prepare the sauce as above, adding to it (for the prescribed quantity) one-half pint of duck fumet obtained from the carcases and remains of roast duckling, and finish it, away from the fire, with the juice of four oranges and a heaped tablespoonful of orange rind, cut finely. Julienne-fashion, and scalded for five minutes.

For Feathered Game

Treat the Chaud-froid sauce as indicated in Formula №34, adding one-half pint of the fumet of the game constituting the dish in order to lend it that game’s characteristic taste. Observe the same precaution for the cooling.

For Fish

Proceed as in Formula №34, but:

substitute the Espagnole of fish for the half glaze;
intensify the first Espagnole with one-half pint of very clear fish essence;
use Lenten jelly instead of meat jelly.

Remarks upon the Use of Chaud-froid Sauces

The chaud-froid sauce may be prepared beforehand, and when it is wanted it need only be gently melted without heating it in the least. It ought simply to be made sufficiently liquid to give a good coating to substances immersed in it.

Devilled Sauce

Put in a vegetable pan two oz. of sliced shallots and one-third pint of white wine. Reduce the latter to two-thirds, add one-half pint of half glaze, reduce to two-thirds, season strongly with cayenne pepper, and strain through muslin. This sauce may be served with grilled fowls or pigeons. It also forms an excellent accompaniment to re-dished meat which needs a spicy sauce.

“Escoffier” Devilled Sauce

This sauce, which may be bought ready-made, is admirably fitted to accompany grilled fish and grills in general. In order to make it ready, all that is needed is to add its own volume of fresh butter to it, the latter being previously well softened so as to ensure its perfect mixture with the sauce.

Genevoise Sauce

Heat two oz. of butter in a stewpan; insert one lb. of Mirepoix (№228) without bacon. Slightly brown, add two lbs. of head of salmon and remains or bones of fish, and stew with lid on for twenty minutes. Let the stewpan lean slightly to one side, so that the butter may be drained; moisten with one bottle of excellent red wine; reduce the latter by half; add one pint of Lenten Espagnole, and allow to cook gently for half an hour.

Rub the sauce through a sieve, pressing it so as to extract all the essence. Let it rest awhile; carefully remove the fat which has risen to the surface, and add one liqueur-glass of burnt brandy, one-half pint of red wine, and as much fish fumet. Boil again, then move stewpan to the side of fire to despumate for one and one-half hours. Frequently remove what the ebullition causes to rise to the surface, this second period of cooking being only to ensure the purification of the sauce. If the ebullition has been well effected, the sauce should reach the proper degree of reduction and despumation at the same moment of time. It is then strained through muslin or tammy, and it is finished at the last minute with a few drops of anchovy essence and four oz. of butter per quart of sauce.

N.B.—The Genevoise Sauce, like all red-wine sauces, may be served without being buttered. It is thus clearer and more sightly in colour, but the addition of butter in small quantities makes it mellower and more palatable.

Remarks on Red-wine Sauces

In the general repertory of cooking we also have, in the way of red-wine sauces, the “Bourguignonne”, “Matelote”, and “Red-Wine” sauces, which are closely allied to the “Genevoise”, and only differ from it in details of procedure.

The “Bourguignonne” Sauce is composed of red-wine accompanied by aromatics, and reduced by half. In accordance with ordinary principles, it is thickened by means of three oz. of manied butter per quart of reduced wine. This sauce is buttered with four oz. of butter per quart, and is especially regarded as a domestic preparation for poached, moulded, and hard-boiled eggs.

“Matelote” Sauce is made from Court-bouillon, with red wine which has been used for cooking fish. This Court-bouillon, with the mushroom parings added, is reduced by two-thirds, and is thickened with one pint of Lenten Espagnole per pint of the reduced Court-bouillon.

This sauce should be reduced by a third, strained through a tammy, and finished by means of two oz. of butter and a little cayenne per pint of sauce.

The Red-Wine Sauce resembles the two preceding ones in so far as it contains mirepoix browned in butter and diluted with red wine. The wine is reduced by half, thickened by a pint of Lenten Espagnole per pint of the reduction, and the sauce is despumated for about twenty minutes. It is strained through a tammy, and finished, when ready, by a few drops of anchovy essence, a little cayenne, and two oz. of butter per pint of sauce.

Grand-Veneur Sauce

Take one pint of Poivrade Sauce (№49) and boil it, adding one pint of game stock to keep it light; reduce the sauce by a good third; remove it from the fire, and add four tablespoonfuls of red-currant jelly. When the latter is well dissolved, complete the sauce by one-quarter pint of cream per pint of sauce.

This sauce is the proper accompaniment for joints of venison.

Italian Sauce

Ordinary Italian Sauce

Put into a stewpan six tablespoonfuls of Duxelles (see Formula №223), two oz. of very lean, cooked ham, cut very finely, brunoise-fashion, and one pint of half glaze tomatée. Boil for ten minutes, and complete, at the moment of dishing up, with one teaspoonful of parsley, chervil, and tarragon, minced and mixed.

Lenten Italian Sauce

Same preparation, only:

omit the ham, and
substitute Lent Espagnole (combined with fish fumet made from the fish for which the sauce is intended) for half glaze with tomatoes.

Thickened Gravy

Boil one pint of poultry or veal stock (according to the nature of the dish the gravy is intended for). Thicken this sauce by means of three-quarters oz. of fæcula, diluted cold, with a little water or gravy, and pour this leason into the boiling gravy, being careful to stir briskly.

The thickened gravy with the veal-stock base is used for choicest pieces of butcher’s meat; that with a poultry-stock base is for fillets of poultry.

Veal Gravy Tomaté

Add to one pint of veal stock two oz. of purée and one-quarter pint of tomato juice, and reduce by a fifth. Strain the gravy through linen. This gravy is for butcher’s meat.

Lyonnaise Sauce

Finely mince two oz. of onions and brown them slightly in two oz. of butter. Moisten with one-quarter pint of white wine and as much vinegar; almost entirely reduce the liquid; add one and one-half pints of clear half-glaze, and set to cook slowly for half an hour. Rub the sauce through a tammy.

N.B.—The onion may be left in the sauce or not, according to the preparation for which it is intended and the taste of the consumer.

Madeira Sauce

Put one and one-half pints of half glaze into a sauté-pan, and reduce it on a brisk fire to a stiff consistence. When it reaches this point, take it off the fire and add one-fifth pint of Madeira to it, which brings it back to its normal consistence. Rub through a tammy, and keep it warm without allowing it to boil.

Marrow Sauce

Follow the proportions as indicated under “Sauce Bordelaise” (№32) for the necessary quantity of this sauce, the Marrow Sauce being only a variety of the Bordelaise. Finish it with six oz. per quart of beef marrow, cut into cubes, poached and well drained, and one teaspoonful of chopped parsley, scalded for a second. If the sauce is to accompany vegetables, finish it, away from the fire, with three oz. of butter, and then add the cubes of marrow and the parsley.

Pignons Sauce

Take the necessary amount of Poivrade Sauce prepared according to Formula №49, and let it boil. Now, for one pint of sauce, prepare an infusion of juniper berries, with one-quarter pint of water and two oz. of concassed berries; one oz. of grilled fir-apple kernels, and one oz. of raisins, stoned and washed, and left to soak in tepid water for about an hour. Finish the sauce, when dishing up, by adding the infusion of juniper berries strained through linen, the grilled kernels, the soaked raisins, and one-eighth pint of Madeira wine.

This sauce is specially suited to joints of venison.

Périgueux Sauce

Prepare a “Sauce Madère” as explained in Formula №44, and add to the half glaze, to be reduced, half its volume of very strong veal stock, and keep it a little denser than usual. Finish this sauce by adding one-sixth pint of truffle essence and three oz. of chopped truffles per quart of Madeira Sauce. It is used for numerous small entrées, timbales, hot pâtés, &c.

Piquante Sauce

Put into a vegetable pan two oz. of minced shallots, one-quarter pint of vinegar, and as much white wine. Reduce the liquid by a good half, and add one pint of half glaze; set the sauce to boil, and despumate it for half an hour. At the last moment finish it, away from the fire, with two oz. of gherkins, one oz. of capers, and a teaspoonful of chervil, parsley, and tarragon, mixed; all the ingredients to be finely chopped. This sauce generally accompanies grilled or boiled pork, and cold meat re-dished and minced which needs spicy flavouring.

49—Ordinary Poivrade Sauce

Heat two oz. of butter in a stewpan, and insert one lb. of raw Mirepoix (№228). Fry the vegetables until they are well browned; moisten with one-quarter pint of vinegar and one-half pint of Marinade (Formula №169); reduce to two-thirds; add one pint of Espagnole Sauce, and cook for three-quarters of an hour. Ten minutes before straining the sauce, put in a few crushed peppercorns. If the pepper were put in the sauce earlier, it might make it bitter.

Pass the sauce through a strainer, pressing the aromatics add a further one-half pint of Marinade, and despumate for one-quarter of an hour, keeping it simmering the while. Strain again through tammy, and finish the sauce, when ready for dishing, with two oz. of butter.

This sauce is suitable for joints marinaded or not.

Poivrade Sauce for Venison

Fry, with two oz. of butter and two oz. of oil, one lb. of raw Mirepoix (№228) to which are added four lbs. of well-broken bones and ground-game trimmings. When the whole is well browned, drain the grease away, and dilute with one pint of vinegar and one pint of white wine. Reduce this liquid by three-quarters, then add three quarts of game stock and a quart of Espagnole Sauce. Boil, cover the saucepan, and put into a moderate oven, where it should stay for at least three hours. At the end of this time take out the saucepan and pour its contents into a fine sieve placed over a tureen; press the remains so as to expel all the sauce they hold, and pour the sauce into a tall, thick saucepan. Add enough game stock and Marinade, mixed in equal parts, to produce three quarts in all of sauce, and gently reduce the latter while despumating it. As it diminishes in volume, it should be passed through muslin into smaller saucepans, and the reduction should be stopped when only a quart of sauce remains.

N.B.—This sauce, like red-wine sauces, may be served as it stands. It is brilliant, clear, and perhaps more sightly thus, but the addition of a certain quantity of butter (four oz. per quart) makes it perfectly mellow, and admirably completes its fragrance.

Provençal Sauce

Peel, remove the seeds, press and concass twelve medium tomatoes. Heat in a sauté-pan one-fifth pint of oil, until it begins to smoke a little; insert the tomatoes seasoned with pepper and salt; add a crushed garlic clove, a pinch of powdered sugar, one teaspoonful of chopped parsley, and allow to melt gently for half an hour. In reality, true Provençale is nothing but a fine fondue of tomatoes with garlic.

Robert Sauce

Finely mince a large onion and put it into a stewpan with butter. Fry the onion gently and without letting it acquire any colour. Dilute with one-third pint of white wine, reduce the latter by one-third, add one pint of half glaze, and leave to simmer for twenty minutes. When dishing up, finish the sauce with one tablespoonful of meat glaze, one teaspoonful of mustard, and one pinch of powdered sugar. If, when finished, the sauce has to wait, it should be kept warm in a bain-marie, as it must not boil again. This sauce—of a spicy flavour—is best suited to grilled and boiled pork. It may also be used for a mince of the same meat.

Escoffier Roberts Sauce

This sauce may be bought ready-made. It is used either hot or cold. It is especially suitable for pork, veal, poultry, and even fish, and is generally used hot with grills after the equivalent of its volume of excellent brown stock has been added to it. It may also be served cold to accompany cold meat.

Rouennaise Sauce

Prepare a “Bordelaise” sauce according to Formula №32. The diluent of this sauce must be an excellent red wine. For one pint of sauce, pass four raw ducks’ livers through a sieve; add the resulting purée to the Bordelaise, and heat the latter for a few minutes in order to poach the liver. Be careful, however, not to heat the sauce too much nor too long, lest the liver be cooked. Serve this sauce with duckling à la Rouennaise.

Salmis Sauce

The base of this sauce, which rather resembles the cullis, is unchangeable. Its diluent only changes according to the kind of birds or game to be treated, and whether this game is to be considered ordinary or Lenten.

Cut and gently brown in butter five oz. of Mirepoix (Formula №228). Add the shin detached from the limbs and the chopped carcass of the bird under treatment, and moisten with one pint of white wine. Reduce the latter to two-thirds, add one-half pint of half glaze, and boil gently for three-quarters of an hour. Pass through a strainer, while pressing upon the carcass and the aromatics, with the view of extracting their quintessence, and thin the cullis thus obtained by means of one-half pint of game stock or mushroom liquor, if the game be Lenten. Now despumate for about one hour, finally reduce the sauce, bring it to its proper consistency with a little mushroom liquor and truffle essence, rub it through tammy, and butter it slightly at the last moment.

Tortue Sauce

Boil one-half pint of veal stock, adding a small sprig of sage, sweet marjoram, rosemary, basil, thyme, and as much bay, two oz. of mushroom parings, and one oz. of parsley. Cover and allow to infuse for half an hour. Two minutes before straining the infusion, add four concassed peppercorns.

After straining through fine linen, add one-half pint of half glaze and as much tomato sauce (away from the fire) with four tablespoonfuls of sherry, a little truffle essence, and a good pinch of cayenne.

N.B.—As this sauce must be spicy, the use of cayenne suggests itself, but great caution should be observed, as there must be no excess of this condiment.

Venison Sauce

Prepare a Poivrade sauce for game, as explained in Formula №50. Finish this sauce with two tablespoonfuls of red-currant jelly, previously dissolved, and mixed with five tablespoonfuls of fresh cream per pint of sauce. This addition of cream and red currants must be made away from the fire.

Serve this sauce with big ground-game.

Small White and Compound Sauces

American Sauce

This sauce consists of lobster prepared “à l’Américaine” (see Formula №939). As it generally accompanies a fish, the meat of the lobster or lobsters which have served in its preparation is sliced and used as the garnish of the fish.

Anchovy Sauce

Put into a small stewpan one pint of unbuttered “Normande Sauce” (№99), and finish it, away from the fire, with three oz. of anchovy butter, and one oz. of anchovy fillets, washed, well sponged, and cut into small pieces.

Aurore Sauce

Into one-half pint of boiling velouté put the same quantity of very red tomato purée (Formula №29), and mix the two. Let the sauce boil a little, pass it through a tammy, and finish, away from the fire, with three oz. of butter.

Lenten Aurore Sauce

This sauce is made like the preceding one, i.e., with the same quantities of velouté and tomato purée, replacing ordinary velouté by fish velouté.

Béarnaise Sauce

Put into a small stewpan one teaspoonful of chopped shallots, two oz. of chopped tarragon stalks, three oz. of chervil, some mignonette pepper, a pinch of salt, and four tablespoonfuls of vinegar. Reduce the vinegar by two-thirds, take off the fire, let the stewpan cool a little, and add to this reduction the yolks of five eggs. Now put the stewpan on a low fire and gradually combine with the yolks six oz. of melted butter. Whisk the sauce briskly, so as to ensure the cooking of the yolks, which alone, by gradual cooking, effect the leason of the sauce.

When the butter is combined with the sauce, rub the latter through tammy, and finish it with a teaspoonful of chervil parings and chopped tarragon leaves. Complete the seasoning with a soupçon of cayenne. This sauce should not be served very hot, as it is really a mayonnaise with butter. It need only be tepid, for it would probably turn if it were over-heated. Serve it with grilled, butcher’s meat and poultry.

Béarnaise Sauce with Meat Glaze, Otherwise Valois Sauce or Foyot Sauce

Prepare a Béarnaise sauce as explained in Formula №62. Complete it with three tablespoonfuls of dissolved pale meat glaze, which may be added in small quantities at a time. Serve it with butcher’s meat.

Béarnaise Tomatée Sauce or Choron Sauce

Proceed in exactly the same way as for Béarnaise Formula №62. When the sauce is made and rubbed through tammy, finish it with one-third pint of very red tomato purée. In this case the final addition of chervil and tarragon should not be made.

This is proper to “Tournedos Choron”, but it may accompany grilled poultry and white, butcher’s meat.

Bercy Sauce

Heat two oz. of chopped shallots. Moisten with one-half pint of white wine and as much fish fumet, or, when possible, the same quantity of fish liquor, the latter being, of course, that of a fish similar to the one the sauce is to accompany. Reduce to a good third, add one-third pint of velouté, let the sauce boil some time, and finish it, away from the fire, with four oz. of butter (added by degrees), a few drops of fish glaze, half the juice of a lemon, and one oz. of chopped parsley.

Serve with medium-sized poached fish.

Butter Sauce

Mix two oz. of sifted flour with two oz. of melted butter. Dilute with one quart of boiling water, salted to the extent of one-quarter oz. per quart. Stir briskly to ensure a perfect leason, and do not allow to boil. Add immediately the yolks of six eggs mixed with one-quarter pint of cream and the juice of half a lemon. Rub through a tammy, and finish the sauce with five oz. of best fresh butter.

Be careful that the sauce does not boil after it has been thickened.

Bonnefoy Sauce, or White Bordelaise Sauce

Put in a stewpan two oz. of minced shallots and one-half pint of Graves, Sauterne, or any other excellent white Bordeaux. Reduce the wine almost entirely, add one-quarter pint of velouté, let it simmer twenty minutes, and rub it through a tammy. Finish it, away from the fire, with six oz. of butter and a little chopped tarragon.

Serve it with grilled fish and grilled white meat.

Caper Sauce

This is a derivative of the Butter Sauce described under Formula №66, and there need only be added two tablespoonfuls of capers per pint of sauce. It frequently accompanies boiled fish of all kinds.

Cardinal Sauce

Boil one pint of Béchamel, to which add one-half pint of fish fumet and a little truffle essence, and reduce by a quarter. Finish the sauce, when dishing up, with three tablespoonfuls of cream and three oz. of very red lobster butter (№149).

This sauce is poured over the fish.

Mushroom Sauce

If this be intended for poultry, add one-fifth pint of mushroom liquor and eight oz. of button-mushroom heads turned or channelled and cooked, to one pint of very stiff Allemande Sauce.

If it be intended for fish, take one pint of fish velouté, thickened with the yolks of four eggs, and finish it with mushroom liquor, as above.

The sauce that I suggest for poultry may also be used for fish, after adding the necessary quantity of fish fumet.

Châteaubriand Sauce

Put one oz. of chopped shallots, a sprig of thyme and a bit of bay, one oz. of mushroom parings, and one-quarter pint of white wine into a stewpan. Reduce the wine almost entirely, add one-half pint of veal gravy, and reduce again until the liquid only measures one-quarter pint. Strain through muslin, and finish the sauce away from the fire with four oz. of butter “Maître d’Hotel” (№150), to which may be added a little chopped tarragon. Serve with grilled fillet of beef, otherwise “Châteaubriand”.

White Chaud-froid Sauce

Boil one pint of velouté in a stewpan, and add three-quarters pint of melted white poultry jelly. Put the stewpan on an open fire, reduce the sauce by a third, stirring constantly the while, and gradually add one-half pint of very fresh cream. When the sauce has reached the desired degree of consistency rub it through a tammy, and stir it frequently while it cools, for fear of a skin forming on its surface, for if this happened it would have to be strained again. When dishing up, this sauce should be cold, so that it may properly coat immersed solids and yet be liquid enough to admit of the latter being easily steeped into it.

Ordinary Chaud-froid Sauce

Proceed exactly as above, substituting Allemande Sauce for the velouté, and reducing the quantity of cream to one-quarter pint. Observe the same precautions while cooling.

Chaud-froid Sauce, à l’aurore

Prepare a white Chaud-froid (№72). The same may be coloured by the addition of fine red tomato purée—more or less to match the desired shade—or by an infusion of paprika, according to the use for which it is intended. This last product is preferable when not too deep a shade is required.

Chaud-froid Sauce, Au Vert-Pré

Add to the velouté of the white Chaud-froid sauce, at the same time as the jelly, an infusion prepared thus:— Boil one-quarter pint of white wine, and add to it one pinch of chervil stalks, a similar quantity of tarragon leaves, chives, and parsley leaves. Cover, allow infusion to proceed away from the fire for ten minutes, and strain through linen.

Treat the sauce as explained, and finish with spinach-green (Formula №143). The shade of the sauce must not be too pronounced, but must remain a pale green. The colouring principle must therefore be added with caution and in small quantities, until the correct shade is obtained. Use this sauce for Chaud-froids of fowl, particularly that kind distinguished as “Printanier”.

Lent Chaud-froid Sauce

Proceed as for white Chaud-froid, using the same quantities, and taking note of the following modifications:

Substitute fish velouté for ordinary velouté
Substitute white fish jelly for poultry jelly

I have adopted the use of this ordinary Chaud-froid sauce for the glazing of fillets and escalopes of fish and shell-fish, instead of cleared Mayonnaise, formerly used, which had certain inconveniences—not the least being the oozing away of the oil under the shrinkage of the gelatine. This difficulty does not obtain in the ordinary Chaud-froid, the definite and pronounced flavour of which is better than that of the cleared Mayonnaise.

“Escoffier” Cherry Sauce

This sauce may be bought ready-made. Like the Roberts Sauce, it can be served hot or cold. It is an excellent adjunct to venison, and even to small ground-game. Saddle of venison with this sauce constitutes one of the greatest dainties that an epicure could desire.

78—Chivry Sauce

In one-half pint of boiling poultry stock put a large pinch of chervil pluches, tarragon and parsley leaves, a head of young pimpernel (the qualification here is very important, for this aromatic plant grows bitter as it matures), and a good pinch of chives. Cover up, and let infusion proceed for ten to twelve minutes; then add the liquid (strained through linen) to one pint of velouté. Boil, reduce by a quarter, and complete it with two oz. of Green Butter (Formula №143). Chivry Sauce is admirably suited to boiled or poached poultry.

Shrimp Sauce

Boil one pint of fish velouté or, failing this, Béchamel sauce, and add to it one-quarter pint of cream and one-quarter pint of very clear fish fumet. Reduce to one pint, and finish the sauce, away from the fire, with two oz. of Shrimp Butter (Formula №145) and two oz. of shelled shrimps’ tails.

Curry Sauce

Slightly brown the following vegetables in butter:—Twelve oz. of minced onions, one oz. of parsley roots, four oz. of minced celery, a small sprig of thyme, a bit of bay, and a little mace. Sprinkle with two oz. of flour and a teaspoonful of curry pepper.

Cook the flour for some minutes without letting it acquire any colour, and dilute with one and one-half pints of white stock. Boil, cook gently for three-quarters of an hour, and rub through a tammy. Now heat the sauce, remove its grease, and keep it in the bain-marie. Serve this sauce with fish, shell-fish, poultry, and various egg-preparations.

N.B.—This sauce is sometimes flavoured with cocoa-nut milk in the proportion of one-quarter of the diluent.

Diplomate Sauce

Take one pint of Normande Sauce, prepared according to Formula №99, and finish it with two oz. of lobster butter and three tablespoonfuls of lobster meat, and truffles cut into small, regular tubes.

Herb Sauce

Prepare one pint of White-wine Sauce (№111). Finish it away from the fire with three oz. of shallot butter, a tablespoonful of parsley, chervil, tarragon, and chives, chopped and mixed. Serve this sauce with boiled or poached fish.

84—Gooseberry Sauce

Prepare one pint of Butter Sauce (Formula №66). Meanwhile put one lb. of green gooseberries into a small copper saucepan containing boiling water. Boil for five minutes, then drain the gooseberries, and put them in a little stewpan with one-half pint of white wine and three oz. of powdered sugar. Gently cook the gooseberries, rub them through a tammy, and add the resulting pulp to the butter sauce. This sauce is excellent with grilled mackerel and the poached fillets of that fish.

Oyster Sauce

Take one pint of Normande Sauce, finish it as directed in that recipe, and complete it with one-quarter pint of reduced oyster liquor, strained through linen, and twelve poached and trimmed oysters.

Ivory Sauce, or Albufera Sauce

Take the necessary quantity of Suprême Sauce, prepared as explained in Formula №105a. Add to this four tablespoonfuls of dissolved, pale, meat glaze per quart of sauce, in order to lend the latter that ivory-white tint which characterises it. Serve this sauce chiefly with poultry and poached sweet-bread.

Joinville Sauce

Prepare one pint of Normande Sauce (№99), as given in the first part of its formula, and complete it with two oz. of shrimp butter and two oz. of crayfish butter. If this sauce is to accompany a fish à la Joinville, which includes a special garnish, it is served as it stands. If it is served with a large, boiled, ungarnished fish, one oz. of very black truffles cut Julienne-fashion should be added. As may be seen, Joinville Sauce differs from similar preparations in the final operation where crayfish and shrimp butter are combined.

Maltese Sauce

To the Hollandaise Sauce, given under Formula №30, add, when, dishing up, the juice of two blood oranges (these late-season oranges being especially suitable for this sauce) and half a coffee-spoonful of grated orange-rind.

Maltese Sauce is the finest for asparagus.

Marinière Sauce

Take the necessary quantity of Bercy Sauce (№65), and add, per pint of sauce, one-quarter pint of mussel liquor and a leason composed of the yolks of three eggs.

Serve this with small poached fish and more particularly with mussels.

Mornay Sauce

Boil one pint of Béchamel Sauce with one-quarter pint of the fumet of that fish which is to constitute the dish. Reduce by a good quarter, and add two oz. of Gruyère and two oz. of grated Parmesan.

Put the sauce on the fire again for a few minutes, and ensure the melting of the cheese by stirring with a small whisk. Finish the sauce away from the fire with two oz. of butter added by degrees.

Mousseline Sauce

To a Hollandaise Sauce, prepared as explained (№30), add, just before dishing up, one-half pint of stiffly-whipped cream per pint of sauce.

Mousseuse Sauce

Scald and wipe a small vegetable-pan, and put into it one-half lb. of stiffly-manied butter, properly softened. Season this butter with table-salt and a few drops of lemon-juice, and whisk it while gradually adding one-third pint of cold water. Finish with two tablespoonfuls of very firm, whipped cream. This preparation, though classified as a sauce, is really a compound butter, which is served with boiled fish. The heat of the fish alone suffices to melt it, and its appearance is infinitely more agreeable than that of plain, melted butter.

Mustard Sauce

Take the necessary quantity of butter sauce and complete it, away from the fire, with one tablespoonful of mustard per pint of sauce.

N.B.—If the sauce has to wait, it must be kept in a bain-marie, for it should not on any account boil. It is served with certain small grilled fish, especially fresh herrings.

Nantua Sauce

Boil one pint of Béchamel Sauce, add one-half pint of cream, and reduce by a third. Rub it through a tammy, and finish it with a further addition of two tablespoonfuls of cream, three oz. of very fine crayfish butter, and one tablespoonful of small, shelled crayfishes’ tails.

Newburg Sauce (First Method with Raw Lobster)

Divide a two lb. lobster into four parts. Remove its creamy parts, pound them finely with two oz. of butter, and put them aside.

Heat in a sauté-pan one and one-half oz. of butter and as much oil, and insert the pieces of lobster, well seasoned with salt and cayenne. Fry until the pieces assume a fine, red colour entirely drain away the butter, and add two tablespoonfuls of burnt brandy and one-third pint of Marsala or old Sherry.

Reduce the wine by two-thirds, and wet the lobster with one-third pint of cream and one-half pint of fish fumet. Now add a faggot, cover the sauté-pan, and gently cook for twenty-five minutes. Then drain the lobster on a sieve, remove the meat and cut it into cubes, and finish the sauce by adding the creamy portions put aside from the first. Boil so as to ensure the cooking of these latter portions; add the meat, cut into cubes, and verify the seasoning.

N.B.—The addition of the meat to the sauce is optional; instead of cutting it into cubes it may be stewed and displayed on the fish constituting the dish.

Newburg Sauce (Second Method with Cooked Lobster)

The lobster having been cooked in a Court-bouillon, shell the tail and slice it up. Arrange these slices in a sauté-pan liberally buttered at the bottom; season them strongly with salt and cayenne, and heat them on both sides so as to effect the reddening of the skin. Immerse, so as to cover, in a good Sherry, and almost entirely reduce same.

When dishing up, pour on to the slices a leason composed of one-third pint of fresh cream and the yolks of two eggs. Gently stir, away from the fire, and roll the saucepan about until the leason is completed.

Originally, these two sauces, like the American, were exclusively composed of, and served with, lobster. They were one with the two very excellent preparations of lobster which bear their name. In its two forms lobster may only be served at lunch, many people with delicate stomachs being unable to digest it at night. To obviate this serious difficulty, I have made it a practice to serve lobster sauce with fillets or Mousselines of sole, adding the lobster as a garnish only. And this innovation proved most welcome to the public.

By using such condiments as curry and paprika, excellent varieties of this sauce may be obtained, which are particularly suited to sole and other white Lenten fish. In either of these cases it is well to add a little rice “à I’Indienne” to the fish.

Noisette Sauce

Prepare a Hollandaise Sauce according to the recipe under Formula №30. Add two oz. of hazel-nut butter at the last moment.

Serve this with salmon, trout, and all boiled fish in general.

Normande Sauce

Put in a sauté-pan one pint of fish velouté, three tablespoonfuls of mushroom liquor, as much oyster liquor, and twice as much sole fumet, the yolks of three eggs, a few drops of lemon-juice, and one-quarter pint of cream. Reduce by a good third on an open fire, season with a little cayenne, rub through a tammy, and finish with two oz. of butter and four tablespoonfuls of good cream.

This sauce is proper to fillet of sole “à la Normande”, but it is also frequently used as the base of other small sauces.

Oriental Sauce

Take one pint of American Sauce, season with curry, and reduce to a third. Then add, away from the fire, one-quarter pint of cream per pint of sauce.

Serve this sauce in the same way as >American Sauce.

Poulette Sauce

Boil for a few minutes one pint of Sauce Allemande, and add six tablespoonfuls of mushroom liquor. Finish, away from the fire, with two oz. of butter, a few drops of lemon-juice, and one teaspoonful of chopped parsley. Use this sauce with certain vegetables, but more generally with sheep’s trotters.

Ravigotte Sauce

Reduce by half, one-quarter pint of white wine with half as much vinegar. Add one pint of ordinary velouté, boil gently for a few minutes, and finish with one and one-half oz. of shallot butter and one teaspoonful of chervil, tarragon, and chopped chives. This sauce accompanies boiled poultry and certain white “abats”.

Regency Sauce

If this sauce is to garnish poultry, boil one pint of Allemande Sauce with six tablespoonfuls of mushroom essence and two tablespoonfuls of truffle essence. Finish with four table-spoonfuls of poultry glaze.

If it is to garnish fish, substitute for the Allemande Sauce some fish velouté thickened with egg-yolks and the essences of mushroom and truffle as above. Complete with some fish essence.

Soubise Sauce

Stew in butter two lbs. of finely-minced onions, scalded for three minutes and well dried. This stewing of the onions in butter increases their flavour. Now add one-half pint of thickened Béchamel; season with salt and a teaspoonful of powdered sugar. Cook gently for half an hour, rub through a tammy. and complete the sauce with some tablespoonfuls of cream and two oz. of butter.

Soubise Sauce with Rice

The same quantity as above of minced onions, scalded and well drained. Garnish the bottom and the sides of a tall, medium stewpan with some thin rashers of fat bacon. Insert the onions, together with one-quarter lb. of Carolina rice, one pint of white consommé, a large pinch of powdered sugar, and the necessary salt. Cook gently in the front of the oven for three-quarters of an hour. Then pound the onions and rice in a mortar, rub the resulting purée through a tammy, and finish with cream and butter as in the preceding case.

N.B.—This sauce, being more consistent than the former, is used as a garnish just as often as a sauce.

Soubise Sauce Tomatée

Prepare a soubise in accordance with the first of the two above formulæ, and add to it one-third of its volume of very red tomato purée.

Remarks

The Soubise is rather a cullis than a sauce; i.e., its consistence must be greater than that of a sauce.
The admixture of Béchamel in Soubise is preferable to that of rice, seeing that it makes it smoother. If, in certain cases, rice is used as a cohering element, it is in order to give the Soubise more stiffness.
In accordance with the uses to which it may be put, the Soubise Tomatée may be finally seasoned either with curry or paprika.

Suprême Sauce

The salient characteristics of Suprême Sauce are its perfect whiteness and consummate delicacy. It is generally prepared in small quantities only.

Preparation

Put one and one-half pints of very clear poultry stock and one-quarter pint of mushroom cooking liquor into a sautépan. Reduce to two-thirds; add one pint of “poultry velouté”; reduce on an open fire, stirring with the spatula the while, and combine one-half pint of excellent cream with the sauce, this last ingredient being added little by little.

When the sauce has reached the desired consistence, strain it through a sieve, and add another one-quarter pint of cream and two oz. of best butter. Stir with a spoon, from time to time, or keep the pan well covered.

Venetian Sauce

Put into a stewpan one tablespoonful of chopped shallots, one tablespoonful of chervil, and one-quarter pint of white wine and tarragon vinegar, mixed in equal quantities. Reduce the vinegar by two-thirds; add one pint of white wine sauce (Formula №111); boil for a few minutes; rub through a tammy, and finish the sauce with a sufficient quantity of Herb Juice (№183) and one teaspoonful of chopped chervil and tarragon. This sauce accompanies various fish.

Villeroy Sauce

Put into a sautépan one pint of Allemande Sauce to which have been added two tablespoonfuls of truffle essence and as much ham essence.

Reduce on an open fire and constantly stir until the sauce is sufficiently stiff to coat immersed solids thickly.

Villeroy Soubisée Sauce

Put into a sauté-pan two-thirds pint of Allemande Sauce and one-third pint of Soubise purée (Formula №105). Reduce as in the preceding case, as the uses to which this is put are the same. Now, according to the circumstances and the nature of the solid it is intended for, a few teaspoonfuls of very black, chopped truffles may be added to this sauce.

Villeroy Tomatée Sauce

Prepare the sauce as explained under Formula №108, and add to it the third of its volume of very fine tomato purée. Reduce in the same way.

Remarks

Villeroy sauce, of whatsoever kind, is solely used for the coating of preparations said to be “à la Villeroy”.
The Villeroy Tomatée may be finally seasoned with curry or paprika, according to the preparation for which it is intended.

White Wine Sauce

The three following methods are employed in making it:

Add one-quarter pint of fish fumet to one pint of thickened Velouté, and reduce by half. Finish the sauce, away from the fire, with four oz. of butter. Thus prepared, this white wine sauce is suitable for glazed fish.
Almost entirely reduce one-quarter pint of fish fumet. To this reduction add the yolks of four eggs, mixing them well in it, and follow with one lb. of butter, added by degrees, paying heed to the precautions indicated under sauce Hollandaise (Formula №30).
Put the yolks of five eggs into a small stewpan and mix them with one tablespoonful of cold fish-stock. Put the stewpan in a bain-marie and finish the sauce with one lb. of butter, meanwhile adding from time to time, and in small quantities, six tablespoonfuls of excellent fish fumet. The procedure in this sauce is, in short, exactly that of the Hollandaise, with this distinction, that here fish fumet takes the place of the water.

Hot English Sauces

Bread Sauce

Boil one pint of milk, and add three oz. of fresh, white bread-crumb, a little salt, a small onion with a clove stuck in it, and one oz. of butter. Cook gently for about a quarter of an hour, remove the onion, smooth the sauce with a whisk, and finish it with a few tablespoonfuls of cream.

This sauce is served with roast fowl and roast feathered game.

Celery Sauce

Clean six stalks of celery (only use the hearts), put them in a sauté-pan, wholly immerse in consommé, add a faggot and one onion with a clove stuck in it, and cook gently. Drain the celery, pound it in a mortar, then rub it through a tammy and put the purée in a stewpan. Now thin the purée with an equal quantity of cream sauce and a little reduced celery liquor. Heat it moderately, and, if it has to wait, put it in a bain-marie.

This sauce is suited to boiled or braised poultry. It is excellent, and has been adopted in French cookery.

Cranberry Sauce

Cook one pint of cranberries with one quart of water in a stewpan, and cover the stewpan. When the berries are cooked drain them in a fine sieve through which they are strained. To the purée thus obtained add the necessary quantity of their cooking liquor, so as to make a somewhat thick sauce. Sugar should be added according to the taste of the consumer.

This sauce is mostly served with roast turkey. It is to be bought ready-made, and, if this kind be used, it need only be heated with a little water.

Fennel Sauce

Take one pint of Butter Sauce (Formula №66) and finish it with two tablespoonfuls of chopped fennel, scalded for a few seconds.

This is principally used with mackerel.

Egg Sauce with Melted Butter

Dissolve one-quarter pound of butter, and add to it the necessary salt, a little pepper, half the juice of a lemon, and three hard-boiled eggs (hot and cut into large cubes); also a teaspoonful of chopped and scalded parsley.

Scotch Egg Sauce

Make a white roux with one and one-half oz. of butter and one oz. of flour. Mix in one pint of boiling milk, season with salt, white pepper, and nutmeg, and boil gently for ten minutes. Then add three hot hard-boiled eggs, cut into cubes (the whites and the yolks).

This sauce usually accompanies boiled fish, especially fresh haddocks and fresh and salted cod.

Horse-Radish or Albert Sauce

Rasp five oz. of horse-radish and place them in a stewpan with one-quarter pint of white consommé. Boil gently for twenty minutes and add a good one-half pint of butter sauce, as much cream, and one-half oz. of bread-crumb; thicken by reducing on a brisk fire and rub through tammy. Then thicken with the yolks of two eggs, and complete the seasoning with a pinch of salt and pepper, and a teaspoonful of mustard dissolved in a tablespoonful of vinegar.

Serve this sauce with braised or roast beef—especially fillets.

Parsley Sauce

This is the Butter Sauce (№66), to which is added, per pint, a heaped tablespoonful of freshly-chopped parsley.

Reform Sauce

Put into a small stewpan and boil one pint of half glaze sauce and one-half pint of ordinary Poivrade sauce. Complete with a garnish composed of one-half oz. of gherkins, one-half oz. of the hard-boiled white of an egg, one oz. of salted tongue, one oz. of truffles, and one oz. of mushrooms. All these to be cut Julienne-fashion and short.

This sauce is for mutton cutlets when these are “à la Reform”.

Chapter IV Cold Sauces and Compound Butters

Aioli Sauce, or Provence Butter

Pound one oz. of garlic cloves as finely as possible in a mortar, and add the yolk of one raw egg, a pinch of salt, and one-half pint of oil, letting the latter gradually fall in a thread and wielding the pestle meanwhile, so as to effect a complete amalgamation. Add a few drops of lemon juice and cold water to the sauce as it thickens, these being to avoid its turning.

Should it decompose while in the process of making or when made, the only thing to be done is to begin it again with the yolk of an egg.

Andalouse Sauce

Take the required quantity of Mayonnaise sauce (№126) and add to it the quarter of its volume of very red and concentrated tomato purée, and finally add two oz. of capsicum cut finely. Julienne-fashion, per pint of sauce.

Bohemian Sauce

Put in a bowl one-quarter pint of cold Béchamel, the yolks of four eggs, a little table salt and white pepper. Add a quart of oil and three tablespoonfuls of tarragon vinegar, proceeding as for the Mayonnaise.

Finish the sauce with a tablespoonful of mustard.

Genoa Sauce

Pound in a mortar, and make into a smooth, fine paste, one oz. of pistachios and one oz. of fir-apple kernels, or, if these are not available, one oz. of sweet almonds; add one-half tablespoonful of cold Béchamel. Put this paste into a bowl, add the yolks of six eggs, a little salt and pepper, and finish the sauce with one quart of oil, the juice of two lemons, and proceed as for the Mayonnaise.

Complete with three tablespoonfuls of purée of herbs, prepared with equal quantities of chervil, parsley, tarragon, and fresh pimpernel, scalded for one minute. Cool quickly, press so as to expel the water, and pass through a fine sieve.

Serve this sauce with cold fish.

Gribiche Sauce

Crush in a basin the yolks of six hard-boiled eggs, and work them into a smooth paste, together with a large tablespoonful of French mustard, the necessary salt, a little pepper, and make up the sauce with one pint of oil. Complete with one dessertspoonful of parsley, chervil, and tarragon (chopped and mixed), as many capers and gherkins, evenly mixed, and the hard-boiled whites of three eggs, cut short, Julienne-fashion.

This sauce is chiefly used with cold fish.

Mayonnaise Sauce

Put in a basin the yolks of six raw eggs, after having removed the cores. Season them with one-half oz. of table-salt and a little cayenne pepper. Gradually pour one-fifth pint of vinegar on the yolks while whisking them briskly. When the vinegar is absorbed add one quart of oil, letting the latter trickle down in a thread, constantly stirring the sauce meanwhile. The sauce is finished by the addition of the juice of a lemon and three tablespoonfuls of boiling water the purpose of the latter being to ensure the coherence of the sauce and to prevent its turning.

Mayonnaise prepared in this way is rather liquid, but it need only be left to rest a few hours in order to thicken considerably. Unless it be exposed to too low a temperature, the Mayonnaise, prepared as above, never turns, and may be kept for several days without the fear of anything happening to it. Merely cover it to keep the dust away.

Remarks

In the matter of sauces there exist endless prejudices, which I must attempt to refute:

If the sauce forms badly, or not at all, the reason is that the oil has been added too rapidly at first, before the addition of the vinegar, and that its assimilation by the yolks has not operated normally.
It is quite an error to suppose that it is necessary to work over ice or in a cold room. Cold is rather deleterious to the Mayonnaise, and is invariably the cause of this sauce turning in winter. In the cold season the oil should be slightly warmed, or, at least, kept at the temperature of the kitchen, though it is best to make it in a moderately warm place.
It is a further error to suppose that the seasoning interferes with the making of the sauce, for salt, in solution, rather provokes the cohering force of the yolks.

Causes of the Disintegration of the Mayonnaise

The too rapid addition of the oil at the start.
The use of congealed, or too cold, an oil.
Excess of oil in proportion to the number of yolks, the assimilating power of an egg being limited to two and one-half oz. of oil (if the sauce be made some time in advance), and three oz. if it is to be used immediately.

Means of Bringing Turned Mayonnaise Back to its Normal State

Put the yolk of an egg into a basin with a few drops of vinegar, and mix the turned Mayonnaise in it, little by little. If it be a matter of only a small quantity of Mayonnaise, one-half a coffee-spoonful of mustard can take the place of the egg-yolk. Finally, with regard to acid seasoning, a whiter sauce is obtained by the use of lemon juice instead of vinegar.

Cleared Mayonnaise Sauce

Take the necessary quantity of Mayonnaise and gradually add to it, per one and one-half pints of the sauce, one-half pint of cold and rather firm melting aspic jelly—Lenten or ordinary, according to the nature of the products for which the sauce is intended.

Remarks

It is this very Mayonnaise, formerly used almost exclusively for coating entries and cold relevees of fish, filleted fish, escalopes of common and spiny-lobster, &c., which I have allowed the Lenten Chaud-froid (see remarks Formula №76) to supersede.

Whisked Mayonnaise

Put into a copper basin or other bowl three-quarters pint of melted jelly, two-thirds pint of Mayonnaise, one tablespoonful of tarragon vinegar, and as much rasped and finely-chopped horse-radish. Mix up the whole, place the utensil on ice, and whisk gently until the contents get very frothy. Stop whisking as soon as the sauce begins to solidify, for it must remain almost fluid so as to enable it to mix with the products for which it is intended.

This sauce is used principally for vegetable salads.

Ravigote Sauce, or Vinaigrette

Put into a bowl one pint of oil, one-third pint of vinegar, a little salt and pepper, two oz. of small capers, three tablespoonfuls of fine herbs, comprising soine very finely chopped onion, as much parsley, and half as much chervil, tarragon, and chives. Mix thoroughly. The Ravigote accompanies calf’s head or foot, sheep’s trotters, &c.

Two or three tablespoonfuls of the liquor with which its accompanying solids have been cooked, i.e., calf’s head or sheep’s trotters liquor, &c., are often added to this sauce when dishing up.

Remoulade Sauce

To one pint of Mayonnaise add one large tablespoonful of mustard, another of gherkins, and yet another of chopped and pressed capers, one tablespoonful of fine herbs, parsley, chervil, and tarragon, all chopped and mixed, and a coffee-spoonful of anchovy essence.

This sauce accompanies cold meat and poultry, and, more particularly, common and spiny lobster.

Green Sauce

Take the necessary quantity of thick Mayonnaise and spicy seasoning, and add to these, per pint of sauce, one-third pint of herb juice, prepared as indicated hereafter (Formula №132).

This is suitable for cold fish and shell fish.

Vincent Sauce

Prepare and carefully wash the following herbs:—One oz. each of parsley, chervil, tarragon, chives, sorrel-leaves, and fresh pimpernel, two oz. of water-cress and two oz. of spinach. Put all these herbs into a copper bowl containing salted, boiling water. Boil for two minutes only; then drain the herbs in a sieve and immerse them in a basin of fresh water. When they are cold they are once more drained until quite dry; then they must be finely pounded with the yolks of eight hard-boiled eggs. Rub the purée thus obtained through a sieve first, then through tammy, add one pint of very stiff Mayonnaise to it, and finish the sauce with a dessertspoonful of Worcestershire sauce.

Cold English Sauces

Cambridge Sauce

Pound together the yolks of six hard-boiled eggs, the washed and dried fillets of four anchovies, a teaspoonful of capers, a dessertspoonful of chervil, tarragon, and chives, mixed. When the whole forms a fine paste, add one tablespoonful of mustard, one-fifth pint of oil, one tablespoonful of vinegar, and proceed as for a Mayonnaise. Season with a little cayenne; rub through tammy, applying pressure with a spoon, and put the sauce in a bowl. Stir it awhile with a whisk to smooth it, and finish with one teaspoonful of chopped parsley.

It is suited to cold meats in general; in fact, it is an Anglicised version of Vincent Sauce.

Cumberland Sauce

Dissolve four tablespoonfuls of red-currant jelly, to which are added one-fifth pint of port wine, one teaspoonful of finely-chopped shallots, scalded for a few seconds and pressed, one teaspoonful of small pieces of orange rind and as much lemon rind (cut finely, Julienne-fashion, scalded for two minutes, well-drained, and cooled), the juice of an orange and that of half a lemon, one teaspoonful of mustard, a little cayenne pepper, and as much powdered ginger. Mix the whole well.

Serve this sauce with cold venison.

Mint Sauce

Cut finely, Julienne-fashion, or chop, two oz. of mint leaves. Put these in a bowl with a little less than one oz. of white cassonade or castor sugar, one-quarter pint of fresh vinegar, and four tablespoonfuls of water.

Special sauce for hot or cold lamb.

Oxford Sauce

Make a Cumberland sauce according to Formula №134, with this difference: that the Julienne of orange and lemon rinds should be replaced by rasped or finely-chopped rinds, and that the quantities of same should be less, i.e., two-thirds of a teaspoonful of each.

Horse-Radish Sauce

Dilute one tablespoonful of mustard with two tablespoonfuls of vinegar in a basin, and add one lb. of finely-rasped horseradish, two oz. of powdered sugar, a little salt, one pint of cream, and one lb. of bread-crumb steeped in milk and pressed. Serve this sauce very cold.

It accompanies boiled and roast joints of beef.

Compound Butters for Grills and for the Completion of Sauces

With the exception of those of the shell-fish order, the butters, whose formulæ I am about to give, are not greatly used in kitchens. Nevertheless, in some cases, as, for instance, in accentuating the savour of sauces, they answer a real and useful purpose, and I therefore recommend them, since they enable one to give a flavour to the derivatives of the Velouté and Béchamel sauces which these could not acquire by any other means.

With regard to shell-fish butters, and particularly those of the common and spiny lobster and the crayfish, experience has shown that when they are prepared with heat (that is to say, by melting in a bain-marie a quantity of butter which has been previously pounded with shell-fish remains and afterwards strained through muslin into a basin of iced-water where it has solidified) they are of a finer colour than the other kind and quite free from shell particles. Biit the heat, besides dissipating a large proportion of their delicacy, involves considerable risk, for the slightest neglect gives the above preparation quite a disagreeable taste. To obviate these difficulties I have adopted a system of two distinct butters, one which is exclusively colorific and prepared with heat, and the other which is prepared with all the creamy parts, the trimmings and the remains of common and spiny lobsters, without the shells, pounded with the required quantity of fresh butter and passed through a sieve. The latter is used to complete sauces, particularly those with a Béchamel base to which it lends a perfect savour.

I follow the same procedure with shrimp and crayfish butters, sometimes substituting for the butter good cream, which, I find, absorbs the aromatic principles perhaps better than the former. With the above method it is advisable to pass the butter or the cream through a very fine sieve first and afterwards through tammy, so as to avoid small particles of the pounded shell being present in the sauce.

Bercy Butter

Put into a small stewpan one-quarter pint of white wine and one oz. of finely-chopped shallots, scalded a moment. Reduce the wine by one-half, and add one-half lb. of butter softened into a cream; one teaspoonful of chopped parsley, two oz. of beef marrow cut into cubes, poached in slightly salted water and well drained, the necessary table-salt, and, when dishing up, a little ground pepper and a few drops of lemon-juice.

This butter must not be completely melted, and it is principally served with grilled beef.

Chivry or Ravigote Butter

Put into a small saucepan of salted, boiling water six oz. of chervil, parsley, tarragon, fresh pimpernel, and chives, in equal quantities, and two oz. of chopped shallots. Boil quickly for two minutes, drain, cool in cold water, press in a towel to completely remove the water, and pound in a mortar. Now add one-half lb. of half-melted butter, mix well with the purée of herbs, and pass through tammy.

This butter is used to complete Chivry sauce and other sauces that contain herb juices, such as the Venetian, &c.

Châteaubriand Butter

Reduce by two-thirds four-fifths pint of white wine containing four chopped shallots, fragments of thyme and bay, and four oz. of mushroom parings. Add four-fifths pint of veal gravy, reduce the whole to half, rub it through tammy, and finish it away from the fire with eight oz. of Maître d’Hôtel butter (Formula №150) and half a tablespoonful of chopped tarragon.

Colbert Butter

Take one lb. of Maître d’Hôtel butter (Formula №150) and add six tablespoonfuls of dissolved, pale meat glaze and one teaspoonful of chopped tarragon.

Serve this sauce with fish prepared à la Colbert.

Red Colouring Butter

Put on to a dish any available remains of shell-fish after having thoroughly emptied and well dried them in the oven. Pound them until they form a fine powder, and add their weight of butter.

Put the whole into a saucepan and melt in a bain-marie, stirring frequently the while. When the butter is quite clarified strain it through muslin, twisting the latter over a tureen of iced-water in which the strained butter solidifies. Put the congealed butter in a towel, press it heavily so as to expel the water, and keep cool in a small bowl.

Remarks

A very fine and decided red colour is obtained by using paprika as a condiment for sauces intended for poultry and certain butcher’s meats, in accordance with the procedure I recommend for the Hongroise. But only the very best quality should be used—that which is mild and at the same time produces a nice pink colour without entailing any excess of the condiment. Among the various kinds of paprika on the market I can highly recommend that of Messrs Kotangi, which I have invariably found satisfactory.

Green Colouring Butter

Peel, wash, and thoroughly shake (so as to get rid of every drop of water) two lbs. of spinach. Pound it raw and then press it in a strong towel, twisting the latter so as to extract all the vegetable juice. Pour this juice into a sauté-pan, let it coagulate in a bain-marie, and pour it on to a serviette stretched over a bowl in order to drain away the water. Collect the remains of the colouring substance on the serviette, making use of a palette-knife for the purpose, and put these into a mortar; mix with half their weight of butter, strain through a sieve or tammy, and put aside to cool. This green butter should in all cases take the place of the liquid green found on the market.

Various Coulis

Finely pound shrimp and crayfish shells, and combine with these the available creamy parts and spawn of the common and spiny lobsters; add one-quarter pint of rich cream per lb. of the above remains, and strain, first through a fine sieve and then through tammy. This cullis is prepared just in time for dishing up, and serves as a refining principle in certain fish sauces.

Shrimp Butter

Finely pound any available shrimp remains, add to these their weight of butter, and strain through tammy. Place in a bowl and put aside in the cool.

Shallot Butter

Put eight oz. of roughly minced shallots in the corner of a clean towel, and wash them quickly in boiling water. Cool, and press them heavily. Then pound them finely with their own weight of fresh butter and strain through tammy.

This butter accentuates the savour of certain sauces, such as Bercy, Ravigote, &c.

Crayfish Butter

Pound, very finely, the remains and shells of crayfish cooked in Mirepoix. Add their weight of butter, and strain through a fine sieve, and again through tammy, so as to avoid the presence of any shell particles. This latter precaution applies to all shellfish butters.

Tarragon Butter

Quickly scald and cool eight oz. of fresh tarragon, drain, press in a towel, pound in a mortar, and add to them one lb. of butter. Strain through tammy, and put aside in the cool if it is not to be used immediately.

Lobster Butter

Reduce to a paste in the mortar the spawn, shell, and creamy parts of lobster. Add their equal in weight of butter and strain through tammy.

Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel

First manie and then soften into a cream one-half lb. of butter. Add a tablespoonful of chopped parsley, a little salt and pepper, and a few drops of lemon-juice.

Serve this with grills in general.

Manied Butter

Mix, until perfectly combined, four oz. of butter and three oz. of sifted flour. This butter is made immediately before the time of dishing up, and is used for quick leasons like the Matlotes, &c.

The sauce to which manied butter has been added should not boil if this can possibly be avoided, as it would thereby acquire a very disagreeable taste of raw flour.

Butter à la Meunière

Put into a frying-pan the necessary quantity of butter, and cook it gently until it has acquired a golden tint and exudes a slight smell of nut. Add a few drops of lemon-juice, and pour on the fish under treatment, which should have been previously sprinkled with concassed parsley.

This butter is proper to fish “à la Meunière” and is always served on the fish.

IS3—Montpellier Butter

Put into a saucepan containing boiling water equal quantities of watercress leaves, parsley, chervil, chives, and tarragon (six oz. in all), one and one-half oz. of chopped shallots, and one-half oz. of spinach leaves. Boil for two minutes, then drain, cool, press in a towel to expel water, and pound in a mortar with one tablespoonful of pressed capers, four oz. of gherkins, a garlic clove, and the fillets of four anchovies well washed.

Mix this paste with one and one-half lbs. of butter; then add the yolks of three boiled eggs and two raw eggs, and finally pour in, by degrees, two-fifths pint of oil. Strain through a fine sieve or through tammy, put the butter into a basin, and stir it well with a wooden spoon so as to make it smooth. Season with table-salt and a little cayenne.

Use this butter to deck large fish, such as salmon and trout; but it is also used for smaller pieces and slices of fish.

Remarks

When this butter is specially prepared to form a. coat on fish, the oil and the egg yolks are omitted and only butter is used.

Black Butter

Put into a frying-pan the necessary amount of butter, and cook it until it has assumed a brown colour and begins to smoke. At this moment add a large pinch of concassed parsley leaves and spread it immediately over the object to be treated.

Hazel-Nut Butter

Put eight oz. of shelled hazel-nuts, for a moment, in the front of the oven, in order to slightly grill their skins and make them easily removable. Now crush the nuts in a mortar until they form a paste, and add a few drops of cold water with a view to preventing their producing any oil. Add their equivalent in weight of butter and rub through tammy.

Pistachio Butter

Put into boiling water eight oz. of pistachios, and keep them on the side of the fire until the peel may be easily removed. Drain, cool in cold water, clean the pistachios, and finely pound while moistening them with a few drops of water.

Add two oz. of butter and pass through tammy.

Printanier Butter

These butters are made from all early-season vegetables, such as carrots, French beans, peas, and asparagus heads.

When dealing with green vegetables cook quickly in boiling, salted water, drain, dry, pound with their weight of butter, and rub through tammy.

With carrots: Mince and cook with consommé, sugar, and butter until the diluent is quite reduced. After cooling they are pounded with their own weight of butter and rubbed through tammy.

Chapter V Savoury Jellies or Aspics

Jellies are to cold cookery what consommés and stock are to hot. If anything, the former are perhaps more important, for a cold entrée—however perfect it may be in itself—is nothing without its accompanying jelly.

In the recipes which I give hereafter I have made a point of showing how melting jellies may be obtained, i.e., served in a sauce-boat simultaneously with the cold comestible, or actually poured over it custom nowadays.

This method of serving cold entrées, which I inaugurated at the Savoy Hotel with the “Suprême de Volaille Jeannette”, is the only one which allows of serving a jelly in a state of absolute perfection.

Nevertheless, if a more solid jelly were required, either for the decking of cold dishes or for a moulded entrée, there need only be added to the following formulæ a few gelatine leaves—more or less—according to the required firmness of the Jelly.

But it should not be forgotten that the greater the viscosity of the jelly the less value will the same possess.

The various uses of jellies are dealt with in Part II. of this work, where the formulæ of their divers accompanying dishes will also appear.

Ordinary Aspics

Stock for Ordinary Aspic—Quantities for making Four Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Strung knuckle of veal | 4 | lbs.
Strung knuckle of beef | 3 | lbs.
Veal bones, well broken up | 3 | lbs.
Calf’s feet, boned, and blanched | 3 | lb.
Fresh pork rind, well blanched and with fat removed | ½ | lb.

Mode of Procedure

Put the meats in a very clean and well-tinned stockpot or stewpan. Add eight quarts of cold water, boil, and skim after the manner indicated under Formula №1. Having well skimmed the stock add one oz. of salt, put it on the side of the fire, and let it boil gently for four hours. Then remove the meat, taking care not to disturb the stock. Carefully remove the fat, and garnish with one-half lb. of carrots, six oz. of onions, two oz. of leeks, a stick of celery, and a large faggot. Put the whole back on to the fire and cook gently for a further two hours. Strain through a sieve in to a very clean basin and leave to cool.

Clarification of Aspic

When the stock, prepared according to the above directions, has cooled, the grease that has formed on its surface should be removed. Then pour off gently into a stewpan of convenient size in such a way as to prevent the deposit at the bottom of the basin from mixing with the clear liquor. Test the consistence of the aspic, when it should be found that the quantities given above have proved sufficient to form a fairly firm jelly. If, however, this be not the case, a few leaves of gelatine steeped in cold water should be added, being careful not to overdo the quantity. Now add to the stock two lbs. of lean beef (first minced and then pounded together with the white of an egg), a little chervil and tarragon, and a few drops of lemon-juice. Place the saucepan on an open fire, stir its contents with a spatula until the liquid begins to boil, remove it from the fire, and place it on the side of the stove, where it may boil gently for half an hour.

At the end of this time take the saucepan off the fire and remove what little grease has formed on the aspic while cooking. Strain through a serviette stretched and fastened across the legs of an overturned stool, and let the aspic fall into a basin placed between the legs. Ascertain whether the liquid is quite clear, and if, as frequently happens, this be not the case, what has already been strained should once more be passed through the serviette, renewing the operation until the aspic becomes quite transparent.

Flavouring the Aspic

The aspic obtained as above is limpid, has an agreeable savour, and is the colour of fine amber. It now only requires flavouring according to the tastes of the consumer and the purpose for which it is intended. For this operation it should be allowed to become quite tepid, and the following quantities of choice wine are added to it, viz.:

If the wine is of a liqueur kind, such as Sherry, Marsala, Madeira, &c., one-fifth pint per quart.
If it is another kind of wine, for example, champagne, hock, &c., one-fourth pint per quart.

The wine used should be very clear, free from any deposit, and as perfect as possible in taste.

Chicken Aspic

The quantities of meat are the same as for ordinary aspic; there need only be added to it either two oven-browned hens, or their equivalent in weight of roasted fowl carcases, and poultry giblets if these are handy. It is always better, however, to prepare the stock with the hens and giblets and to keep the carcases for the clarification. This clarification follows the same rules as that of the ordinary aspic, except that a few roasted-fowl carcases, previously well freed from fat, are added to it.

In the case of this particularly delicate aspic, it is more than ever necessary not to overdo the amount of gelatine. It should be easily soluble to the palate in order to be perfect.

160—Game Aspic

Prepare this aspic stock in exactly the same way as that of ordinary aspic, only substitute game, such as deer, roebuck, doe, or hare, or wild rabbit (previously browned in the oven), for the beef. When possible also add to this stock a few old specimens of feathered game, such as partridges or pheasants that are too tough for other purposes and which suit admirably here.

The clarification changes according to the different flavours which are to be given to the aspic. If it is not necessary to give it a special characteristic, it should be prepared with the meat of that ground game which happens to be most available at the time, adding to the quantity used roast carcases of feathered game, the respective amounts of both ingredients being the same as for ordinary aspic. If, on the other hand, the aspic is to have a well-defined flavour, the meat used for the clarification should naturally be that producing the flavour in question, i.e., either partridge or pheasant, or hazel-hen, &c.

Some aspics are greatly improved by being flavoured with a small quantity of old brandy. Rather than use an inferior kind of this ingredient, however, I should advise its total omission from the aspic.

Without aromatisation the aspic, though imperfect, is passable; but aromatised with bad brandy it is invariably spoilt.

Lenten Aspics

Fish Aspic with White Wine

The stock for this aspic is prepared in precisely the same manner as fish stock, Formula №11. The stewpan need not, however, be buttered previous to the insertion of the onions, parsley-stalks, and fish-bones. If the aspic is not required to be quite white, a little saffron may be added to it, as the aroma of this condiment blends so perfectly with that of fish.

When the stock is prepared its consistence should be tested, and rectified, if necessary, by means of gelatine. The quantity of this substance should on no account exceed eight leaves per quart of aspic, and, at the risk of repeating myself, I remind the reader that the less gelatine is used the better the aspic will be.

The clarification should be made with fresh caviare if possible, but pressed caviare is also admirably suited to this purpose. The quantities are the same as for the clarification of fish consommé, Formula №4.

In flavouring white fish aspics either dry champagne or a good Bordeaux or Burgundy may be used. Take care, however:

That the wine used be of an unquestionably good quality.
That it be only added to the aspic when the latter is already cold and on the point of coagulating, as this is the only means of preserving all the aroma of the wine.

Finally, in certain cases, a special flavour may be obtained by the use of crayfish, which are cooked, as for bisque, then pounded, and added to the fish stock (Formula №11 ten minutes before straining it. A proportion of four little crayfish à bisque per quart of aspic is sufficient to secure an excellent aroma.

162—Fish Aspic with Red Wine

This aspic stock is the Court-bouillon with red wine Formula №165, which has served in cooking the fish for which the aspic is intended; this fish is generally either trout or salmon; sometimes also, but less commonly, a carp or a pike.

This stock must first of all have its grease thoroughly removed; it should then be poured carefully away, reduced if necessary, and the required quantity of gelatine added. This cannot be easily determined, as all gelatines are not alike, and the stock may have contracted a certain consistence from its contact with the fish. One can, therefore, only be guided by testing small quantities cooled in ice, but care should be taken that the aspic be not too firm.

The clarification of this aspic is generally made with white of egg in the proportion of one white per quart. The white, half-whisked, is added to the cold stock, and the latter is put over an open fire and stirred with a spatula. As soon as it boils the aspic is poured through a serviette fixed on to the legs of an overturned stool. The first drippings of the fluid are put back on to the serviette if they do not seem clear, and this operation is repeated until the required clearness is obtained.

It almost invariably happens that, either during the cooking of the fish or during the clarification, the wine loses its colour through the precipitation of the colouring elements derived from the tannin.

The only way of overcoming this difficulty is to add a few drops of liquid carmine or vegetable red; but, in any case, it is well to remember that the colour of red-wine aspic must never be deeper than a sombre pink.

Chapter VI The Court-bouillons and the Marinades

Court-Bouillon with Vinegar

Quantities Required for Five Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Water | 5 | quarts
Vinegar | ½ | pint
Grey salt | 2 | oz.
Peppercorns | ½ | oz.
Carrots | ¾ | lb.
A little thyme and bay
Parsley stalks | 2 | oz.

Preparation

Put into a saucepan the water, salt, and vinegar, the minced carrots and onions, and the parsley, thyme, and bay, gathered into a bunch. Boil, allow to simmer for one hour, rub through tammy, and put aside until wanted.

Remarks

Put the peppercorns into the court-bouillon only twelve minutes before straining the latter. If the pepper were in for too long a time it would give a bitterness to the preparation. This rule also applies to the formulæ that follow, in which the use of peppercorns is also required.

This court-bouillon is principally used for cooking trout and salmon, as well as for various shell-fish.

Court-Bouillon with White Wine

Quantities Required for Two Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
White wine | 1 | quart
Water | 1 | quart
Minced onions | 3 | oz.
Large faggot | 1
Grey salt | ½ | oz.
Peppercorns | a few

Preparation

This is the same as for the court-bouillon with vinegar, except that it is boiled for half an hour and is strained through tammy.

Remarks

If the court-bouillon has to be reduced the quantity of salt should be proportionately less. This preparation is principally used for poaching fresh-water fish.

Plain Court-Bouillon

The quantity of court-bouillon is determined by the size of the piece which it is to cover. It is composed of cold, salt water (the salt amounting to a little less than one-half oz. per quart of water), one-quarter pint of milk per quart of water, and one thin slice of peeled lemon in the same proportion. The fish is immersed while the liquor is cold; the latter is very slowly brought to the boil, and as soon as this is reached, the receptacle is moved to the side of the fire, where the cooking of the fish is completed.

This court-bouillon, which is used with large pieces of turbot and brill, is never prepared beforehand.

Special Court-Bouillon, or Blanc

This preparation is a genuine court-bouillon, though it is not used in cooking fish.

The Quantities Required for Five Quarts of this Court-bouillon

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Flour | 2 | oz.
Grey salt | 1½ | quart
Juice of lemons or good vinegar | 3 or ⅛ pint |
Water | 5 | quarts

Gradually mix the flour and the water; add the salt and the lemon juice, and pass through a strainer. Set to boil, and stir the mixture the while, in order to prevent the flour from precipitating; as soon as the boil is reached, immerse the objects to be treated. These are usually calf’s head or foot, previously blanched; sheep’s trotters, cocks’ kidneys or combs, or such vegetables as salsify, cardoon, &c.

Remarks upon the use of Court-Bouillon

Court-bouillon must always be prepared in advance for all fish, the time for poaching which is less than half an hour, except turbots and brills.
When a fish is of such a size as to need more than half an hour’s poaching, proceed as follows: Place under the drainer of the fish-kettle the minced carrots and onions and the faggot; put the fish on the drainer, and cover it with water and vinegar, or white wine, in accordance with the kind of court-bouillon wanted and the quantity required. Add the salt, boil, and keep the court-bouillon gently simmering for a period of time fixed by the weight of the fish. The time allowed for poaching the latter will be given in their respective formulæ.
Fish, when whole, should be immersed in cold court-bouillon; when sliced, in the same liquor, boiling. The exceptions to this rule are small trout “au bleu” and shell-fish.
If fish be cooked in short liquor the aromatics are put under the drainer and the liquid elements of the selected court-bouillon (as, for example, that with red or white wine) are so calculated as to cover only one-third of the solid body. Fish cooked in this way should be frequently basted.
Court-bouillon for ordinary and spiny lobsters should always be at full boiling pitch when these are immersed. The case is the same for small or medium fish “au bleu”.
Fish which is to be served cold, also shell-fish, should cool in the court-bouillon itself; the cooking period is consequently curtailed.

Marinades and Brines

Marinades play but a small part in English cookery, venison or other ground-game being generally preferred fresh. However, in the event of its being necessary to resort to these methods of preparation, I shall give two formulæ for venison and two for mutton.

The use of the marinade for venison is very much debated. Certainly it is often desirable that the fibre of those meats that come from old specimens of the deer and boar species be softened, but there is no doubt that what the meat gains in tenderness it loses in flavour. On the whole, therefore, it would be best to use only those joints which come from young beasts.

In the case of the latter, the marinade may well be dispensed with. It would add nothing to the savour of a haunch of venison, such as may be got in England, while it would be equally ineffectual in the case of the roebuck or hare. A summary treatment of these two, with raw marinade, may well be adopted, as also for deer.

As for cooked marinade, its real and only use lies in the fact that during stormy summer weather it enables one to preserve meat which would otherwise have to be wasted. It may, moreover, be used for braised venison, but this treatment of game is very uncommon nowadays.

Cooked Marinade for Venison

The Quantities Required for Five Quarts of this Court-bouillon

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Minced carrots | ½ | lb.
Minced onions | ½ | lb.
Minced shallots | 2 | oz.
Crushed garlic clove. | 1
Faggot, including 1 oz. of parsley stalks, 2 sprigs of rosemary, as much thyme, and 2 bay leaves. | 1

Preparation

Heat one-half pint of oil in a stewpan, add the carrots and onions, and fry them while stirring frequently. When they begin to brown add the shallots, the garlic, and the faggot, then one pint of vinegar, two bottles of white wine, and three quarts of water. Cook this marinade for twenty minutes, and add a further two oz. of salt, one-half oz. of peppercorns, and four oz. of brown sugar. Ten minutes afterwards pass it through a strainer and let it cool before inserting the meats.

N.B.—In summer the marinade very often decomposes because of the blood contained by the meat under treatment in it. The only means of averting this is to boil the marinade every two or three days at least.

Raw Marinade for Butcher’s Meat or Venison

This marinade is prepared immediately before using. The meat to be treated is first salted and peppered on all sides, then it is put in a receptacle just large enough to hold it, and laid therein on a litter of aromatics, including minced carrots and onions, a few chopped shallots, parsley stalks, thyme, and bay in proportion to the rest. Now sprinkle the meat copiously with oil and half as much vinegar; cover the dish with oil-paper, and put it somewhere in the cool. Remember to turn the meat over three or four times a day, covering it each time with a layer of vegetables.

This marinade is very active, and is admirably suited to all butcher’s meat and venison, provided these be not allowed to remain in it for too long a time. It is very difficult to say how long the meat must stay in these marinades; the time varies according to the size and quality of the joints, and the taste of the consumer, &c. All that can be said is that three hours should be sufficient to marinade a cutlet or escalope of roebuck, and that for big joints such as saddle or leg the time should not exceed four days.

Marinade for Mutton, Roebuck-Style

This is exactly the same as cooked marinade, Formula №168. There need only be added one oz. of juniper berries, a few sprigs of rosemary, wild thyme, and basil, two extra garlic cloves, and one quart less of water.

Marinade with Red Wine for Mutton

By substituting red wine for white in the preceding formula the quantity of the liquid equalling that of the water—and by slightly increasing the quantity of aromatics, an excellent marinade for mutton is obtained, which in summer enables one to preserve meat, otherwise perishable, for some days.

Brine

Quantities Required for Fifty Quarts

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Grey salt | 56 | lbs.
Water | 50 | quarts
Saltpetre | 6 | lbs.
Brown sugar | 3½ | lbs.

Mode of Procedure

Put the salt and the water in a tinned copper pan, and put it on an open fire. When the water boils, throw in a peeled potato, and, if the latter float, add water until it begins to sink. If, on the contrary, the potato should sink immediately, reduce the liquid until it is able to buoy the tuber up. At this stage the sugar and saltpetre are added; let them dissolve, and the brine is then removed from the fire and is allowed to cool. It is then poured into the receptacle intended for it, which must be either of slate, stone, cement, or well-jointed tiles. It is well to place in the bottom of this reservoir a wooden lattice, whereon the meats to be salted may be laid, for, were the immersed objects to lie directly on the bottom of the receptacle, the under parts would be entirely shielded from the brine.

If the meats to be salted are of an appreciable size, they should be inoculated with brine by means of a special syringe. Without this measure it would be impossible to salt regularly, as the sides would already be over-saturated before the centre had even been properly reached.

Eight days should be allowed for salting a piece of beef of what size soever, above eight or ten lb., since the process of inoculation equalises the salting.

Ox-tongue intended for salting, besides having to be as fresh as possible, must be trimmed of almost all the cartilage of the throat, and carefully beaten either with a beater or roller. Then it must be pricked on all sides with a string-needle, and immersed in the liquid, where it should be slightly weighted by some means or other in order to prevent its rising to the surface. A medium-sized tongue would need about seven days’ immersion in the brine.

Though brine does not turn as easily as the cooked marinades, it would be well, especially in stormy weather, to watch it and occasionally to boil it. But, as the process of boiling invariably concentrates the brine, a little water should be added to it every time it is so treated, and the test of the potato, described above, should always be resorted to.

Chapter VII 1. Elementary Preparations

Before broaching the question of the numerous preparations which constitute the various soup, relevé, and entrée garnishes, it will be necessary to give the formulae of the elementary preparations, or what are technically called the mise en place. If the various operations which go to make the mise en place were not, at least summarily, discussed here, I should be compelled to repeat them in each formula for which they are required—that is to say, in almost every formula. I should thus resemble those bad operators who, having neglected their mise en place, are obliged to make it in the course of other work, and thereby not only run the risk of making it badly, but also of losing valuable time which might be used to better advantage.

Elementary preparations consist of those things whereof one is constantly in need, which may be prepared in advance, and which are kept available for use at a moment’s notice.

Anchovies (Fillets of)

Whether they be for hors d’œuvres or for culinary use, it is always best to have these handy.

After having washed and well wiped them, in order to remove the white powder resulting from the little scales with which they are covered, they should be neatly trimmed to the shape of extended oblongs. Then detach the fillets from the bones by gentle pulling, divide each fillet lengthwise into three or four smaller fillets, put the latter into a small narrow dish or a little bowl, and cover them with oil. The fillets may also be kept whole with a view to rolling them into rings.

Anglaise (for Egg-and-Bread–Crumbing)

It is well to have this always ready for those dishes which are to be panés à l’anglaise, or as many of the recipes direct: treated à l’anglaise.

It is made of well-whisked eggs, salt, pepper, and one dessertspoonful of oil per couple of eggs.

Its uses

The solids to be panés à l’anglaise are dipped into the preparation described above, taking care that the latter coats them thoroughly; whereupon, according to the requirements, they are rolled either in bread-crumbs or in fine raspings. From this combination of egg with bread-crumbs or raspings there results a kind of coat which, at the moment of contact with the hot fat, is immediately converted into a resisting crust. In croquettes this crust checks the escape, into the fat, of the substances it encloses, and this is more especially the case when the croquettes contain some reduced sauce, or are composed of raw meats or fish whose juices are thereby entirely retained. A solid prepared à l’anglaise and cooked in fat should always be put into the latter when this is very hot, so as to ensure the instantaneous solidification of the egg and breadcrumbs.

N.B.—Objects to be treated à l’anglaise are generally rolled in flour before being immersed in the anglaise, for the flour helps the foregoing to adhere to the object.

The crust formed over the solid thus acquires a density which is indispensable.

Aromatics

Aromatics play a very prominent part in cookery, and their combination with the condiments constitutes, as Grinod de la Reynière said, “the hidden soul of cooking”. Their real object, in fact, is to throw the savour of dishes into relief, to intensify that savour, and to give each culinary preparation its particular stamp.

They are all derived from the vegetable kingdom; but, while some are used dry, others are used fresh.

The first-named should belong to the permanent kitchen stock; they are: sage, basil, rosemary, sweet marjoram, thyme, and bay.

Also to be included in the permanent stock are: cinnamon, ginger, juniper-berries, nutmeg, cloves, mace, and vanilla.

The last-named comprise those aromatic herbs used fresh, such as: parsley, chervil, tarragon, pimpernel, and common savory; while, under this head, there may also be included bits of common- and Seville-orange rind and zests of lemon rind.

Seasoning and Condiments

Seasonings are divided into several classes, which comprise:

Saline seasonings

Salt, spiced salt, saltpetre.

Acid seasonings

Plain vinegar, or the same aromatised with tarragon; verjuice, lemon juice, and common- or Seville-orange juices.

Hot seasonings

Peppercorns, ground or concassed pepper, or mignonette; paprika, curry, cayenne, and compound spices.

Saccharine seasonings

Sugar and honey.

Condiments are likewise subdivided, the three classes being:

The pungents

Onions, shallots, garlic, chives, and horseradish.

Hot condiments

Mustard, gherkins, capers, English sauces, such as Worcester, Harvey, Ketchup, Escoffier’s sauces, &c.; the wines used in reductions and braisings; the finishing elements of sauces and soups.

Fatty substances

Most animal fats, butter, vegetable greases (edible oils and cocoanut butter).

Remarks

In cookery it should be borne in mind that both excellence and eatableness depend entirely upon a judicious use and a rational blending of the aromatics, seasonings, and condiments. And, according as the latter have been used and apportioned, their action will be either beneficial or injurious to the health of the consumer.

In the matter of seasoning there can be no question of approximation or half measures; the quantities must be exact, allowing only of slight elasticity in respect of the various tastes to be satisfied.

Clarified Butter

A certain quantity of clarified butter should always be kept ready and handy.

To prepare this butter, put one lb. to melt in a saucepan large enough to hold twice that amount. Place the saucepan on the side of the fire, over moderate heat; remove all the scum which rises to the surface, and, when the butter looks quite clear and all foreign substances have dropped to the bottom, put the liquid carefully away and strain it through muslin.

Faggots (Bouquet Garnis)

The name “faggot” is given to those little bunches of aromatics which, when the contrary is not stated, are generally composed (in order to weigh one ounce) of eight-tenths oz. of parsley stalks and roots, one-tenth oz. of bay leaves, and one-tenth oz. of thyme. These various aromatics are put neatly together so that no sprig of the one sticks out beyond the others, and they are properly strung together.

Chervil

Chopped Chervil

Clean the chervil and remove the stalks wash, dry it well while tossing it, then chop it finely and put it aside on a plate in the cool, if it is not for immediate use.

Concassed Chervil

Proceed as above, except that, instead of chopping it, compress it between the fingers and slice it after the manner of a chaff-cutter. Concussed and chopped chervil are, if possible, only prepared at the last moment.

Chervil Pluches

The pluches are greatly used in the finishing off of soups. They are, practically, the serrated portions only of the leaves, which are torn away in such a manner as to show no trace of the veinings. They are immersed in water, and at the last moment withdrawn, so as to be added, raw, to either soups or boiling consommés.

Raspings

Golden raspings are obtained by pounding and passing through a fine sieve bread-crusts which have been previously well dried in the oven.

White raspings are similarly prepared, except that very dry, white crumb is used.

Peeled, Channelled, and Zested Lemons

Lemons are greatly used in cookery, as dish and comestible garnish. When a whole lemon is used for marinades of fish, for the “blancs”, &c., it is well to peel it to the pulp, i.e., to remove the peel and the whole of the underlying white. The lemon is then cut into more or less large slices, according to the use for which it is intended.

The rind of a lemon thus peeled may be cut into bits and used in this form as the necessity arises. When cutting it up, flatten the rind inside uppermost on the table, and, with a very sharp and flexible knife, remove all the white; then slice the remaining peel (which constitutes what is called zest) into strips about one inch wide, and cut these laterally in fine julienne-fashion.

Scald the resulting bits for five minutes, cool them, drain them carefully, and put them aside until wanted. Sometimes, instead of cutting julienne-fashion, the zest may be finely chopped, but the rest of the process remains the same.

Lemons are channelled by means of a little knife, or a special instrument for the purpose, which excises parallel ribbons from the surface of the rind and lays the white bare. A lemon channelled in this way is cut in two, lengthwise with the core; its two extremities are removed, and the two halves are cut laterally into thin, regular slices to look like serrated half-discs.

The lemon may also be cut at right angles to the core.

Fried fish, oysters, and certain game are generally garnished with lemon slices fashioned according to the taste of the cook but the simplest, and perhaps the best, way is to cut the lemon through the centre, after having trimmed the two ends quite straight, and then to remove the rind roughly from the edge.

For whatever purpose the lemon be intended, it should be, as far as possible, only prepared at the last moment. If it must be prepared beforehand, it would be well to keep it in a bowl of fresh water.

Shallots

Chopped Shallots

Clean the shallots, and, by means of a very sharp knife, cut them lengthwise into thin slices; let these cling together by not allowing the knife to cut quite through them, and, this done, turn them half round and proceed in the same way at right angles to the other cuts.

Finally, cut them laterally, and this will be found to produce very fine and regular, small cubes.

Ciseled Shallots

The name “ciseled shallots” is often erroneously given to those shallots resulting from the above process.

But ciseled shallots are merely laterally sliced, the result of which operation is a series of thin, regular discs. Ciseled or chopped shallots should, when possible, only be prepared when required; if, however, they must be treated in advance, they should be kept somewhere in the cool until wanted.

Spices

Strictly speaking, spices include cinnamon, nutmeg, ginger, mace; and the many varieties of peppers and pimenta, cayenne, paprika, &c.

These various condiments are found ready-made on the market, and they need only be kept dry in air-tight boxes in order to prevent the escape of their aroma.

But there is another kind of preparation, in cookery, to which the name of spice or all-spice is more especially given.

Nowadays several market varieties of this preparation exist, and vie with each other for custom, though in most cases they deserve it equally well.

Formerly this was not so, and every chef had his own formula.

The following is a recipe for the spice in question, which would be found useful if it had to be prepared at a moment’s notice:

Obtain the following, very dry

Ingredient | Amount
Quantity | Unit
Bay leaves | 5 | oz.
Thyme (half of it wild, if possible). | 3 | oz.
Coriander | 3 | oz.
Cinnamon | 4 | oz.
Nutmeg | 6 | oz.
Cloves | 4 | oz.
Ginger root | 3 | oz.
Mace | 3 | oz.
Mixed pepper (half black and half white) | 10 | oz.
Cayenne | 1 | oz.

Put all these ingredients into a mortar and pound them until they are all able to pass through a very fine sieve. Put the resulting powder into an air-tight box, which must be kept dry.

Before being used, this spice is generally mixed with salt (Formula №188).

Flour

For whatever use the flour is intended, it is always best to sift it. This is more particularly necessary in the case of flour used for coating objects to be fried; for the latter, being first dipped into milk, must of necessity let a few drops of that liquid fall into the flour they are rolled in. Lumps would therefore form, which might adhere to the objects to be fried if the flour were not sifted.

Herb Juice

This is to finish or intensify certain preparations.

To prepare it, throw into a small saucepan of boiling water some parsley, chervil, and tarragon and chive leaves, in equal quantities, according to the amount of juice required.

Set to boil for two minutes, drain, cool, press the herbs in a towel, twisting the latter; pound very finely, and extract the juice from the resulting paste by twisting a strong towel round it.

Keep this juice in the cool.

Bread-Crumbs

Thoroughly rub, in a closed towel, some stale bread-crumb previously well broken up. Pass it through a fine sieve or colander, according as to whether it is required very fine or not, and put it aside in a convenient receptacle.

Chopped Onion

Cut the onion finely, like the shallots, but if it is to be minced with a view to making it even finer, it should be freed of its pungent juice, which would cause it to blacken with exposure to the air.

To accomplish this, put the onion in the corner of a towel, pour plenty of cold water over it, and twist the towel in order to express the water. By this means the onion remains quite white.

Turned or Stoned Olives

There are special instruments for stoning olives, but, failing these, cut the fruit spirally from the stone with the point of a small knife.

Keep the olives in slightly salted water.

Parsley

Chopped Parsley

If parsley be properly chopped, no juice should be produced. If, on the contrary, the operation be performed badly, it amounts to a process of pounding which, perforce, expresses the juice.

In the latter case the particles cohere, and they are sprinkled with difficulty over an object. To remedy this shortcoming, wash the choppings in fresh water, as in the case of the onion, pressing in a similar manner so as to expel the water.

Concassed Parsley

Is that kind which is roughly chopped. When a culinary preparation is dressed with concassed parsley, the latter should be added to it a few moments before serving, in order to undergo a slight cooking process; whereas chopped parsley may be strewn over a dish at the last moment.

It should be remembered that parsley, when quite fresh and used in moderation, is an excellent thing; but, should it have remained too long in the heat, it becomes quite insufferable.

I cannot, therefore, too strongly urge the advisability of using it in the freshest possible state, and it would even be wiser to discard it entirely than to be forced to ignore this condition.

Parsley Sprays

These are chiefly used in garnishing dishes, and it is well for the purpose to make as much use as possible of the curled-leaf kind, after having removed the long stalks. Keep the sprays in fresh water until required.

Fried Parsley

This consists of the sprays, well drained of water after washing, and immersed for an instant in very hot fat. The moment it is fried carefully drain it, salt it, and place it in a clean towel, where it may get rid of any superfluous grease. It is used to dress fried viands.

Salt

Two kinds of salt are used in cooking, viz., grey, or sea-salt, and rock-salt. Grey-salt is used more especially for Brines and in the preparation of ices, as its grey colour does not allow of its being used indiscriminately.

Be this as it may, many prefer it to rock-salt for the salting of stock-pots, roasts, and grills. For the last two purposes it is crushed with a roller, without being pounded, and the result should be such that every grain is distinctly perceptible to the touch.

This salt, in melting over a roast or a grill, certainly imparts a supplementary flavour to the latter which could not be got with the use of rock-salt.

Rock Salt

This is found on the market in the forms of cooking and table-salt. If the kitchen is only supplied with cooking salt, the quantity required for several days should be dried, pounded in the mortar, and passed through a fine sieve; and then put aside in a dry place for use when wanted. Even table-salt, as it reaches one from the purveyor, sometimes needs drying and passing through a sieve before being used.

Spiced Salt

This condiment, which serves an important purpose in the preparation of pies and galantines, is obtained from a mixture of one lb. of table salt with three and one-half oz. of spices (Formula №181).

This kind of salt should be carefully kept in a very dry place.

2. The Various Kinds of Garnishes for Soups, Relevés, and Entrées, Hot or Cold

Stuffings and Forcemeats

Various Panadas for Stuffings

Panadas are those preparations which go to make the leason of forcemeats and which ensure their proper consistence when they are cooked. They are not necessary to every forcemeat; for the mousseline kind, which are the finest and lightest, do not require them. Nevertheless, they are useful for varying the taste and the uses of forcemeats, and I thought it advisable to introduce them here. The reader will thus be able to use either forcemeats with a panada base or mousseline forcemeats; in accordance with the requirements and his resources.

A. Bread Panada

Put one-half lb. of the crumb of bread and one-half oz, of salt into one-half pint of boiling milk. When the crumb has absorbed all the milk, place the saucepan over a brisk fire and stir with a spatula until the paste has become so thick as not to cling any longer to the end of the spatula. Turn the contents of the saucepan into a buttered platter, and lightly butter the surface of the panada in order to avoid its drying while it cools.

B. Flour Panada

Put into a small saucepan one-half pint of water, a little salt, and two oz. of butter. When the liquid boils add five oz. of sifted flour thereto, stirring the while over a brisk fire until it reaches the consistence described in the case of bread panada. Use the same precautions with regard to cooling.

C. Frangipan Panada

Put into a stewpan four oz. of sifted flour, the yolks of four eggs, a little salt, pepper, and nutmeg. Now add by degrees three oz. of melted butter and dilute with one-half pint of boiled milk. Pass through a strainer, stir over the lire until the boil is reached; set to cook for five minutes while gently wielding the whisk, and cool as in the preceding cases.

Chicken Forcemeat with Panada and Butter

Remove the tendons from, and cut into cubes, one lb. of chicken-meat. Pound, and add one-third oz. of salt, a little pepper and nutmeg. When the meat is well pounded remove it from the mortar, and place in its stead one-half lb. of very cold panada (see Formula №190). Finely pound this panada, and then add one-half lb. of butter thereto, taking care that the two ingredients mix thoroughly. Now put in the chicken-meat,and wield the pestle vigorously until the whole mass is completely mixed. Finally, add consecutively two whole eggs and the yolks of four, stirring incessantly the while and seeing that each egg is only inserted when the one preceding it has become perfectly incorporated with the mass. Rub through a sieve, put the forcemeat into a basin, and smooth it with a wooden spoon.

Test the forcemeat by poaching a small portion of it in salted, boiling water. This test, which is indispensable, allows of rectifying the seasoning and the consistence if necessary. If it be found that the forcemeat is too light, a little white of egg could be mingled with it; if, on the ether hand, it should be too stiff add a little softened butter.

N.B.—By substituting for chicken veal, game, or fish, &c., any kind of forcemeat may be made; for the quantities of the other ingredients remain the same whatever the basic meat may be.

Chicken Forcemeat with Panada and Cream

(For Fine Quenelles.)

Finely pound one lb. of chicken-meat after having removed the tendons, and seasoned with one-quarter oz. of salt, a little pepper and nutmeg.

When the meat has been reduced to a fine paste, add, very gradually, two oz. of white of egg. Finish with seven oz. of Frangipan Panada (Formula №192), and work vigorously with the pestle until the whole is amalgamated. Strain through a fine sieve, put the forcemeat into a vegetable-pan sufficiently large to allow of ultimately working it with ease, and place it on dee for a good hour.

This done, stir the forcemeat (still on the ice) for a few seconds with a wooden spoon, then add, in small quantities at a time, one pint of raw cream. At this stage complete the preparation by adding thereto one-half pint of whipped cream. It should then be found to be very white, smooth, and mellow. Test as directed in the preceding recipe, and add a little white of egg if it be too light, and a little cream if it be too stiff.

N.B. This forcemeat may be prepared from all butcher’s meats, game, or fish.

Fine Chicken Forcemeat or “Mousseline”

Remove the tendons from, trim, and cut into cubes, one lb. of chicken-meat. Season with one oz. of salt, a little pepper and nutmeg.

Finely pound, and, when it is reduced to a paste, gradually add the whites of two eggs, vigorously working with the pestle meanwhile.

Strain through a fine sieve, put the forcemeat into a vegetable-pan, stir it once more with the wooden spoon for a moment or two, and combine with it, gradually, one pint of thick, fresh cream, working with great caution and keeping the receptacle on ice.

Remarks Relative to Mousseline Forcemeat

This, like the preceding forcemeats, may be prepared from any kind of meat. The addition of the white of egg is not essential if the meats used already possess a certain quantity of albumen; but without the white of egg the forcemeat absorbs much less cream.

This forcemeat is particularly suited to preparations with a shell-fish base. Incomparably delicate results are obtained by the process, while it also furnishes ideal quenelles for the purpose of garnishing soup. In a word,it maybe said of mousseline forcemeat that, whereas it can replace all other kinds, none of these can replace it.

N.B.— Mousseline forcemeats of all kinds, with meat, poultry, game, fish, or shell-fish, may be made according to the principles and quantities given above.

Pork Forcemeat for Divers Uses

Remove the tendons of, and cut into large cubes, two lbs. of fillet of pork, and the same weight of fresh, fat bacon. Season with one and three-quarter oz. of Spiced Salt (Formula №188), chop the fillet and bacon up, together or separately, pound them finely in the mortar, and finish with two eggs and two tablespoonfuls of brandy.

This forcemeat is used for ordinary pies and terrines. Strictly speaking, it is “sausage-meat”. The inclusion of eggs in this forcemeat really only obtains when it is used to stuff joints that are to be braised, such as stuffed breast of veal; or in the case of pies and terrines. The addition of the egg in these cases prevents the grease from melting too quickly, and thus averts the drying of the forcemeat.

Forcemeat for Galantines, Pies and Terrines

Remove the tendons from, and cut into cubes, one lb. of fillet of veal and as much fillet of pork; add to these two lbs. of fresh, fat bacon, also cut into cubes. Season with three oz. of Spiced Salt, chop the three ingredients together or apart, and then finely pound them. Finish with three eggs and three tablespoonfuls of burnt brandy, strain through a sieve, and place in a basin.

When about to serve this stuffing, add to it a little fumet corresponding with the meat that is to constitute the dish. For terrines, pies, and galantines of game, one-quarter or one-fifth of the forcemeat’s weight of gratin stuffing (proper to the game under treatment) is added.

Veal Forcemeat with Fat or Godiveau

Remove the tendons from, and cut into cubes, one lb. of fillet of veal; also pare, i.e., detach skin and filaments from, two lbs. of the very dry fat of kidneys of beef. First, chop these up separately, then combine and pound them in the mortar. Season with one-half oz. of salt, a little pepper, some nutmeg, and pound afresh until the veal and fat become a homogeneous mass. Now add four eggs, consecutively, and at intervals of a few minutes, without ceasing to pound, and taking care only to insert each egg after the preceding one has been properly mixed with the mass. Spread the forcemeat thus prepared on a dish, and put the latter on ice until the next day.

The next day pound once more, and add little by little fourteen oz. of very clean ice (in small pieces); or, instead, an equal weight of iced water, adding this also very gradually.

When the godiveau is properly moistened, poach a small portion of it in boiling water in order to test its consistence. If it be too firm, add some more ice to it; if, on the other hand, it seem too flimsy, add a little of the white of an egg. For the uses of godiveau and quenelles see Formula №205.

Veal Forcemeat with Fat And Cream

Chop finely and apart one lb. of very white fillet of veal, with tendons removed, cut into cubes, and one lb. of the fat of pared kidney of beef.

Combine the veal and the fat in the mortar, and pound until the two ingredients form a fine and even paste. Season with one-half oz. of salt, a little pepper, and some nutmeg, and add consecutively two eggs and two yolks, after the manner of the preceding recipe and without ceasing to pound. Strain through a sieve, spread the forcemeat on a dish, and keep it on ice until the next day.

Next day pound the forcemeat again for a few minutes, and add to it, little by little, one and one-half pints of cream.

Test as before, and rectify if necessary, either by adding cream or by thickening with the white of an egg.

Chicken Forcemeat for Galantines, Pies and Terrines

The exact weight of chicken-meat used as the base of this forcemeat determines the quantities of its other ingredients. Thus the weight of meat afforded by a fowl weighing four lbs. is estimated at twenty oz. after deducting the fillets which are always reserved. Hence the quantities for the forcemeat are regulated thus:—

Chicken-meat, twenty oz.; lean pork, eight oz.; fillet of veal, eight oz.; fresh, fat bacon, thirty oz.; whole eggs, five; Spiced Salt, two oz.; brandy, one-fifth pint.

Chop up, either together or apart, the chicken-meat, the veal, the pork, and the bacon. Put all these into the mortar, pound them very finely with the seasoning, add the eggs consecutively, and, last of all, pour in the brandy.

Remarks

The quantity of spiced salt varies, a few grammes either way, according as to whether the atmosphere be dry or damp,
According to the purpose of the forcemeat, and with a view to giving it a finer flavour, one may, subject to the resources at one’s disposal, add a little raw trimmings of foie gras to it; but the latter must not, in any case, exceed one-fifth of the forcemeat in weight.
As a rule, forcemeat should always be rubbed through a sieve so as to ensure its being fine and even.
Whether the foie gras be added or not, chicken forcemeat may always be completed with two or three oz. of chopped truffles per lb. of its volume.

Game Forcemeat for Pies and Terrines

This follows the same principles as the chicken forcemeat, i.e., the weight of the game-meat determines the quantities of the other ingredients. The proportions are precisely the same as above as regards the veal, the pork, the bacon, and the seasoning. The procedure is also the same, while the appended remarks likewise apply.

Gratin Forcemeat for Ordinary Hot, Raised Pies

Put into a sauté-pan containing one oz. of very hot butter, one-half lb. of fresh, fat bacon, cut into large cubes, brown quickly, and drain on a dish.

Quickly brown in the same butter one-half lb. of fillet of veal cut like the bacon and drain in the same way.

Now rapidly brown one-half lb. of pale, calf’s liver, also cut into large cubes. Put the veal and the bacon back into the sauté-pan with the liver, add the necessary quantity of salt and pepper, two oz. of mushroom parings, one oz. of truffle parings (raw if possible), chopped shallots, a sprig of thyme, and a fragment of bay. Put the whole on the fire for two minutes, drain the bacon, the veal, and the liver, and put the gravy aside. Swill the sauté-pan with one-quarter pint of Madeira.

Pound the bacon, veal, and liver quickly and finely, while adding consecutively six oz. of butter, the yolks of six eggs, the gravy that has been put aside, one-third pint of cold, reduced Espagnole, and the Madeira used for swilling.

Strain through a sieve, place in a tureen, and smooth with the wooden spoon.

N.B.—To make a gratin forcemeat with game, substitute for the veal that game-meat which may happen to be required.

Pike Forcemeat for Quenelles à La Lyonnaise

Forcemeats prepared with the flesh of the pike are extremely delicate. Subject to circumstances, they may be prepared according to any one of the three formulæ (№193, №194, №195). There is another excellent method of preparing this forcemeat which I shall submit here, as it is specially used for the preparation of pike forcemeat à La Lyonnaise.

Pound in a mortar one lb. of the meat of a pike, without the skin or bones; combine with this one-half lb. of stiff frangipan, season with salt and nutmeg, pass through a sieve, and put back into the mortar.

Vigorously work the forcemeat in order to make it cohere, and gradually add to it one-half lb. of melted beef-fat. The whole half-pound, however, need not necessarily be beef-fat; beef-marrow or butter may form part of it in the proportion of half the weight of the beef-fat.

When the forcemeat is very fine and smooth, withdraw it from the mortar and place it in a bowl surrounded with ice until wanted.

Special Stuffings for Fish

These preparations diverge slightly from the forcemeats given above, and they are of two kinds. They are used to stuff such fish as mackerel, herring, shad, &c., to which they lend a condimentary touch that makes these fish more agreeable to the taste, and certainly more digestible.

First Method

Put into a bowl four oz. of raw, chopped milt, two oz. of bread-crumb, steeped in milk and well pressed, and one and one-half oz. of the following fine herbs, mixed in equal quantities and finely chopped:— Chives, parsley, chervil, shallots, sweet basil, half a garlic clove (crushed), then two whole eggs, salt, pepper, and nutmeg.

Chop up all these ingredients together so as to mix them thoroughly.

Second Method

Put into a bowl four oz. of bread-crumb steeped in milk and well pressed; one-half oz. of onion and one-half oz. of chopped shallots, slightly cooked in butter, and cold; one oz. of raw mushrooms, chopped and well pressed in a towel a tablespoonful of chopped parsley; a piece of garlic the size of a pea, crushed; salt, pepper, and nutmeg, and two eggs.

Mix it as above.

Forcemeat Balls or Quenelles

Divers ways of Moulding and Poaching them.—Whatever be the required size or shape of quenelles there are four ways of making them:

By rolling them
by moulding them with; a spoon;
by forming them with a piping-bag;
by moulding them by hand into the shape of a kidney.

To roll quenelles it is necessary to keep the forcemeat somewhat stiff, and therefore this process could not well apply to the mousseline forcemeats. Place one-quarter lb. of forcemeat, when ready, on a floured board, and, with hands covered in flour, roll the preparation until it has lengthened itself into the form of a sausage, the thickness of which depends upon the required size of the intended quenelles.

Cut up the sausage of forcemeat laterally with a floured knife, and roll each section with the finger-ends until the length it assumes is thrice that of its diameter. The balls should be put aside on a floured tray as soon as they are made.

The Poaching of Rolled Quenelles.—When all the forcemeat has been used up, the balls are gently tilted into a saucepan containing boiling, salted water, so calculated in quantity as to allow of their not being too tightly squeezed. The saucepan is covered and kept on the side of the fire until all the balls have risen to the surface and are almost out of the water. They are then removed with a skimmer and placed in a bowl of cold water.

At last, when they have properly cooled, they are carefully drained on a cloth and put aside on a dish until required. When the quenelles are needed for immediate use it would be better not to cool them.

To Mould Quenelles with a Spoon.—This method may be applied to all forcemeats, and allows of the balls being much softer, as the forcemeat need not be so stiff. First, butter the sauté-pan or the tray, whereon the balls are to be laid, by means of a brush, and let the butter cool.

Put the sauté-pan on the table in front and a little to the right of one; on the left, place the sautépan or bowl containing the forcemeat, and on the further side of the buttered sauté-pan there should be a receptacle containing hot water, into which the spoon used for moulding is inserted. For ordinary quenelles two coffee-spoons are used, one of which is kept in the hot water as stated above. Now, with the other held in the left hand, take up a little of the forcemeat (just enough to fill the spoon); withdraw the second spoon from the hot water and place it, with its convex side uppermost, on the other spoon.

This smoothens the upper surface of the forcemeat. Now, with the help of the second spoon, remove the whole of the contents of the first spoon, and overturn the second spoon on the spot in the tray or sauté-pan which the ball is intended to occupy. The second spoon, being at once moist and hot, allows the forcemeat to leave it quite easily in the shape of a large olive. Renew this operation until the whole of the forcemeat has been used.

The Poaching of Spoon-moulded Quenelles.—When all the balls have been moulded, place the tray on the side of the stove and pour enough boiling, salted water over them to moisten them abundantly. Leave them to poach, and from time to time move the tray; then, when they have swollen sufficiently and seem soft and firm to the touch, drain them. If they are to be used at once they should be placed directly in the sauce. If they have been prepared in advance, it would be well to cool them as directed under rolled quenelles.

To Form Quenelles with a Piping-bag.—This process is especially recommended for small, fine, and light forcemeat balls intended for soup garnish. For, besides being extremely quick, it allows of making them in any desirable size or shape. Butter a tray or a sauté-pan, and leave to cool. Put the forcemeat into a bag fitted with a pipe at its narrowest end. The pipe may be grooved or smooth, and its size must be in accordance with that intended for the proposed balls. Now squeeze out the latter, proceeding in the usual way and laying them very closely.

The Poaching of Quenelles made by the above Process, with ordinary or Mousseline Forcemeat.—These quenelles are poached in exactly the same way as the spoon-moulded ones.

The Poaching of Godiveau Quenelles made with a Piping-bag.—These quenelles or balls are laid on a piece of fine, buttered paper, which in its turn is placed upon a buttered tray. The godiveau must not be too stiff, and the balls are laid by means of the piping-bag side by side and slightly touching one another. When the tray is covered push it into a very moderate oven for a few minutes. The balls are poached when a thin dew of grease may be seen to glisten on their surfaces. On the appearance of this dew withdraw them from the oven and overturn the tray, carefully, upon a marble slab, taking care that the tray does not press at all upon the balls, lest it crush them. When the latter are nearly cold the paper which covers them is taken off with caution, and all that remains to be done is to put them carefully away on a dish until they are wanted.

To Mould Forcemeat with the Fingers.—This excellent process is as expedient as that of the bag, and it produces beautifully shaped balls. Place on the edge of a table, in front of one, a saucepan three-quarters full of boiling, salted water, the handle of the receptacle being turned to the far side. Now take a piece of string one yard in length, double it over, and tie the free ends to a weight of two lbs., letting the two strands twist round each other.

This done, there should be a loop at the top of the string. Put this loop round the handle of the saucepan, and draw the string diametrically across the latter, letting the weight pull the string tightly down on the side opposite to the handle. When this has been effected the operator, with his left hand, takes some of the forcemeat, smoothening it with a spoon, and, placing the spoon near the string with his right, first finger, he removes from its extremity a portion of the preparation about equal to the intended size of the balls. This portion of the forcemeat remaining suspended on his first finger, the operator now scrapes the latter across the string, and the ball falls beneath into the saucepan containing the water. When all the stuffing has been moulded in this way the saucepan is placed on the fire to complete the poaching of the balls, and the precautions indicated in the preceding processes are observed.

Chapter VIII The Various Garnishes for Soups

Royales

Ordinary Royale

Put one oz. of chervil into one pint of boiling consommé, cover the saucepan, and let infusion proceed away from the fire for twenty minutes. Now pour this infusion over two eggs and six yolks, beaten briskly in a basin, and mix with the whisk. Strain through muslin, and carefully remove therefrom the froth that has formed. Pour into buttered moulds; poach in a bain-marie, as in the case of cream, and take great care that the water in the bain-marie does not boil.

According to the way in which the royale is to be divided, it may be poached either in large or small “Charlotte” moulds; but the latter, large and small alike, must be well buttered.

If the preparation be put into large moulds, thirty-five or forty minutes should be allowed for poaching; if, on the other hand, the moulds are small, about fifteen minutes would suffice.

Always let the royale cool in the moulds.

Deslignac or Cream Royal

Boil one pint of thin cream, and pour it, little by little, over one egg and six yolks, well whisked in a basin. Season with a little salt and nutmeg, strain through muslin, and, for the poaching, follow the directions given above.

Chicken Royale

Finely pound three oz. of cooked white chicken-meat, and add thereto three tablespoonfuls of cold Béchamel. Put this paste in a bowl, season with a little salt and a dash of nutmeg, dilute with one-fifth pint of cream, and strain through tammy.

Thicken this preparation with one egg and the yolks of three, and poach in small or large moulds, in accordance with the procedure already described.

Game Royale

Finely pound three oz. of the cooked meat of that game which gives its name to the preparation, and add three tablespoonfuls of cold Espagnole Sauce and one-fifth pint of rich cream, in small quantities at a time. Warm the seasoning with a very little cayenne, strain through tammy, thicken with one egg and three yolks, and poach as before.

Fish Royale

Stew in butter four oz. of fillet of sole cut into cubes, or the same quantity of any other fish suited to the nature of the intended soup. Cool, pound finely, and add, little by little, two tablespoonfuls of cold Béchamel and one-quarter pint of cream. Season with salt and a pinch of nutmeg, and strain through tammy. Thicken by means of the yolks of five eggs, and poach in large or small moulds.

Carrot or Crécy Royale

Stew gently in butter five oz. of the red part only of carrots. Cool, crush in a mortar, and gradually add two tablespoonfuls of Béchamel and one-fifth pint of rich cream. Season with table-salt and a pinch of castor sugar, and deepen the tint of the royale with a few drops of vegetable red. Strain through tammy, thicken with one egg and four yolks, put into moulds, and poach.

Fresh Peas or St Germain Royale

Cook one-half lb. of fresh, small peas in boiling water with a bunch of chervil and a few leaves of fresh mint. Pass through a sieve, and dilute the resulting purée (in a saucepan) with two-fifths of its volume of the liquor it has been cooked in and one-fifth of cream. Add a little sugar, the necessary salt, one egg, and two yolks. Pass through a fine strainer, and poach in well-buttered moulds.

Various Royales

Royales may also be made with leeks, celery, &c., the procedure being as follows:—

Finely mince six or seven oz. of the chosen vegetable; stew the same gently and thoroughly in butter, and strain through tammy. Add to the resulting purée three tablespoonfuls of Béchamel, one-fifth pint of cream, two eggs, and four yolks. Put into large or small moulds, and poach.

Remarks

In order that these royales may have the required delicacy, I should urge the reader not to exceed the prescribed quantities of eggs and yolks, these being so calculated as to exactly produce the density required.

The Dividing-up of Royales

When the poaching is done take the mould or moulds out of water, and leave the royale to cool in them. Do not turnout the moulds whilst the preparation is hot, as it would surely scatter. It only assumes the necessary solidity for being divided up by means of the aggregation and contraction of its various constituents during the cooling process.

If the royale has been poached in small moulds, slightly trim the cylinders of royale, divide them up laterally into discs, and stamp them uniformly with a plain or indented fancy cutter.

If the royale has been poached in large moulds, withdraw it from these, and place it on a serviette; trim the tops, cut into half-inch slices, and stamp with small, fancy cutters of different shapes. These little divisions of royale must always be stamped very neatly and quite regularly.

Chiffonade

The name “Chiffonade” is given to a mince of sorrel or lettuce, intended as a complement for such soups as “Potage de santé”, “le Germiny”, &c., or various clear consommés like “Julienne”.

To prepare Chiffonade, first carefully shred the sorrel or lettuce, and remove therefrom all the leaf-ribs. Carefully wash the leaves, and squeeze the latter tightly between the fingers of the left hand and the table. Now cut them into fine strips with a sharp knife.

If the chiffonade be intended for a consommé, add it to the latter half an hour before dishing up; it is thus actually cooked in the soup itself. If, as is most often the case, it be intended for a thick soup, it is better to let it melt well in butter, to moisten it with a little consommé, and to let it boil for ten minutes before adding it to the soup.

Whatever the purpose be for which it is made, chiffonade should always be prepared with very tender sorrel or lettuce.

Directions for Soup With Pastes

Vermicelli and the various Italian pastes should measure about three oz. per quart of consommé. They should first be thrown into boiling, salted water, where they are left to poach for three minutes, whereupon they are drained, cooled, and their cooking is completed in the consommé.

The parboiling of these pastes is necessary in order to get rid of the little agglomerations of flour which adhere to them, and which would otherwise make the consommé cloudy.

Tapioca, sago, salep, &c., should also be apportioned at about three oz. per quart. But this is only an average, for the quality of this kind of products varies greatly, and it is best to choose the goods of an excellent maker, and, in order to avoid surprises, to abide by that choice.

These products need no parboiling; they are merely sprinkled into the boiling consommé while stirring the latter, and they are left to cook until the soup is quite clear. The boiling should be gentle, and the scum should be removed as often as it forms.

The time allowed for cooking naturally varies in accordance with the quality of the goods, but the absolute transparency of the consommé is an infallible sign of its having been completed.

Brazilian, Japanese, and other pearls are used in the same quantities, but they should poach for thirty minutes if required to be very transparent.

Threaded Eggs

Beat up three eggs in a bowl, season with salt and pepper, and strain through a sieve. Now pour the eggs into a fine strainer, hold same over a sautépan containing some boiling consommé, and shift it about in such wise as to let the egg fall in threads into the boiling liquid beneath, and thus immediately coagulate. Drain the egg-threads very carefully lest they break.

Profiterolles for Soups

These consist of little choux about the size of a large hazel-nut, stuffed with some kinds of purée, such as that of foie gras with cream, or of chicken, or of vegetables, &c. Four profiterolles should be allowed for each person.

To make profiterolles, put a few tablespoonfuls of “pâte à choux” without sugar (№2374) into a piping-bag fitted with a smooth pipe, whose orifice should be about one-quarter inch in diameter. Squeeze out portions of the preparation on to a tray, so as to form balls about the size of a small hazel-nut; gild by means of beaten egg applied with a fine brush, and cook in a moderate oven.

Do not take the profiterolles from the oven until they are quite dry.

Chapter IX Garnishing Preparations for Relevés and Entrées

Potato Croquettes

Cook quickly in salted water two lb. of peeled and quartered potatoes. As soon, as they seem soft to the finger, drain them, place them in the front of the oven for a few minutes in order to dry them, and then tilt them into a sieve lying on a cloth, and press them through the former without rubbing.

Place the purée in a sautépan; season with salt, pepper, and nutmeg; add one oz. of butter, and dry; i.e., stir over a brisk fire until the purée becomes a consistent paste.

Take off the fire, complete with the yolks of three eggs, well mixed with the rest, and turn the paste out on to a buttered dish, taking care to spread it in a rather thin layer, so as to precipitate its cooling. Butter the surface to prevent the preparation’s drying.

To make croquettes, equal portions of this paste, i.e., portions weighing about one and one-half oz. of it, are rolled on a flour-dusted board into the shape of a cork, a ball, or a quoit. These are now dipped into an Anglaise (Formula №174) and rolled in bread-crumbs or raspings, the latter being well patted on to the surface of the croquettes, lest they should fall into the frying fat. Let the patting also avail for finishing off the selected shape of the objects. These are then plunged into hot fat, where they should remain until they have acquired a fine, golden colour.

Dauphine Potatoes

Prepare as above the required quantity of paste, and add thereto per lb. six oz. of pâte à choux without sugar (Formula №2374).

Mix the two constituents thoroughly.

Dauphine potatoes are moulded in the shape of small cylinders, and they are treated à l’Anglaise, like the croquettes.

Duchesse Potatoes

These are the same as the croquettes, though they are differently treated. They are made on a floured board in the shape of diminutive cottage-loaves, little shuttle-shaped loaves, small quoits, and lozenges or rectangles. They are gilded with beaten egg, and when their shape is that of quoits, rectangles, or lozenges, they are streaked by means of a small knife.

After this operation, which is to prevent the gilding from blistering, they are baked in the oven for a few minutes previous to being used in dressing the dishes they accompany.

Marquise Potatoes

Take one lb. of croquette paste and add thereto six oz. of very red, reduced tomato-purée. Pour this mixture into a bag fitted with a large, grooved pipe, and squeeze it out upon a baking-tray in shapes resembling large meringues.

Slightly gild their surfaces with beaten egg, and put them into the oven for a few minutes before using them to dress the dish.

Ordinary or Dry Duxelle

The uses of Duxelle are legion, and it is prepared thus:—Slightly fry one teaspoonful of onions in one tablespoonful of butter and oil mixed. Add to this four tablespoonfuls of mushroom stalks and parings, chopped and well pressed in a towel with the view of expelling their vegetable moisture. Stir over a brisk fire until the latter has completely evaporated; season with salt, pepper, and nutmeg, and one coffee-spoonful of well-chopped parsley, mixing the whole thoroughly.

Transfer to a bowl, cover with a piece of white, buttered paper, and put aside until wanted.

Duxelle For Stuffed Vegetables (Tomatoes, Mushrooms, &c.)

Put six tablespoonfuls of dry duxelle into a small stewpan, and add thereto three tablespoonfuls of half glaze sauce containing plenty of tomato, crushed garlic the size of a pea, and two tablespoonfuls of white wine. Set to simmer until the required degree of consistence is reached.

N.B.—A tablespoonful of fine, fresh bread-crumbs may be added to the duxelle in order to thicken it.

Duxelle for Garnishing Small Pies, Onions, Cucumbers, &c.

To four tablespoonfuls of dry duxelle add four tablespoonfuls of ordinary pork forcemeat (Formula №196).

Maintenon (preparation used in stuffing preparations à la Maintenon)

Put one pint of Béchamel into a vegetable-pan with one-half pint of Soubise (Formula №104), and reduce to half while stirring over a brisk fire. Thicken, away from the fire, by means of the yolks of five eggs, and add four tablespoonfuls of minced mushrooms, either cooked in the ordinary way or stewed in butter.

Matignon

This preparation serves chiefly for covering certain large joints of butcher’s meat, or fowl, to which it imparts an appropriate flavour. It is made as follows:—Finely mince two medium carrots (the red part only), two onions, and two sticks of celery taken from the heart. Add one tablespoonful of raw lean ham, cut paysanne-fashion, a sprig of thyme, and half a leaf of bay, crushed.

Stew in butter, and finally swill the saucepan with two tablespoonfuls of Madeira.

Mirepoix

The purpose of Mirepoix in culinary preparations is the same as that of Matignon, but its mode of use is different.

Its constituents are the same as those of the Matignon, but instead of being minced they are cut up into more or less fine dice, in accordance with the use for which the preparation is intended.

Instead of the ham, fresh and slightly-salted breast of pork may be used, while both the ham and the bacon may be excluded under certain circumstances.

Fine or Bordelaise Mirepoix

Coarse Mirepoix, which are added to certain preparations in order to lend these the proper flavour, are generally made immediately before being used, but this is not so in the case of the finer Mirepoix, which chiefly serves as an adjunct to crayfish and lobsters, This is made in advance, and as follows:—

Cut into dice four oz. of the red part only of carrots, the same quantity of onion, and one oz. of parsley stalks. In order that the Mirepoix may be still finer, these ingredients may now be chopped, but in this case it is advisable to thoroughly press them in a corner of a towel, so as to squeeze out their vegetable moisture, the mere process of stewing not being sufficient for this purpose.

Should this water be allowed to remain in the Mirepoix, more particularly if the latter must be kept some time, it would probably give rise to mustiness or fermentation.

Put the ingredients into a small stewpan with one and one-half oz. of butter and a little powdered thyme and bay, and stew until all are well cooked. This done, turn the preparation out into a small bowl, heap it together with the back of a fork, cover it with a piece of white, buttered paper, and put aside until wanted.

Various Salpicons

This term stands for a certain preparatory method applied to a series of preparations.

Salpicons are simple or compound. Simple if they only contain one product, such as the meat of a fowl, or of game, butcher’s meat, foie gras, various fish, ham or tongue, mushrooms, truffles, &c. Compound if they consist of two or more of the above-mentioned ingredients which may happen to combine suitably.

The preparatory method consists in cutting the various ingredients into dice.

The series of preparations arises from the many possible combinations of the products, each particular combination bearing its own name.

Thus Salpicons may be Royal, Financier, Chasseur, Parisien, Montglas, &c.; of whichever kind, however, Salpicons are always incorporated with a vehicular sauce which is in accordance with their constituents.

Batter for Various Fritters

Put into a bowl one lb. of sifted flour, one-quarter oz. of salt, one tablespoonful of oil or melted butter, and the necessary quantity of barely lukewarm water. If the batter is to be used at once mix the ingredients by turning them over and over without stirring with the spoon, for this would give the preparation an elasticity which would prevent its adhering to immersed solids. Should the batter be prepared beforehand, however, it may be stirred, since it loses its elasticity when left to stand any length of time.

Before using it add the whites of two eggs whisked to a froth.

Batter For Vegetables (Salsify, Celery, &c.)

Put one lb. of sifted flour into a bowl with one-quarter oz. of salt and two tablespoonfuls of oil or melted butter. Dilute with one egg and the necessary quantity of cold water. Keep this batter somewhat thin, do not stir it, and let it rest for a few hours before using.

Batter for Fruit and Flower Fritters

Put one lb. of flour into a bowl with one-quarter oz. of salt and two tablespoonfuls of oil or melted butter. Dilute gradually with one-quarter pint of beer and a little tepid water.

When about to use the batter mix therewith the whites of two eggs whisked to a froth.

N.B.—Keep this batter thin, if anything, and above all do not stir overmuch.

Batter for Oven-Glazed Fruit Fritters

Mix one lb. of flour with two tablespoonfuls of oil, a grain of salt, two eggs (added one after the other), the necessary quantity of water, and one oz. of sugar. Keep this preparation in a lukewarm place to let it ferment, and stir it with a wooden spoon before using it to immerse the solids.

Remarks

Batter for fruit fritters may contain a few tablespoonfuls of brandy, in which case an equal quantity of the water must be suppressed.

Provençale (preparation for stuffing cutlets à la Provençale)

Put one pint of Béchamel into a vegetable-pan and reduce it until it has become quite dense. Thicken it with the yolks of four eggs, and finish it away from the fire with a crushed piece of garlic as large as a pea, and one-quarter lb. of grated cheese.

Chapter XI Hors-d’Œuvres

General Remarks

The preparations described hereafter all belong to the order of cold hors-d’œuvres. I did not deem it necessary to touch upon the hot kind, for, apart from the fact that these are very seldom served in England, at least under the head of hors-d’œuvres, they are mostly to be found either among the hot Entrées or the Savouries proper.

Generally speaking, hors-d’œuvres should only form part of a meal that does not comprise soup, while the rule of serving them at luncheons only ought to be looked upon as absolute.

It is true that restaurants à la carte deliberately deviate from this rule, but it should be remembered, in their case, that, in addition to the fact that “hors-d’œuvres de luxe”, such as caviare, oysters, plovers’ and lapwings’ eggs, &c., are mostly in question, they also find the use of hors-d’œuvres expedient if only as a means of whiling away the customers’ time during the preparation of the various dishes that may have been ordered.

Moreover, the hors-d’œuvres enumerated are not subject to the same objection as those composed of fish, salads, and marinaded vegetables. The use of cold hors-d’œuvres in these special cases is thus, to a certain extent, justified, but it is nevertheless to be regretted that an exception of this kind should degenerate into a habit, and that it should be made to prevail under circumstances which, in themselves, are insufficient warrant for the abuse.

In Russia it is customary to have a sideboard in a room adjoining the dining-room, dressed with all kinds of special pastries, smoked fish, and other products, and these the diners partake of, standing, together with strong liqueurs, before taking their seats at the table. The general name given to the items on the sideboard is “Zakouski”. Caterers and hotel-keepers in different parts of the world, more zealous than judicious, introduced the custom of the zakouski without allowing for the differences of race, which are due, to some extent, to the influence of climate; and at first, probably owing to everybody’s enthusiasm for things Russian, the innovation enjoyed a certain vogue, in spite of the fact that, in many cases, the dishes served resembled the Zakouski in name alone, and consisted of cold and very ordinary hors-d’œuvres, served at the dining-table itself.

At length the absurdity of investing such common things as hors-d’œuvres with an exotic title began to be perceived, and nowadays the occasions are rare when the Russian term is to be found on a menu; nevertheless, the custom unfortunately survives.

For my own part, I regard cold hors-d’œuvres as quite unnecessary in a dinner; I even consider them counter to the dictates of common sense, and they are certainly prejudicial to the flavour of the soup that follows.

At the most, caviare might be tolerated, the nutty taste of which, when it is quite fresh, can but favourably impress the consumer’s palate, as also certain fine oysters, provided they be served with very dry Rhine wine or white Bordeaux. But I repeat that hors-d’œuvres consisting of any kind of fish, salad, marinaded vegetables, &c., should be strictly proscribed from the items of a dinner.

The custom of serving cold hors-d’œuvres at lunch is, on the contrary, not only traditional, but indispensable, and their varied combinations, thrown into relief by tasteful and proper arrangement, besides lending a cheerful aspect to the table, beguile the consumer’s attention and fancy from the very moment of his entering the dining room. It has been said, with reason, that soups should foretell the dominant note of the whole dinner, and cold hors-d’œuvres should in the same way reveal that of a luncheon.

Possibly it was with a sense of the importance of hors-d’œuvres, from this standpoint, that their preparation was transferred from the office (the exclusive concern whereof used, formerly, to be the hors-d’œuvres) to the kitchen.

The results of this change manifested themselves immediately in prodigious variations and transformations of the hors-d’œuvres, both in respect of their preparation and dishing-up, so much so, indeed, that perhaps in no other department of culinary art has there been such progress of recent years.

Their variety is infinite, and it would be impossible to compute, even approximately, the number of combinations an ingenious artist could effect in their preparation, seeing that the latter embraces almost every possible use of every conceivable esculent product.

Well may it be said that a good hors-d’œuvrier is a man to be prized in any kitchen, for, although his duties do not by any means rank first in importance, they nevertheless demand in him who performs them the possession of such qualities as are rarely found united in one person, viz., reliable and experienced taste, originality, keen artistic sense, and professional knowledge.

The hors-d’œuvrier should be able to produce something sightly and good out of very little, and the beauty and attractiveness of a hors-d’œuvre should depend to a much greater degree upon his work and the judicious treatment of his material than upon the nature of the latter.

Preparation for Hors-d’Œuvres

Butters and Creams

The seasoning of butters for hors-d’œuvres is effected when dishing them up. When prepared in advance, they ought to be placed in a bowl and put aside somewhere in the cool, covered with a piece of clean paper.

Anchovy Butter

Wash twelve or fifteen anchovies in cold water, and dry them thoroughly. Remove the fillets from the bones, pound them smoothly with four oz. of butter, rub the whole through a fine sieve, smooth it with a spoon, and put it aside.

Caviare Butter

Pound three oz. of pressed caviare with four oz. of butter, and rub through a fine sieve.

Shrimp Butter

Pound four oz. of shrimps with four oz. of butter; rub through a fine sieve first, then through muslin, after having softened the preparation.

This may also be made from the shelled tails of shrimps, which process, though it is easier, does not yield a butter of such delicate taste as the former.

Curry Butter

Soften four oz. of butter in a bowl, and add thereto sufficient curry-powder to ensure a decided taste. The exact quantity of curry cannot be prescribed, since the quality of the latter entirely governs its apportionment.

Crayfish Butter

Cook the crayfish with mirepoix, as for Bisque. Finely pound the shells after having removed the tails, and add thereto four oz. of butter per two oz.; rub through a fine sieve first, then through muslin.

N.B.—The whole crayfish may be pounded, but the tails are usually laid aside with a view to supplying the garnish of the toasts for which the butter is intended.

Red-Herring Butter

Take the fillets of three red-herrings; remove the skins, and pound finely with three oz. of butter. Rub through a fine sieve.

Red-Herring Butter

Pound four oz. of lobster trimmings and spawn, and a little of the coral with four oz. of butter. Rub through a fine sieve.

Milt Butter

Poach four oz. of milt in a covered and buttered sauté-pan, with the juice of half a lemon; pound in the mortar, and add to the preparation its weight of butter and a teaspoonful of mustard. Rub through a fine sieve.

Montpelier Butter (Green Butter)

See Compound Butter for Sauces (Formula №153).

Horse-Radish Butter

Grate two oz. of horse-radish and pound with four oz. of butter. Rub through a fine sieve.

Smoked Salmon Butter

Finely pound four oz. of smoked salmon with as much butter, and rub through a fine sieve.

Paprika Butter

Soften four oz. of butter in a bowl, and mix therewith a small teaspoonful of paprika infused in a few drops of white wine or consommé, with a view to strengthening the colour of the paprika.

Pimento Butter

Pound four oz. of preserved or freshly-cooked capsicum; add as much butter thereto, and rub through a fine sieve.

Caviare Cream

Pound four oz. of preserved caviare and add thereto, little by little, two tablespoonfuls of fresh cream and two oz. of softened butter. Rub through a fine sieve, and finish the preparation by an addition of three tablespoonfuls of whisked cream

N.B.—This cream and those that follow often take the place of the butters in the preparation of hors-d’œuvres. The addition of previously well-softened butter to these creams is necessary in order to make them sufficiently consistent when they cool.

Lobster Cream

Pound four oz. of lobster trimmings, spawn, and coral, and add thereto three tablespoonfuls of fresh cream and two oz. of softened butter.

Rub through a sieve, and complete the preparation with whisked cream, as above.

Game Cream

Pound four oz. of cold, cooked game-meat with three tablespoonfuls of fresh cream and two oz. of softened butter. Rub through a sieve, and finish the preparation with three tablespoonfuls of whisked cream.

Smoked Salmon Cream

Finely pound four oz. of smoked salmon, and add thereto, little by little, three tablespoonfuls of fresh cream and two oz. of softened butter. Rub the whole through a sieve, and finish with an addition of three tablespoonfuls of whisked cream.

Tunny Cream

Finely pound four oz. of tunny in oil, and finish the cream similarly to that of the Smoked Salmon.

Chicken Cream

Finely pound four oz. of cold fowl (white parts only) and add thereto two tablespoonfuls of fresh cream and two oz. of softened butter. Rub through a sieve, and finish with three tablespoonfuls of whisked cream.

N.B.—This cream ought to be made and seasoned with salt immediately before being served.

Mustard Sauce with Cream

Put three tablespoonfuls of mustard in a bowl with a little salt, pepper, and a few drops of lemon-juice. Mix the whole and add, little by little, the necessary quantity of very fresh cream.

Hors-d’Œuvres

Anchovy Allumettes

Roll some puff-paste trimmings into rectangular strips two and one-half inches wide and one-eighth inch thick. Spread thereon a thin coating of fish stuffing, finished with anchovy butter; lay the anchovy fillets, prepared beforehand, lengthwise on this stuffing, and cut in to pieces about one inch wide. Place the pieces on a baking-tray, and set to bake in the oven for twelve minutes.

Anchovy Fillets

Cut each halved anchovy, which should have been previously marinaded in oil, into two or three little fillets. Place them across each other in a hors-d’œuvre dish, after the manner of a lattice; garnish with chopped parsley and the chopped white and yolk of a hard-boiled egg, alternating the colours. Put a few capers on the fillets, and besprinkle moderately with oil. Anchovy fillets may also be served on a salad of ciseled lettuce, for the sake of variety.

Fresh Marinaded Anchovies

Take a few live anchovies, cleanse them, and put them in salt for two hours. This done, plunge them in smoking oil, where they may remain only just long enough to stiffen. Drain, place them in a moderately acid marinade, and serve on a hors-d’œuvre dish with a little marinade.

Rolled Anchovies

Turn some fine olives and stuff them with anchovy butter; when quite cold, encircle them with a ring of anchovy fillet, kept whole.

Anchovy Medallions

Cut into discs, about the size of half-a-crown, potatoes boiled in water or baked beetroot. Cover their edges with fine anchovy fillets marinaded in oil, and garnish their centres either with caviare, chopped hard-boiled egg, or milt purée, &c.

Anchovy Paupiettes

Prepare some thick slices of blanched and marinaded cucumber, about the size of half-crowns, and hollow their centres slightly. Place rings composed of the fillets of anchovies in oil upon these slices, and fill up their centres with tunny cream or the cream of any fish or shell-fish.

Anchovy with Pimentos

Prepare some anchovy fillets in oil, and place them across each other in a lattice, using fillets of pimento alternately with those of the anchovies. Garnish in the same way as for anchovy fillets, i.e., with the chopped white and yolk of a hard-boiled egg, and chopped parsley.

Norwegian Anchovies or Kilkis

These are found ready-prepared on the market. Place them on a hors-d’œuvre dish with some of their liquor, and without any garnish.

Smoked Eel

Serve it plain, cut into fillets.

Eel with White Wine and Paprika

Divide the eel into lengths of three and one-half inches; poach these in exactly the same way as for matelote, but with white wine and paprika seasoning. Let them cool in their cooking-liquor; cut the pieces lengthwise into large fillets, and cover them with the liquor after all grease has been removed therefrom and it has been clarified and cleared.

Eel au Vert

Stew in butter two oz. of sorrel, one-quarter oz. of parsley, as much chervil, a few tarragon leaves, a little fresh pimpernel, two oz. of tender nettle, one-quarter oz. of savory, a sprig of green thyme, and a few sage-leaves, all of which must be ciseled. Remove the skins from two lbs. of small eels, suppress the heads, and cut into pieces two inches long. Put these pieces with the herbs, stiffen them well, and add one pint of white wine and a little salt and pepper. Set to cook for ten minutes, thicken with the yolks of four eggs and a few drops of lemon-juice, and leave to cool in a bowl. This preparation of eel is served very cold.

Eel au Vert à la Flamande

Remove the skin from, and cut into small pieces, two lbs. of small eels. Stiffen the pieces in butter, moisten with one pint of beer, season, and set to cook for ten minutes. Add the herbs enumerated above, raw and roughly chopped. Once more set to cook for seven or eight minutes, thicken with fæcula if the sauce is too thin, and transfer the whole to a bowl to cool. Serve very cold.

Artichokes à la Grecque

Take some very small and tender artichokes. Pare them, cut the leaves short, and plunge them into a large saucepan of acidulated water. Set to parboil for eight or ten minutes, drain, cool in fresh water, and drain once more in a sieve.

For twenty artichokes prepare the following liquor:—one pint of water, one-quarter pint of oil, a little salt, the juice of three lemons, a few fennel and coriander seeds, some peppercorns, a sprig of thyme, and a bay-leaf. Set to boil, add the parboiled artichokes, and leave to cook for twenty minutes. Transfer to a bowl.

Serve these artichokes very cold upon a hors-d’œuvre dish, accompanied by a few tablespoonfuls of their cooking-liquor.

Small Artichoke-Bottoms

Remove the leaves and the hearts of some little artichokes; trim their remaining bases, and plunge each as soon as trimmed into acidulated water lest they blacken. Cook them “au blanc” (Formula №167), and leave them to cool in their liquor.

Drain them well, dry them, place them in a pan, and marinade them for twenty minutes in oil and lemon-juice. This done, garnish them, either with a salpicon thickened with mayonnaise, a milt or other purée, a small macédoine, or a vegetable salad, &c. Place on a hors-d’œuvre dish with a garnish of parsley sprays.

Barquettes

These are a kind of small Croustades with indented edges, made in very small, boat-shaped moulds, and they may be garnished in any conceivable way.

As their preparation is the same as that of Tartlets, see the latter (Formula №387); also refer to “Frivolities” (Formula №350).

SMOKED HAMBURG BEEF

Cut it into very thin slices; divide these up into triangles, and roll the latter into the shape of cones. The slices may also be served flat.

Dish up at the last moment, and serve very cold.

Canapés and Toast

In the matter of hors-d’œuvres, the two above names have the same meaning. The preparation consists of small slices of the crumb of bread, about one-quarter inch thick, slightly toasted and with a garnish on one of their sides. The garnish is subject to the taste of the consumer, the resources at the disposal of the cook, or the latter’s fancy, which may here be fully indulged.

But the garnish, par excellence, for Canapés or Toast, is fresh butter combined with a fine mince of white roast chicken-meat, the meat of shell-fish or fish, or cheese, &c., as I pointed out above under the butters for hors-d’œuvres.

Whatever be the garnish of Canapés or Toast, and even when it would be unreasonable to let butter form a part of it, as, for example, in the case of marinaded fish, anchovies, filleted herring, &c., it is always best to put plenty of butter on the pieces of toast while they are still hot, with the view of keeping them soft.

When the garnish consists of a purée, i.e., a compound butter, I should advise the use of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe, for laying the preparation upon the toast. This method is both clean and expeditious, and lends itself to any fanciful arrangement which the varying shape of the toast may suggest.

The principal shapes given to the toast are as follows: round, square, rectangular, oval, triangular, crescented, star-like, crossed, &c.

They should never exceed one and one-half inches in diameter, and a corresponding size in the other shapes.

I shall only indicate here a few kinds of specially garnished toast, and leave the thousand and one other kinds for the operator himself to discover.

Anchovy Toast

Make the pieces of toast oval. Cover with anchovy butter, and place thereon, lattice-wise, some fillets of anchovy cut to the length of the toast. Garnish the pieces of toast all round with the separately chopped whites and yolks of hard-boiled eggs, alternating the colours.

Caviare Toast

Make the pieces of toast round; cover with caviare butter; garnish the edges with a thread of softened butter, laid on by means of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe. Put fresh caviare in the centre.

Shrimp Toast

Make the pieces of toast round; cover with shrimp butter, and garnish by means of a border composed of shelled shrimps’ tails with a caper in the centre.

City Toast

Make the pieces of toast round, and cover with a thick coating of the following preparation, viz.:—four oz. of fresh butter, softened; two oz. of fresh Gruyère and two oz. of Parmesan, both grated; a dessertspoonful of cream, and a little salt and cayenne. Cover this preparation with two half-discs, which when juxtaposed are equal in circumference to the round of the toast. The half-discs should be cut respectively from a Lyons sausage and a Gruyère cheese; both should be thin, and equal in thickness.

Danish Toast

Prepare some slices of brown bread, equal in thickness to the toast; but only heat, do not grill them. Spread some horseradish butter over them, and cover with alternate strips of smoked salmon, caviare, and filleted herrings marinaded in white wine. Now stamp the garnished slices with a sharp fancy-cutter, the shape of which is optional.

Crayfish Toast

Make the pieces of toast crescented; cover with crayfish butter, deck the edges with a string of softened butter, and garnish with a crayfish’s tail, cut into two lengthwise The two halves of the tail should be placed in the middle of each crescent, close together and with their thickest side innermost.

Tongue Toast

Prepare some slices of crumb of bread, equal in thickness, and toast them. Now garnish with a coating, half as thick as the slices themselves, of mustard butter. Cover the butter with thin slices of very red, salted tongue, and let the butter harden.

Stamp out the pieces of toast with a star-shaped fancy-cutter, which should be dipped from time to time in boiling water in order to facilitate the operation. Finally, make a rosette of mustard butter in the middle of each piece of toast.

Lucile Toast

Make the pieces of toast oval, cover with mustard butter, and border their edges with a line of finely chopped and very red tongue. Garnish the middle of each with chopped white chicken-meat, and in the centre drop a pinch of chopped truffle.

Various Carolines

These are very small éclairs of pâte à choux without sugar. When quite cold, garnish them inside with a purée, either of tongue, fowl, game, or foie gras, &c., then coat them thinly with a chaud-froid sauce in keeping with the purée forming the inside garnish.

When the sauce has cooled, glaze it, by means of a brush, with a little cold melted jelly, with a view to making it glossy.

N.B.—Carolines are also used as a garnish for certain cold preparations, aspics, &c.

Caviare and Blinis

Caviare is undoubtedly the richest and most delicate of hors-d’œuvres, granted, of course, that it be of good quality and consist of large, light-coloured, and transparent particles. Its price is always high, owing to the difficulty attending its importation. It is served very simply, either in a silver timbale or in its original receptacle, surrounded with ice, and accompanied by a dish of Blinis, whereof the preparation is as follows:—

Make a thin paste with one oz. of yeast and one lb. of sifted flour diluted with one pint of lukewarm milk. Leave this paste to ferment for two hours in a lukewarm atmosphere, and then add thereto one-half lb. of flour, the yolks of four eggs, a pinch of salt, one-half pint of tepid milk; mix the whole without letting it acquire any body, and finally add the whites of four eggs, whisked. Let the preparation ferment for half an hour, and, when about to serve, cook the Blinis quickly, after the manner of pancakes, in special little omelet-pans. Dish them up very hot on a napkin.

Failing fresh caviare, the pressed and salted kind may also be used for hors-d’œuvres. Some cooks serve finely-chopped onions with fresh caviare, but a worse practice could not be imagined. Fresh caviare, the flavour of which is perfect, does not need any supplementary condiment.

Celery “à la Bonne-Femme”

Take equal quantities of very tender celery sticks and peeled, quartered and cored russet apples. Finely mince the celery and apples, season with a mustard-and-cream sauce, and place on a hors-d’œuvre dish.

Celery à la Grecque

Select a few hearts of celery, very equal; trim, wash, and parboil them in acidulated water, as directed under “artichokes à la Grecque”." Prepare the cooking-liquor from the same ingredients, using the same quantities thereof, and cook similarly.

Serve very cold on a crystal hors-d’œuvre dish with a portion of the cooking-liquor.

Celeriac

Quarter, peel, and cut the vegetable in julienne fashion. Prepare the seasoning with mustard, salt, pepper, and vinegar add the julienne of Celeriac and mix thoroughly. When the roots are quite soft, a seasoning consisting of mustard-and-cream sauce is preferable.

Marinaded Cèpes

Select some very small and fresh cèpes. Parboil them for eight minutes, drain and cool them, put them into a basin, and cover them with the boiling marinade after having passed the latter through a strainer.

Marinade for Two lbs. of Cèpes

Put into a saucepan one pint of vinegar, one-third pint of oil, a crushed clove of garlic, a fragment of bay, and a little thyme, six peppercorns, a pinch of coriander, a few fennel leaves, and a small root of parsley. Set to boil for five minutes. Leave the mushrooms to marinade for five or six hours before using them.

Cherries à l’Allemande

Take five lbs. of Morella cherries, put them into a bottle, as in the case of cherry brandy, and add thereto three cloves, a fragment of cinnamon, some grated nutmeg, and a sprig of tarragon. Pour over the cherries two quarts of vinegar, boiled with one-half lb. of brown sugar and properly cooled. Cork the bottle, and leave the fruit to macerate for a fortnight.

Brains à la Robert

Cook well-cleansed sheep’s or lamb’s brains in court-bouillon, and cool. Divide them up into thin and regular slices, and place them on a hors-d’œuvre dish. Rub the brain remains through a fine sieve, combine the resulting purée with a mustard-and-cream sauce, and add thereto a fine julienne of the white part only of celery.

Cover the slices of brain with the sauce.

Cucumber à la Danoise

Cut the cucumber to the shape of small cassolettes or barquettes, blanch and marinade them.

Garnish with a preparation composed of a purée of salmon mixed with fillets of herring and chopped, hard-boiled eggs in equal quantities.

Sprinkle a little chopped horse-radish over the garnish.

Stuffed Cucumbers

Prepare them as above, in the shape of small barquettes or cassolettes. Cook them, at the same time keeping them firm; marinade them for twenty minutes, when they are quite cold, in oil and vinegar, and garnish them, by means of a piping-bag, either with a thick purée, some mince-meat thickened with mayonnaise, or a small vegetable macédoine, &c.

Cucumber Salad

Carefully peel the cucumbers, cut them into two lengthwise, remove their seeds, and mince finely. Place them in a bowl, sprinkle with table-salt, and leave them to exude their vegetable moisture for twenty-five minutes. This done, drain them, press them in a towel, season with pepper, oil, and vinegar, and add some chopped chervil.

Cucumber and Pimento Salad

Select some very fresh, medium-sized cucumbers, peel them, and cut them into pieces two inches in length. Cut these pieces spirally, beginning at their peripheries and working towards their centres; then cut them diametrally, so as to produce curved strips of the vegetable. Add an equal quantity of pimentos cut into strips, and season as in the case of cucumber salad.

York Cones

Cut slices from a York ham as thinly as possible, and trim them to the shape of triangles. Roll the triangles into cones, and garnish their insides (by means of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe) with any butter or cream (see Formulæ №280 to 299).

Tongue Cones

Proceed as for York Cones.

Moulded Creams

Prepare a hors-d’œuvre cream in accordance with any one of the recipes (Formulæ №294 to 299). Put this cream into very small, slightly-oiled, and ornamented moulds, and leave it to set in the cool or on ice. Empty the moulds, at the moment of dishing up, either directly upon a dish, on tartlets garnished with a purée in keeping with the cream, or on toast. With these moulded creams, endless varieties of delicate and recommendable little hors-d’œuvres may be prepared, while in their preparation the moulds used in pastry for “petits fours” may serve a useful purpose.

Shrimps and Prawns

Get these very fresh and serve them on boat-shaped hors-d’œuvre dishes, arranging them so that they overlap one another. Either garnish the middle of the dishes with curled-leaf parsley, or lay the crustaceans directly upon parsley.

Duchesses

This hors-d’œuvre is almost equivalent to the Carolines (№325), except that the shape of the Duchesses is that of little choux, about the size of a pigeon’s egg, and that, as a rule, they are merely glazed with some melted jelly, and not covered with a chaud-froid sauce. Sprinkle them with chopped pistachios, and serve them very cold on ornamented dish-papers.

Nantua Duchesses

Stuff the little choux, referred to above, with crayfish purée, and sprinkle them, again and again, with cold, melted jelly, in order to cover them with a transparent film.

Duchesses à la Reine

Stuff the little choux with a purée of fowl with cream. Glaze with jelly, as above, and sprinkle some very black, finely-chopped truffles over the jelly.

Duchesses à la Sultane

Stuff the little choux with a purée of fowl, completed with pistachio butter. Glaze with jelly, and sprinkle a little chopped pistachio upon each little chou.

Caviare Duchesses

Stuff with fresh caviare or caviare cream. Glaze with jelly and serve iced.

Smoked-Salmon Duchesses

Stuff the little choux with a purée of smoked salmon and butter, and glaze them with a maigre jelly.

Norwegian Duchesses

Stuff the choux with a purée of Kilkis and butter, and glaze with jelly.

Karoly Éclairs

These are little éclairs stuffed with a purée made from the entrails of woodcock with champagne. The purée is buttered and slightly seasoned. Cover the éclairs with a brown chaud-froid sauce, mask them with game jelly, and serve them, iced, on ornamented dish-papers.

Crayfish en Buisson

Prepare them in accordance with the recipes “à la nage” or “à la marinière”, and serve them very cold.

Marinaded Smelts

Fry some well-dried and floured smelts in oil; as soon as this is done, put them in a deep dish or a bowl. Add to the oil, per pint (which quantity should be allowed for every two lbs. of the fish), eight unpeeled garlic-cloves, an onion, and a carrot cut into thin, round slices, all of which vegetables should be slightly fried. Drain off the oil, moisten with one-quarter pint of vinegar and as much water, and season with a little salt, two small pimentos, a small bay-leaf, a sprig of thyme, and a few parsley stalks. Dip the smelts for twelve minutes in this marinade, and transfer them to the dish, where they may be left to marinade for twenty-four hours.

Serve very cold with a portion of the marinade.

Fennel à la Grecque

Same process as for artichokes and celery à la Grecque.

Fresh Figs

Place them on a layer of very green leaves, and surround them with broken ice.

Foie Gras

If in the form of a sausage, cut it into thin slices. If potted, shape it into little shells, after the manner in which butter is sometimes served, only a little smaller. In all cases serve it iced, and as soon as it is ready.

Frivolities

I adopted the above term for those small, light, and elegant little preparations, the radical types whereof are barquettes and tartlets, which often take the place of hors-d’œuvres on a menu. The term seems plain, clear, and explicit, and no other could denote more happily this series of trifles which constitute mere gewgaws of the dining-table.

Frogs or Nymphs à l’aurore

For various reasons, I thought it best, in the past, to substitute the mythological name “Nymphs” for the more vulgar term “Frogs” on menus, and the former has been universally adopted, more particularly in reference to the following “Chaud-froid à l’Aurore”:—

Poach the frogs’ legs in an excellent white-wine court-bouillon. When cooled, trim them properly, dry them thoroughly in a piece of fine linen, and steep them, one after the other, in a chaud-froid sauce of fish with paprika, the tint of which should be golden. This done, arrange the treated legs on a layer of champagne jelly, which should have set beforehand on the bottom of a square, silver dish or crystal bowl. Now lay some chervil pluches and tarragon leaves between the legs in imitation of water-grasses, and cover the whole with champagne jelly to counterfeit the effect of water.

Send the dish to the table, set in a block of ice, fashioned as fancy may suggest.

Salad of Filleted Salted Herrings

Remove the fillets whole; take off the skins; set to soak and then trim them. Dish, and cover them with the following sauce:—Add the purée of eight soft roes, moistened with two tablespoonfuls of vinegar, to four tablespoonfuls of mayonnaise. Season with onion, parsley, chervil, chives, and tarragon, all finely chopped; flavour moderately with cayenne.

Fresh Herrings Marinaded in White Wine

For twelve herrings, put one pint of white wine into a sauce-pan, with one-quarter pint of vinegar, an onion cut into thin slices, half a carrot cut into grooved roundels, a faggot, the necessary salt, and a few peppercorns. Set to boil gently for twenty minutes.

Place the cleaned herrings in a sauté-pan, pour the boiling marinade upon them, and let them poach for fifteen minutes.

Serve them very cold with the marinade, the roundels of carrot, and thin strips of onion.

Lucas Herrings

Raise the fillets from fine salted herrings, soak them first in cold water, and then in milk for an hour.

Prepare a sauce as follows:—Beat up the yolks of two eggs in a bowl with salt and pepper and one tablespoonful of mustard; add five tablespoonfuls of oil and two of vinegar, proceeding as in the case of mayonnaise, and complete with shallots and one dessertspoonful of chopped chervil and gherkins. Season with cayenne, immerse the drained and dried fillets of herrings in this sauce, and send them to the table on a hors-d’œuvre dish.

Herrings à la Livonienne

Take some fine salted herrings’ fillets, clean them, and cut them into dice. Place these in a bowl, and add thereto, in equal quantities, some cold, boiled potatoes and russet apples cut into dice, parsley, chervil, and chopped fennel and tarragon. Season with oil and vinegar, salt and pepper; make the preparation into shapes resembling herrings, and place the heads and tails, which should have been put aside for the purpose, at each extremity of every supposed herring.

Herrings à la Russe

Cut some fine, cleaned fillets of salted herrings into thin slices. Dish up, and alternate the rows of sliced fillets with rows of sliced, cold, boiled potatoes. Season with oil and vinegar, and finish up with chopped chervil, fennel, tarragon, and shallots.

Herrings with French Beans

These hors-d’œuvres can only be served at their best in the months of September and October, when the first shoals of herrings begin to appear. Dutch fishermen know of a means of salting and marinading this fish, which greatly increases its value, and it is not unusual to pay as much as two or three shillings for one in the early part of the season. They can only be kept a few days, but they form an excellent dish, and their flavour Is exquisite. Before serving them, it is only needful to skin them, whereupon they may be dished up with a little chopped parsley. Send a bowl of French beans to the table with them, the vegetables having been freshly cooked, kept somewhat firm, buttered, and not cooled. Some cooks serve the beans cold, in the form of a salad, but as a rule they are preferred hot with butter, while the herrings should be very cold.

Oysters

The best oysters to be had are those of Whitstable, Colchester, Burnham, and Zeeland. The green, French Marennes, which might equal the above, are not favoured by everyone on account of their colour. Ostend oysters are also excellent, but they are neither as delicate nor as fleshy as the English ones.

Oysters are the dish par excellence; their delicacy satisfies the most fastidious of epicures, and they are so easily digested that the most delicate invalid can partake of them freely. With the exception of caviare, they are the only hors-d’œuvres which should ever appear on the menu of a well-ordered dinner.

Oysters ought to be served very cold; hence the prevailing custom of dishing them on ice. In England they are served plain on the flat half of the shell, whereas in France and elsewhere they are left in the hollow half, which is better calculated to retain the natural liquor of the oyster, held in high esteem by many. Send some slices of brown bread and butter to the table with the oysters.

The various methods of treating oysters will be given hereafter in the chapter dealing with fish. I have given them merely because consumers and caterers alike may wish to have them; but the real and best way of serving oysters is to send them to the table raw.

Ardennes Ham

This is served like smoked breast of goose, cut, raw, into thin and even slices.

Cantaloup Melon

Melon makes an excellent hors-d’œuvre for summer luncheons. It should be just ripe, and have a nice perfume. Serve it as fresh as possible.

English Melons

The English variety of melons is inferior in quality to the French.

Their shape is oval, their peel is yellow, thin, and smooth, and their pulp, which is white, more nearly resembles the water-melon than the melon in flavour.

Melon with Port, Marsala, or Sherry, &c.

Select a Cantaloup or other melon of the same kind as the former, and let it be just ripe. Make a round incision about the stalk, three inches in diameter; withdraw the plug thus cut, and through the resulting hole thoroughly remove all the pips by means of a silver spoon.

Now pour one-half pint of best Port, Marsala, or Sherry into the melon, replace the plug, and keep the melon for two or three hours in a cooler surrounded by broken ice. Do not cut the melon into slices when serving it. It should be taken to the table, whole, and then the piece containing the stalk is withdrawn and the fruit is cut into shell-like slices with a silver spoon, and served with a little of the accompanying wine upon iced plates.

Various Melons

France produces a large variety of melons, of which the principal kinds are the Sucrins of Tours, the St Laud melon, the black melons of the Carmes, &c. They are all excellent, and are served like the Cantaloups.

Natives with Caviare

This is a typically luxurious hors-d’oeuvre. Cook some little tartlet crusts for hors-d’œuvre (Formula №314). When about to dish up, garnish these with a tablespoonful of fine, fresh caviare; make a hollow in the latter and place therein a fine Whitstable oyster (cleared of its beard), seasoned with a little powdered pepper and a drop of lemon-juice.

Smoked Breast of Goose

Cut it into the thinnest possible slices, and garnish with very green parsley.

Plain Olives

Olives of all kinds are suitable for hors-d’œuvres, and they are served plain. Three or four varieties are known, all of which are excellent, provided they be fleshy, firm, very green, and moderately salted.

Stuffed Olives

For this purpose, select large Spanish olives and stone them, either by cutting them spirally, or by means of a special machine. In the place of the stone, put one of the butters or creams for hors-d’œuvres (Formulæ №280 to 299). Before serving these olives, it is well to let them rest awhile in a moderately warm atmosphere. For, since stuffed olives are generally kept in the cool, immersed in oil with which they become thoroughly saturated, it follows that the moment they are put into contact with a slightly higher temperature they will exude that oil. Wherefore, if the above precaution were not observed, by the time the olives reached the table they would, more often than not, be swimming in oil, when they would be neither nice nor appetising.

Plain Lapwings’ and Plovers’ Eggs

Though the lapwing and the plover are different in respect of their plumage, they are, nevertheless, birds of similar habits and haunts, and their eggs are remarkably alike. The latter, which are a little larger than pigeons’ eggs, have a light-green shell covered with black spots.

When cooked, the albuminous portions acquire a milky colour, and never assume the solidity of the whites of other eggs.

When served as a hors-d’œuvre, these eggs are always boiled hard. Put them in a saucepan of cold water, and leave them to cook for eight minutes after the boil is reached. Cool them, shell their pointed ends, and serve them in a nest composed of watercress or curled-leaf parsley.

N.B.—Test the freshness of the eggs before boiling them by plunging them in a bowl of cold water. If they float, their freshness is doubtful, and they should be discarded.

Lapwings’ Eggs in Aspic

Decorate a border-mould according to taste, and let a thin coating of very clear aspic jelly set on the bottom of the utensil. Besprinkle the articles used in decorating with a few drops of melted jelly, in order to keep them from shifting; then cover them with a few tablespoonfuls of jelly, and let it set. On this coating of jelly arrange the shelled, hard-boiled lapwings’ eggs with their points downwards, so that they may appear upright when the aspic is withdrawn from the mould. Fill up the mould by means of successive layers of melted jelly.

When about to serve, dip the mould into hot water; quickly wipe it, and then turn the aspic out on to a folded napkin lying on a dish.

Lapwings’ Eggs à la Moderne

Boil the eggs soft; mould them in dariole-moulds, coated with jelly, and garnished in Chartreuse fashion. Heap a vegetable-salad, thickened with mayonnaise, in the middle of the dish, and place the eggs removed from their moulds all round.

Lapwings’ Eggs à la Moderne

Cook the eggs as above; shell them; slice a piece off their thicker ends to make them stand, and arrange them on a dish, placing them upon little tartlet-crusts, garnished with a foie-gras purée.

For twelve eggs put two tablespoonfuls of foie-gras purée in a small saucepan; add thereto one tablespoonful of chopped truffles and as much melted jelly, the latter with a view to making the preparation more liquid. Take some of this preparation in a tablespoon and pour it over the eggs, taking care that each of these gets well covered with it. Let the coating set in the cool, and dish up the tartlets on a napkin, arranging them in the form of a circle with curled-leaf parsley as a centre-garnish.

Lapwings’ Eggs à la Moscovite

Boil the eggs hard; cool and shell them. Prepare as many tartlet-crusts as there are eggs. When dishing up, garnish the tartlets with a coffee-spoonful of caviare, and place one egg in the middle of each.

Various Hard-Boiled Eggs

With hard-boiled eggs for base, a large number of hors-d’œuvres may be made. I shall limit myself to a few only, which, by means of a small change in their form, garnish, or ornamentation, may be varied at will:

Egg Discs

Cut the eggs laterally into roundels one-third inch in thickness, and discard the two end-pieces of each egg, in order that the shapes may be almost uniform, and that the yolks may appear about the same size throughout. In the centre of each roundel make a little rosette of butter, by means of a small, grooved pipe. Different butters, such as the Shrimp, Montpellier, Caviare, and other kinds, may be used with the view of varying the colours.

Halved, Stuffed Eggs

Take some very small, hard-boiled eggs; cut them into two, lengthwise; remove the yolk’s, and trim the oval hollow of each of the remaining whites to the shape of an oblong, the edges of which may then be indented.

Garnish, either with a purée of tunny, salmon, milt, &c., or a hash or salpicon of lobster, shrimp, &c., thickened by means of a mayonnaise with jelly, or a fine macédoine of vegetables with mayonnaise, or a purée composed of the withdrawn yolks combined with a little butter, some cold Béchamel sauce, and herbs.

Quartered, Stuffed Eggs

The simplest way of doing this is to proceed as above, to stuff the halved white with a buttered purée, or a purée mixed with jelly, to leave the stuffing to set, and then to cut the halves in two.

Salad of Eggs

With alternate rows of sliced eggs and either tomatoes, potatoes, cucumbers, or beetroot, and a salad-seasoning composed of oil and vinegar or cream, a dozen different salads may be prepared, each of which constitutes an excellent hors-d’œuvre.

Lark Pâté

For this hors-d’œuvre use the ready-made pâté, which is obtained either in pots or crusts. Thoroughly set it by means of ice; turn it out of its receptacle, cut it into very small and thin slices, and arrange them on a hors-d’œuvre dish with a little broken jelly in the middle.

Mild, Grilled Capsicum

Grill the capsicum on a moderate fire until the skins are so scorched as to be easily removed.

Now cut them up julienne-fashion, and season with oil and vinegar.

Radishes

In the preparation of hors-d’œuvres by the kitchen, radishes are used chiefly as a garnish. When they constitute a hors-d’œuvres of themselves, their preparation is relegated to the pantry.

They are used especially in imitating the pendulous flowers of the fuchsia; sometimes, too, they are sliced and placed on cut cucumber to form a dish-border; but their uses in garnishing are as numerous as they are various.

American Relishes

These consist of divers kinds of fruit and of small onions and gherkins, prepared with vinegar, seasoned with sugar and cinnamon, and flavoured with cayenne.

They resemble what the Italians call “Aceto-dolce”. This hors-d’œuvre is accompanied by special cinnamon biscuits, and remains on the table throughout the meal.

Rillettes and Rillons

Both these preparations, which belong to the province of the pork-butcher, may be found on the market.

The rillettes are served in their pots, and are always sent to the table very cold.

Red Mullet à l’orientale

Select small ones, as far as possible. Place them in an oiled pan, and add peeled and concassed tomatoes, parsley-root, fennel, thyme, bay, a little garlic, peppercorns, coriander, and saffron, the latter being the dominating ingredient.

Cover the whole with white wine; salt moderately, set to boil, and then leave to poach on the side of the fire for twelve or eighteen minutes, in accordance with the size of the mullet.

Leave the fish to cool in their cooking-liquor, and serve them with a little of the latter and a few slices of peeled lemon.

Sardines

The various kinds of sardines for hors-d’œuvres may be found on the market.

Salads

Salads for hors-d’œuvres may consist of an endless diversity of products, and their preparation varies so that it would be impossible to prescribe fixed rules for the latter. I shall therefore restrict myself to saying merely that they should be made as light and as sightly as possible, in order that they may be in keeping with the general idea and purpose of hors-d’œuvre.

Gotha and Milan Salami

Cut these into very thin slices, and place them, one on top of the other, on a hors-d’œuvre dish, in the form of a crown, with a sprig of curled-leaf parsley in the middle. They may also be laid flat upon a litter of parsley.

Arles, Bologne or Large Lyons Sausages

Cut these up and arrange them like the Salami.

Foie-Gras Sausages

Cut into thin roundels and dish up with chopped aspic jelly as a centre-garnish.

Smoked Salmon

Cut into triangular, thin slices; roll these into cones, and arrange in the form of a crown with curled-leaf parsley in the middle.

Sprats

These are smoked sardines. Select the very fleshy ones, for there exist many kinds, a few of which are dry and quite flavourless.

In order to prepare them, suppress the heads and remove or leave on the skins, in accordance with the consumer’s taste. Put them on a dish with some finely-chopped shallots, chopped parsley, and oil and vinegar, using a very little of each ingredient. Leave them to marinade for five or six hours, taking care to turn them over from time to time so as to thoroughly saturate them with the marinade.

Tartlets and Barquettes

These articles play an important part in the service of hors-d’œuvres, and represent the class I designated under the name of Frivolities.

The garnishes suitable for tartlets are likewise used with barquettes, the latter only differing from the former in their shape. The directions which follow below, and which should be carefully noted, apply equally to both.

Special Paste for Tartlets and Barquettes

Sift one lb. of flour on to a mixing-board; make a hole in the centre, into which put one-eighth oz. of salt, one-half lb. of cold, melted butter, one egg, the yolks of two, and a few drops of water. Mix the whole into a paste, handling it as little as possible; roll it into a ball, and put it aside in the cool for two hours.

The Preparation of Tartlet- and Barquette-crusts

Roll out the paste to the thickness of one-eighth inch, and stamp it with an indented fancy-cutter into pieces of the same size as the tartlet-moulds to be used, which in this case are the same as for “petits fours”, and, therefore, very small.

The fancy-cutter should be round for tartlets, and oval for barquettes. Lay the paste in the moulds, prick the parts lying on the bottom, lest they should blister, garnish the insides with pieces of kitchen-paper to protect the paste, and fill them with rice or flour. Bake in a moderate oven; remove the rice or flour, the sole object of which was to preserve the shape of the tartlets or barquettes; turn the latter out of their moulds, and set them to cool.

The Garnishes of Tartlets and Barquettes

These may be divided into two classes, viz.,

those with a compound butter for base,
those with an aspic jelly base.

The first class comprises all the garnishes I gave for Canapés and Toast, as also all those which the operator’s fancy, taste, and inventiveness may devise.

The second class generally consists of a layer, on the bottom, of some kind of mousse, upon which a whole piece of a different colour from the mousse is placed, and which is then coated with a very clear jelly.

Example

Garnish the bottom of a tartlet or barquette with a coating of pink, shrimp, crayfish or lobster mousse. Upon this lay a very white poached oyster, or a slice of hard-boiled egg, stamped with an indented fancy-cutter. In the centre of the yolk put a little lobster coral, and coat the whole with jelly to the level of the tartlet edges.

The explanations given above warrant my refraining from a more detailed discussion of these delicate preparations. Sufficient has been said to allow of any operator, with a little taste and inventiveness, easily making an endless variety of combinations.

Tunny in Oil

This is found on the market, and it may be served as it stands. It is very greatly used as a garnish for hors-d’œuvres.

Tunny with Tomatoes

Lay alternate slices of tunny and tomato upon a hors-d’œuvre dish, and between each slice lay a thin round of onion. Garnish the edge of the dish with a border composed of sliced potato, and sprinkle the whole with an ordinary salad seasoning.

Mock Tomatoes

Select some about the size of a walnut, and peel them carefully. Press them in a piece of linen, and set them to marinade for half an hour in oil and vinegar. Then stick a small piece of parsley stalk into each tomato, in imitation of the stalk, and surround it with little leaves made from green butter by means of a small piping-bag.

Tomatoes à l’américaines

Select some firm, medium-sized tomatoes, and cut them into thin slices. Put them into a dish with salt, pepper, oil, and a few drops of vinegar, and leave them to marinade for twenty minutes. Then arrange them on a hors-d’oeuvre dish, garnishing the border with fine rings of onion.

Tomatoes à la Moneqasque

Select some small tomatoes about the size of walnuts, and cut a slice from each in the region of the stalk. Squeeze out all their water and seeds, and marinade them, inside, for twenty minutes. Prepare a mince of tunny with oil, and add thereto, per two oz. of the fish, half a tablespoonful of finely-chopped onion, a tablespoonful of chopped parsley, chervil, and tarragon, and a small, hard-boiled egg, also chopped.

Thicken the whole with a tablespoonful of thick mayonnaise; put it into a bag fitted with a smooth, medium-sized pipe, and garnish the tomatoes with the preparation, using enough of the latter to form a kind of dome upon each tomato.

Quartered Tomatoes

Use medium-sized tomatoes, somewhat firm and with very smooth skins. Peel them and empty them, and then fill them, either with a fish purée cleared with jelly, or with a macédoine of vegetables thickened by means of a mayonnaise with jelly. Place on ice for half an hour, and cut the tomatoes into regular quarters. The tomatoes may also be cut into four, previous to stuffing them, whereupon they may, with the help of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe, be filled with one of the compound butters.

Marinaded Trout

Select some very small trout, clean and dress them, and poach them in a white-wine court-bouillon (Formula №164) to which vinegar has been added in the proportion of one-third of its volume.

Leave the fish to cool in the liquor, and dish up with a few tablespoonfuls of the latter, placing some thin, grooved slices of lemon upon the fish.

Chapter XII Eggs

Of all the products put into requisition by the art of cookery, not one is so fruitful of variety, so universally liked, and so complete in itself as the egg. There are very few culinary recipes that do not include eggs, either as a principal constituent or as an ingredient.

The many and various egg-preparations constitute chiefly breakfast or luncheon dishes; nevertheless, at a Lenten dinner they may be served as entries with advantage, for, at a time when fish, shell-fish, and water-game are the only resources in this respect, eggs form a pleasant and welcome change.

Eggs on the Dish

Eggs cooked in this way derive all their quality from the way in which the cooking process is conducted. They must be evenly cooked, on top and underneath, and should remain soft. An important condition of the process is that the eggs should be exceedingly fresh. After having heated sufficient butter in the dish to cover the whole of the bottom, break two eggs into it, baste the yolks with a little very hot butter, salt them slightly, and push them into the oven. As soon as the white of the eggs assumes a milky-white colour, they are cooked and should be withdrawn from the oven to be served immediately.

Great attention should be bestowed upon the cooking process, a few seconds more or less than the required time being sufficient to spoil the eggs. Special care ought to be taken that they do not cook either too much or too quickly, for it should be remembered that, even were the cooking checked before the proper time, the heat of the dish does, to a certain extent, make good the deficiency.

Eggs à la poêle, which, in England, are called “fried eggs”, are a variety of eggs on the dish, very often served on toast, or accompanied by sausages or fried bacon. They are cooked in an omelet-pan, trimmed neatly witli a fancy-cutter, and placed, by means of a spatula, upon the prepared toast.

About one-half oz. of butter should be allowed for every two eggs, which number constitutes the working-base of the following recipes.

Bercy Eggs

Put half of the butter to be used in a dish; let it melt, break the eggs, taking care not to burst the yolks; baste the latter with the rest of the butter, and season. Cook as directed that is to say, until the whites are quite done and the yolks are glossy. Garnish with a small, grilled sausage, placed between the yolks, and surround with a thread of tomato sauce.

Eggs with Brown Butter

There are two methods:

Cook the eggs in a dish as usual, and then cover them with one-quarter oz. of brown butter and a few drops of vinegar, which should be added after the butter.
Put one-half oz. of butter into a small omelet-pan, and cook it until it is almost black. Break the eggs into it, season, cook, tilt them gently on to a dish, and besprinkle with a few drops of vinegar, with which the omelet-pan has been rinsed.

Eggs Chasseur

Cook the eggs as per Formula №395. This done, garnish on either side with a tablespoonful of sliced chicken’s liver, rapidly sautéd and cohered with a little Chasseur sauce.

Devilled Eggs

Cook the eggs in the omelet-pan; turn them, after the manner of pancakes, taking care lest they break. Slide them gently into a dish, and besprinkle them with brown butter and a few drops of vinegar with which the omelet-pan has been rinsed.

Eggs à la Florentine

Garnish the bottom of a dish with spinach-leaves stewed in butter; sprinkle thereon two pinches of grated cheese; break the eggs upon this garnish, and cover them with two tablespoonfuls of Mornay sauce. Place in a fierce oven, so that the cooking and glazing of the eggs may be effected simultaneously.

Eggs au Gratin

Put a tablespoonful of very hot Mornay sauce into a dish. Break the eggs into it, cover them with Mornay sauce, sprinkle with grated cheese mixed with fine raspings, and cook in a fierce oven, in order that the eggs and the gratin may be done at the same time.

Isoline Eggs

Cook the eggs according to Formula №395. Place between them, and all round the dish, some small, halved tomatoes à la Provençal. Put in the centre of each halved tomato a fine chicken’s liver sautéd with Madeira.

Jockey Club Eggs

Cook the eggs in an omelet-pan; tilt them gently on to a dish, and trim them with a round fancy-cutter. Place each egg upon a round, thin piece of toast, and then cover them with foie-gras purée. Arrange them in the form of a crown, on a dish, and pour into the middle a garnish of calf’s kidneys cut into dice and sautéd, and truffles similarly cut, the latter being cohered by means of some dense half glaze.

Lully Eggs

Cook the eggs in an omelet-pan, and cut them with a round fancy-cutter. Place each egg on a slice of raw ham, cut to the same shape as the former, and fried in butter. Then place the egg and ham on toast similarly shaped and of the same size. Arrange the eggs in a circle round the dish, and garnish the middle of it with macaroni combined with concassed tomatoes stewed in butter.

Meyerbeer Eggs

Cook the eggs as in Formula №395. Place a small, grilled sheep’s or lamb’s kidney between each yolk, and surround with a thread of Périgueux sauce.

Mirabeau Eggs

Substitute for ordinary butter, anchovy butter. Break the eggs and cook them. Surround each yolk with anchovy fillets, and garnish each of these with a spray of parboiled tarragon leaves. Place a large olive stuffed with tarragon butter on either side of the yolks.

Omer-Pacha Eggs

Garnish a dish with a large tablespoonful of minced onions cooked in butter and unbrowned. Break the eggs over the garnish, sprinkle them with a small tablespoonful of dry, grated Parmesan cheese, and cook in a sufficiently fierce oven for a slight gratin to form as soon as the eggs are done.

Parmentier Eggs

Bake some fine Dutch potatoes in the oven. Open them, from above, with an oval fancy-cutter; remove the pulp from the inside, rub it through a sieve, and make a smooth purée of it. Half-fill the potato-shells with this purée, break an egg into each, besprinkle with cream, and cook in the oven. Replace the part of the baked shell removed in the first instance, and dish up on a napkin.

Eggs à la Portugaise

Put a tablespoonful of tomato fondue into a dish. Break the eggs upon this, season, and cook. Between the eggs and at each end of the dish put a little heap of tomato fondue, and on each of the heaps drop a pinch of chopped parsley.

Eggs à la Reine

Cook the eggs in an omelet-pan, and trim them with a round fancy-cutter. Put each egg upon a small disc of Duchesse potatoes, of the same size as the egg, previously browned in the oven. Arrange the eggs in a circle round the dish; in the middle put a chicken mincemeat, and surround with a border of Suprème sauce.

Poached and Soft-boiled Eggs

All the recipes given hereafter apply equally to poached and soft-boiled eggs, wherefore I shall only mention “poached” in the titles, leaving soft-boiled to be understood.

Procedure for Poached Eggs

The one and only essential condition in this case is the use of perfectly fresh eggs, for it is quite impossible to expect an even poaching if this condition is not fulfilled.

Have ready a sauté-pan containing boiling salted water (one-third oz. of salt per quart of water), slightly acidulated with vinegar. Break the eggs over that part of the water which is actually boiling.
In order that the eggs may poach freely, do not put more than eight or ten at a time into the same sauté-pan; better even poach them six at a time, for then the poaching will be effected more equally.
As soon as the eggs are in the water, let the latter simmer. The egg is poached when the white has enveloped the yolk, reassuming, as it were, the form of a raw egg, and when it may be touched without breaking. The usual time allowed for poaching is three minutes.
Withdraw the eggs by means of a slice; dip them into cold water, trim their whites, and put them back into moderately warm water until ready to serve.

The Cooking of Soft-boiled Eggs

These ought to be very fresh, as in the case of poached eggs. With a view to equalising their cooking, it is a good plan to put them in a colander perforated with large holes, whereby they may be plunged into and withdrawn from the water together. Keep the water boiling; plunge the eggs therein as directed; leave them to cook for six minutes from the time the water has regained the boiling-point; drain, steep for a moment in a bowl of cold water, and shell the eggs carefully. Keep them in moderately-salted hot water until ready to serve.

The Dishing of Poached and Soft-Boiled Eggs

There are many ways of doing this, viz.:

On rusks of bread-crumb, slightly hollowed, ornamented according to taste (i.e., indented by means of the point of a small knife) and fried in clarified butter. Their shape is oval for poached eggs, and round for soft-boiled eggs, the latter being generally dished upright.
On little, oval feuilletés for poached eggs, on feuilletés in the shape of indented crowns, or in small patties for soft-boiled eggs.
In borders of forcemeat or other preparations, the kind of which is indicated by the name of the particular egg-preparation. These borders are laid on the dish by means of a piping-bag or by hand; they are either oval or round, plain or indented, poached or oven-browned, according to the nature of the preparation used.
On tartlet-crusts which are garnished so as to be in keeping with the method of dressing the eggs.

Remarks

Poached or soft-boiled eggs, when dished upon fried rusks, feuilletés, or tartlets, should, before being placed on the latter, be covered with sauce. Also before being treated with sauce they should be well drained.
Having given the general outlines of the procedure, I shall now pass on to the particular recipes, stating them briefly, and reminding the reader that all of them apply equally to poached and soft-boiled eggs. Thus “Poached Eggs Mireille” stands for “Poached or Soft-boiled Eggs Mireille”.

Poached Eggs Argenteuil

Garnish the bottom of some tartlet-crusts with asparagus cut into pieces and cooked, and six green asparagus-heads, about one and one-half inches in length, arranged like a star. Place an egg, coated with cream sauce mixed with half its volume of asparagus purée, upon each tartlet.

Poached Eggs à l’Aurore

Coat the eggs with Aurora sauce, and dish them on oval feuilletés if poached, or upright on feuilletés in the shape of rings if soft-boiled.

Poached Eggs en Berceau

Bake some fine Dutch potatoes in the oven. Cut each potato in half, lengthwise, with the point of a small knife, and remove the pulp. Emptied in this way, the halved potatoes resemble little cradles. Coat the interior of each cradle with a fine chicken mincemeat mixed with cream, and place an egg coated with Aurora sauce in each.

Poached Eggs à la Bohémienne

Garnish the bottom of some tartlet-crusts with a salpicon of foie-gras and truffles cohered with a few tablespoonfuls of the following sauce:—For six eggs, dissolve one teaspoonful of white-meat glaze; add thereto half a teaspoonful of truffle essence, and finish with a lump of butter about the size of a pigeon’s egg. Take enough of this sauce to effect the cohering of the salpicon; coat the eggs with Hungarian sauce, and place one upon each garnished tartlet.

Poached Eggs Boïeldieu

Garnish the tartlets with a white-chicken-meat, foie-gras, and truffle salpicon cohered with poultry velouté. Coat the eggs with a reduced and thickened poultry gravy.

Poached Eggs à la Bruxelloise

Garnish some tartlet-crusts with braised, minced endives thickened with cream. Place an egg, coated with cream sauce, upon each; sprinkle moderately with biscotte raspings, and set to glaze quickly in a fierce oven.

Poached Eggs à la Clamart

Garnish some tartlet-crusts with small, green peas, cooked à la française (Formula №2193), and mixed with finely ciseled lettuce which should have cooked with them. Place an egg, coated with cream sauce which has been finished with fresh-pea butter, upon each.

Poached Eggs Colbert

Garnish some tartlet-crusts with a macédoine cohered with Béchamel. Place a plainly-poached egg upon each, and send Colbert butter, separately, to the table with the tartlets.

Poached Eggs à la Comtesse

Garnish some tartlet-crusts with white asparagus purée. Place an egg coated with Allemande sauce upon each, and sprinkle with very black chopped truffles.

Poached Eggs Grand Duc

There are two modes of procedure:

Place the eggs on fried rusks, with a nice slice of truffle on each; arrange them in a circle round the dish, coat with Mornay sauce, and set to glaze in a fierce oven. On withdrawing the dish from the oven, put in the centre a garnish composed of asparagus-heads and a small faggot of the latter, very green and cooked.
Prepare a croustade, moulded in a flawn ring, the size of which must be in proportion to the number of eggs to be served. Arrange the eggs in a circle in the croustade, coat them with Mornay sauce, and set to glaze in a fierce oven. On withdrawing the croustade from the oven, garnish its centre with asparagus-heads and a small faggot as above.

Poached Eggs Maintenon

Garnish some tartlet-crusts with a Soubise à la Béchamel, slightly thickened by reduction. Coat the eggs with Mornay sauce, besprinkle with grated cheese, and place them in the crusts by means of a slice.

Set to glaze in a fierce oven, and, on withdrawing the dish from the oven, surround the crusts with a thread of melted meat-glaze.

Poached Eggs Masséna

Heat some medium-sized artichoke-bottoms in butter. Slightly hollow them, if necessary, and garnish each with a tablespoonful of Béarnaise sauce. Place an egg, coated with tomato sauce, upon each artichoke-bottom; then place a slice of poached marrow upon each egg, and a little chopped parsley upon each slice of marrow.

Poached Eggs Mireille

Slightly press some saffroned pilaff rice in buttered tartlet moulds.

Prepare as many pieces of toast of the same size as the tartlets, and fry them in oil. Place an egg, coated with cream sauce, finished with saffron, upon each. Turn the rice-tartlets out of the moulds, and arrange them in a circle on a dish, alternating them with the eggs on toast; put a coffee-spoonful of concassed tomatoes, stewed in butter and kept rather thick, upon each rice-tartlet.

Poached Eggs Mornay

Coat the eggs with Mornay sauce, and besprinkle with grated Gruyère and Parmesan cheese mixed with fine raspings. Then, by means of a slice, carefully transfer the eggs to pieces of toast fried in oil. Arrange them in a circle on a dish, sprinkle each egg with a few drops of melted butter, and set to glaze quickly in a fierce oven.

Poached Eggs d’Orsay

Place the eggs upon toast fried in butter. Arrange them in a circle on a dish, and coat them with Châteaubriand sauce.

Poached Eggs Rossini

Garnish some tartlet-crusts, each with a slice of foie gras (raw if possible) seasoned, dredged with flour, and fried in butter. Place an egg, coated with thickened veal gravy with Madeira, on each tartlet, and complete by means of a large slice of very black truffle on each egg.

Poached Eggs Sévigné

Prepare some thin rusks; fry them in clarified butter, and stuff them with a mince of braised lettuce. Place an egg on each stuffed rusk; coat with velouté mixed with poultry essence arrange in a circle on a dish, and complete by means of a ring of very black truffle on each egg.

Poached Eggs Victoria

Garnish some tartlet-crusts with a salpicon made from three oz. of spiny-lobster meat and one-half oz. of truffles, cohered with three tablespoonfuls of Diplomate sauce. Place an egg, coated with Diplomate sauce, on each tartlet. Dish, and set to glaze in a fierce oven.

Poached Eggs with Red Wine

These eggs may either be poached with red wine, or in the ordinary way.

In the first case, the wine used for poaching may serve to prepare the red wine or Bordelaise sauce (Formula №32). In either case, the eggs are dished on oval rusks, slightly hollowed and fried in butter; they are coated with the sauce, after having been dished, and they are quickly glazed.

Hard-boiled Eggs

Boiling eggs hard may seem an insignificant matter, but, like the other modes of procedure, it is, in reality, of some importance, and should be effected in a given period of time. If, for a special purpose, they have to be just done, it is pointless and even harmful to boil them beyond a certain time-limit, seeing that any excess in the boiling only makes them tough, and the whites particularly so, owing to their albuminous nature. In order to boil eggs uniformly, they should be put into a colander with large holes, whereby they may be plunged at the same moment of time into the boiling water. From the time the water regains the boiling point, eight minutes should be allowed in the case of medium-sized eggs, and ten minutes in the case of larger ones; but these times should never be exceeded. As soon as they are done drain the eggs and dip them in cold water, and then shell them carefully.

Hard-boiled Eggs Carème

Have ready beforehand a timbale crust (Formula №2395), somewhat shallow.

For six hard-boiled eggs, slice four artichoke-bottoms of medium size, and stew them in butter; cut some truffles into slices, allowing four slices to each egg, and cut up the eggs into discs about one-half inch thick. Prepare also in advance one-half pint of Nantua sauce.

Garnish the crust with alternate layers of sliced artichoke-bottoms, egg-discs, and sliced truffles. Finish with a coating of sauce and a ring of sliced truffles.

Dish up the crust on a napkin.

Hard-boiled Eggs Chimay

Cut the eggs, lengthwise, in two. Remove the yolks, pound them into a paste, and add thereto an equal quantity of dry Duxelle (Formula №223). Fill the empty whites with the preparation; place them on a buttered gratin-dish; cover them with Mornay sauce; besprinkle with grated cheese; pour a few drops of melted butter upon the sauce, and set to glaze in a fierce oven.

Hard-boiled Eggs in Croquettes

Cut the eggs into small dice (white and yolks). Per six eggs add five oz. of cooked mushrooms and one oz. of truffles, cut into dice.

Thicken the whole with one-quarter pint of reduced Béchamel, and spread on a plate to cool.

When cold, divide the preparation into portions weighing about two oz.; roll these portions into balls on a floured mixing-board, and then shape them like eggs. Dip them into an anglaise (Formula №174), taking care to cover them well with it, and then roll them in fine and fresh bread-crumbs, letting this operation avail for finishing off the shape. Put them into hot fat seven or eight minutes before dishing up; drain, salt moderately, place on a napkin, with a centre garnish of very green, fried parsley, and send a cream sauce to the table with them.

Hard-boiled Eggs in Rissoles

Make a preparation of eggs, as for the croquettes, using a little more sauce. Roll some puff-paste trimmings to a thickness of one-quarter inch, and stamp it with a round indented cutter two and one-half inches in diameter.

Place a small tablespoonful of the preparation in the middle of each piece of paste; moisten slightly all round, and make the rissoles by folding the outside edges of the paste over one another to look like a closed purse, taking care to press them well together so as to join them, thus completely enclosing the preparation. Treat them à l’anglaise; put them into hot fat eight minutes before serving, and dish up on a napkin, with a centre garnish of parsley.

Eggs à la Tripe

For six eggs, finely mince two onions, and stew them in butter, without letting them acquire any colour. Add thereto one-half pint of Béchamel sauce, and set to cook gently for ten minutes. A few minutes before serving add the eggs, cut into large slices, to the sauce.

Dish up in a timbale.

Eggs à la Tripe, Bourgeoise

For six eggs chop up two large onions and stew them in butter without colouration. Sprinkle them with one-half oz. of flour, moisten with one pint of boiling milk, and season with salt, pepper, and nutmeg.

Set to cook, gently, for twenty minutes; rub through a fine sieve or through tammy, and transfer the preparation to a saucepan, and heat it well. Dish up the eggs, which should be quartered, in a timbale, and cover them with the preparation of onions, very hot.

Eggs en Cocotte

The poaching of eggs en cocotte is done in the bain-marie.

Cocottes for eggs, which may be replaced by little china or plaited cases, are a kind of small saucepan in earthenware, in porcelain, or in silver, provided with a little handle. The time generally allowed for the cooking or poaching of eggs in this way is ten minutes, but this time is subject to variations either way. In order to accelerate the process I should advise the warming of the cocottes before the insertion of the eggs.

Mode of Procedure

Having garnished the cocottes and broken the eggs into them, as directed in the recipes given hereafter, set them in a sauté-pan and pour therein enough boiling water to reach within one-half inch of the brims of the cocottes. Place in the oven and cover, just leaving sufficient opening for the steam to escape.

The eggs are done when the whites are almost set and the yolks are glossy. After having properly wiped the cocottes, dish them on a napkin or on a fancy dish-paper.

Eggs en Cocotte au Chambertin

Prepare a red-wine sauce au Chambertin. Fill the cocottes, one-third full, with this sauce. Set to boil on a corner of the stove; break the eggs into the boiling sauce, season with a grain of salt, and put the cocottes, one by one, into a sauté-pan containing the necessary quantity of boiling water.

Poach as directed, and set to glaze quickly at the last moment.

Eggs en Cocotte with Cream

This preparation constitutes the radical type of this series of eggs, and, for a long time, was the only one in use. Heat the cocottes beforehand; pour a tablespoonful of boiling cream into each, followed by an egg, broken; season, and add two little lumps of butter, the size of peas. Place the cocottes in a bain-marie, and poach as before.

Eggs en Cocotte à la Jeannette

Garnish the bottom and the sides of the cocottes with a thickness of one-third inch of chicken-forcemeat with cream, mixed with a fifth of its volume of foie gras. Break the egg over the middle, season, and poach in the usual way. When about to serve, surround the eggs with a thread of poultry velouté.

Eggs en Cocotte with Gravy

Break the eggs into buttered cocottes. Season, poach, and, when about to serve, surround the yolks with a thread of reduced veal gravy.

Eggs en Cocotte à la Lorraine

Put a teaspoonful of breast of pork, cut into dice and fried, into each cocotte, also three thin slices of Gruyère cheese and one tablespoonful of boiling cream. Break the eggs, season, and poach in the usual way.

Eggs en Cocotte à la Maraichère

Garnish the bottom and sides of the cocottes with cooked spinach, chopped and pressed, and sorrel and lettuce leaves, both of which should be stewed in butter. Break the eggs, season, poach in the usual way, and, when about to send the eggs to the table, drop a fine chervil pluche on each yolk.

Eggs en Cocotte with Morels

Garnish the bottom and sides of the cocottes with minced morels fried in butter and thickened with a little reduced half-glaze. Break the eggs, season, poach, and surround the yolks with a thread of half glaze when dishing up.

Eggs en Cocotte à la Soubise

Garnish the bottom and sides of the cocottes with a coating of thick Soubise purée. Break the eggs, season, and poach. When dishing up, surround the yolks with a thread of melted meat-glaze.

Moulded Eggs

These form a very ornamental dish, but the time required to prepare them being comparatively long, poached, soft-boiled, and other kinds of eggs are generally preferred in their stead. They are made in variously shaped moulds, ornamented according to the nature of the preparation, and the eggs are broken into them direct, or they may be inserted in the form of scrambled eggs, together with raw eggs poached in a bain-marie.

Whatever be the mode of preparation, the moulds should always be liberally buttered. The usual time allowed for the poaching of the eggs in moulds is from ten to twelve minutes, but when withdrawn from the bain-marie it is well to let the moulds stand awhile with the view of promoting a settling of their contents, which action facilitates the ultimate turning out of the latter.

Empty the moulds on small pieces of toast or tartlets, and arrange these in a circle round the dish.

Moulded Eggs à la Carignan

Butter some Madeleine-moulds, shaped like elongated shells, and garnish them with a thin coating of chicken-stuffing or crayfish butter. Break the eggs in the middle of the forcemeat; season, place carefully in a bain-marie, and poach, with cover on, in the oven, leaving a small opening for the escape of the generated vapour. Empty the moulds on toast cut to the same shape as the moulds and fried in butter; arrange them on the dish, and coat with a Châteaubriand sauce.

Moulded Eggs à la Duchesse

Butter some baba-moulds; garnish the bottom of each with a large slice of truffle; break an egg into each, and poach in the bain-marie. Turn out the moulds on to little fluted galettes made from Duchesse potatoes and coloured in the oven after having been gilded.

Dish up in the form of a crown, and coat with a thickened veal gravy.

Galli-Marié, Moulded Eggs

For four people:

Prepare five scrambled eggs, keeping them very soft; add thereto three raw, beaten eggs and one teaspoonful of capsicum, cut into dice. Mould this preparation in four little shallow cassolettes, well buttered, and poach in the bain-marie.
Have ready and hot as many cooked artichoke-bottoms as there are cassolettes; the former should have had their edges fluted. Have also ready a “Rice à la Grecque” (Formula №2253).
Garnish the artichoke-bottoms with the rice; turn out the cassolettes upon the latter; arrange on a dish, and cover with highly-seasoned and buttered Béchamel sauce. Put the dish in a fierce oven, so as to glaze quickly, and serve immediately.

Moulded Eggs à la Mortemart

Scramble five eggs, keeping them soft, and add thereto three raw, beaten eggs. Butter some shallow, timbale moulds; garnish their bottoms with a fine slice of truffle, and fill them with the preparation of eggs. Poach in a bain-marie.

Turn out each mould on a tartlet-crust, garnished with mushroom purée à la crême (Formula №2079), and arrange in a circle on a round dish. Send a sauceboat containing some melted and buttered meat-glaze to the table with the eggs.

Neapolitan Moulded Eggs

Make a preparation consisting of scrambled eggs and Parmesan cheese, keeping it very soft; add thereto, per five scrambled eggs, two raw eggs. Fill some little, well-buttered brioche-moulds with this preparation, and poach in the bain-marie. As soon as their contents are properly set, turn out the moulds on to a buttered gratin dish, besprinkle with grated Parmesan cheese, and coat the eggs with reduced and buttered half glaze, well saturated with tomato.

Moulded Eggs Palermitaine

Butter some baba-moulds; garnish the bottoms with a slice of truffle, and besprinkle the sides with very red, chopped tongue. Put the moulds in ice for a while, in order that the tongue may set in the butter. Break an egg into each mould, season, and poach in the bain-marie. Turn out the moulds on tartlet-crusts garnished with macaroni with cream.

Polignac Moulded Eggs

Butter some baba-moulds, and garnish the bottoms with a slice of truffle. Break an egg into each; season, and poach in a bain-marie.

Turn out the moulds upon little round pieces of toast; arrange them in a circle on a dish, and coat the eggs with Maître d’Hôtel butter, the latter being dissolved and mixed with three tablespoonfuls of melted meat-glaze per every one-quarter lb. of its weight.

Princess Moulded Eggs

Butter some narrow and deep dariole-moulds; garnish their bottoms with a slice of very black truffle, and their sides with a very thin coating of chicken forcemeat.

Make a preparation of scrambled eggs, asparagus-heads, and truffles cut into dice, keeping them very soft, and add thereto raw, beaten eggs in the proportion of one raw egg to every four scrambled.

Fill the moulds, two-thirds full, with this preparation; cover the eggs with a coating of forcemeat, and poach in a bain-marie for twelve minutes.

Turn out the moulds upon little, round pieces of toast; set these in a circle on a dish, and surround them with a thread of clear poultry velouté. Or the velouté may be sent to the table separately, in a sauceboat.

Printanier Moulded Eggs

Butter some hexagonal moulds, and garnish them. Chartreuse-fashion, with cut-up, cooked vegetables, varying the shades. Break an egg into each mould; season, and poach in a bain-marie. Turn out the moulds upon little, round pieces of toast; arrange these in a circle on a dish, and pour in their midst a cream sauce finished by means of a Printanier butter with herbs, in the proportion of one oz. of butter to one-quarter pint of sauce.

Scrambled Eggs

This dish is undoubtedly the finest of all egg-preparations, provided the eggs be not over-cooked, and they be kept soft and creamy.

Scrambled eggs are mostly served in silver timbales, but, in certain cases, they may also be dished in special little croustades, in little receptacles made from hollowed brioches, or in tartlet-crusts. Formerly, it was customary to garnish scrambled eggs served in a silver timbale with small, variously-shaped pieces of toast, or with small scraps of puff-paste, cooked without colouration, and shaped like crescents, lozenges, rings, palmettes, &c.. This method has something to recommend it, and may always be adopted. In old cookery, scrambled eggs were sanctioned only when cooked in a bain-marie. This measure certainly ensured their being properly cooked, but it considerably lengthened the procedure. The latter may therefore be shortened by cooking the eggs in the usual way, i.e., in a utensil in direct contact with the fire; but in this case the heat must be moderate, in order that, the process of cooking being progressive and gradual, perfect homogeneity of the particles of the eggs (effecting the smoothness of the preparation) may result.

Method of Scrambling Eggs

For six eggs, slightly heat one oz. of butter in a thick-bottomed sauté-pan. Add the six eggs, beaten moderately, together with a large pinch of salt and a little pepper; place the pan on a moderate fire, and stir constantly with a wooden spoon, taking care to avoid anything in the way of sudden, fierce heat, which, by instantaneously solidifying the egg-molecules, would cause lumps to form in the mass—which, above all, should be guarded against.

When, by cooking, the eggs have acquired the proper consistence, and are still smooth and creamy, take the sauté-pan off the fire, and finish the preparation by means of one and one-half oz. of butter (divided into small quantities) and three tablespoonfuls of cream. Only whisk the eggs to be scrambled when absolutely necessary.

N.B.—Having given the mode of procedure, which is unalterable for scrambled eggs, I shall now pass on, in the following recipes, to the various garnishes suited to this kind of dish. The quantities I give are those required for six  scrambled eggs.

Scrambled Eggs à la Bohemienne

Take one cottage brioche for every two eggs. Remove the tops of the brioches, and the crumb from the remaining portions, so as to form cases of these. Add one-half oz. of foie gras to the scrambled eggs, and half as much truffles, cut into dice, for every two eggs. Fill the emptied brioches with this preparation, and place a slice of truffle coated with meat-glaze upon each.

Scrambled Eggs with Mushrooms

Add to the scrambled eggs one oz. of cooked mushrooms cut into dice, or raw mushrooms, minced and sautéd in butter, for every two eggs.

Dish in a timbale; put a fine, cooked, and grooved mushroom in the middle, and surround with a crown of sliced mushrooms, also cooked.

Scrambled Eggs, Chasseur

Dish the scrambled eggs in a timbale. Hollow out the middle, and place therein a garnish of one fine chicken’s liver, sautéd, per every two  eggs. Sprinkle a pinch of chervil and tarragon on the garnish, and surround with a thread of chasseur sauce (Formula №33).

Scrambled Eggs, Chatillon

Dish the eggs in a timbale, and place a garnish of mushrooms in the centre. The mushrooms should first be minced raw, and then sautéd in butter. Sprinkle a pinch of chopped parsley on the garnish, and surround with a thread of melted meat-glaze. Border the whole, close to the sides of the timbale, with small crescents of puff-paste, baked pale.

Scrambled Eggs with Shrimps

Dish the scrambled eggs in a silver timbale. Place a little heap of shrimps’ tails bound with a few tablespoonfuls of shrimp sauce in the middle, and surround with a thread of the same sauce.

Scrambled Eggs with Herbs

Add to the scrambled eggs a tablespoonful of parsley, chervil pluches, chives, and tarragon leaves in equal quantities and chopped.

Scrambled Eggs with Cheese

Break the eggs, beat them, season, and add thereto, for every two eggs, one-half oz. of fresh grated Gruyère cheese, and as much grated Parmesan. Cook the eggs in the usual way on a very moderate fire, in order to keep them creamy.

Scrambled Eggs Grand-Mère

Add to the scrambled eggs a tablespoonful of little crusts, cut into dice, fried in clarified butter, and prepared in time to be inserted into the eggs very hot. Dish in a timbale with a pinch of chopped parsley in the middle.

Scrambled Eggs Georgette

Bake three fine Dutch potatoes, or six smaller ones, in the oven. Open them by means of an incision on their tops; withdraw the pulp from the interior with the handle of a spoon, and keep the remaining shells hot. Prepare the scrambled eggs in the usual way, and finish them away from the fire with one and one-half oz. of crayfish butter, and eight or ten shelled crayfish tails. Garnish the potato shells with this preparation, and dish up on a napkin.

Scrambled Eggs for Hot Luncheon Hors-d’Œuvre

I only give one recipe of this kind, but the series may be extended at will without involving much deep research, since all that is needed for the purpose of variety is the modification of the garnish and a change in the soufflé preparation. The mode of procedure remains unalterable. Prepare the scrambled eggs, and garnish them as fancy may suggest. Also make a “Soufflé with Parmesan Cheese” (Formula №2295a).

Put the scrambled eggs into a large tartlet-crust, cook without colouration, filling them only two-thirds full. Cover with the soufflé preparation, taking care to make it project in a mound above the tartlets; place these on a tray, poach quickly in a hot oven, and glaze at the same time.

Scrambled Eggs with Morels

Add to the scrambled eggs some minced morels, sautéd in butter and seasoned. Dish in timbales, and place a fine, cooked morel in the centre of each.

Scrambled Eggs with Mousserons

Proceed as for Formula №471.

Scrambled Eggs, Orloff

Break the eggs, beat them, and add thereto a little fresh, thick cream. Cook them in the usual way, and add three crayfishes’ tails per every two eggs. Dish in little porcelain cases, place a fine slice of truffle in each of the cases, and arrange these upon a napkin lying on a dish.

Scrambled Eggs, à la Piémontaise

Add to the scrambled eggs, per every two of the latter, one-half oz. of grated Parmesan cheese and a coffee-spoonful of raw, grated. Piedmont truffles. Dish in a timbale, and garnish with a fine crown of sliced truffles of the same kind as the above.

Scrambled Eggs, à la Portugaise

Dish the eggs in a timbale, and place, in the middle, some fine, concassed tomatoes, seasoned and sautéd in butter. Sprinkle a pinch of concassed parsley on the tomatoes, and surround with a thread of meat-glaze.

Scrambled Eggs, Princess Mary

Prepare some small timbales in dariole-moulds from puff-paste scraps, and bake them without colouration; also some little covers of puff-paste, stamped out with an indented fancy-cutter, two inches in diameter. Set the covers on a tray, gild them slightly, place on each a scrap of indented paste, and leave this uncoloured. Bake the timbales and the covers in a moderate oven.

Make a preparation of scrambled eggs and Parmesan cheese add to this, away from the fire, two tablespoonfuls of reduced velouté with truffle essence and truffles cut into dice.

Garnish the timbales, put a cover on each, and dish up on a napkin.

Scrambled Eggs, Rachel

Add some truffles, cut into dice, and some asparagus-heads to the scrambled eggs. Dish on a timbale; put a fine little faggot of asparagus-heads in the middle, and surround with a crown of sliced truffles.

Scrambled Eggs, Reine Margot

Prepare the scrambled eggs in the usual way, and finish them with the necessary quantity of almond butter. Place this preparation in small tartlet-crusts, baked without colouration, and surround the tartlets with a thread of Béchamel sauce, finished with pistachio butter, the thread of sauce being close up to the edge of the tartlets.

Scrambled Eggs, Rothschild

Finely pound the remains of six crayfish (cooked in Mirepoix) the tails of which have been put aside, and add thereto, little by little, two tablespoonfuls of thick cream. Rub through tammy.

Add this crayfish cream to the six beaten eggs; season, and cook on a moderate fire with the object of obtaining a smooth, soft, and creamy preparation. Serve in a timbale and garnish, firstly with a small faggot of asparagus-heads placed in the middle of the eggs, secondly with crayfish tails arranged in a circle round the asparagus, and thirdly with large slices of very black truffles arranged in a crown around the crayfish tails.

Scrambled Eggs with Truffles

Add one tablespoonful of truffles, cooked in Madeira and cut into dice, to the scrambled eggs. Place these in a timbale, and garnish with a crown of sliced truffles.

Or place the preparation in tartlet-crusts, made from trimmings of puff-paste and baked without colouration, with a large slice of truffle on the eggs, in each tartlet.

Fried Eggs

In the long series of egg-preparations, fried eggs are those which hold the least important place, for the fried eggs which are so commonly served at breakfasts in England and America are really eggs à la poêle. The real fried egg is almost unknown in England and America. As a rule, the garnish given to this kind of eggs is served apart, while the latter are dished, either on a napkin or on pieces of toast, with a little fried parsley laid in the middle of the dish.

The Preparation of Fried Eggs

Any fat, provided it be well purified, may be used for these eggs, but oil is the more customary frying medium. To do these eggs properly, only one should be dealt with at a time.

Heat some oil in an omelet-pan until it begins to smoke slightly; break the egg on a plate; season it, and let it slide into the pan. Then, with a wooden spoon, quickly cover up the yolk with the solidified portions of the white, in order to keep the former soft.

Drain the egg on a piece of stretched linen, and proceed in the same way with the other eggs until the required quantity has been treated.

Fried Eggs à la Bordelaise

Prepare as many halved tomatoes à la Provençale (see tomatoes) as there are eggs, adding a pinch of chopped shallots to each halved tomato. When cooked, garnish them with cèpes, finely minced and sautéd à la Bordelaise; place a fried egg on each garnished half-tomato, and arrange them in a circle on a dish, with fried parsley in the middle.

>

Harvesters’ Fried Eggs

Fry as many blanched rashers of breast of bacon as there are eggs. Arrange in a circle on a dish, alternating the rasher with the eggs. Garnish the centre with large peas, cooked with ciseled lettuce and finely-sliced potatoes.

Fried Poached Eggs

This kind is recommended, because it may be served with various garnishes—either vegetables of the same nature, a macédoine, vegetable purées, or divers coulis, sauces in keeping with the eggs, artichoke-bottoms, mushrooms, morels, &c. (sliced and sautéd in butter), or tomato-fondue, &c.

After having properly drained and dried the poached eggs, which should have been prepared beforehand, dip them carefully in a Villeroy sauce (Formula №108), and arrange them, one by one, on a dish. When the sauce has set, pass the point of a small knife round the eggs to remove any excess of sauce; take them off the dish to treat them with an anglaise (Formula №174), and then roll them in very fine, fresh bread-crumbs.

Plunge them into very hot fat three or four minutes before serving; drain them on a piece of linen; salt slightly, arrange in a circle on a dish, and set the selected garnish in the middle.

Fried Eggs à la Portugaise

Place each of the fried eggs upon a half-tomato à la Portugaise, i.e., stuffed with rice after having been previously half-baked in the oven. Arrange in a circle on a dish, and garnish the centre with concassed tomatoes sautéd in butter.

Fried Eggs à la Provençale

Put each fried egg on a half-tomato on a large, thick slice of egg-plant, seasoned, rolled in flour, and fried in oil.

Set in a circle on a dish, with fried parsley in the centre.

Fried Eggs à la Romaine

Place the eggs, fried in oil, on little, oval subrics of spinach. The preparation of spinach should have anchovy fillets, cut into dice, added to it.

Fried Eggs à la Verdi

Cut six hard-boiled eggs lengthwise. Remove the yolks, pound them with two oz. of butter, and add thereto two tablespoonfuls of thick, cold Béchamel, two tablespoonfuls of cooked herbs, and one tablespoonful of lean ham, cooked and chopped. Garnish each half-white of egg with a good tablespoonful of this preparation, and smooth it with the blade of a small knife, shaping it in such wise as to represent the other half of the egg. Dip each whole egg, thus formed, into an anglaise, and roll in fine, fresh bread-crumbs. Plunge in hot fat six minutes before serving, and dish on a napkin, with fried parsley in the centre. Send, separately, to the table a garnish composed of asparagus-heads.

Fried Poached Eggs à la Villeroy

Prepare the eggs, poached beforehand, as explained under Formula №486. Fry them similarly, and dish them on a napkin, with a garnish of fried parsley in the centre.

Omelets

The procedure for omelets is at once very simple and very difficult, for tastes differ considerably in respect of their preparation. Some like them well done, others insist upon their being just done, while there are yet others who only enjoy them when they are almost liquid.

Nevertheless, the following conditions apply to all—namely, that there should be homogeneity of the egg-molecules; that the whole mass should be smooth and soft; and that it should be borne in mind that an omelet is in reality scrambled eggs enclosed in a coat composed of coagulated egg.

I take as my standard an omelet consisting of three eggs, the seasoning of which comprises a small pinch of table-salt and a little pepper, and which requires one-half oz. of butter for its preparation. The quantities of garnishing ingredients given below, therefore, are based upon this standard.

The Preparation of Omelets

Heat the butter in the omelet-pan, until it exhales the characteristic nutty smell. This will not only lend an exquisite taste to the omelet, but the degree of heat reached in order to produce the aroma will be found to ensure the perfect setting of the eggs.

Pour in the beaten and seasoned eggs, and stir briskly with a fork, in order to heat the whole mass evenly. If the omelet is to be garnished inside, this ought to be done at the present stage, and then the omelet should be speedily rolled up and transferred to a dish, to be finished in accordance with the nature of its designation.

When the omelet is on the dish, a piece of butter may be quickly drawn across its surface, to make it glossy.

Agnes Sorel Omelet

Stuff the omelet with one tablespoonful of mushrooms, minced and sautéd in butter. Roll it up, and transfer it to a dish.

Then lay eight small slices of very red tongue upon it, letting their edges overlap; surround with a thread of veal gravy.

Omelet à la Bruxelloise

Stuff the omelet with two tablespoonfuls of braised endives, ciseled and thickened with cream. Surround with a thread of cream sauce.

Omelet with Cèpes

Finely mince two oz. of cèpes; toss them in butter in an omelet-pan until they have acquired a brown colour; add thereto a pinch of chopped shallots, and toss them again for a moment.

Pour the eggs into the omelet-pan; make the omelet; dish up, and surround with a thread of half glaze.

Omelet with Mushrooms

Mince two oz. of raw mushrooms; toss them in butter in an omelet-pan; add the eggs thereto, and make the omelet. Transfer it to a dish, lay three little cooked and grooved mushrooms upon it, and surround with a thread of half glaze.

Omelet à la Choisy

Stuff the omelet with two tablespoonfuls of braised lettuce the latter should have been ciseled and cohered by means of cream sauce.

Roll and dish the omelet, and surround it with a thread of cream sauce.

Omelet à la Clamart

Stuff the omelet with two tablespoonfuls of fresh peas, bound by means of butter and combined with a portion of the lettuce used in cooking them, finely ciseled. Roll and dish the omelet, make an opening lengthwise in the centre, and fill the interspace with a tablespoonful of fresh peas.

Omelet with Crusts

Combine with the beaten and seasoned eggs two tablespoonfuls of small crusts, cut into dice, fried in clarified butter, and very hot.

Make the omelet very quickly.

Omelet with Spinach

Stuff the omelet with two tablespoonfuls of spinach with cream, and surround with a thread of cream sauce.

Omelet à la Fermière

Add to the beaten and seasoned eggs one tablespoonful of very lean, cooked ham cut into dice. Pour the eggs into the omelet-pan, and cook them quickly, taking care to keep them very soft. Let the outside harden slightly; tilt into the dish after the manner of a pancake, and besprinkle the surface with a pinch of chopped parsley.

Omelet Aux Fines Herbes

Add to the eggs one tablespoonful of parsley, chervil, chive, and tarragon leaves, all to be finely chopped and almost equally apportioned.

Make the omelet in the usual way.

Omelet with Vegetable Marrow Flowers

Add to the eggs one and one-half oz. of the calices of freshly-plucked and young vegetable-marrow flowers; cisel and stew them, and add thereto a pinch of chopped parsley. Surround the omelet with a thread of tomato sauce.

N.B.—This omelet may be made with oil, as well as with butter.

Omelet with Chicken’s Liver

Stuff the omelet with two tablespoonfuls of chicken’s liver, which should be cut into dice or finely sliced, seasoned, quickly sautéd in butter, and cohered with half-glaze. Dish the omelet, make an opening lengthwise in the centre, and place one tablespoonful of chicken’s liver, prepared as above, in the interspaces. Besprinkle with chopped parsley, and surround the omelet with a thread of half-glaze.

Omelet with Artichoke-bottoms

Finely mince two small artichoke-bottoms (raw if possible), season them, and slightly colour them in butter. Add the beaten and seasoned eggs, and make the omelet in the usual way.

Omelet with Young Shoots of Hops

Stuff the omelet with two tablespoonfuls of young shoots of hops, cohered with cream, and finish it in the usual way. Open it slightly along the top, and garnish with a few young shoots of hops put aside for the purpose.

The omelet may be surrounded with a thread of cream sauce, but this is optional.

Omelet à la Lyonnaise

Finely mince half an onion, and cook it with butter in an omelet-pan, letting it brown slightly. Add the eggs, with which a large pinch of chopped parsley has been mixed, and make the omelet in the usual way.

Omelet Maxim

Make the omelet in the usual way. Lay upon it alternate rows of crayfish tails and slices of truffle. Surround the omelet with a fine border of frogs’ legs “sautéd à la Meunière”, i.e., seasoned raw, rolled in flour, and sautéd in butter until quite cooked and well gilded.

Omelet with Morels

Mince and toss in butter two oz. of very firm morels. Two should be put aside, which, after having been cut in two, lengthwise, and sautéd with the others, should be placed on a dish when the omelet is about to be made. Having dished the latter, place the four sautéd and reserved pieces of morels upon it, and surround it with a thread of half-glaze.

Omelet Mousseline

Beat the yolks of three eggs in a bowl with a small pinch of salt and a tablespoonful of very thick cream. Add thereto the three whites, whisked to a stiff froth, and pour this preparation into a wide omelet-pan containing one oz. of very hot butter. Sauté the omelet, tossing it very quickly, and taking care to turn the outside edges of the preparation constantly towards the centre; when the whole mass seems uniformly set, roll the omelet up quickly, and dish it. This omelet should be sent to the table immediately.

Omelet with Mousserons

Mince two oz. of very fresh mousserons; toss them in butter in the omelet-pan; add thereto the eggs mixed with a pinch of chopped parsley; make the omelet, dish it, and surround it with a thread of half-glaze.

Omelet à la Nantua

Add to the omelet six little crayfishes’ tails, each of which must be cut into three, and the whole mixed with a little Nantua sauce. Put two fine crayfishes’ tails on the omelet, making them touch at their thicker ends, and surround with a thread of Nantua sauce.

Omelet Parmentier

Add a pinch of chopped parsley to the eggs, and, when about to pour the latter into the omelet-pan, add two tablespoonfuls of potato cut into dice, seasoned, sautéd in butter, and very hot. Make the omelet in the usual way.

Omelet à la Paysanne

Frizzle with butter, in the omelet-pan, two oz. of breast of bacon cut into dice. Add to the eggs one tablespoonful of finely-sliced potatoes sautéd in butter, one-half tablespoonful of ciseled sorrel stewed in butter, and a pinch of concassed chervil.

Pour the whole over the bacon-dice; cook the eggs quickly, keeping them soft; turn the omelet after the manner of a pancake, and tilt it immediately on to a round dish.

Omelet with Asparagus-tops

Add one and one-half tablespoonfuls of blanched asparagus-tops, stewed in butter, to the omelet. Having dished the omelet, open it along the middle, and lay a nice little faggot of asparagus-tops in the interspace.

Omelet à la Provençale

Rub the bottom of the omelet-pan lightly with a clove of garlic; put two tablespoonfuls of oil into the utensil, and heat it until it smokes.

Throw into the oil a fine, peeled, pressed, and pipped tomato, cut into dice and besprinkled with a pinch of concussed parsley. Cook it quickly, tossing it the while, and add it to the beaten and seasoned eggs. Make the omelet in the usual way.

N.B.—The nature of this preparation demands the use of oil in treating the tomato, but, failing oil, clarified butter may be used.

Omelet with Kidneys

Add to the omelet a tablespoonful of calf’s or sheep’s kidney, cut into dice, seasoned with salt and pepper, sautéd quickly in butter, and cohered by means of half-glaze. Having dished the omelet, divide it down the middle, lay some reserved kidney-dice in the interspace, and surround with a thread of half-glaze.

Omelet à la Rossini

Add to the beaten and seasoned eggs one dessertspoonful of cooked foie gras and as much truffle, cut into small dice. Having dished the omelet, place in the middle thereof a small rectangular piece of heated foie gras, and two slices of truffle on either side of the latter. Surround it with a thread of half-glaze flavoured with truffle essence.

Omelet with Truffles

Add to the omelet one tablespoonful of truffles, cut into dice. Make the omelet, dish it, and lay a row of fine slices of truffles upon it. Surround it with a thread of melted meat-glaze.

Hot Lapwings’ and Plovers’ Eggs

Note.—In the chapter on hors-d’œuvres, where recipes were given which deal with lapwings’ eggs, I made a few remarks relative to their freshness, and indicated the procedure for boiling them soft and hard.

Scrambled Lapwings’ Eggs

Proceed as for ordinary scrambled eggs, all the recipes given for the latter being perfectly applicable to lapwings’ eggs. They require, however, very great care in their preparation, and it should be borne in mind that one ordinary hen’s egg is equal to about three lapwings’ eggs.

Lapwings’ Eggs à la Danoise

Poach the eggs as directed in the recipe dealing with the process, and dish them up in tartlet-crusts garnished with a purée of smoked salmon.

Omelet of Lapwings’ Eggs

Proceed as for other omelets, but one ordinary hen’s egg is generally added to every six lapwings’ eggs in order to give more body to the preparation. All the omelet recipes already given may be applied to lapwings’ eggs.

Lapwings’ Eggs à la Royale

Garnish as many small tartlet moulds as there are eggs with chicken-forcemeat. Poach, turn out the moulds, and hollow out the centres of the tartlets in such wise as to be able to set an egg upright in each.

Place a soft- or hard-boiled egg on each forcemeat tartlet, coat the eggs with a light purée of mushrooms, besprinkle with chopped truffles, and arrange in a circle on a dish.

Lapwings’ Eggs au Troubadour

Select as many large morels as there are eggs. Remove the stalks, and widen the openings of the morels; season them, and stew them in butter. Boil the lapwings’ eggs soft.

Garnish each stewed morel with an egg; set them on little tartlet-crusts garnished with a light, foie-gras purée, and arrange them in a circle on a dish.

Cold Eggs

The preparation of cold eggs is not limited by classical rules; it rests with the skill and artistic imagination of the operator, and, since fancifulness and originality are always closely allied to artistic imagination, it follows that the varieties evolved may be infinite.

Indeed, so various and numerous are the recipes dealing with this kind of egg-preparations that I must limit myself to a selection only of the more customary ones, culled as far as possible from my own repertory.

Cold Eggs Alexandra

Take some cold, well-trimmed, poached eggs; dry them and cover them with a white chaud-froid sauce. Place a fine indented slice of truffle in the centre of each, and sprinkle with a cold, white, melted aspic jelly until they are thinly coated therewith. Slip the point of a small knife round each egg with the view of moving them more easily, and transfer them to oval tartlet-crusts made from puff-paste trimmings, baked without colouration.

Lay a border of caviare round the eggs; dish them in the form of a crown, and put some chopped jelly in the centre.

Cold Eggs à l’andalouse

Cover some cold, well-dried, poached eggs with a tomato purée combined with a full third of its volume of Soubise purée and one-half pint of melted aspic jelly per pint of sauce. Cut some pimentos, marinaded in oil, into very thin strips, and lay these, after the manner of a lattice, upon each egg.

Now garnish as many oiled, oval tartlet-moulds as there are eggs with tomato purée, thickened with jelly, and let the garnish set on ice. Turn out the moulds, and put an egg upon each of the tomato tartlets; arrange the latter in a circle on a dish surrounded with a chain composed of linked rings of onion, and garnish the centre with chopped, white jelly.

Cold Eggs Argenteuil

Coat some well-dried, soft-boiled eggs, slightly cut at their base to make them stand, with a white chaud-froid sauce combined with a good third of its volume of asparagus-tops purée. Sprinkle repeatedly with cold, melted, white jelly, until a glossy coating is obtained.

Garnish the centre of a dish with a salad of asparagus-tops surround this with fine slices of cold potato, cooked in water and cut up with an even fancy-cutter, one inch in diameter, and arrange the eggs all round.

Cold Eggs Capucine

Carefully dry some cold, poached eggs, and half-coat them lengthwise with a white chaud-froid sauce; complete the coating on the other side with a smooth purée of truffles, thickened with jelly. Leave these two coats to set, placing the eggs in the cool or on ice for that purpose.

Garnish the centre of a round dish with a small pyramid of cold, truffled Brandade of morue, and set the eggs round the latter.

Cold Eggs Carème

Cook the eggs on the dish, leave them to cool, and trim them with an even fancy-cutter, oval in shape. Place each egg on an oval tartlet-crust, garnished with dice of cooked salmon, cohered with mayonnaise.

Surround with a thread of caviare, and lay a thin slice of very black truffle on each egg.

Cold Eggs Colbert

Garnish some small, oval moulds in Chartreuse fashion, i.e., like a draught-board. Put a small, cold, poached egg in to each mould, fill up with melted, white jelly, and leave to set. Garnish the centre of a dish with a heaped vegetable salad; arrange the eggs taken from their moulds around this, and surround with a little chopped jelly.

Cold Eggs Colinette

Let a thin coat of white jelly set upon the bottom and sides of some small, oval moulds. Garnish the latter with some small dice, consisting of white of egg and truffles, placing them so as to simulate a draught-board; now insert a very small, cold, poached egg into each mould, and fill up with a melted jelly.

Garnish the centre of a dish with a “Rachel” salad, encircled by a ring of sliced, cold potatoes, cooked in water, and place the eggs, removed from their moulds, all round. Border the dish with indented crescents of white jelly.

Cold Eggs with Tarragon

Mould these in baba-moulds, or in porcelain cocottes; some times they may simply be dished up on small tartlet-crusts.

The preparation consists of poached or soft-boiled eggs, garnished with blanched tarragon leaves, or coated or moulded with a very fine tarragon jelly.

Cold Eggs, Frou-frou

Select some very small poached eggs of equal size, cover them with a white chaud-froid sauce combined with about a third of its volume of a purée of hard-boiled egg-yolks.

Garnish the top of each egg with an indented ring of very black truffle, and surround the base of the eggs with a narrow ribbon composed of chopped truffles. Glaze with jelly, and leave to set on ice.

Prepare a salad of green vegetables (peas, French beans cut into dice or lozenges, asparagus-tops); thicken it with a very little mayonnaise mixed with melted jelly. Pour this preparation into an oiled mould, and leave it to set. For dishing, turn out the salad in the middle of a dish; surround the base with a line of chopped jelly; encircle the whole with the eggs, letting them rest on the jelly, and garnish the dish with a border of dice cut in very clear, white jelly.

Cold Eggs Moscovite

Slightly level both ends of some shelled, hard-boiled eggs. Surround the tops and the bases with three little anchovy fillets, and place a bit of truffle just half-way along each egg. Eggs prepared in this way resemble little barrels, whereof the anchovy fillets imitate the iron hoops, and the bits of truffle the bungs. By means of a tubular cutter empty the eggs with care; garnish them with caviare, and shape the latter to a point, outside the edges of the egg.

Lay each egg in an artichoke-bottom, cooked white, and garnished with finely-chopped jelly, and arrange them in a circle on a dish with chopped jelly in the centre.

Cold Eggs à la Nantua

Prepare some hard-boiled eggs to resemble little barrels, after the manner described above. For every six eggs keep ready and cold eighteen crayfish cooked à la Bordelaise. Shell the tails, put two aside for each egg, and cut the remainder into dice; finely pound the bodies and remains, add thereto three tablespoonfuls of thick cream, and rub through tammy. Add to this cullis one tablespoonful of thick mayonnaise.

Bind the crayfish tails, cut into dice, with a few tablespoonfuls of this sauce, and garnish the eggs, emptied by the method indicated above, with the preparation of dice, making it stand out of the eggs in the shape of a small dome. Garnish each dome with a rosette composed of four halved crayfish tails and four truffle lozenges.

Glaze well with jelly; set the eggs upon artichoke-bottoms garnished with a mayonnaise with crayfish cullis, and arrange in a circle on a dish.

Cold Eggs Polignac

Prepare some eggs à la Polignac, as explained under “Moulded Eggs”, and leave them to cool. Select some moulds a little larger than those used in the cooking of the eggs; pour into each half a tablespoonful of melted, white jelly, and leave to set. Then put an egg into each mould, and fill up the space around the eggs with melted, white jelly.

Leave to set, turn out the moulds, arrange the mouldings on a dish, and surround them with dice of faintly coloured jelly.

Cold Eggs à la Reine

Prepare some soft-boiled eggs, and leave them to cool. Take as many cottage brioches as there are eggs; trim them to the level of the fluting, and remove the crumb from the inside, so as to form little croustades of them. Garnish the bottom and the sides of these croustades with a fine mince of white chicken-meat, thickened with mayonnaise, and season moderately with cayenne. Place a shelled, soft-boiled egg in each croustade coat thinly with mayonnaise slightly thickened by means of a jelly; lay a fine piece of truffle on each egg, and, when the sauce has set, glaze with jelly, using a fine brush for the purpose.

Dish up on a napkin.

Cold Eggs, Rubens

Season some cooked young shoots of hops with salt and freshly-ground pepper; add thereto some chopped parsley and chervil, and a purée of plainly-cooked tomatoes combined with just sufficient jelly to ensure the cohesion of the hops. Mould in oiled tartlet-moulds.

Coat some well-dried, cold, poached eggs with white chaud-froid sauce; garnish with pieces of tarragon leaves, and glaze with jelly.

Turn out the tartlet-moulds; set an egg on each of the mouldings, and arrange them in a circle on a dish, placing between each egg a piece of very clear jelly, cut to the shape of a cock’s comb.

Chapter XIII Soups

Soups are divided into two leading classes, viz.:

Clear soups, which include plain and garnished consommés.
Thick soups, which comprise the Purées, Veloutés, and Creams.

A third class, which is independent of either of the above, inasmuch as it forms part of plain, household cookery, embraces vegetable soups and Garbures or gratined soups. But in important dinners—by this I mean rich dinners—only the first two classes are recognised.

When a menu contains two soups, one must be clear and the other thick. If only one is to be served, it may be either clear or thick, in which case the two kinds are represented alternately at different meals.

In Part I. of this work I indicated the general mode of procedure for consommés and thick soups; I explained how the latter might be converted from plain purées into veloutés or creams, or from veloutés into creams; and all that now remains is to reveal the recipes proper to each of those soups.

Remarks.—In the course of the recipes for consommés, given hereafter, the use of Royales (№206 to №213) and of Quenelles, variously prepared (№193 to №195), will often be enjoined. For the preparation of these garnishes, therefore, the reader will have to refer to the numbers indicated.

The quantities for the clear soups that follow are all calculated to be sufficient for a standard number of six people, and the quantity of Royales is always given in so many dariole-moulds, which contain about one-eighth pint, or baba-moulds, which hold about one-fifth pint.

Of course, it will be understood that the poaching need not necessarily have been effected in these moulds, for very small “Charlotte” moulds would do quite as well. But I had recourse to the particular utensils mentioned above, in order that there might be no sort of doubt as to the exact quantity of royale it would be necessary to prepare for any one of the soups.

Clear Soups and Garnished Consommés

Consommé Alexandra

Have a quart of excellent chicken consommé ready; add thereto, in order to thicken it slightly, three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca, strained through muslin, and very clear.

Put the following garnish into the soup-tureen: One tablespoonful of white chicken-meat cut in fine julienne-fashion, one tablespoonful of small chicken quenelles, grooved and long in shape, and one tablespoonful of lettuce chiffonade.

Pour the boiling consommé upon this garnish, and send to the table immediately.

Consommé Ambassadrice

Have one quart of chicken consommé ready; also there should have been prepared beforehand, with the view of using them quite cold, three different kinds of royales, consisting respectively of truffle purée, tomato purée, and purée of peas, each of which should have been poached in a dariole-mould.

Cut these royales up into regular dice, and put them in the soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of chicken fillet and an equal quantity of small, freshly-cooked mushrooms, finely minced. Pour the boiling consommé over these garnishes, and serve at once.

Consommé Andalouse

Prepare a baba-mould of royale made from tomato purée. When quite cold, cut it into dice, and put these in the soup-tureen with one small tablespoonful of cooked ham cut in julienne-fashion, one tablespoonful of boiled rice, with every grain distinct and separate, and two tablespoonfuls of threaded eggs (№217).

When about to serve, pour one quart of very clear chicken consommé over the garnish.

Consommé d’Arenberg

With a small spoon-cutter, pick out a spoonful of carrot pellets and the same quantity of turnip pellets. Cook these vegetables by boiling them in consommé, taking care that the latter be reduced to a glaze when the vegetables are cooked.

With the same spoon take the same quantity as above of very black truffle; also prepare a dariole-mould of royale made from asparagus heads, and a dozen small chicken-forcemeat quenelles, which should be moulded to the shape of large pearls.

Poach the quenelles, cut the royales up into slices, which must be stamped with an indented fancy-cutter, and put the whole into the soup-tureen with the carrots, turnips, and truffle pellets, and one tablespoonful of very green peas.

Pour a quart of chicken consommé over the garnish, and send to the table at once.

Consommé à la Bohémienne

Prepare three dariole-moulds of foie-gras purée, and twelve profiteroles (№218) of the size of hazel-nuts, the latter being made very crisp.

When the royale is cold, cut it into little, regular squares, and put these into the soup-tureen.

When about to serve, pour over this garnish a quart of chicken consommé, thickened by means of three tablespoonfuls of tapioca, poached and strained through linen.

Send the profiteroles to the table separately, and very hot.

Consommé Boïdeldieu

Prepare eighteen chicken-forcemeat quenelles, moulded by means of a small teaspoon; some should be stuffed with foie-gras purée, moistened with a little velouté; others with chicken purée; and yet others with truffle purée—in short, six of each kind.

Place these, one by one, on a buttered sauté-pan; poach them, drain them, and put them in the soup-tureen with a tablespoonful of white chicken-meat, cut into dice.

When about to serve, pour one quart of chicken consommé, thickened as above with tapioca, over the garnish.

Consommé Bouquetière

Prepare a garnish of carrots and turnips, cut with the tubular cutter or with the spoon; French beans cut into lozenges, asparagus-heads, and green peas, all of which vegetables should be fresh and young. Cook each vegetable according to its nature, and put the whole into the soup-tureen.

When about to serve, pour over the garnish one quart of chicken consommé thickened with two tablespoonfuls of tapioca, poached and strained through fine linen.

Consommé Bourdaloue

Prepare a dariole-mould of each of the four following royales:

Of a purée of haricot-beans with a slight addition of tomato.
Of a chicken purée moistened with velouté.
Of a purée of asparagus-tops combined with a few cooked spinach leaves, to deepen the colour.
Of a carrot purée (Purée Crécy).

Having poached and cooled the royales, cut them as follows:—

Into dice,
into lozenges,
into little leaves, and
into stars.

Place them all in the soup-tureen, and, when about to serve, pour one quart of boiling and very clear chicken consommé over them.

Potage Bortsch

Cut in julienne-fashion the heads of two leeks, one carrot, half of an onion, four oz. of the white of cabbage leaves, half a root of parsley, the white part of a stick of celery, and four oz. of beetroot; set the whole to stew gently in butter.

Moisten with one quart of white consommé and two or three tablespoonfuls of the juice of grated beetroot; add a small bunch of fennel and sweet marjoram, two lbs. of moderately fat breast of beef, and the half of a semi-roasted duck; set to cook gently for four hours.

When about to serve, cut the breast of beef into large dice, and cut the duck into small slices; finish the soup with one-quarter pint of beetroot juice, extracted from grated beetroot pressed in linen, and a little blanched and chopped fennel and parsley. Put the beef dice and sliced duck into the soup, with twelve grilled and despumated chipolatas.

Serve, separately, a sauceboat of sour cream.

N.B.—The chipolatas may be replaced by very small patties with duck forcemeat, which should be served separately.

Consommé Brunoise

Cut into small dice the red part only of two small carrots, one small turnip, the heads of two leeks, a small stick of celery, and the third of an onion of medium size.

Season the vegetables moderately with salt and a pinch of sugar, and stew them in butter. Moisten with one-half pint of consommé, and complete the cooking of the Brunoise gently. Five minutes before serving, finish with one quart of boiling, ordinary consommé, a moderate tablespoonful of peas, and the same quantity of French beans, cut into dice and kept very green.

Pour into the soup-tureen, and add a pinch of fine chervil pluches.

Consommé Carmen

Prepare one quart of consommé, to which add, while clarifying, one-quarter pint of raw tomato purée, in order to give it a faint, pink tinge.

Also peel and press a small and rather firm tomato; cut into dice, and poach the latter in some of the consommé; put them in the soup-tureen with a small tablespoonful of mild capsicum, cut in fine julienne-fashion, and one tablespoonful of plain-boiled rice.

When about to serve, pour the boiling consommé over the garnish, and add a small pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Castellane

Prepare

one quart of game consommé, flavoured with a fumet of woodcock;
two baba-moulds of royale, two-thirds of which consists of a purée of woodcock and one-third of lentils, with half the yolk of a hard-boiled egg, chopped and thickened with the usual leason.

Cut this royale into slices, about the size of a florin, one-half inch thick. Put these into the soup-tureen, together with one tablespoonful of a julienne of roast woodcock fillets, and pour thereon the boiling game consommé.

Consommé Célestine

Prepare one quart of chicken consommé, and add thereto three small tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca, strained through fine linen.

For the garnish make three pannequets (formula №2476) without sugar, and spread over each a thin coating of chicken force-meat with cream. Place one on top of the other, sprinkle the layer of forcemeat on the uppermost one with finely-chopped, very black truffles, and place in the front of the oven for a few minutes, in order to poach the forcemeat.

Stamp the pannequets out with an even fancy-cutter about one inch in diameter. Put the pieces into a soup-tureen, and, when about to serve, pour in the boiling consommé.

Consommé Chartreuse

Prepare

eighteen small ravioles (formula №2296)—six from spinach purée, six from foie-gras purée, and the remaining six from chopped mushrooms;
two small tablespoonfuls of tomato dice. Ten minutes before serving, poach the ravioles in boiling, salted water, and the tomato dice in some of the consommé.

Put the ravioles and the tomato dice (well drained) into the soup-tureen, and pour over them one quart of consommé with a moderate addition of tapioca. Add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé aux Cheveux d’Ange

About two minutes before serving, plunge three oz. of very fine vermicelli, known as Angel’s Hair (Cheveux d’Ange) into one quart of excellent, boiling consommé.

An instant only is needed to poach the vermicelli, and the latter does not require to be blanched.

This soup, like those containing pastes, should be accompanied by freshly-grated Parmesan cheese.

Consommé Colbert

Have ready one quart of excellent Printanier chicken consommé (formula №601). Also poach six small eggs in slightly salted and acidulated water. The eggs should be as small and as fresh as possible, both of which conditions are absolutely necessary for a proper poaching (see poached eggs, №411). Set these eggs in a small timbale with a little consommé, and send them to the table with the Printanier. Having poured the latter into the plates, put one of the eggs into each of these.

Consommé Columbine

Prepare a good tablespoonful of carrot pearls, and as many turnip pearls, keeping the latter very white. Cook them in the customary way, and put them in the soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of very green peas, one tablespoonful of a julienne of roast-pigeon fillets, and six poached pigeons’ eggs, which latter should be sent to the table in a timbale at the same time as the consommé.

Pour over the other garnish one quart of very clear, boiling, chicken consommé, and serve immediately.

This soup can only appear on summer and spring menus, when the pigeons’ eggs are in season.

Croûte Au Pot

Prepare a freshly-cooked vegetable garnish for a stock-pot:—Carrots and turnips cut into small sticks and trimmed; a few heads of leeks, and cabbage, parboiled, minced, and cooked in very fat consommé.

Put these vegetables in a somewhat greasy broth for ten minutes.

Also prepare seven or eight crusts of French soup “flutes” besprinkle them with stock grease, and dry them in the oven. Put the vegetable garnish into the soup-tureen; pour thereon one quart of consommé of the Petite Marmite (formula №589), and add to the dried crusts.

Consommé Cyrano

Prepare

one quart of consommé with a fumet of duck;
twelve small quenelles of duck forcemeat, which should be made flat and oval.

Having poached the quenelles, drain them, and set them in a small, shallow earthen pan or timbale sprinkle with a little grated Parmesan cheese and a few drops of chicken glaze, and set to glaze in the oven.

The quenelles are served separately in the pan in which they have been glazed, and the consommé is sent to the table in a soup-tureen.

Consommé Demidoff

With the small spoon-cutter, pick out a good tablespoonful of carrot, and the same quantity of turnip pearls. Cook these vegetables in the customary way, and put them in the soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of truffle pearls, the same quantity of peas, and small, poached, chicken-forcemeat quenelles with herbs. Pour one quart of boiling chicken consommé over this garnish, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Deslignac

Prepare

two small, stuffed lettuces, rolled into sausage form and poached;
two baba-moulds of royale with cream.

Cut the royale into small, regular dice; trim the lettuce, and cut it into slices; put this garnish into the soup-tureen, and pour thereon one quart of boiling chicken consommé, thickened with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca, strained through linen. Add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé aux Diablotins

Cut a French soup “flute” into twelve slices one-quarter inch thick. Reduce about one-quarter pint of Béchamel to a thick consistence; add thereto, away from the fire, two heaped tablespoonfuls of grated Gruyère cheese, and season with a little cayenne.

Garnish the slices of soup “flute” with this preparation, arranged in the form of a dome, upon a tray, and set it to glaze a few minutes before serving.

Pour one quart of chicken consommé into the soup-tureen, and add the diablotins.

Consommé Diplomate

Roll into small sausage-form three oz. of chicken forcemeat, finished with crayfish butter. Poach the sausages, cut them into thin roundels, and put them into the soup-tureen with one dessertspoonful of very black truffle, cut in julienne-fashion.

Pour over this garnish one quart of boiling chicken consommé, thickened with two tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca, strained through linen.

Consommé Divette

Prepare two baba-moulds of royale made from crayfish velouté, eighteen small quenelles of smelt forcemeat, moulded to the shape of pearls, and one tablespoonful of small pearls of very black truffle.

Cut the royale into oval slices, and put these into the soup with the poached quenelles and the truffle pearls.

Pour one quart of very clear, boiling consommé over the garnish.

Consommé Doria

Prepare the following garnish:—Thirty pellets of cucumber in the shape of large pearls; eighteen small quenelles of chicken forcemeat, long in shape and grooved; six little pellets, about the size of a large pea, of pâte à choux, combined with grated cheese, rolled by hand; and one and one-half tablespoonfuls of Japanese pearls, poached in some of the consommé.

Put the cucumber pellets, cooked in consommé, into the soup-tureen; add the poached quenelles and the Japanese pearls. Four minutes before serving, plunge the pellets of pâte à choux into hot fat, keeping them crisp.

When about to serve, pour over the garnish one quart of boiling chicken consommé; complete with a pinch of chervil pluches, and serve the little, fried pellets separately.

Consommé Douglas

With an even cutter, the size of a penny, cut up some braised and cooled sweetbread into twelve roundels one-third inch thick with the same cutter cut out twelve more roundels from some cooked artichoke-bottoms, and put the whole into the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of very green asparagus-heads.

When about to serve, pour one quart of boiling, highly seasoned, ordinary consommé upon the garnish.

Consommé à l’Écossaise

Prepare a special mutton broth, and, at the same time, cook a fine piece of breast of mutton for the garnish.

Per two quarts of broth, put into the soup-tureen four tablespoonfuls of pearl-barley, cooked very gently beforehand; two tablespoonfuls of French beans, cut into lozenges, and the breast of mutton cut into regular dice of one-half inch side, in the proportion of one tablespoonful for each person.

Pour the boiling mutton broth over this garnish, after having removed all the grease and strained it through linen.

Consommé Favourite

With a spoon-cutter, pick from out some violet potatoes eighteen pellets the size of small hazel-nuts, and cook them in salted water in good time for them to be ready for the dishing up of the soup. Put them in the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of a julienne of artichoke-bottoms and the same quantity of cooked mushrooms, also cut in julienne-fashion.

Pour over the garnish one quart of chicken consommé, thickened with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca strained through linen. Add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Fermière

Mince, somewhat finely, one small carrot, one small turnip, the heads of two leeks, and the half of an onion. Slightly stew these vegetables in one and one-half oz. of butter; moisten with one and one-half pints of white consommé; add two oz. of parboiled cabbage, cut roughly into a julienne, and complete the cooking gently, taking care to remove all grease, with the view of obtaining a very clear consommé.

Pour into the soup-tureen, and add a few thin slices of French soup “flute”, slightly dried.

Consommé Florentine

With fine chicken forcemeat make twenty-four small quenelles on a buttered tray, their shape being that of small Mecca loaves. To the forcemeat of six of these quenelles add some very finely chopped tongue; add white chicken-meat to that of another six; and to that of the remaining twelve add some very reduced spinach purée. The quenelles with spinach should number twice those with the other two ingredients, in order that the preparation may be in keeping with its designation “à la Florentine”.

Poach the quenelles; put them in the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of very green, cooked peas.

>When about to serve, pour one quart of very clear, boiling chicken consommé over this garnish, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Gauloise

Prepare two dariole-moulds of ham royale, and poach the latter in a small, well-buttered Charlotte mould. When quite cold, cut it into large lozenges, and put these into the soup-tureen with six small cocks’ combs and six small cocks’ kidneys (these latter as small as possible).

When about to serve, pour over this garnish one quart of chicken consommé, thickened slightly with two tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca, strained through linen.

Consommé George Sand

Have ready one quart of consommé flavoured with very clear fish fumet. Also prepare twelve small quenelles of whiting forcemeat, finished with crayfish butter; stew twelve morels, which should be left whole if very small, and cut into two if they are of medium size; twelve small slices of poached carps’ milt, and twelve little roundels of French soup “flutes”.

Put the poached quenelles and the stewed morels into the soup-tureen; pour therein the boiling, fish consommé, and send the slices of carps’ milt set on the roundels of French soup “flute” separately to the table.

Consommé Germaine

Prepare two dariole-moulds of royale made from a purée of very green peas, combined with a tablespoonful of Mirepoix stewed in butter, and a strong pinch of small, chervil pluches; eighteen small quenelles of chicken forcemeat with cream, moulded to the form of pastils.

When the royale is cold, cut it into regular roundels, and put these into the soup-tureen with the poached quenelles.

When about to serve, pour one quart of boiling chicken consommé over the garnish.

Consommé Girondine

Prepare

one quart of highly-seasoned beef consommé;
two baba-moulds of ordinary royale made with whole eggs and combined with two tablespoonfuls of cooked and finely-chopped lean ham;
three tablespoonfuls of a julienne of carrots (the red part only) stewed in butter, the cooking of which should be completed in the consommé.

Put the royale, cut into large, regular lozenges, and the julienne of carrots into the soup-tureen, and pour in the boiling beef consommé.

Consommé Grimaldi

Have ready one quart of excellent ordinary consommé, to which have been added, while clarifying, four tablespoonfuls of raw tomato purée, strained through fine linen.

Also prepare two dariole-moulds of ordinary royale, and three tablespoonfuls of a fine julienne of the white of celery, stewed in butter, finally cooked in the consommé, and with all grease removed.

Put the royale, cut into large dice, and the julienne of celery into the soup-tureen, and pour thereon the boiling consommé with tomatoes.

Consommé Impériale

Prepare three dariole-moulds of mousseline forcemeat of fowl (forumla №195), and put it to poach in a small Charlotte mould.

When quite cold, cut it, by means of a cutter, into roundels the size of a penny, and put these in the soup-tureen with six small blanched cocks’ combs and three sliced cocks’ kidneys, and two tablespoonfuls of very green peas.

Pour over this garnish one quart of chicken consommé, thickened with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca strained through linen.

Consommé à l’Indienne

Have ready one quart of ordinary consommé seasoned with curry. Also prepare three baba-moulds of royale made from cocoanut milk, and, when quite cold, cut into small dice.

Put this royale into the soup-tureen; pour on it the boiling consommé with curry, and send to the table, separately, four tablespoonfuls of Rice à l’Indienne (formula №2254).

Consommé à l’Infante

With some pâte à choux (formula №2374) prepare eighteen profiteroles of the size of hazel-nuts. Cook them, taking care to keep them very crisp, and stuff them when cold with purée de foie gras moistened with velouté.

Put two tablespoonfuls of a fine julienne of mild capsicum into the soup-tureen, and pour thereon one quart of boiling chicken consommé, moderately thickened with poached tapioca strained through linen.

Serve the profiteroles of foie gras separately, after having heated them in the front of the oven.

N.B.—The garnish of Consommé à l’Infante may consist only of the profiteroles, and the julienne of capsicum may be suppressed; this is a matter of taste.

Consommé Jacqueline

With a small spoon-cutter, pick from out some carrots twenty-four little oval pellets, which should be cooked in the consommé. Prepare two baba-moulds of royale with cream.

Put into the soup-tureen the pellets of carrots and the royale cut to the shape of pastils, one tablespoonful of peas, the same quantity of very green asparagus-heads, and one tablespoonful of rice.

When about to serve, pour one quart of boiling chicken consommé over this garnish.

Consommé Julienne

Cut into fillets, two inches in length, the red part only of two medium-sized carrots, one medium-sized turnip, one leek, half a stick of celery, some cabbage leaves, and half an onion. Season these vegetables with a pinch of salt and as much castor sugar; stew them in one oz. of butter; moisten with one and one-half pints of white consommé and then add two oz. of small parboiled cabbages, cut after the manner of the other vegetables.

Finish the cooking gently, removing the grease the while, and complete with one small tablespoonful of very green, cooked peas, one tablespoonful of sorrel and lettuce chiffonade, and one pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Lorette

Have ready one quart of chicken consommé. Also prepare two tablespoonfuls of a fine julienne of celery stewed in butter and cooked in the consommé; twelve small “pommes à la lorette“(formula №2226), the size of hazel-nuts, and shaped like small crescents. These potatoes should be fried in hot fat four  minutes before serving.

Put into the soup-tureen the julienne of celery, twelve small, freshly-poached cocks’ kidneys, and one tablespoonful of a julienne of pimentos; pour the boiling consommé over this garnish; add a pinch of chervil pluches, and send the lorette potatoes to the table separately.

Consommé MacDonald

Prepare

one quart of highly seasoned beef consommé;
two dariole-moulds of brain-purée royale;
two tablespoonfuls of cucumbers cut into small dice and cooked in consommé until the latter is reduced to a glaze;
five little ravioles garnished with chicken forcemeat combined with a third of its volume of spinach.

Put these ravioles to poach in salted boiling water twelve minutes before serving.

Consommé Marguerite

Take two tablespoonfuls of chicken forcemeat with cream, and roll it into sausage-form on the floured mixing-board. Put the sausage to poach. Rub the yolk of an egg through a fine sieve, and cohere it with half a teaspoonful of raw forcemeat.

Having poached and cooled the chicken sausage, cut it into thin roundels, and stamp each roundel with a fancy-cutter to the shape of a marguerite. Arrange the marguerites on a dish, and lay in the middle of each a bit of the egg and forcemeat, in imitation of the flower-centre.

Put these marguerites into the soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of small, green asparagus cut into lengths of one inch. When about to serve, pour one quart of very clear, boiling chicken consommé over this garnish.

Consommé Marquise

Prepare one quart of good, ordinary consommé, to which three sticks of celery have been added, while clarifying, in order that the taste of the celery may be very decided.

Make thirty small quenelles of chicken forcemeat combined with finely-chopped filberts, giving them the shape of pastils.

Poach these quenelles ten minutes before serving. Also poach in court-bouillon two calf’s piths, and cut them into thin roundels.

Put the poached quenelles and the roundels of calf’s piths into the soup-tureen, and pour thereon the boiling consommé.

Consommé Mercédès

Prepare one quart of chicken consommé with pimentos, combined, at the last minute, away from the fire, with one-half pint of sherry.

Put into the soup-tureen two tablespoonfuls of capsicum, cut in fine julienne-fashion and short, and some small, freshly-cooked cocks’ combs.

When about to serve, pour the consommé over this garnish.

Consommé Messaline

Prepare one quart of chicken consommé, and add thereto, while clarifying, one-quarter pint of tomato essence, obtained by reducing the moisture contained by the tomato to a syrup.

Put into the soup-tureen twelve small, freshly-poached cocks’ combs, two tablespoonfuls of Spanish capsicum cut into a julienne and poached in the consommé if fresh (this should have been previously grilled, with the view of removing the skins), and two tablespoonfuls of poached rice, every grain of which should be distinct.

Pour the boiling consommé over this garnish.

Consommé Metternich

Prepare one quart of game consommé with pheasant fumet. Also poach two dariole-moulds of royale, made from a purée of artichokes combined with some tablespoonfuls of the reduced game Espagnole. Cut this royale into dice; put these into a soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of a julienne of pheasant fillets, and pour thereon the boiling consommé.

Consommé à la Milanaise

Cook in slightly salted boiling water two oz. of moderately thick macaroni. As soon as it is cooked, drain it, lay it on a piece of linen, and cut it into small rings. Also prepare one-quarter pint of Béchamel, thickened with the yolk of one egg combined with one oz. of grated cheese, and keep it very dense.

Mix the rings of macaroni with this sauce; spread the whole on a dish, and leave to cool. Now divide up the preparation into portions the size of walnuts; roll these into balls, and then flatten them out to form quoits about the size of shillings. Treat these quoits with an anglaise, and very fine bread-crumbs, and plunge into hot fat four minutes before serving. Drain them when they have acquired a fine golden colour.

Pour one quart of boiling chicken consommé into the soup-tureen, and send to the table, separately,

the fried macaroni quoits;
one and one-half oz. of Gruyère and Parmesan cheese, in equal quantities, grated and mixed.

Consommé Mireille

Add one tablespoonful of very concentrated tomato purée to three oz. of chicken forcemeat; roll this preparation into the form of a somewhat large sausage, and poach it. When cold, cut it into roundels, one-quarter inch thick, and stamp each roundel with an oval fancy-cutter in the shape of a medallion. Put these medallions in the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of saffroned pilaff rice (formula №2255), and, when about to serve, pour thereon one quart of very clear, boiling chicken consommé.

Consommé Mirette

Make eighteen quenelles of chicken forcemeat in the shape of large pearls, and poach them. Prepare two tablespoonfuls of lettuce chiffonade (the heart of one lettuce cut julienne-fashion and stewed in butter); make eighteen paillettes with Parmesan (formula №2322), and put them in a very hot oven eight or ten minutes before serving.

Put the poached quenelles and the lettuce chiffonade into the soup-tureen; pour thereon one quart of boiling consommé of the Petite Marmite, and one pinch of chervil pluches.

Send the paillettes au Parmesan to the table separately, and have them very hot.

Consommé Monte Carlo

Make and poach thirty small quenelles of chicken forcemeat; cisel and stew in butter the heart of one lettuce; prepare twelve little profiteroles of pâte à choux, the size of hazel-nuts, and cook them, taking care to keep them crisp.

Put the quenelles and the lettuce chiffonade into the soup-tureen; pour thereon one quart of very clear, boiling, chicken consommé, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Serve the profiteroles separately and very hot.

Consommé Montmorency

Have ready one quart of chicken consommé thickened with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca, strained through linen. Prepare eighteen small grooved quenelles of chicken forcemeat. Poach, drain, and put them into the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of very green asparagus-heads and two tablespoonfuls of poached rice, every grain of which should be distinct and separate.

Consommé à la Moscovite

Prepare one quart of sterlet or sturgeon consommé, and add thereto some cucumber essence, obtained by pounding a cored and peeled cucumber, and straining the resulting purée through linen.

Put into the soup-tureen two tablespoonfuls of a julienne of salted mushrooms, one oz. of soaked vesiga cut into dice and cooked in broth, and pour thereon the boiling consommé.

N.B.—Vesiga or the spine-marrow of the sturgeon ought to be soaked in cold water for a few hours in order to soften and swell it, after which it should be cut into dice and cooked in broth. For every four tablespoonfuls of cooked vesiga, one oz. of dry vesiga should be allowed.

Consommé Nesselrode

Have ready one quart of game consommé, prepared with hazel-hen fumet. Poach two baba-moulds of royale made from chestnut pur®e with two small tablespoonfuls of game salmis sauce added thereto; cut it into roundels half-inch thick, and trim these with a grooved fancy-cutter.

Put them into the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of a julienne of hazel-hen fillets, the same quantity of a julienne of mushrooms, and pour thereon the boiling game consommé.

Consommé aux nids d’Hirondelles

The nests used for this soup are those of the esculent swallow, and their shape somewhat resembles that of the rind of a quartered, dry orange.

In the first place, prepare a chicken consommé containing a large proportion of nutritious principles. Set three nests to soak in cold water for twenty-four hours, the object being to swell the mucilaginous elements of which they are composed and to make them transparent.

When they have soaked sufficiently remove any pieces of feather which may have remained in them, using for this purpose the point of a needle, and, when the nests are quite clean, drain them and put them into the consommé. At this stage set the consommé to boil, gently, for thirty or thirty-five minutes without interruption. During this time the gummy portions of the nests will melt into the consommé, giving the latter its characteristic viscidity, and there will only remain visible those portions which, in the natural state, constitute the framework of the nests; that is to say, little threads not unlike superfine transparent vermicelli.

Consommé aux Œufs de Fauvette

I introduced this consommé in honour of the illustrious singer, Adelina Patti.

It consists of a chicken consommé, which should be made as perfect as possible, and a garnish composed of the poached eggs of small birds.

Consommé Olga

Prepare one quart of excellent ordinary consommé, and add thereto, when about to serve and away from the fire, one-quarter pint of port wine.

Also cut into a fine julienne the quarter of a small celeriac, the white of a leek, and the red part only of a small carrot. Stew this julienne in butter and complete its cooking in consommé, reducing the latter to a glaze.

When about to serve put this julienne in a soup tureen, add a few tablespoonfuls of a julienne of salted gherkins, and pour thereon the consommé with port.

Consommé d’Orléans

Lay on a buttered tray ten small quenelles of ordinary chicken forcemeat, ten others of chicken forcemeat combined with a very red tomato purée, and ten more of the same forcemeat, combined with a purée of spinach, all the quenelles being grooved.

Ten minutes before serving poach these quenelles, drain them, put them in the soup-tureen, and pour therein one quart of chicken consommé thickened with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca strained through linen. Add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé d’Orsay

Prepare one quart of very clear chicken consommé, also make fifteen small quenelles of pigeon forcemeat moulded to the shape of eggs by means of a very small spoon, and poach the yolks of ten eggs, taking care to keep them very soft.

Put the quenelles and the poached yolks into the soup-tureen with a julienne of three fillets of pigeon and a tablespoonful of asparagus-heads, and pour thereon the boiling consommé. Serve at once.

Ox-tail Soup

For Ten People.—Garnish the bottom of a small stock-pot or stewpan with one fine carrot and two medium-sized onions cut into roundels and browned in butter, and one faggot. Add two small ox-tails, or one of medium size weighing about four lbs. (The tails should be cut into sections, each of which should contain one of the caudal vertebræ, and they should then be browned in the oven.) Also add two lbs. of gelatinous bones, broken very small and likewise browned in the oven.

Now proceed exactly as for brown veal stock (formula №9), taking note that the whole moistening must consist of no more than two and one-half quarts of ordinary broth and one quart of water.

Set to boil very gently for four and one-half or five hours. This done, strain the broth, which should be reduced to two and one-half quarts, and completely remove its grease. Transfer the largest sections of the tails, by means of a braiding-needle, one by one to another saucepan. Cover them with broth, and keep them warm for the garnish.

Finely chop one lb. of very lean beef; put this mince into a saucepan with the white of a leek cut into dice and half the white of an egg, and mix thoroughly. Add the broth, the grease of which has been removed, set to boil, stirring constantly the while, and then leave to simmer for one hour, which is the time required for the beef to exude all its juices and for the clarification of the broth.

While the clarification is in progress cut a small carrot in brunoise fashion, or turn it by means of a very small spoon.

Cook this garnish in a little water with butter, salt, and sugar. A few minutes before serving strain the ox-tail broth through a napkin, put the sections of ox-tail and brunoise into the soup-tureen, and pour thereon the prepared broth. This soup may be flavoured with port or sherry, but this is optional.

N.B.—If a thickened ox-tail soup be required add to the broth per every quart of it one-third of an oz. of arrowroot diluted with a little of the broth or some cold water.

Consommé Parisienne

Have one quart of chicken consommé ready.

For the garnish prepare two dariole-moulds of royale made from a purée of ordinary julienne, a small macédoine of vegetables, comprising one heaped tablespoonful each of carrots and turnips divided up by means of a small grooved spoon and cooked in the usual way, one tablespoonful of small peas, the same quantity of fine French beans cut into lozenges, and one tablespoonful of asparagus-heads.

Cut the royale into regular roundels; put these in the soup-tureen with the macédoine of vegetables, and, when about to serve, pour thereon the boiling chicken consommé. Add a pinch of fine chervil pluches.

La Petite Marmite

For Ten People.—Prepare a consommé in a special earthenware stock-pot in accordance with the procedure indicated in recipe №1, but with the following quantities, viz., two lbs. of lean beef and as much breast of beef, one marrow-bone tied in a muslin-bag, and the necks, the pinions, and the gizzards of six large fowls, these giblets being inserted in the stewpan one hour before dishing up.

Moisten with three and one-half quarts of water and add three-quarters of an oz. of salt. Set to boil, skim as indicated, and cook gently with the view of obtaining a very clear broth. One hour before serving add six oz. of carrots and the same quantity of turnips, both cut to the shape of large olives, five oz. of the white of leeks, and a heart of celery.

Cook a quarter of a very white, properly blanched cabbage, separately, in a saucepan with a little consommé and some stock grease.

When about to serve test the seasoning of the consommé, which latter should be very clear; thoroughly clean the stewpan, which may even be covered with a clean napkin; withdraw the marrow-bone; take it out of its muslin-bag, and send it and the cabbage to the table separately, accompanied by a plate of small pieces of hot toast for the marrow.

The Pot-au-Feu

Prepare this exactly like the Petite Marmite.

Poule au Pot, or Poule au Pot Henri IV

This is a variation of the Petite Marmite, in which a tender and very fleshy hen is substituted for the giblets of fowl.

Strictly observe the rule of never using a new earthenware stock-pot before having boiled water in it for at least twelve hours. Also bear in mind that earthenware stock-pots should be washed in hot water only, without any soda or soap.

Consommé Printanier

Have ready one quart of chicken consommé, also cut one carrot and one turnip into roundels one-half inch thick. With a tubular cutter one-eighth inch in diameter, cut these roundels into little rods, making a sufficient number to fill one tablespoonful with each vegetable. Cook these little rods in consommé, and reduce the latter to a glaze.

Put the carrot and turnip rods into the soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of small peas, the same quantity of small French beans and asparagus-heads, the former cut into lozenges, ten roundels of sorrel leaves, and as many of lettuce leaves, the latter being poached in some consommé. When about to serve pour the boiling consommé over these garnishes and add a large pinch of small chervil pluches.

Consommé Printanier aux Quenelles

Prepare the printanier exactly as directed above, but slightly lessen the quantities of the vegetables constituting the garnish. Make eighteen small quenelles of chicken forcemeat in the shape of little grooved meringues, and poach them ten minutes before dishing up.

Drain them, put them into the soup-tureen with the other garnishes, and pour thereon the boiling consommé.

Consommé aux Profiteroles

Prepare forty very dry profiteroles (formula №218), and add an excellent chicken consommé to them at the last moment.

The profiteroles may also be made to the size of walnuts, in which case they may be stuffed with a purée of chicken, foie gras, &c.

Consommé Rachel

Prepare one quart of chicken consommé, and thicken it with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca strained through linen. With a round, even cutter stamp out twelve roundels of crumb of bread the size of pennies and one-half inch thick. Poach in consommé as many slices of very fresh beef-marrow as there are roundels of bread.

Six minutes before serving fry the roundels of bread in clarified butter, hollow out their centres, and place on each a slice of poached beef-marrow suitably trimmed.

Put three tablespoonfuls of a julienne of cooked artichoke bottoms into the soup-tureen, pour thereon the thickened consommé, and add the roundels of bread garnished with marrow.

Consommé Réjane

Prepare one quart of excellent white consommé, set it to boil, and add a julienne of the white of half a fowl and the heads of two leeks cut similarly to the fowl. Set to cook gently for ten minutes, taking care to disturb the consommé as little as possible, add three oz. of potatoes cut into a julienne, complete the cooking, and serve immediately.

Consommé Renaissance

Prepare one quart of clear chicken consommé.

For the garnish make two dariole-moulds of royale with a purée of early-season herbs thickened with velouté and whole eggs; with a small grooved spoon-cutter pick out one tablespoonful of pellets from a turnip and the red part only of a carrot.

Cook these vegetables in the usual way. Cut the royale with a grooved fancy-cutter into pieces of the shape of small leaves. Put the leaves of royale into the soup-tureen with the carrot and turnip pellets, one tablespoonful of very green peas, the same quantity of French beans cut into lozenges, one tablespoonful of asparagus-heads, and twelve very small particles of very white cauliflower. Pour the boiling consommé over these garnishes, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Richelieu

Have ready one quart of highly-seasoned beef consommé. Also

prepare twelve quenelles of chicken forcemeat moulded by means of a small coffee-spoon, proceeding as follows:—Line the spoon with a thin coating of the forcemeat, and in the middle lay some chopped, reduced, cold chicken aspic. Cover the jelly with a layer of forcemeat, shaping it like a dome; insert another spoon (first dipped in hot water) under the quenelle, and place the latter upon a buttered sauté-pan. Repeat the operation until the required number of quenelles have been moulded. Treated in this way, the quenelles, when poached, contain, so to speak, a liquid core. Five minutes before dishing up, poach the quenelles.
Cut six rectangles out of lettuce leaves; spread a thin layer of forcemeat over each; roll into paupiettes, and poach in some of the consommé.
Prepare two tablespoonfuls of a coarse julienne of carrots and turnips, stew them in butter, and complete their cooking in the consommé, which should be thoroughly cleared of grease.

Put the julienne, the paupiettes, and the stuffed quenelles into the soup-tureen; pour therein the boiling beef consommé, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Rossini

Prepare one quart of chicken consommé, slightly thickened with two tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca strained through linen.

Make eighteen profiterolles, from pâte à choux without sugar (formula №2374), to the size of hazel-nuts. Bake them in a moderate oven, keeping them very crisp, and garnish them, inside, with a foie-gras and truffle purée.

When about to serve, pour the consommé into the soup-tureen, and dish the profiteroles separately, after having placed them in good time in the front of the oven, so that they may reach the table very hot.

Consommé Rothschild

Have ready one quart of game consommé, prepared with pheasant fumet. Add thereto, when about to serve, one-quarter pint of reduced Sauterne. Make two dariole-moulds of royale from a preparation consisting of one-third of the whole of purée of pheasant, one-third of chestnut purée, and one-third of pheasant salmis sauce. Poach the royale; cut it into grooved roundels, and place these in the soup-tureen with one tablespoonful of a julienne of fillets of pheasant.

When about to serve, pour the boiling consommé over the garnish.

Consommé Saint Hubert

Take one quart of game consommé, prepared with venison fumet. Finish the consommé, at the time of serving, with one-quarter pint of Marsala.

Make three dariole-moulds of royale from a preparation consisting of one-third of the whole of venison purée, one-third of lentil purée, and one-third of reduced game Espagnole. Poach the royale in a small Charlotte mould, and, when it has cooled, cut it up. with a fancy-cutter of the shape of a cross. Put the crosses of royale into the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of a julienne consisting of fillets of hare, and pour thereon the boiling consommé.

Potage Sarah Bernhardt

Sprinkle three tablespoonfuls of tapioca into one quart of boiling chicken consommé, and leave to poach gently for fifteen or eighteen minutes.

Make twenty small quenelles from chicken forcemeat, finished by means of crayfish butter, and mould them to the shape of small, grooved meringues. Poach these quenelles. Cut twelve roundels, the size of a penny, from a piece of beef-marrow, and poach them in the consommé.

Put the drained quenelles and the poached roundels of marrow into the soup-tureen; add one tablespoonful of a julienne of very black truffles, and the same quantity of asparagus-heads. Pour the boiling consommé, with tapioca, over this garnish.

Consommé Sévigné

Keep one quart of very clear chicken consommé very warm.

Prepare ten quenelles of chicken forcemeat, moulded by means of a small coffee-spoon, and poach them; also have ready four braised lettuces.

Put the quenelles, the lettuce cut into small sections and properly trimmed, and one tablespoonful of peas into the soup-tureen; pour therein the boiling consommé and a pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Souveraine

Have ready one quart of chicken consommé.

Make ten large quenelles from chicken forcemeat, and stuff them with a very fine brunoise, proceeding as follows:—Line a dessertspoon with a thin coat of forcemeat, and garnish the centre with the brunoise, previously cooked in consommé, and cold. Cover the brunoise with a layer of forcemeat, shaping it like a dome; insert another dessertspoon dipped into hot water under the quenelle, and transfer the latter to a buttered sauté-pan. Repeat the operation until the required number of quenelles have been moulded.

Allow eight minutes for the poaching of these quenelles; put them into the soup-tureen with two tablespoonfuls of peas; pour thereon the boiling consommé, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Turtle Soup

With the exception of a few leading London restaurants, where a large quantity of this preparation is constantly in demand, turtle soup is very rarely prepared in the kitchens of catering establishments. It is more generally obtained ready-made, either fresh or preserved, and as a rule of exceptional quality, from firms whose speciality it is to make it, and who deliver it in excellent condition.

From among the London firms who have deservedly earned a reputation for this soup, “Pécriaux” may be quoted as one whose produce is quite irreproachable.

When a comparatively small quantity of this soup is required, it is best to buy it ready-made; in the event of its being desirable to prepare it oneself, the following recipe will be found the simplest and most practical for the purpose.

Particulars of the Operation

The Slaughtering of the Turtle

For soup, take a turtle weighing from 120 to 180 lbs., and let it be very fleshy and full of life.

To slaughter it, lay it on its back on a table, with its head hanging over the side. By means of a double butcher’s hook, one spike of which is thrust into the turtle’s lower jaw, while the other suspends an adequately heavy weight, make the animal hold its head back; then, with all possible dispatch, sever the head from the body.

Now immediately hang the body over a receptacle, that the blood may be collected, and leave it thus for one and one-half or two hours.

Then follows the dismemberment:—To begin with, thrust a strong knife between the carapace or upper shell and the plastron or lower shell, exactly where the two meet, and separate the one from the other. The turtle being on its back, cut all the adhering flesh from the plastron, and put the latter aside. Now cut off the flippers; remove the intestines, which throw away, and carefully collect all the green fat. Whereupon cut away the flesh adhering to the carapace; once more remove all fat, and keep both in reserve.

The Treatment of the Carapace, the Plastron, and the Flippers

The carapace and plastron, which are the outside bony framework of the turtle, constitute the only portions wherefrom the gelatinous flesh, used as the garnish of the soup, are obtained.

Saw the carapace into six or eight pieces, and the plastron into four.

Put these pieces with the flippers into boiling water or into steam, to blanch. Withdraw the flippers as soon as they are sufficiently stiff for their skin to be removed, and leave the pieces of carapace and plastron to blanch for five minutes, in order that they may admit of being scraped. Now cool the pieces of carapace and plastron and the flippers, and put them into a stewpan containing enough water to abundantly cover them. Set to boil; garnish with vegetables, as in the case of an ordinary broth, and add a small quantity of turtle herbs.

Five or six hours should be allowed for the cooking of the carapace and the plastron, but the flippers, which are put to further uses in other culinary preparations, should be withdrawn at the end of five hours.

When the pieces are taken from the cooking-liquor, remove all the flesh from the bones, and cool the former; then trim it carefully, and cut it into little squares of one and one-half inches side. It is these squares together with the green fat (poached in salted water and sliced) which constitute the garnish of the soup.

The Preparation of Turtle Soup

There are two modes of procedure, though their respective results are almost identical.

Make a broth of the flesh of turtle alone, and then add a very gelatinous beef consommé to it, in pursuance of the method employed when the turtle soup is bought ready-made.

This procedure is practically the best, more particularly if the soup has to be kept some time.

Make an ordinary broth of shin of beef, using the same quantity of the latter as of turtle. Also include half a calf’s foot and one-half lb. of calf’s shin per 3 lbs. of the beef. Add the flesh of the turtle, or, in the event of its being thought necessary to clarify, which operation I do not in the least advise, reserve it for that purpose.

The condiments and aromatics being the same for both methods, I shall now describe the procedure for method №1.

The Ingredients of the Soup

Put into a stewpan of convenient size the flesh of the turtle and its head and bones. Moisten partly with the cooking-liquor of the carapace, and complete the moistening, in the case of a turtle weighing 120 lbs., with enough water to bring the whole to 50 quarts. By this means a soup of about thirty to thirty-five quarts will be obtained at the end of the operation. Add salt in the proportion of one oz. per every five quarts; set to boil; skim, and garnish with twelve carrots, a bunch of leeks (about ten bound with a head of celery), one lb. of parsley stalks, eight onions with ten cloves stuck into them, two lbs. of shallots, and one head of garlic. Set to boil gently for eight hours. An hour before straining the soup, add to the garnish four strips of lemon-peel, a bunch of herbs for turtle, comprising sweet basil, sweet marjoram, sage, rosemary, savory, and thyme, and a bag containing four oz. of coriander and two oz. of peppercorns.

Finally, strain the soup through a napkin; add the pieces of flesh from the carapace and plastron which were put aside for the garnish, and keep it until wanted in specially-made sandstone jars.

The Serving of the Soup

When about to serve this soup, heat it; test and rectify its seasoning, and finish it off by means of a port wine glass of very old Madeira to every quart.

Very often a milk punch is served with turtle soup, the recipe being:—

Milk Punch

Prepare a syrup from one-half pint of water and three and one-half oz. of sugar, the consistence at the boil being 17° (Baumé’s Hydrometer). Set to infuse in this syrup two orange and two lemon zests. Strain at the end of ten minutes, and add one-half pint of rum, one-fifth pint of kirsch, two-thirds pint of milk, and the juice of three oranges and three lemons. Mix thoroughly. Let it stand for three hours; filter, and serve cold.

Consommé Tosca

Have ready one quart of chicken consommé thickened with three tablespoonfuls of poached tapioca strained through linen.

Also prepare two tablespoonfuls of a julienne of carrots stewed in butter, the cooking of which is completed in the consommé; ten small quenelles of chicken forcemeat, combined, in the proportion of one-third, with foie gras and chopped truffles ten small, very crisp profiteroles, stuffed with a purée of chicken with pistachio kernels.

Put the quenelles and the julienne into the soup-tureen, pour therein the boiling consommé, and send the profiteroles to the table separately, and very hot.

Consommé Vert Pré

Sprinkle two tablespoonfuls of tapioca into one quart of boiling consommé, and set to cook gently for a quarter of an hour.

Put into the soup-tureen one tablespoonful of asparagus-heads, the same quantity of peas and of French beans cut into lozenges, a few roundels of sorrel leaves, and as many roundels of poached lettuce leaves.

Pour the boiling consommé, with tapioca, over this garnish, and add a large pinch of chervil pluches.

Consommé Villeneuve

Have ready one quart of chicken consommé.

Prepare the following garnish:—Two small blanched lettuces, stuffed with chicken forcemeat combined with braised and chopped salted tongue; two dariole-moulds of ordinary royale, and two pancakes coated with a layer of chicken forcemeat, which should be placed in the front of the oven for a few moments with the view of poaching the forcemeat.

Put the cut-up lettuces, the pancakes cut into small, narrow lozenges, and the royale cut into pastils, into the soup-tureen and, when about to serve, pour the boiling consommé over the whole.

Special Cold Consommé for Suppers

Remarks Relative to the Consommés.—I gave the recipes of these consommés in Part I. of this work (formula №6), and shall now, therefore, limit myself to the following remarks, which are of paramount importance:

These consommé must be perfect in limpidness and quality.
The flavour which typifies them should be at once decided and yet not too pronounced.
When the flavour is imparted by a wine, the latter should be of the best possible quality. Rather than make use of inferior wines, the presence of which in the soup would tend to depreciate its quality, completely discard wine flavourings.
Supper consommés never contain any garnish.

Consommé à l’Essence de Cailles

Use roast quails in the proportion of two for each pint of consommé; the fillets may be reserved for a cold entrée.

Consommé à l’Essence de Céleri

It is impossible to state exactly how much celery should be used, the quantity being entirely subject to the more or less decided flavour of the vegetables at one’s disposal.

Experience alone can guide the operator in this matter.

Consommé à l’Essence de Morilles

Allow five oz. of small fresh morels, or three oz. of dry ones per quart of the consommé. Pound them and mix them with the clarification.

Consommé à l’Essence de Truffle

Use fresh truffles only in this case. Allow two oz. of peelings and trimmings per quart of the consommé; pound them and mix them with the clarification.

Consommé aux Fumet de Perdreau

Proceed as in formula №618; allow one partridge for each quart of the consommé.

Consommé aux Paillettes d’Or

Take a very superior chicken consommé; add thereto, per quart, a glass of excellent liqueur brandy, and, in the same proportion, one gold-leaf cut into small spangles.

Consommé aux Piments Doux

Add one-half oz. of fresh or preserved capsicum to every quart of the consommé. The product should be pounded and mixed with the clarification.

Consommé à la Madriléne

Add four oz. of raw tomato and one oz. of capsicum to the consommé per every quart of the latter. Mix these ingredients with the clarification, and serve as cold as possible.

Consommé à la Portugaise

Add to the consommé for every quart one-third pint of raw tomato purée and one-sixth pint of tomato juice. Cook with lid on for twenty minutes, taking care not to let it reach the boil; strain through muslin, pressing lightly the while, and season moderately with cayenne. Set to cool, and serve very cold.

Consommé aux Vins

By adding a port wine glass full of the chosen wine to one pint of excellent cold chicken consommé, the following series of consommés may be made:—

Consommé au vin de Chypre.
Consommé au vin de Madère.
Consommé au vin de Malvoisie.
Consommé au vin de Marsala.
Consommé au vin de Porto doré.
Consommé au vin de Porto rose.
Consommé au vin de Samos.
Consommé au vin de Zucco.

Gelée aux Pommes d’Amour

Proceed as for the “Consommé Portugaise”, and use that variety of small tomatoes which, in Provence, are called “Pommes d’amour”.

Gelée de Volaille à la Napolitaine

Proceed as for the “Consommé Portugaise”, but finish it with one port wine-glassful of port or old Marsala per quart.

Thick Soups

In Part I., Chapter I., of this work I pointed out what thick soups consist of. I likewise touched upon the general rules which should be observed in the preparation of each class of these soups, and showed how most of them could, if necessary, be converted into and served as coulis, purées, bisques, veloutés, or creams. The principles governing these alterations are very simple, and after a moment’s reflection the operator will thoroughly grasp their import. Be this as it may, the reader will find the necessary directions at the end of each recipe that admits of various methods of preparation.

With regard to those recipes which are not followed by any directions of the sort referred to, and which I simply class under the name of Potages, these are unalterable preparations which may only be served in accordance with the directions given. This being clear, the reader will understand that I have refrained from repeating the quantities of butter, cream, thickening ingredients, &c., in each recipe. These particulars having been given in Part I., it will be necessary to refer to that part of the book for them.

Purée de Carottes, otherwise Crécy

Cut one lb. of the red part only of carrots into fine slices; chop one onion, and put the whole into a stewpan with a sprig of thyme and two oz. of butter. Stew gently for twenty minutes, and season with a pinch of salt and sugar. Add the thickening ingredient, i.e., either two oz. of rice or five and one-half oz. of bread dice fried in butter; also add one and one-half pints of white consommé, and set to cook very gently.

Rub through tammy, test the consistence, despumate, and add butter when dishing up.

Ordinary garnish: small bread dice fried in butter.

Occasional garnish: poached Japanese pearls in the proportion of two tablespoonfuls per quart of the soup.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream or a velouté à la Nivernaise (see formula №674).

Purée de Carottes au Tapioca, otherwise Velours

Make one pint of carrot purée as above, and poach two tablespoonfuls of tapioca in a pint of white consommé.

When about to serve, and after having buttered the purée of carrots, mix therewith the prepared tapioca.

Purée de Céleri-rave

Finely mince one lb. of celeriac; blanch it; thoroughly drain it, and stew it gently in one oz. of butter. Moisten with one quart of white consommé; add two medium-sized potatoes, minced, and set to cook gently. Rub through tammy; despumate the purée gently for half an hour, and add butter when dishing up.

Garnish: small bread dice fried in butter.

Purée de Choux de Bruxelles, otherwise Flamande

Parboil and drain one lb. of very fresh Brussels sprouts. Set them to stew gently in three oz. of butter; moisten with one pint of white consommé; for the leason add two medium-sized quartered potatoes, and complete the cooking.

Rub the whole through tammy, finish the purée with milk, despumate it in the usual way, and add butter when dishing up. Garnish with small bread dice fried in butter.

Purée de Choux-fleurs, otherwise Dubarry

Parboil one lb. of cauliflower divided into bunches.

Drain them and put them in a saucepan with one pint of boiled milk and two medium-sized minced potatoes for the thickening. Set to cook gently, rub through tammy, finish with boiled milk, despumate, and add butter.

Garnish with small bread dice fried in butter.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream with small pieces of cauliflower as garnish.

Purée de Crosnes, otherwise Japonaise

Parboil and drain one lb. of well-cleaned stachys. Stew them in one oz. of butter; moisten with one pint of boiled milk or white consommé, according as to whether the purée is to be a Lenten one or not; add two medium-sized minced potatoes, and complete the cooking gently.

Rub through tammy, test the consistence, and add, if necessary, either a little boiled milk or some consommé; despumate, and add butter.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of Japanese pearls poached in consommé or milk.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée de Flageolets, otherwise Musard

Cook together with the ordinary aromatic garnish three-quarters pint of dry flageolets, or, if they are in season, use twice that quantity of fresh ones.

Drain, pound, and moisten the purée with a little of the cooking-liquor of the flageolets, rub through tammy, and rectify the consistence with some white consommé and the necessary quantity of boiled milk. Despumate, and butter it when about to dish up.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of small bread dice fried in butter.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream, but for either of the latter it is preferable to use fresh flageolets, the garnish for both consisting of very small flageolets and chervil pluches.

Purée de Haricots Blancs, otherwise Soissonnaise

Cook in the usual way, that is to say, with carrots, a faggot, and one onion stuck with a clove, a good half-pint of dry haricot beans.

Crush all these, moisten with a few tablespoonfuls of their cooking-liquor, and rub through tammy.

Rectify the consistence of the purée with the necessary quantity of white consommé and milk, despumate, add butter when about to dish up, and garnish with small bread dice.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée de Haricots Verts, otherwise Cormeilles

Parboil one and one-half lbs. of French beans and keep them very green. After having well drained them, stew them for ten or twelve minutes in one oz. of butter, moisten with one pint of white consommé, and add two medium-sized minced potatoes for the thickening.

Set to cook gently, rub through tammy, rectify the consistence of the purée with a little boiled milk, despumate, and add butter when dishing up.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of cooked French beans cut into narrow lozenges.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée de Haricots Rouges, otherwise Condé

Put a heaped pint of red beans into cold water, set to boil slowly, skim, add three oz. of carrots, one small faggot, one onion stuck with a clove, and a bottleful of boiling red wine. Set to cook gently.

Drain the beans and crush them in a mortar. Moisten the purée with a few tablespoonfuls of the cooking-liquor of the beans, rub through tammy, rectify the consistence of the purée with some white consommé, follow the procedure of all purées, and add butter when about to serve.

Garnish with bread dice fried in butter.

Purée de Lentilles, otherwise Conti

Soak three-quarters of a pint of lentils in lukewarm water for two hours. Put them in a stewpan with two oz. of very lean breast of bacon, blanched, cooled, and cut into dice, and one quart of white consommé. Set to boil, skim, add three oz. of carrots, one onion, and one faggot, and cook very gently.

Drain the lentils, pound them together with the bacon, moisten the purée with a few tablespoonfuls of cooking-liquor, and rub through tammy. Rectify the consistence with some reserved cooking-liquor, then treat the purée in the usual way and add butter when about to serve.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of bread dice fried in butter and a pinch of chervil pluches.

N.B.—It should be borne in mind that the aromatic garnish used in cooking dry vegetables of what kind soever should be withdrawn before pounding the latter, that they may be rubbed through a tammy.

Purée de Navets, otherwise Freneuse

Finely mince one lb. of very firm turnips, parboil, driain, and stew them in one and one-half oz. of butter, the necessary salt, and one-half oz. of sugar, until they are almost completely cooked. Moisten with one-half pint of white consommé, and complete the cooking. Meantime, cook two medium-sized, peeled and quartered potatoes in some consommé.

Now put the turnips and the potato into the same stewpan crush them, and rub them through tammy. Bring the purée to the proper consistence by means of boiled milk, and finish it in the usual way.

Garnish with some small bread dice fried in butter.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée d’Oseille et de Vermicelle à la Crème

Sprinkle three oz. of well-separated vermicelli into one pint of boiling milk or white consommé (according as to whether the preparation be a Lenten one or not). Let the vermicelli poach gently for twenty-five minutes, and then add four tablespoonfuls, of sorrel cooked in butter.

Rub the whole through tammy; finish the purée with sufficient milk or thin cream; heat until the boil is reached, and, when about to serve, complete by means of a leason composed of the yolks of two eggs and one-quarter pint of very fresh cream.

For the garnish, refer to the remarks under formula №646.

Purée d’Oseille et de Sagou à la Crème

Proceed exactly as directed in the preceding recipe; but instead of vermicelli use three oz. of sago. Allow the usual time for cooking, and add the same quantity of sorrel cooked in butter.

Use the same quantities of milk or consommé in order to bring the purée to the proper consistence, and make use of a precisely similar leason.

Purée d’Oseille et de Semoule à la Crème

The same as the above, but use three oz. of semolina. All other particulars remain the same.

Purée d’Oseille et de Tapioca à la Crème

Procedure like that of formula №642, using instead of the vermicelli three oz. of tapioca.

Remarks Relative to the Possible Variations of the Four Preceding Recipes

A large variety of this kind of soups may be prepared by using the quantity prescribed of salep, buckwheat, oatmeal, barley-meal, &c.

These soups derive a particular and agreeable flavour from their cohering element.

The chief point to be remembered in their preparation is their consistence, which should be that of a thin cream.

When too thick, these soups are pasty and disagreeable; when too thin, they are insipid; hence the desirability of aiming at a happy medium.

Their garnish is exceedingly variable, the more preferable forms being small bread dice fried in clarified butter, pressed; peeled tomatoes cut into dice and tossed in butter; small printaniers, brunoises, juliennes, paysannes, or well-poached rice.

Thus, from the typical recipe of these soups, a whole series may be prepared, which need not be gone into separately here.

Purée de Pois aux Croûtons

Wash three-quarters of a pint of split peas in cold water and put them into a stewpan with one quart of cold water, a little salt, and one-half lb. of raw ham. Set to boil, skim, and add two oz. of mirepoix, the minced green leaves of three leeks, a fragment of thyme and bay, salt, and one-half oz. of sugar. Set to cook very gently.

Rub through tammy, bring the purée to the proper consistence by means of white consommé, despumate it sufficiently, and add butter to it when dishing up.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of small bread dice fried in butter.

Purée de Pois Frais, otherwise Saint-Germain

The two following methods may be employed, viz.:—

Cook quickly one and one-quarter pints of fresh peas, just shelled, in boiling, salted water. Drain them, pound them in a mortar, moisten the purée with one pint of white consommé, and rub it through tammy. Bring it to the proper degree of heat, and add butter when about to serve. Prepared in this way, the purée should be of a perfect shade.
Stew one and one-quarter pints of fresh peas in one and one-half oz. of butter, a little lettuce chiffonade, one and one-half oz. of the green part of leeks, a pinch of chervil, a little salt and sugar, and one-seventh pint of water.

Pound the peas as soon as they are cooked, moisten the purée with one pint of white consommé, and rub through tammy. Bring the preparation to the proper degree of heat, and add butter at the last moment.

Treated thus, the purée will be of a fainter shade than the preceding one, but is flavour will be more delicate.

Garnish, in both cases, with one and one-half tablespoonfuls of very green, fine peas, and some chervil pluches. This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée de Pois Frais à la Menthe

Make the purée according to one of the above-mentioned methods, and add to the peas, while cooking, a faggot consisting of three little sprigs of fresh mint. Finish with consommé, and add butter in the usual way.

Garnish with nice peas, as above, and some very tender mint-leaves, chopped, instead of the chervil pluches.

Remarks Relative to those Soups which have a Purée of Peas for Base

A large number of soups may be made from purées of fresh peas; among others I may mention the following, with brief directions as to their constituents and garnish, viz.—

Potage Ambassadeurs

Purée of fresh peas, quite ready for soup; finish with a small tablespoonful of sorrel and lettuce chiffonade, and two tablespoonfuls of poached rice per quart of purée.

Potage Camélia

Prepare this after the recipe of potage Lamballe; finish with one tablespoonful of a julienne of the white of a leek and one tablespoonful of white chicken meat, cut julienne-fashion, per quart of the soup.

Potage Fontanges

Purée of fresh peas ready for soup; add two tablespoonfuls of a chiffonade of sorrel and a pinch of chervil pluches per quart of the purée, and two tablespoonfuls of poached rice.

Potage Lamballe

Half of this consists of a finished purée of peas, and the other half of tapioca poached in consommé as for the ordinary “potage au tapioca”.

Potage Longchamps

This is the “potage Fontange”," kept somewhat clear, and with a garnish composed of one and one-half oz. of vermicelli, poached in consommé, and a pinch of chervil pluches per quart of the soup.

Potage Marigny

Proceed as for “potage Fontange”, and add a garnish of one tablespoonful of peas and one tablespoonful of fine French beans cut into lozenges.

Potage Marcilly

Half of this consists of a purée of peas and the other half of a purée of chicken. Prepare these purées in the usual way and mix them together when about to serve.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of Japanese pearls poached in consommé and twelve small quenelles of chicken forcemeat, in the shape of pearls, per quart of the soup.

Potage Saint-Marceau

This is an ordinary purée of peas with butter, combined with two tablespoonfuls of a julienne consisting of the white of a leek and some chervil pluches per quart of the purée. This list could be considerably lengthened, but what there is of it amply suffices to show the great number of soups that may be obtained from the combination of other suitable products with the purée of peas and the modification of the garnish in each case.

Purée de Pommes de Terre, otherwise Parmentier

Finely mince the white of two medium-sized leeks, and fry them without colouration in one oz. of butter. Add three medium-sized peeled and quartered potatoes, one pint of white consommé, and cook quickly. The moment the potatoes seem soft to the touch crush them and rub them through tammy.

Finish the purée with some boiled milk or thin cream, heat until the boil is reached, and add butter when dishing up.

Garnish with two tablesponfuls of small bread dice fried in butter and some chervil pluches.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée de Tomatoes, otherwise Portugaise

Fry in one oz. of butter a somewhat finely-cut mirepoix consisting of one oz. of breast of bacon cut into dice, one-third of a carrot, half an onion, a fragment of thyme and bay. Add to this fried mirepoix eight medium-sized tomatoes, pressed and cut into pieces the size of a clove of garlic, a pinch of sugar, two and one-half oz. of rice, and one pint of white consommé.

Set to cook gently, rub through tammy, and finish with the necessary quantity of consommé.

When about to serve complete the purée by adding thereto, away from the fire, two oz. of butter.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of poached rice, each grain being separate, and the same quantity of peeled tomatoes cut into dice and briskly tossed in butter.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Purée de Tomatoes au Tapioca, otherwise Waldèze

Prepare one and one-half pints of tapioca in white consommé, and keep it a little lighter than ordinary tapioca. Also press, peel, and cut into dice the pulp of three medium-sized, very red tomatoes; poach these dice in some consommé and mix them with the tapioca.

Or, failing fresh tomatoes, add to the tapioca two tablespoonfuls of concentrated tomato purée diluted in a bowl with some white consommé.

Send two oz. of grated cheese to the table separately.

Purée de Topinambour, otherwise Palestine

Finely mince two lbs. of Jerusalem artichokes and stew them in one oz. of butter. Add five torrefied and crushed filberts, moistened with one pint of white consommé, and set to cook gently. Rub through tammy; finish the purée with one-quarter pint of milk, in which one tablespoonful of fecula has been diluted, cold. Set to boil and add butter when dishing up.

Garnish with small bread dice fried in butter.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Bisque d’Écrevisses

Cut into very small dice one oz. of carrot, one oz. of onion, and two parsley stalks. Add a fragment of thyme and bay; brown this mirepoix with butter, in a sauté-pan; throw in fifteen crayfish for “Bisque” (their average weight being about one and one-third oz.), and toss them in the mirepoix until they acquire a very red colour. Sprinkle with two tablespoonfuls of burnt brandy and one-quarter pint of white wine, season with a large pinch of salt and a pinch of ground pepper, and set to reduce.

This done, moisten with one-quarter pint of white consommé and leave to cook for ten minutes.

Also cook three oz. of rice in one and one-half pints of white consommé.

Shell the crayfishes’ tails and put them aside; also reserve eight carapaces. Drain the crayfishes of all their cooking-liquor; finely pound them and their remains and the mirepoix. Add the rice, properly cooked, and the cooking-liquor of the crayfish, and rub through a sieve, first, and then through tammy.

Add to the resulting purée one-half pint of white consommé, set to boil, wielding a whisk the while, pass through a strainer, and then keep the preparation in a bain-marie, taking care to place a few lumps of butter on its surface lest a skin should form while the bisque is waiting to be served.

Finish the preparation when dishing up with two and one-half oz. of butter, three tablespoonfuls of excellent thick cream, and a very little cayenne.

Garnish with the crayfish tails cut into dice, and the eight carapaces stuffed with a fish forcemeat with cream and poached seven or eight minutes previously.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Bisque de Homard

After substituting for the crayfish a raw lobster weighing three lbs., cut into small sections, the procedure is the same as that of formula №662. It is only necessary, therefore, to refer to that recipe for all particulars relating to preparation and quantities.

Garnish with the meat taken from the tail; this should have been kept aside and cut into small dice.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Bisque de Crevettes

The mode of procedure for this bisque, the mirepoix, the thickening ingredients, the moistening, and the finishing of the soup are identical with those of formula №662.

All that is needed, therefore, is to substitute for the crayfish two lbs. of raw shrimps.

Instead of using ordinary butter in finishing this bisque, use three oz. of shrimp butter. Garnish with twenty-five reserved tails, these being shelled and trimmed.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Coulis de Gibier, otherwise au Chasseur

Prepare six oz. of the meat of a wild rabbit, six oz. of that of a partridge, and six oz. of a pheasant. These meats should be roasted and their roast-cases swilled with a liqueur-glass of burnt brandy. The resulting gravy should be added to the soup.

Now finely pound these meats together with one-half pint of cooked and drained lentils. When the whole has become a smooth purée add the cooking-liquor of the lentils and the swillings referred to above and rub through tammy.

Finish the cullis with the necessary quantity of consommé, heat it, and pass it through a strainer. Add butter at the last moment and season moderately.

Garnish with three tablespoonfuls of small, very fresh mushrooms; these to be finely minced and tossed in butter.

Coulis de Grives au Pain Noir, otherwise à l’Ardennaise

Fry four fine thrushes in butter and complete their cooking in one pint of feathered game consommé containing five oz. of rye-bread dice fried in butter. These dice constitute in this case the thickening element of the soup. Remove and put aside the thrushes’ fillets, finely pound the carcasses together with two juniper-berries, add the leason of bread dice, and rub through tammy.

Add to the resulting purée one-quarter pint of feathered-game consommé, set to boil, and pass through a strainer. Finish the cullis with two and one-half oz. of butter and four tablespoonfuls of cream.

Garnish with the reserved fillets cut into thin slices or into a julienne.

Coulis de Grouse ou de Qelinotte à l’Ancienne

Proceed as in Formula №666 in so far as the preparatory details and the quantities are concerned, but take note of the following changes in other directions:—

Substitute for the thrushes two grouse or two hazel-hens, taking care to discard the legs and the carcasses.
Use ordinary bread dice instead of those of rye-bread.

Coulis de Lapereau au Currie

Cut the legs of a young wild rabbit into small pieces, stiffen these in butter, and put them into the stewpan with a few roundels of carrot and onion, one small faggot of parsley and celery, and one quart of white consommé. Set to cook gently.

Also lightly brown in butter two tablespoonfuls of chopped onion, besprinkle with one-half tablespoonful of fecula and a sufficient quantity of curry, moisten with the strained cooking-liquor of the pieces of rabbit, bring to the boil, and set to simmer for seven or eight minutes. Rub through tammy and then despumate for twenty minutes, adding from time to time one or two tablespoonfuls of consommé with the view of promoting the clarification of the cullis. When about to serve finish the latter with three or four tablespoonfuls of cream.

Garnish with eighteen very small slices taken from the pieces of rabbit and two oz. of rice à l’Indienne, serving the latter separately.

Coulis de Perdreau à la Purée de Marrons, otherwise à la Mancellee

Split the shells of fifteen fine chestnuts, put them in a stewpan with water, boil them for five minutes, and shell and peel them quickly while they are still very hot. Then cook them gently in one-half pint of white consommé with one-third of a stick of celery, minced, and one piece of loaf-sugar.

Poêle a partridge, remove the fillets for the purpose of garnish, bone the rest, and pound it finely together with the carcass and the poêling liquor. Add the chestnuts, pound the whole, and add some consommé to the resulting purée with the object of facilitating the rubbing through tammy. This done, add to the preparation about one-quarter pint of very clear game stock, bring the whole to the boil, pass it through a strainer, and finish the cullis, when dishing up, with a very little cayenne and one and one-half oz. of butter.

Garnish with the fillets of partridge cut into a small julienne.

Coulis de Volaille, otherwise à la Reine

Poach in one quart of white consommé a cleaned fowl weighing about three lbs. and two oz. of rice previously blanched. Having cooked the fowl, withdraw it, raise its fillets, and put them aside. Bone the remainder and finely pound the meat. When the latter is a smooth paste mix therewith the rice, which should be very well cooked, add the necessary amount of white consommé to the purée, and rub through tammy. Bring the cullis to the boil and pass it through a fine strainer.

Finish the preparation, when dishing up, with a leason composed of the yolks of three  eggs, one-sixth pint of cream, and three oz. of butter.

Garnish with the reserved fillets cut into small, regular dice. This soup may also be prepared as a velouté or a cream.

Velouté Agnès Sorel

Prepare one and one-half pints of poultry velouté, keeping it somewhat thin,
Clean, wash, peel, and quickly pound eight oz. of very fresh mushrooms, newly gathered if possible.

Rub through a fine sieve, and add the resulting purée of raw mushrooms to the velouté. Bring the whole to the boil once or twice, and this done rub through tammy immediately. Finish with the leason and add butter when dishing up.

Garnish with one tablespoonful of a julienne of raw mushrooms tossed in butter, one tablespoonful of chicken fillets, and as much salted tongue, both of which should also be cut in julienne-fashion.

N.B.—With regard to veloutés I remind the reader that the velouté of ordinary consistence represents one-half of the soup, the purée typifying the latter represents one-quarter, while the consommé required to bring the soup to the correct degree of consistence should be in the proportion of the remaining quarter.

The leason, per quart of the soup, should consist of the yolks of three eggs and one-sixth pint of cream, while the average quantity of butter should measure about two and one-half oz. (see formula №242).

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté de Blanchaille au Currie

Bear in mind that this soup ought to be made and served within the space of twenty minutes, for if it be left to stand for however short a time, it will most probably turn, in spite of every possible precaution.

Cook three oz. of finely chopped onion in butter without colouration, besprinkle with one-half coffee-spoonful of curry, moisten with one and one-half pints of boiling water, add a faggot, a pinch of salt, a few sprigs of saffron (or a little of it powdered), and two oz. of Viennese bread.

Set to boil for ten minutes; this done add three-quarters lb. of very fresh Blanchailles, and cook over a brisk fire.

Rub through a hair-sieve, finish by means of a leason consisting of the yolks of three eggs and one-fifth pint of cream, and pour the whole into the soup-tureen over some dried slices of bread (buttered), over rice, or over some previously poached vermicelli. Serve at once.

Velouté Carmélite

Prepare one and one-half pints of fish velouté, stew four oz. of fillets of sole and the same quantity of fillets of whiting in one and one-half oz. of butter and lemon juice. Pound the fish, add it to the velouté, and rub through tammy.

Add the necessary quantity of consommé, heat the velouté, and finish it, when about to serve, with a leason and butter.

Garnish with one tablespoonful of a julienne of poached fillets of sole and twelve small quenelles of smelt forcemeat.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté aux Carottes, otherwise Nivernaise

Cut into thin slices one lb. of the red part only of carrots, season with a pinch of table-salt and twice that amount of castor-sugar, and stew in one oz. of butter.

Add one pint of ordinary thin velouté and let the cooking of the carrots be completed therein. Rub through tammy, finish with one-half pint of white consommé, set to boil, and complete the preparation, when dishing up, with the leason and butter.

Garnish with one and one-half tablespoonfuls of a fine brunoise of the red part of carrots.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté Comtesse

Prepare one pint of ordinary velouté, parboil one and one-half lbs. of white asparagus, and put them into the velouté. Complete the cooking gently. Rub through tammy, add one-half pint of white consommé, heat, and finish the preparation, when dishing up, with the leason and butter.

Garnish with one tablespoonful of a lettuce chiffonade and twelve small white asparagus-heads wherefrom all leaves have been removed.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté au Concombres, otherwise Danoise

Peel, remove the seeds from, mince, and stew in butter one lb. of parboiled cucumber. Add this to one pint of ordinary velouté, which should have been prepared at the same time, and complete the cooking quickly. Rub through tammy, add the necessary quantity of white consommé, heat, and finish the preparation, when dishing up, with a leason and butter in the usual quantities.

Garnish with small bread dice fried in butter.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté Cressonière

After having slightly parboiled them, stew one lb., of very fresh watercress leaves in one and one-half oz. of butter, add them to one pint of ordinary velouté. Set to simmer for seven or eight minutes, rub through tammy, add one and one-half pints of ordinary white consommé, heat, and finish the preparation, when dishing up, with a leason and butter.

Garnish with one oz. of watercress leaves parboiled for three minutes.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté Dame-Blanche

Prepare one and one-half pints of clear poultry velouté. Also finely pound ten or twelve well-washed sweet almonds, moisten them, little by little, with one-sixth pint of fresh water, and rub through a strong towel, twisting the latter to assist the process.

Add this almond milk to the velouté, and finish the latter, when dishing up, with the leason and butter.

Garnish with one tablespoonful of the white of a chicken cut into small dice, and twelve small quenelles of chicken forcemeat (in the shape of pearls) poached just before dishing up.

Velouté d’Artois

Prepare one pint of ordinary velouté, and mix therewith one-half pint of a purée of haricot beans. Rub through tammy; add one-half pint of white consommé; heat, and finish the whole, when dishing up, with the leason and butter.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of an ordinary julienne and a pinch of chervil pluches.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté d’Éperlans

Prepare a thin panada with one pint of boiled milk and two and one-half oz. of crumbled bread. Season with a pinch of salt and a very small quantity of mignonette. Also stew gently, in one oz. of butter, two tablespoonfuls of chopped onion, two and one-half oz. of fillets of smelt, one-half lb. of fillets of sole, or the meat of a dory, and the juice of the quarter of a lemon.

Add the fish, stewed in butter and pounded, to the panada, together with one-half pint of ordinary thin velouté.

Rub through tammy; heat; season with a very little cayenne, and finish the whole, when dishing up, with an ordinary leason and one and one-half oz. of butter.

N.B.—

In view of the decided flavour of the smelt, and the really disagreeable taste it imparts to a preparation which contains overmuch of it, its flesh should never exceed the proportion of one-third of the required quantity of fish. The remaining two-thirds should be supplied by a fish of neutral flavour, such as the sole or dory, both of which are admirably suited to this purpose.
The velouté d’éperlans should, like almost all fish veloutés, be prepared as quickly as possible, and at the last moment. The process should not last longer than thirty minutes, for, if there be any delay, the preparation will turn and lose its flavour.
For this soup I elected to use a panada as the thickening element, instead of a fish velouté, the reason being that, were the latter used, the taste of fish would in the end be too pronounced.

Velouté d’Éperlans

Proceed in the matter of the base of the soup as in formula №680.

Finish the velouté with an ordinary leason and one and one-half oz. of shrimp butter.

Garnish with six crayfish tails, cut into four pieces, and one tablespoonful of a short julienne of truffles and mushrooms.

Velouté d’Éperlans Princesse

The same as above, with twelve small quenelles of smelt forcemeat with crayfish butter, and one tablespoonful of very green asparagus-heads per quart of velouté.

Velouté aux Grenouilles, otherwise Sicilienne

Prepare one and one-half pints of delicate and rather thin fish velouté.

Trim fifteen or twenty frogs’ legs; toss them in butter without letting them acquire any colour, and set them to poach for ten minutes in two tablespoonfuls of white wine and the juice of a lemon. Pound them in a mortar; add the resulting purée to the velouté; set to simmer for seven or eight minutes, and rub through tammy.

Heat the velouté, and finish it, when dishing up, with the ordinary leason and three and one-half oz. of best butter.

Do not garnish this velouté.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté de Homard, otherwise Cardinal

Prepare one and three-quarter pints of bisque de homard (formula №663), but substitute velouté for the thickening with rice. Rub through tammy; heat, and complete, when dishing up, with two and one-half oz. of lobster butter and three-quarters oz. of red butter.

Garnish with two baba-moulds of a royale of lobster, cut by means of a fancy-cutter in the shape of a cross.

Shell-fish veloutés do not admit of an egg-yolk leason.

Velouté de Homard à Cleveland

Break up two small live lobsters or one medium-sized one, and prepare it à l’Américaine (see “Lobster à l’Américaine”). Reserve a few slices of the meat for garnishing purposes. Finely pound the rest with the shell; combine the purée with one quart of ordinary velouté prepared beforehand, and add the lobster sauce. Rub through a sieve, first, then through tammy; heat without allowing to boil; add the required quantity of consommé, and once more pass the whole through a strainer.

Complete, when dishing up, with three oz. of best butter.

Garnish with one-half tablespoonful of peeled tomato pulp, cut into dice and half-melted in butter, and the reserved slices of lobster cut into dice.

Velouté de Homard à l’Indienne

Prepare the lobster à l’Américaine as above, and flavour it with curry. Preserve a sufficient quantity of meat from the tail to afford an abundant garnish.

For the rest of the process proceed exactly as the preceding recipe directs.

Garnish with the reserved meat cut into dice, and four tablespoonfuls of rice à l’Indienne; send the latter to the table separately.

Velouté de Homard à l’Orientale

Prepare a medium-sized lobster after the manner directed in “Homard à la Newburg with raw lobster” (see formula №948), and season with curry.

Reserve a few slices of the meat of the tail for the garnish; finely pound the remaining portions and the shell; add the lobster sauce, and combine the whole with one quart of ordinary velouté, kept somewhat light.

Rub through a sieve, first, then through tammy; heat the velouté without letting it boil; add the necessary quantity of consommé, and finish the preparation, when about to serve, with three oz. of butter.

Garnish with the reserved meat cut into dice, and two tablespoonfuls of rice à l’Indienne, each grain of which should be kept distinct and separate.

Velouté de Homard au Paprika

Prepare a medium-sized lobster à l’Américaine, and, in addition to the usual ingredients of the preparation, include two concassed tomatoes and two roughly chopped onions. Season with paprika.

For the rest of the operation, proceed exactly as directed under “Velouté à la Cleveland".

Garnish with lobster meat cut into dice, two tablespoonfuls of rice, and one tablespoonful of pimentos cut into dice.

Velouté de Homard à la Persane

Proceed exactly as for “Velouté de Homard à l’Orientale”.

Garnish with lobster meat in dice, one tablespoonful of pimentos in dice, and two tablespoonfuls of pilaff rice, to which add a very little saffron.

Remarks relating to the Variation of these Veloutés

By merely substituting an equivalent quantity of crayfish, shrimps, or crabs, for the lobster, the recipes dealing with veloutés of lobster, given above, may be applied to Veloutés of Crayfish, Shrimps, or Crabs.

It would therefore be pointless to repeat them, since all that is needed is to read crayfish, shrimps, or crabs wherever the word lobster appears.

Thus I shall only point out that the number of these veloutés may be increased at will, the only requisites being the change of the basic ingredient and the modification of the garnish.

Velouté aux Huîtres

Prepare one quart of very delicate fish velouté, and bear in mind that the preparation must be made as speedily as possible. (See the remarks dealing with this question which follow upon the model recipe of the velouté d’éperlans.)

Add to the velouté the carefully collected liquor of the twenty-four oysters constituting the garnish, and complete, when about to serve, with a leason and butter.

Garnish with four poached oysters (cleared of their beards) per each person.

Velouté Isoline

Prepare one quart of poultry velouté. Complete it, when dishing up, with an ordinary leason and three oz. of crayfish butter.

Garnish with three tablespoonfuls of Japanese pearls poached in white consommé.

Velouté Marie Louise

Prepare one pint of poultry velouté; mix therewith one-half pint of barley cream (formula №712), and rub through tammy. Add one-half pint of white consommé, and heat the velouté without letting it boil.

Finish it, when about to serve, with a leason and butter. Garnish with one and one-half tablespoonfuls of best macaroni, poached and cut into dice.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté Marie Stuart

Prepare a poultry velouté with barley cream, as above. Finish it, when about to serve, with a leason and butter.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of a brunoise, and the same quantity of fine pearl barley cooked in white consommé.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Velouté au Pourpier

Proceed exactly as directed under “Velouté Cressonière” (formula №677), but substitute purslain for the watercress.

Velouté à la Sultane

Prepare one quart of poultry velouté. Finish it, when dishing up, with a leason composed of the yolks of three eggs diluted with one-fifth pint of sweet-almond milk (made by pounding eighteen sweet almonds, mixing therewith one-fifth pint of water, and straining the whole through a twisted towel), and three oz. of pistachio butter. The velouté should be of a pale green shade.

Garnish with small crescents of chicken forcemeat prepared with crayfish butter, kept of a pink shade. These crescents should be laid, by means of a piping-bag, upon thin roundels of truffle, and poached in consommé.

This soup may also be prepared as a cream.

Cold Chicken Velouté for Suppers

The preparation of these veloutés requires the utmost care, but, as a rule, they are very much liked.

Prepare a white roux from one oz. of butter and one and one-sixth oz. of flour per quart of the moistening. Dilute with some very strong clear consommé, thoroughly cleared of grease; boil, and despumate for one and one-half hours, adding meanwhile half as much consommé as served in the moistening of the velouté.

When the velouté is thoroughly despumated and entirely cleared of grease, strain it through a silk sieve, and add, per quart, one-quarter pint of very fresh thin cream. Cool, stirring incessantly the while; once more strain the velouté through the sieve when it is cold, and, if necessary, add some of the consommé already used, in order to give the velouté the consistence of a thickened consommé. Serve it in cups, and see that it be sufficiently thin to not impaste the mouth of the consumer.

This velouté is usually served as it stands, but it allows of various condimentary adjuncts. Such are:—Tomato and capsicum essences; crayfish, shrimp, or game creams. These creams or essences should be of consummate delicacy, and ought to lend only a very delicate flavour to the velouté.

Crème d’Artichauts au Beurre de Noisette

Have ready one and one-half pints of Béchamel. Parboil, finely mince, and stew in butter four large artichoke-bottoms. Pound the latter; put them in the Béchamel, and rub the whole through tammy.

Add the necessary quantity of white consommé or milk, and set to heat without allowing to boil. Finish the preparation, when dishing up, with one-quarter pint of cream and one oz. of hazel-nut butter (formula №155).

Remarks relative to Creams

I remind the reader here that

the thickening element of creams is a Béchamel prepared in the usual way
in the preparation of a cream, of what kind soever, the Béchamel should constitute half of the whole, the basic ingredient a quarter, and the white consommé or milk the remaining quarter.

As a rule, they comprise no butter, but are finished by means of one-third pint of very fresh cream per quart. Be this as it may, if it be desirable to butter them, one may do so, but in very small quantities, and taking care to use the very best butter.

This class of soups is more particularly suited to Lenten menus.

Crème d’Asperges, otherwise Argenteuil

Parboil for five or six minutes one and one-half lbs. of Argenteuil asparagus, broken off at the spot where the hard part of the stalk begins. Drain them, and set them to complete their cooking gently in one and one-quarter pints of previously prepared Béchamel.

Rub through tammy; add the necessary quantity of white consommé, and heat without allowing to boil.

Finish with cream when dishing up.

Garnish with two tablespponfuls of white asparagus-heads and a pinch of chervil pluches.

Crème d’Asperges Vertes

Proceed exactly as for “Crème Argenteuil”, but substitute green asparagus for Argenteuil asparagus.

Crème au Blé Vert, otherwise Cérès

Put one lb. of dry, green wheat to soak in cold water for four hours. Then cook it slowly in one-half pint of water and as much white consommé. Mix therewith one and one-quarter pints of Béchamel and rub through tammy.

Add the necessary amount of white consommé to the purée; heat the whole without boiling, and finish it with cream when dishing up.

Garnish with a pinch of chervil pluches.

This soup may also be prepared as a purée or a velouté.

Crème de Céleri

Mince one lb. of the white of celery; parboil for seven or eight minutes; drain, and stew in one oz. of butter. Mix one and one-quarter pints of Béchamel with it; complete the cooking slowly, and rub through tammy.

Add one-half pint of white consommé; heat without allowing to boil, and finish the preparation with cream when about to serve.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of a brunoise of celery. This soup may also be prepared as a purée or a velouté.

Crème de Cerfeuil Bulbeux, otherwise Chevreuse

Mince and stew in butter one lb. of bulbous chervil, and mix therewith one and one-quarter pints of Béchamel. Complete the cooking slowly; rub through tammy; add sufficient white consommé; heat, and finish with cream when dishing up. Garnish with one tablespoonful of a fine julienne of chicken fillets and the same quantity of a julienne of truffles.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème de Chicorée De Bruxelles, otherwise Bruxelloise

Take one lb. of very fresh chicory, and stew it for a good half-hour in one and one-half oz. of butter and the juice of one lemon.

Now mix one and one-quarter pints of Béchamel with it, and finish the cooking very slowly. Rub through tammy; add the necessary quantity of white consommé; heat, and complete with cream when serving.

Garnish with a julienne of Belgian chicory, stewed and well drained.

Crème d’Épinards, otherwise Florentine

Quickly parboil one lb. of shredded and well-washed spinach to which a little sorrel may be added; drain, press, and add thereto one and one-half pints of somewhat thin Béchamel. Complete the cooking; rub the whole through tammy, and finish it with the necessary amount of fresh cream.

Garnish with a julienne of spinach, quickly parboiled and stewed in butter.

Crème de Fèves Nouvelles

Skin two-thirds lb. of new broad beans, freshly gathered, if possible. Cook them for ten minutes in boiling salted water containing a sprig of savory, and then add one and one-quarter pints of Béchamel. Complete the cooking of the broad beans in the Béchamel; rub through tammy; add one-half pint of white consommé or milk; heat without allowing to boil, and finish the preparation with cream when dishing up.

Garnish with very small skinned broad beans, split in two and parboiled with a sprig of savory.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème d’Ignames, otherwise Brésilienne

Bake the yams in the oven, without peeling them. As soon as this is done, cut them in two, remove their pulp, and quickly rub the latter through a sieve while it is still hot. Dilute the purée with boiling milk or thin Béchamel in the proportion of one pint of the former and one-half pint of the latter per lb. of the purée. (This Béchamel should be made from one and one-half oz. of butter and one oz. of flour per quart of milk.)

Rub the whole through tammy, and finish the preparation in the usual way. Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of Japanese pearls, poached in consommé.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème de Laitues, otherwise Judic

Parboil and stew in butter two medium-sized ciseled lettuces, the greenest leaves of which should have been discarded. Add these to one and one-half pints of Béchamel.

Rub through tammy; add one pint of white consommé; heat, and finish as usual with cream.

Garnish with roundels of lettuce leaves, lightly coated with chicken forcemeat, a bit of truffle laid in their centre, and the whole poached at the last minute.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème de Maïs, otherwise Washington

Cook some fresh maize in salted water (or use the preserved kind if the fresh is out of season), and combine therewith an equal quantity of thin Béchamel. Rub through tammy; heat, and finish with cream when dishing up.

Garnish with grains of maize cooked in salted water.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté by substituting for the Béchamel an excellent poultry velouté.

Crème d’Oseille à l’Avoine, otherwise Washington

Pour one-quarter lb. of oatmeal diluted with one-half pint of cold milk into one quart of slightly salted boiling milk. Stir over the fire until the boil is reached; move the stewpan to the side of the fire, and simmer for two hours.

This done, add six tablespoonfuls of a fondue of sorrel and butter; set to simmer again for one-quarter hour, and rub the whole through tammy.

Complete the operation after the manner common to all creams.

Crème d’Oseille à l’Orge

Proceed exactly as for formula №708, using the same quantities, but substituting barley-meal for oatmeal.

Remarks upon the Two above Creams

They may also be prepared as veloutés. Their garnish may be greatly varied, and may consist of chiffonade of lettuce and sorrel; pressed peeled tomatoes, cut into dice and cooked in butter; poached rice or pastes (i.e., vermicelli, &c.); fine well-cooked pearl barley; brunoise; small printaniers, &c.

They belong, in fact, to the same order of soups as the purées of sorrel with pastes, the recipes of which were given earlier in the chapter.

Crème d’Oxalis

Peel and slice the oxalis roots, and half-cook them in salted water. Drain, add it to one and one-half pints of Béchamel, and complete its cooking gently in the sauce.

Rub through tammy; add one-half pint of white consommé, and finish after the manner of other creams. Garnish with chervil pluches.

This soup may also be prepared as a purée or a velouté.

Crème de Riz

Wash one-half lb. of rice in cold water; blanch it; cool it, and cook it very gently in one quart of white consommé. Crush in the mortar; rub through tammy, and dilute the rice purée with one pint of white consommé. Heat and finish the preparation, when dishing up, with the necessary quantity of cream.

Or pour four tablespoonfuls of rice cream, diluted with one-half pint of cold milk, into three pints of boiling milk; set to boil, stirring the while, and leave to cook very gently for twenty-five minutes. Rub through tammy, and finish the preparation, when dishing up, with the required quantity of cream.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème d’Orge

Wash three-quarters lb. of coarse pearl barley in lukewarm water, and cook it gently for about two and one-half hours in one pint of white consommé containing one piece of the white part of a stick of celery.

Crush in a mortar; rub through tammy; dilute the purée of barley with one pint of white consommé; heat, and finish the preparation, when dishing up, with the necessary quantity of cream.

This soup may also be prepared with barley-meal, the procedure in that case being the same as that of the “Crème de Riz” above.

Garnish with very fine, well-cooked pearl barley.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème de Volaille Princesse

Mix one and one-half pints of thin Béchamel with one-half pint of chicken purée. Rub through tammy; add one-half pint of white consommé to the preparation, or the same quantity of boiled milk; heat without allowing to boil, and finish with cream when dishing up.

Garnish with twenty very small slices of chicken fillets, white asparagus-heads, and chervil pluches.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Crème Reine-Margot

Mix one-half pint of chicken purée with one pint of thin Béchamel. Rub through tammy; add one and one-half pints of white consommé and one-quarter pint of almond milk (formula №678). Heat without allowing to boil, and finish with cream.

Garnish with very small grooved quenelles of chicken forcemeat combined with one oz. of pistachio purée per three oz. of forcemeat.

This soup may also be prepared as a velouté.

Potage à l’Aurore

Wash one-quarter lb. of fine pearl barley in plenty of water. Put it into a stewpan with one quart of consommé, as much water, a faggot comprising parsley, celery, and chervil, and set to cook very gently for five hours. While the cooking progresses, take care to remove all the skin which forms on the surface, in order that the cooking-liquor may remain very clear.

When the barley is well cooked, transfer it to another stewpan, and add to it four tablespoonfuls. of a thick and very red tomato purée, strained through muslin, and two tablespoonfuls of celery, minced in paysanne-fashion, stewed in butter, and finally cooked in consommé.

This excellent soup should not be made too thick.

Potage Bagration Gras

Cut two-thirds lb. of very white fillet of veal into large dice, and stiffen these in butter without letting them acquire any colour. Add one and one-quarter pints of thin velouté with a veal base, and set to cook very gently.

Finely pound the veal; dilute the purée with velouté, and rub through tammy. Add one pint of white consommé; heat without boiling, and complete the preparation, when dishing up, with a leason of the yolks of three eggs diluted with four tablespoonfuls of cream and two oz. of butter.

Garnish with thin macaroni cut into short lengths, and send some grated cheese to the table separately.

Potage Bagration Maigre

Prepare one and one-half pints of fresh velouté, and mix therewith one-quarter pint of mushroom velouté. (For making this, see “Velouté Agnès Sorel”, formula №671.)

Heat without boiling; pass through a strainer, and finish, when about to serve, with the same leason as for ordinary velouté, and two and one-half oz. of butter. Garnish with one fillet of sole, poached very white, and cut into a julienne; twelve small quenelles of sole or whiting forcemeat finished with crayfish butter, and six crayfishes’ tails cut into small pieces.

Potage Choiseul

Prepare a “purée Conti” (formula №640) with an excellent fumet of game.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of sorrel, ciseled and cooked in butter, and two tablespoonfuls of poached rice.

Potage Compiègne

Prepare a light “Purée Soissonaise”; butter it well, and add thereto as garnish three tablespoonfuls of ciseled sorrel cooked in butter, and chervil pluches.

Potage Derby

Add one-half pint of Soubise purée (formula №104) to one pint of “Crème de Riz” (formula №711) flavoured with a very little curry. Rub the whole through tammy.

Add one-half pint of white consommé, and heat without boiling. Complete, when about to serve, with an ordinary leason and three oz. of butter.

Garnish with twelve small quenelles of chicken forcemeat combined with one-third of its volume of foie-gras purée, one tablespoonful of little truffle pearls, and an equal quantity of poached rice, each grain of which must be kept distinct and separate.

Potage à la Diane

Cook one-half lb. of lentils with the usual garnish. Roast two medium-sized partridges, keeping them slightly underdone, and remove their fillets. Complete the cooking of the partridges with the lentils, drained of their cooking-liquor, in one pint of game consommé.

Prepare a royale (formula №209) with the reserved fillets.

When the birds are cooked, bone them; pound their meat, and add thereto the lentils and the cooking-liquor; rub through tammy.

Finish the purée with one and one-half pints of excellent thin game stock, and complete the soup, when dishing up, with two oz. of butter and two tablespoonfuls of reduced Madeira.

Garnish with the royale, cut into small regular crescents, and twelve small crescents of very black truffle.

Potage Élisa

Prepare one and one-half pints of poultry velouté, and rub it through tammy. Complete with one-half pint of white consommé; heat without boiling, and finish, when dishing up, with an ordinary leason, two and one-half oz. of butter, and two tablespoonfuls of a fondue of sorrel.

Potage Favori

Prepare one pint of a velouté of green asparagus; one-half pint of a velouté of lettuce, and one-half pint of poultry velouté. Put all three into a stewpan; add thereto the necessary quantity of white consommé to bring the soup to the correct degree of consistence; heat without boiling, and pass through a strainer.

Finish the soup, when dishing up, with an ordinary leason and two oz. of butter. Garnish with one tablespoonful of a chiffonade of sorrel, and one tablespoonful of green asparagus-heads.

Potage Germiny

Cisel and melt in butter three oz. of shredded sorrel, and add thereto one and one-half pints of white consommé. Afew minutes before serving, pour into the consommé a leason composed of the yolks of six eggs diluted with one-quarter pint of cream; set on the fire and stir, after the manner of an English custard, i.e., until the preparation begins to show signs of boiling.

Finish, away from the fire, with two and one-half oz. of butter, and add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Remarks concerning the Possible Variation of this Soup

The mode of procedure adopted in the case of the Germiny could, if necessary, be appUed to all thick soups, and it would then constitute a class to which the term “Cream” would be better suited than it is at present to the soups thus designated.

Instead of the ordinary white consommé, which is used in its preparation, a consommé may be used in which such vegetables as carrots, turnips, peas, &c., are cooked, the latter being reserved for the garnish, while the cooking-liquor is thickened with egg-yolks and cream in accordance with the quantities and directions given in the above recipe.

A carrot cream, a cream of fresh peas, or of asparagus-heads, prepared in this way, would be much more delicate than those prepared after the ordinary recipes.

The essential point in this series of soups is the leason; this should consist of enough egg-yolks to render the preparations sufficiently thick and creamy.

Potage aux Herbes

Cut two oz. of sorrel leaves into a julienne, and stew them in butter with one oz. of watercress leaves, one oz. of chervil pluches, and young pimpernel. Add one and one-half pints of water; the necessary salt, three medium-sized, peeled, and quartered potatoes, and cook gently.

Drain and reserve the cooking-liquor; crush the potatoes; dilute the purée with the cooking-liquor, and rub through tammy. Set to boil, and finish, when dishing up, with three oz. of Printanier butter with herbs, combined with a few leaves of sweet basil.

Add a pinch of chervil pluches.

Potage Jubilee, otherwise Balvet

Prepare, according to the directions given (formula №648), one and one-half pints of a purée of fresh peas, and add thereto one-half pint of consommé of “La Petite Marmite”. Set to boil, and finish with two oz. of butter.

Garnish with the vegetables from the Marmite, prepared as for Croûte au Pot.

Potage Longchamps

Refer to the derivative soups of the “Purée de Pois” (formula №654).

Potage Lavallière

Prepare one and one-half pints of “Crème de Volaille” (formula №713), finished with a leason of egg-yolks and cream; also two-thirds pint of “Crème de Céleri”, similarly finished, and combine the two creams.

Garnish, with twelve small profiterolles, stuffed with chicken forcemeat, and a royale of celery in dice.

Potage Madeleine

Prepare and combine the following purées:—One-third pint of artichoke purée, one-fifth pint of haricot-bean purée, one-seventh pint of Soubise purée. Add one pint of white consommé; set to boil; pass through a strainer, and finish, when dishing up, with two oz. of butter.

Garnish with two tablespoonfuls of sago poached in one-half pint of white consommé.

Potage Miss Betsy

Proceed exactly as for “Potage à l’Aurore” (formula №715), but

flavour potage Miss Betsy with curry;
substitute for the celery peeled, cored apples cut into dice and cooked in butter,

N.B.—Both these soups (Aurore and Miss Betsy) are subject to much variation. All that is needed is to alter the flavouring element and the garnish. Thus the quantity of tomato maybe reduced by half, and combined with one-quarter lb. of peas and their cooking-liquor (the peas in this case being cooked in one pint of water with a little salt and sugar); or with the same quantity of French beans, asparagus-heads, or sorrel cooked in butter, &c.

Potage Montespan

Add one-half pint of somewhat thick tapioca to one and one-half pints of “Crème d’Asperges” (formula №697), prepared as directed. Garnish with very fine peas cooked in the English fashion.

Potage Nélusko

Mix one and one-half pints of rather liquid poultry velouté with one-half pint of chicken purée. When serving, add an ordinary leason, and finish with two and one-half oz. of hazelnut butter.

Garnish with very small quenelles of chicken forcemeat combined with one tablespoonful of hazel-nut powder per three oz. of the forcemeat.

Potage Petit Duc

Take a fine woodcock; raise and reserve one of its fillets, and roast it, taking care to keep it very underdone. Then remove the other fillet, and with it prepare two dariole-moulds of royale (formula №209). Finely pound what remains of the woodcock, and combine with the resulting purée one and one-half pints of game velouté prepared with essence of woodcock. Cover the stewpan and place it in the bain-marie for thirty-five minutes. Now rub the whole through tammy; heat without boiling, and finish, when dishing up, with one and one-half oz. of butter, one and one-half oz. of cooked foie-gras purée, diluted with a few tablespoonfuls of the soup, one and one-half tablespoonfuls of cream, and one and one-half tablespoonfuls of burnt liqueur brandy.

Garnish with the royale cut into dice, and the reserved fillet of woodcock, stiffened in butter at the last moment, and cut into thin slices.

Potage Régence

Prepare one quart of barley cream in accordance with the directions under formula №712. Finish it, when dishing up, with an ordinary leason and one and one-half oz. of crayfish butter.

Garnish with twelve small, grooved quenelles of chicken forcemeat finished with crayfish butter; one tablespoonful of small pearl barley, well cooked; and six small cocks’ combs, freshly poached and very white.

Potage Rossolnik

one quart of light, poultry velouté combined with cucumber juice;
ten pieces of parsley root and the same quantity of celery root, turned to the shape of small, new carrots, and split crosswise at their base;
twenty small lozenges of salted cucumber.

Parboil the roots and the cucumber lozenges for fifteen minutes, and add them to the velouté when about to cook the latter. Cook the whole gently for forty minutes, despumating the velouté the while. Finish with one and one-half tablespoonfuls of cucumber juice, and an ordinary leason.

Garnish with small chicken-forcemeat quenelles.

Potage de Santé

Cook quickly, in salted water, three medium-sized, peeled, and quartered potatoes. When their pulps seem soft to the touch, drain them; rub them through a fine sieve, and dilute the resulting purée with one and one-half pints of white consommé. Add two tablespoonfuls of sorrel melted in butter, and finish the preparation with an ordinary leason and one oz. of butter.

Garnish with very thin roundels of French soup-flute and chervil pluches.

Potage Sigurd

Prepare one pint of “Velouté Parmentier” and one pint of tomato velouté. Combine the two; heat, and finish, when dishing up, with two and one-half oz. of butter.

Garnish with twenty small quenelles of chicken forcemeat, combined with one coffeespoonful of chopped capsicum, or capsicum in dice, per three oz., of the forcemeat.

Potage Solférino

Mince the white of two leeks, the third of a medium-sized carrot, and half an onion, and stew the whole in one and one-half oz. of butter. Add one-half lb. of pressed tomatoes cut into pieces, two medium-sized, peeled potatoes, minced; moisten with two-thirds pint of white consommé, and cook gently. Crush the vegetables; rub them through tammy; complete the purée with the necessary quantity of white consommé; set to boil, and finish, when dishing up, with two and one-half oz. of butter.

Garnish with twelve little balls of potato, raised by means of the spoon-cutter, and cooked in salted water; two tablespoonfuls of French beans cut into lozenges; and some chervil pluches.

Potage Viviane

Prepare one quart of “Crème de Volaille” (formula №713), and finish it with the usual leason. Garnish with one tablespoonful of artichoke-bottom, cut into dice, the same quantity of carrot dice, both gently cooked in butter, and one tablespoonful of trufifle dice.

Potage Windsor

Blanch and cool one small, boned calf’s foot, and cook it gently in a good white-wine mirepoix. Prepare one and one-half pints of “Crème de Riz” (formula №711), and add thereto the cooking-liquor of the calf’s foot, strained through muslin.

Finish this cream, when about to serve, with an ordinary leason, one and one-half tablespoonfuls of a slight infusion of turtle-soup herbs, and one and one-half oz. of butter.

Garnish with a julienne of half of the calf’s foot and twenty small quenelles consisting of a purée of hard-boiled egg-yolks and chicken forcemeat, these two preparations being in the proportion of two-thirds and one-third respectively.

Soupe aux Abatis de Volaille à l’Anglaise

Cut the necks into three, the gizzards into four, and the pinions into two. Brown one-half lb. of these giblets in a thick-bottomed stewpan with one oz. of butter. Sprinkle with one tablespoonful of flour; slightly colour the latter, and moisten with one quart of white consommé and one pint of water. Add a faggot containing one stick of celery, and set to cook gently for three hours.

When the pieces of giblets are cooked, drain them, trim them, and put them into a stewpan with one dessertspoonful of parboiled rice and a heaped tablespoonful of the white of celery, minced and fried in butter. Strain the cooking-liquor of the giblets, through a strainer, over the enumerated garnishes; set to cook gently for another quarter of an hour; season strongly with pepper, and serve.

Soup aux Cerises

Stone two-thirds lb. of small, fleshy cherries, and put twenty aside for garnishing purposes. Put the others into a sugar-boiler with two-thirds pint of hot water, a small strip of lemon rind, and a fragment of cinnamon, and set to boil quickly for eight minutes.

Also boil in another sugar-boiler one-half pint of Port or Bordeaux wine. Crush half of the cherry-stones in the mortar; put them into the boiled wine, and let them infuse, away from the fire.

Rub the cooked cherries through a fine sieve; dilute the purée with the juice thickened by means of one tablespoonful of fecula moistened with cold water; add the cherries put aside for the garnish, and one-half tablespoonful of castor sugar, and again set to boil for four minutes.

Complete the preparation with the infusion strained through muslin; pour it into the soup-tureen, and add a few biscottes.

For the sake of variety, lady’s-finger biscuits may be substituted for the biscottes.

Cocky-Leeki Soup

Set half a fowl to cook very gently in one and one-half pints of light and clear veal stock with a few aromatics.

Also prepare a julienne of the white of three leeks; stew this in butter without colouration, and complete the cooking thereof in the cooking-liquor of the fowl, strained and poured carefully away.

Pour the preparation into the soup-tureen, and add the meat of the fowl, cut into a julienne.

Serve some stewed prunes separately, but this is optional.

Soupe aux Foies de Volaille

Make a roux from one and one-half oz. of butter and as much flour. When it has acquired a nice, light-brown colour, moisten it with one quart of white consommé or brown stock, and set to boil, stirring the while.

Add one-half lb. of raw chickens’ livers rubbed through a sieve, and set to cook for fifteen minutes. Rub the whole through tammy; season strongly with pepper; heat, and complete the preparation, at the last moment, with one-quarter lb. of sliced chickens’ livers, tossed in butter, and one wineglass of good Madeira.

Soupe Julienne Darblay

Cook quickly in salted water two small, peeled, and quartered potatoes. Drain them, rub them through a fine sieve, and dilute the purée with one and one-half pints of white consommé. Add three tablespoonfuls of a julienne made in accordance with the above recipe; heat, and finish the preparation with an ordinary leason and one and one-half oz. of butter.

Minestrone

Brown the minced white of two small leeks and one-third of an onion, also minced, in one oz. of chopped, fresh breast of bacon, and one-half oz. of grated, fat bacon. Moisten with one and one-half pints of white consommé, and add one-third of a carrot, one-third of a turnip, half a stick of celery, two oz. of small cabbage, and one small potato, or one-half of a medium-sized one, all of which vegetables must be finely minced.

About twenty-five minutes after the soup has started cooking, complete it with two tablespoonfuls of peas, a few French beans cut into lozenges, and one and one-half oz. of rice, or the same quantity of very thin macaroni broken into very small pieces.

This done, set to cook again for thirty minutes. A few minutes before serving, add to the soup one small, crushed clove of garlic, three leaves of sweet basil, and a small pinch of chopped chervil pluches; mix the whole with one-half tablespoonful of grated bacon.

Send to the table, separately, at the same time as the soup some freshly grated Gruyère.

Mille-Fanti

First make the following preparation:—Beat two small eggs to a stiff froth, and mix therewith one and one-half oz. of the crumb of very good white bread, one oz. of grated Parmesan, and a little nutmeg. Boil one and two-thirds pints of white consommé, and pour the above preparation therein, little by little, stirring briskly the while with the whisk. Then move the stewpan to the side of the fire, put the lid on, and set to cook gently for seven or eight minutes.

When about to serve, stir the soup with a whisk, and pour it into the soup-tureen.

Mulligatawny Soup

Cut a small fowl, or half a medium-sized one, into little pieces, and put these in a stewpan with a few roundels of carrot and onion, a small bunch of parsley and celery, one-half oz. of mushroom parings and one quart of white consommé. Set to boil, and then let cook gently.

Also lightly brown in butter half a medium-sized onion, chopped; besprinkle it with one dessertspoonful of fecula and one coffeespoonful of curry; moisten with the cooking-liquor of the fowl, strained through a sieve; boil, and set to cook gently for seven or eight minutes. Now rub the whole through tammy, and leave it to despumate for twenty minutes, adding one tablespoonful of consommé, from time to time, with the view of promoting the despumation, i.e., the purification of the soup.

When about to serve, finish the preparation with three or four tablespoonfuls of cream. Pour the whole into the soup-tureen; add a portion of the meat of the fowl, cut into thin slices, and serve separately two oz. of rice à l’Indienne.

Soupe aux Gombos ou Okra

This soup is held in high esteem by Americans. It is served either with garnish, as I direct below, or as a consommé, hot or cold, or in cups, after it has been strained.

Fry one medium-sized chopped onion in two oz. of butter, without letting it acquire any colour. Add one-quarter lb. of fresh lean bacon, or raw ham cut into medium-sized dice; fry for a few minutes, and add about one lb. of boned chicken-meat cut into large dice (the white parts of the chicken are used in preference); let these ingredients stiffen well; take care to stir fairly often, and moisten with two quarts of white chicken consommé. Boil, and set to cook gently for twenty or twenty-five minutes with lid on.

Now add about one-half lb. of peeled gombo, cut in coarse paysanne-fashion, and three or four medium-sized tomatoes, peeled, concassed, and with their seeds withdrawn.

When the gombos are well cooked, carefully remove all grease from the preparation; test the seasoning, and, if necessary, add a few drops of Worcestershire sauce.

Garnish the soup with two or three tablespoonfuls of plainly-cooked rice.

N.B.—This soup is excellent if it be finished with one-quarter pint of cream per quart. A cream of gombos may also be prepared, which may be garnished with the dice of chicken meat. In the latter case, the garnish of rice is optional.

Soupe à la Paysanne

Finely mince one small carrot, one small turnip, one leek, one-third of a stick of celery, one-third of an onion, and some cabbage leaves. Stew the vegetables in one oz. of butter; moisten with one and one-half pints of white consommé, and set to boil. A few minutes having elapsed, add two small potatoes minced like the other vegetables, and complete the cooking gently. Send separately some roundels of soup-flutes.

Soupe aux Poireaux et Pommes de Terre, otherwise à la Bonne Femme

Finely mince the white of four medium-sized leeks. Put this into a stewpan with one oz. of butter, and stew gently for a quarter of an hour. Then add three medium-sized quartered potatoes, cut into roundels the thickness of pennies. Moisten with one pint of white consommé; add the necessary quantity of salt, and set to cook gently. When about to serve, finish the soup with one pint of boiled milk and one and one-half oz. of butter; pour it into the soup-tureen, and add twelve roundels of French soup-flutes, cut as thinly as possible.

Soupe aux Rognons

Proceed exactly as for “Soupe aux Foies de Volaille”, but substitute for the garnish of sliced livers one of calf’s or sheep’s kidney cut into large dice, or sliced, and briskly tossed in butter just before dishing up.

Finish the soup similarly to the preceding one, i.e., with Madeira.

Chapter XIV Fish

In matters culinary, fish comprise not only the vertebrates of the sea and river, but also the esculent Crustacea, mollusca, and Chelonii, and one batrachian. Of course, the animals representing these various classes differ enormously in respect of their importance as articles of diet. Fresh-water fish, for instance, with the exception of salmon and some kinds of trout, are scarcely ever eaten in England; and the same applies to the frog. As regards salt-water fish, although certain species, such as the sole and the turbot, are in great demand, many other and excellent ones which are looked upon as inferior are seldom put into requisition by first-class cookery. Thus, Brill, Red Mullet, and Bass are not nearly so popular as they deserve to be, and never appear on a menu of any importance. No doubt. Fashion—ever illogical and wayward—exercises her tyrannical sway here, as in other matters of opinion; for it will be found, even when the distinctions among fish are once established, that there exist a host of incongruities in the un-written law. Fresh cod is a case in point; should this fish appear on the menu of a grand dinner given by Royalty, the guests would not think it at all out of place; but if the chef of a large modern hotel ventured to include it among the items of a plain table-d’hôte dinner he would most probably incur the scorn and indignation of his clientèle.

This example, than which none could be better suited to our case, successfully shows that the culinary value of the fish has far less to do with the vogue the latter enjoys than the very often freakish whims of the public.

One can but deplore the arbitrary proscription which so materially reduces the resources at the disposal of a cook, more particularly at a time when the universally imperious cry is for novelty and variety in dishes and menus respectively; and one can only hope that reason and good sense may, at no remote period, intervene to check the purposeless demands of both entertainers and their guests in this respect.

Having regard to these considerations, I have omitted from this work, which is really a thesaurus of selected recipes and not a complete formulary, all those fish enumerated below, which are very rarely eaten in England, and the recipes for which could therefore serve no purpose:—

Shad

Chiefly served grilled.

Fresh Anchovies

Extremely rare, and may be grilled or fried.

Eels

Considered as common, and principally used in the preparation of a pie held in high esteem by the frequenters of coffee-shops along the banks of the Thames. Small eels are also fried. But the many ways of dressing them which are common on the Continent are seldom practised in England.

Pike

Plentiful and of excellent quality; only used in the preparation of forcemeat and quenelles; the directions for the latter will be given later. Albeit they are sometimes served crimped, or cooked whole in a court-bouillon au bleu, accompanied by parsley or caper sauce, &c. Small pike are generally prepared “à la Meunière”, or fried.

Carp

In still less demand than the pike, and only prized for its milt. It must, however, be admitted that in England, more than anywhere else, I believe, this fish is too often spoilt by the taint of mud.

Dorado

Served boiled with any of the English fish sauces; but, in my opinion, it is best grilled, after the manner generally adopted in the South of France.

Sturgeon

Very rare; it is braised, like veal.

Féra

Comes from the Swiss or Savoy lakes, and is only served à la Meunière.

Gudgeon

Very abundant in all rivers, but never eaten.

Frogs

The pet abomination of all classes of the population, with but few exceptions; nevertheless “Nymphes à l’Aurore”, the recipe of which I gave among the hors-d’œuvres, are generally appreciated.

Fresh Herrings

Abundant and of excellent quality; seldom used in first-class cookery, except, perhaps, for their milt. Bloaters and kippered herrings are, with reason, preferred; of these I shall speak later.

Fresh Herrings

Chiefly used in preparing pies similar to those referred to in №755.

Fresh-water Herrings

Like the Féra, come from Switzerland or Savoy, and are very scarce on the English market Prepared especially à la Meunière.

Lote

Very scarce on the English market; only prized for its liver.

Mostele

Only caught in the region of Monaco; cannot bear transport; especially served à la Meunière or a l’Anglaise.

Mussels

Only used as garnish

Nonat

Replaced in England by whitebait, which it greatly resembles.

Perch

Very moderately appreciated; chiefly served fried, when small, and boiled with some fish sauce when large.

Skate

Generally served boiled, with caper sauce occasionally with brown butter. The smaller specimens are better fried. Often offered for sale, crimped.

Sardines

Generally of inferior quality; used in the preparation of sprats.

Sterlet

Almost unknown in England.

Turtle

With the exception of those firms which make this their speciality, is almost exclusively used in preparing Turtle Soup. The flippers are sometimes served braised au Madère.

I do not think it at all necessary to lay any further stress upon the series of preparations bearing the names of Croquettes, Cromesquis, Cotelettes (cotelettes here only mean those prepared from cooked fish, and which are really but a form of croquettes), Coquilles, Bouchées, Palets, &c., which may be made from any kind of cooked fish. These preparations are so well known that it would be almost superfluous to repeat their recipes.

Divers Ways of Cooking Fish

The divers ways of cooking fish are all derived from one or another of the following methods:—

Boiling in salted water, which may be applied equally well to large pieces and slices of fish.
Frying, particularly suited to small specimens and thin slices of larger ones.
Cooking in butter, otherwise “à la Meunière”, best suited to the same pieces as №2.
Poaching, with short moistening, especially suited to fillets or small specimens.
Braising, used particularly for large pieces.
Grilling, for small specimens and collops.
Cooking au Gratin, same as grilling.

The Boiling of Fish in Salted Water

The procedure changes according as to whether the fish is to be cooked whole or in slices. If whole, after having properly cleaned, washed, and trimmed it, lay it on the drainer of the utensil best suited to its shape; i.e., a fish-kettle. Cover it with water, salt it in the proportion of one-quarter oz. of salt per quart of water, cover the utensil, and bring the liquid to the boil. As soon as this is done skim and move the kettle to the side of the fire, where the cooking of the fish may be completed without boiling.

If the fish is cut into slices, plunge these, which should never be cut too thin, into boiling salted water, and move the fish-kettle containing them to the side of the fire; complete their cooking slowly without allowing the water to boil.

The object of this process is to concentrate, inside the fish, all the juices contained in its flesh, whereof a large portion escapes when the cut fish is plunged in cold water gradually brought to the boil. If this method is not applied to large fish, cooked whole, the reason is that the sudden immersion of these in boiling water would cause such a shrinking of their flesh that they would burst and thereby be spoiled.

In the case of certain kinds of fish, such as Turbot and Brill, milk is added to the water in the proportion of one-eighth of the latter, the object being to increase the whiteness of the fish.

For the various kinds of Salmon and Trout, the court-bouillon (formula №163) is used in the place of salted water, but the general working process remains the same.

The boiled fish is dished on a napkin and drainer; it is garnished with fresh parsley; and the sauce announced on the menu, together with some plain-boiled and floury potatoes, is sent to the table separately.

The Frying of Fish

In Part I. of this work I explained the general theory of frying (Chapter X., formula №26a); I shall now, therefore, only concern myself with the details of the operation in its relation to fish.

As a rule, frying should never be resorted to for very large fish or very thick slices of the latter, for, owing to the very high temperature that the operation enjoins, the outside of the fish would be dried up before the inside had even become affected.

If the fish to be fried is somewhat thick, it is best to cut several gashes in it, lengthwise and across, these being deeper and closer together the thicker the fish may be. The object of this measure is to facilitate the cooking, but the measure itself is quite unnecessary when dealing with small fish. In the case of flat-fish, partly detach the two underlying fillets on either side of the back-bone instead of gashing them.

All fish intended for frying (except Blanchailles and Whitebait) should first be steeped in salted milk, then rolled in flour before being plunged into the hot fat. If they be “panés à l’anglaise”, however, as they generally are in England, the milk may be dispensed with, in which case, after they have been lightly coated with flour, they are completely dipped in an anglaise (formula №174) and afterwards rolled in white breadcrumbs. They should then be patted with the blade of a knife so as to ensure the cohesion of the whole coating, and, finally, the latter should be criss-crossed with the back of a knife with the view of improving the appearance when fried.

Fried fish are served either on a napkin, on a drainer, or on special dish-papers. They are garnished with fried parsley and properly trimmed half-lemons.

The Cooking of Fish à la Meunière

This excellent mode of procedure is only suited to small fish or the slices of larger ones. Nevertheless, it may be resorted to for chicken-turbots, provided their weight do not exceed four lbs.

The operation consists in cooking the fish (or slices or fillets of fish) in the frying-pan with very hot butter, after having seasoned them and sprinkled them with flour. If the fish are very small, ordinary butter is used; if, on the other hand, they are large, the procedure demands clarified butter. When the fish is sufficiently coloured on one side, it is turned over for the completion of the operation. This done, it is transferred, by means of a spatula, to a hot dish, whereon, after having been salted, it is sent to the table.

It may be served as it is with a garnish of trimmed half-lemons.

Fish prepared in this way are termed “dorés” (gilded), “Soles dorés”, “Turbotins dorés”, &c., in order to distinguish them from those prepared à la Meunière.

If the fish is announced “à la Meunière”, a few drops of lemon should be sprinkled upon it; it should be seasoned with salt and pepper, and garnished with concassed, scalded parsley. At the last moment a piece of butter, in proportion to the size of the fish, is put in the frying-pan, and is heated until it begins to brown slightly. This is poured over the fish immediately, and the latter is sent to the table at once while still covered by the froth resulting from the contact of the butter with the parsley.

The Poaching of Fish

This method is best suited to sole, chicken-turbots, and brill, as well as to the fillets of various fish.

Having laid the fish to be poached in a baking-tray or a sauté-pan, either of which should have been previously buttered, season it moderately with salt and moisten with a little very white fish or mushroom fumet; very often the two latter are mixed. Cover the utensil, push it into a moderate oven, and baste from time to time, especially when a large fish is cooking. When the fish is done, drain it carefully, place it on a dish, and, as a rule, reduce the poaching-liquor and add it to the sauce. Poached fish are always served sauced; i.e., covered with the sauce which properly forms their accompaniment. More often than not they are garnished after the manner which will be described later.

I most emphatically urge:

the use of very little fish fumet for the poaching, but this fumet should be perfect and should, above all, not be cooked for longer than the required time;
that the fish be not covered with buttered paper as is often done, for nowadays a suitable paper is very rarely found. All papers found on the market are, owing to the chemical products used in their manufacture, liable to impart a more or less pungent smell to the objects they enclose, which in either degree would prove seriously prejudicial to the preparation.

These remarks not only apply to fish, but to all those objects with which paper was formerly used at some stage in their cooking process.

The Braising of Fish

This method is generally applied to whole or sliced salmon, to trout, and to chicken-turbot. Sometimes the fish treated in this way is larded on one side with strips of bacon-fat, truffles, gherkins, or carrots. The mode of procedure is exactly the same as that described under the “Braising of White Meats” (formula №248). Moisten these braisings in the proportion of one-half with white wine or red wine (according as to how the fish is to be served), and for the other half use a light fish fumet. Place the fish on the drainer of a fish-kettle just large enough to hold the former, and moisten in such wise that the cooking-liquor at the beginning of the operation does not cover more than three-quarters of the depth of the fish. Unless it be for a Lenten dish, the fish may be covered with slices of bacon while cooking. In any case, baste it often. Take care not to close the lid down too tightly, in order that the liquor may be reduced simultaneously with the cooking of the fish.

When the operation is almost completed, take the lid off the fish-kettle with the view of glazing the fish; then take the former off the fire. Now withdraw the drainer with the fish upon it, and lay it athwart the top of the fish-kettle, and let it drain; tilt the fish on to a dish, and cover the latter pending its despatch to the table. Strain the stock remaining in the fish-kettle through a strainer; let it stand for ten minutes, remove all the grease that has formed on its surface, and use it to complete the sauce as I directed above.

Braised fish are generally accompanied by a garnish, the constituents of which I shall give in the particular recipes relating to braising.

The Grilling of Fish

This method is best suited to small fish, to medium-sized chicken-turbots, and to large-sectioned fish.

Unless they are very small, it is best to gash both sides of fish intended for grilling; the reasons given above for this measure likewise apply here.

All white and naturally dry fish should be rolled in flour and besprinkled with butter or very good oil before being placed on the grill to be exposed to the heat of the fire. The flour forms a crust around the fish, which keeps it from drying and gives it that golden colour quite peculiar to objects thus treated.

Salmon, trout, red mullet, mackerel, and herrings, the flesh whereof is fatty, need not be floured, but only besprinkled with melted butter.

Owing to the somewhat fragile texture of most fish, a special double gridiron is used, by means of which they may be turned without fear of damage. This gridiron is placed upon the ordinary grill. I have already given in Part I. of this work the radical principles of grilling (formula №257); to this, therefore, the reader is begged to refer.

Grilled fish are served on a very hot dish, without paper or a napkin; they are garnished with fresh parsley and grooved slices of lemon.

“Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”, anchovy butter, devilled sauce, Escoffier Roberts’ sauce, and butter à la Ravigote constitute the best adjuncts to grilled fish.

The Cooking of Fish au Gratin

I described all the details of this method under Complete Gratin (formula №269), to which I must ask the reader to refer. This process is best suited to small fish, such as sole, whiting, red mullet, chicken-turbot, &c.

The Crimping of Fish

Crimped fish is quite an English speciality. This method of preparation is applied more particularly to salmon, fresh cod, haddock, and skate. The first three of these fish may be prepared whole or in slices, while skate is always cut into more or less large pieces after it has been skinned on both sides.

In order to crimp a whole fish, it should be taken as it leaves the water. Lay it on something flat, and make deep lateral gashes on both its sides from head to tail. Allow a space of about one and one-half inches to two inches between each gash. This done, put the fish to soak in very cold water for an hour or so. When the fish is to be cooked sliced, divide it up as soon as it is caught, and put the slices to soak in very cold water, as in the case of the whole fish.

But does this barbarous method, which stiffens and contracts the flesh of the fish, affect its quality so materially as connoisseurs would have us believe?

It is very difficult to say, and opinions on the matter are divided. This, however, is certain, that fish prepared in the way above described is greatly relished by many.

Whether whole or sliced, crimped fish is always boiled in salted water. Its cooking presents a real difficulty, in that it must be stopped at the precise moment when it is completed, any delay in this respect proving prejudicial to the quality of the dish.

Crimped fish is served like the boiled kind, and all the sauces suited to the latter likewise obtain with the former. Besides the selected sauce, send a sauceboat to the table containing some of the cooking-liquor of the fish.

Salmon (Saumon)

Salmon caught on the Rhine, or Dutch salmon, is generally considered the most delicate that may be had, though, in my opinion, that obtained from certain English rivers, such, for instance, as the Severn, is by no means inferior to the foregoing. Here in England this excellent fish is held in the high esteem it deserves, and the quantity consumed in this country is considerable. It is served as plainly as possible, either boiled, cold or hot, grilled, or à la Meunière; but whatever be the method of preparation, it is always accompanied by cucumber salad.

The slices of salmon, however, thick or thin, large or small, take the name of “Darnes”.

Boiled Salmon

Boiled salmon, whether whole or sliced, should be cooked in court-bouillon in accordance with directions given at the beginning of the chapter (formula №776). All fish sauces are suited to it, but more especially the following, viz.:—Hollandaise sauce, Mousseline sauce, Melted Butter, Shrimp Sauce, Nantua sauce, Cardinal Sauce, &c.

Crimped salmon admits of precisely the same sauces.

Broiled Salmon

Cut the salmon to be grilled in slices from one inch to one and one-half inches thick. Season with table-salt, sprinkle with melted butter or oil, and grill it for the first part on a rather brisk fire, taking care to moderate the latter towards the close of the operation. Allow about twenty-five minutes for the grilling of a slice of salmon one and one-half inches thick. “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”, anchovy butter, and devilled sauce Escoffier are the most usual adjuncts to grilled salmon.

Salmon à la Meunière

Having cut the salmon into moderately thick slices, season these, dredge them slightly, and cook them in the frying-pan with very hot clarified butter.

It is important that the salmon be set and that the cooking be rapid.

Serve it in either of the two ways indicated above (formula №778).

Various Ways of Preparing Salmon

In addition to the three methods of serving salmon described above, and those cold preparations with which I shall deal later, the fish in question lends itself to a whole host of dressings which are of the greatest utility in the varying of menus. The principles of these dressings I shall now give.

Cadgeree of Salmon

Prepare one lb. of cooked salmon, cleared of bones and skin, and cut into small pieces; four hard-boiled eggs cut into dice; one lb. of well-cooked pilaff rice; and three-quarters pint of Béchamel flavoured with curry.

Dish in a hot timbale, alternating the various products, and finish with a coating of sauce.

Cotelettes de Saumon

Prepare some mousseline forcemeat for salmon, the quantity whereof will be in accordance with the number of cutlets to be made, and rub it through a coarse sieve. Line the bottom and sides of some buttered tin moulds, shaped like cutlets, with a coating one-half inch thick of the prepared forcemeat.

Fill the moulds to within one-third inch of their brims with a cold salpicon of mushrooms and truffles, thickened by means of reduced Allemande sauce, and cover this with the stuffing.

Set the cutlets to poach, turn out the moulds; treat the cutlets à l’anglaise, and cook them with clarified butter.

Arrange in a circle round a dish, put a frill on a piece of fried bread counterfeiting the bone of the cutlet, garnish with fried parsley, and send to the table, separately, a “Dieppoise” sauce. Shrimp sauce, or a purée of fresh vegetables, such as peas, carrots, &c. In the latter case, serve at the same time a sauce in keeping with the garnish.

Coulibiac de Saumon

Preparation.—Have ready two lbs. of ordinary brioche paste without sugar (formula №2368). Stiffen in butter one and one-half  lbs. of small salmon collops, and prepare one-sixth lb. of mushrooms and one chopped onion (both of which should be fried in butter), one-half lb. of semolina kache (formula №2292) or the same weight of rice cooked in consommé; two hard-boiled eggs, chopped; and one lb. of vesiga, roughly chopped and cooked in consommé.

For this weight of cooked vesiga about two and one-half oz. of dried vesiga will be needed, which should be soaked for at least four hours in cold water, and then cooked for three and one-half hours in white consommé. It may also be cooked in water.

Roll the brioche paste into rectangles twelve inches long by eight inches wide, and spread thereon in successive layers the kache or the rice, the collops of salmon, the chopped vesiga, the eggs, the mushrooms, and the onion, and finish with a layer of kache or rice. Moisten the edges of the paste and draw the longest ends of it towards each other over the enumerated layers of garnish, and join them so as to properly enclose the latter.

Now fold the two remaining ends over to the centre in a similar way. Place the coulibiac thus formed on a baking-tray, and take care to turn it over in order that the joining parts of the paste lie underneath.

Set the paste to rise for twenty-five minutes, sprinkle some melted butter over the coulibiac, sprinkle with some very fine raspings, make a slit in the top for the escape of vapour, and bake in a moderate oven for forty-five or fifty minutes. Fill the coulibiac with freshly-melted butter when withdrawing it from the oven.

Darnes de Saumon

The few recipes dealing with “Darnes de Saumon”, which I give below, may also be adapted to whole salmon after the size of the fish has been taken into account in measuring the time allowed for cooking.

Darne de Saumon à Chambord

As already explained, the term “darne” stands for a piece of salmon cut from the middle of that fish, and the size of a darne is in proportion to the number of people it is intended for.

Proceed after the manner directed under “The Braising of Fish” (formula №780); moisten in the proportion of two-thirds with excellent red wine and one-third with fish stock, calculating the quantity in such wise that it may cover no more than two-thirds of the depth of the darne. Bring to the boil, then set to braise gently, and glaze the darne at the last moment.

Garnish and Sauce.—Garnish with quenelles of truffled mousseline forcemeat for fish, moulded by means of a spoon: two large ornamented quenelles; truffles fashioned like olives; pieces of milt dipped in Villeroy sauce, treated à l’anglaise and fried when about to dish up; small gudgeon or smelts treated similarly to the milt, and trussed crayfish cooked in court-bouillon.

The sauce is a Genevoise, made from the reduced cooking-liquor of the darne.

Dishing Up.—Surround the darne by the garnishes enumerated, arranging them tastefully, and pierce it with two hatelets, each garnished with a small truffle, an ornamented quenelle, and a crayfish.

Send the sauce to the table separately.

Darne de Saumon à Daumont

Poach the dame in a court-bouillon prepared beforehand.

Dishing Up and Garnish

Surround the darne by medium-sized mushrooms stewed in butter and garnished with small crayfish tails cohered by means of a few tablespoonfuls of Nantua sauce; small round quenelles of mousseline forcemeat for fish, decorated with truffles, and some slices of milt treated à l’anglaise, and fried when about to dish up.

Serve the Nantua sauce separately.

Darne de Saumon à Lucullus

Skin one side of the darne, lard it with truffles, and braise it in champagne.

The Garnish Round the Darne

Very small garnished patties of crayfish tails; small cassolettes of milt; small mousselines of oysters, poached in dariole-moulds.

Sauce

The braising-liquor of the darne finished by means of ordinary and crayfish butter in equal quantities. Send it to the table separately.

Darne de Saumon à Nesselrode

Remove the spine and all other internal bones. Stuff the darne with raw lobster mousse stiffened by means of a little pike forcemeat.

Line a well-buttered, round and even raised-pie mould with a thin layer of hot-water, raised-pie paste (this is made from one lb. of flour, four oz. of lard, one egg, and a little lukewarm water), which should be prepared in advance and made somewhat stiff. Now garnish the inside of the pie with thin slices of bacon and place the darne upright in it. (To simplify the operation the darne may be stuffed at this stage.) Cover the pie with a layer of the same paste, pinch its edges with those of the original lining, make a slit in the top for the steam to escape, and cook in a good oven.

When the pie is almost baked, prod it repeatedly with a larding-needle; when the latter is withdrawn clear of all stuffing the pie should be taken from the oven. This done, turn it upside down in order to drain away the melted bacon and other liquids inside it, but do not let it drop from the mould. Then tilt it on to a dish and take off the mould. Do not break the crust except at the dining-table.

Sauce

Serve an American sauce with the pie, the former being prepared from the remains of the lobsters used in making the mousse, finished with cream, and garnished with very fine oysters (cleared of their beards), poached when about to dish up.

Darne de Saumon Régence

Braise the dame in white wine in accordance with the directions given in formula №780.

Garnish

Surround the darne by spoon-moulded quenelles of whiting forcemeat prepared with crayfish butter, oysters cleared of their beards and poached, small, very white mushrooms, and poached slices of milt.

Normande sauce finished with truffle essence.

Darne de Saumon à Royale

Braise the darne in Sauterne wine.

Garnish

Bunches of crayfishes’ tails, small quenelles of mousseline forcemeat for fish, small mushrooms, slices of truffle, and little balls of potato raised by means of the large, round spoon-cutter, and cooked à l’anglaise.

Send a Normande sauce separately.

Darne de Saumon à Valois

Poach the darne in a white wine court-bouillon.

Garnish

Potato balls raised with the spoon-cutter or turned to the shape of olives, and cooked in salted water, poached slices of milt, and trussed crayfish cooked in court-boullion.

Send a Valois sauce separately.

Mousseline de Saumon

In Part I. I dealt with the preparation of mousseline forcemeat (formula №195), and also the method of poaching spoon-moulded quenelles (formula №205). Now mousselines are only large quenelles which derive their name from the very light forcemeat of which they are composed. These mousseline quenelles are always moulded with the ordinary tablespoon, they are garnished on top with a fine, raw slice of the fish under treatment, and poached after the manner already described.

Mousseline Alexandra

Having made the salmon mousseline forcemeat, mould the quenelles and place them, one by one, in a buttered sauté-pan. Place a small, round and very thin slice of salmon on each, and poach them in a very moderate oven with lid on the utensil containing them.

Drain on a piece of linen, arrange them in a circle on a dish, place a slice of truffle upon each slice of salmon, coat with Mornay sauce, and glaze.

Garnish the centre of the dish with very small peas or asparagus-heads cohered with butter just before dishing up.

Mousseline de Saumon à la Tosca

Combine one and one-half oz. of crayfish cream-cullis with each pound of the salmon mousseline forcemeat. Mould and poach as above, drain, and arrange in a circle on a dish.

Garnish each mousseline with a thin slice of milt cooked in lightly-browned butter, four crayfish tails cut lengthwise into two, and a slice of truffle at each end. Coat with a light Mornay sauce, finished with crayfish butter, and glaze quickly.

N.B.—In addition to these two recipes, all the garnishes suitable for fillets of sole may be applied to mousselines. Garnishes of early-season vegetable purées also suit them admirably, and therein lies an almost inexhaustible source of variety.

Cold Salmon

When salmon is to be served cold it should, as far as possible, be cooked, either whole or in large pieces, in the court-bouillon given under formula №163 and cooled in the latter. Pieces cooked separately may seem better or may be more easily made to look sightly, but their meat is drier than that of the salmon cooked whole. And what is lost in appearance with the very large pieces is more than compensated for by their extra quality.

In dishing cold salmon the skin may be removed and the fillets bared, so that the fish may be more easily decorated, but the real gourmet will always prefer the salmon served in its natural silver vestment.

In decorating cold salmon use pieces of cucumber, anchovy fillets, capers, slices of tomato, curled-leaf parsley, &c.

I am not partial to the decorating of salmon with softened butter, coloured or not, laid on by means of the piping-bag. Apart from the fact that this method of decoration is rarely artistic, the butter used combines badly with the cold sauces and the meat of the salmon on the diner’s plate. Very green tarragon leaves, chervil, lobster coral, &c., afford a more natural and more delicate means of ornamentation. The only butter fit to be served with cold salmon is Montpellier butter (formula №153), though this, in fact, is but a cold sauce often resorted to for the coating of the cold fish in question.

Among the garnishes which suit cold salmon, I might mention small peeled, and emptied tomatoes garnished with some kind of salad; hard-boiled eggs, either wholly stuffed, or stuffed in halves or in quarters, barquettes, tartlets and cassolettes made from cucumber or beetroot, parboiled until almost completely cooked and garnished with a purée of tunny, of sardines, of anchovies, &c.; small aspics of shrimps or of crayfishes’ tails; small slices of lobster, &c.

Almost all the cold sauces may accompany cold salmon.

Saumon Froid, ou Darne de Saumon Froid à la Royale

Having drained and dried the salmon or the darne, remove the skin from one of its sides, and coat the bared fillets with a layer of a preparation of mousse de saumon, letting it lie rather more thickly over the middle than the sides. Coat the layer of mousse with mayonnaise sauce thickened by means of fish jelly, and leave to set.

Now let some clear fish jelly set on the bottom of the dish to be sent to the table; place the salmon or the darne on this jelly, and surround the piece with a border consisting of Montpellier butter, using for the purpose a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe.

Decorate the centre of the piece by means of a fine fleur-de-lys made from truffles, and encircle it with two royale crowns made from anchovy fillets.

Saumon Froid ou Darne de Saumon à la Parisienne

Remove the skin in suchwise as to leave the bared portion in the shape of a regular rectangle, equidistant from the tail and the head; or, in the case of a darne, occupying two-thirds of its surface.

Cover the bared portion with mayonnaise sauce thickened with fish jelly and leave it to set.

Now stand the piece on a small cushion of rice or semolina, shaping the latter like the piece itself; trim the sauced rectangle with a border of Montpellier butter, laid on by means of a piping-bag fitted with a small grooved pipe. Garnish the centre of the rectangle with pieces of lobster coral, the chopped, hard-boiled white and yolk of an egg, chervil leaves, &c.

Encircle the piece with a border of small artichoke-bottoms, garnished, in the form of a dome, with a small macédoine of vegetables cohered with cleared mayonnaise.

Send a mayonnaise sauce to the table separately.

Saumon Froid ou Darne de Saumon Froid à la Riga

Prepare a salmon or a darne as in the preceding recipe, and dish it on a cushion in order that it may be slightly raised.

Surround it with grooved sections of cucumber hollowed to represent small timbales, well parboiled, marinaded with a few drops of oil and lemon-juice and filled with a vegetable salad thickened with mayonnaise; indented, halved eggs filled with caviare; and tartlets of vegetable salad cohered with mayonnaise, and garnished, each with a crayfish-shell stuffed with crayfish mousse; alternate these various garnishes, and encircle with a border of jelly dice.

Saumon Froid ou Darne de Saumon Froid en Belle-Vue

Skin the salmon or the darne, set the piece upright upon the belly side, and decorate the fillets with pieces of truffles, poached white of egg, chervil leaves, and tarragon, &c.

Coat the garnish with a little melted fish aspic so as to fix it.

This done, sprinkle the piece, again and again, with the same melted aspic jelly in order to cover it with a kind of transparent veil.

Place the piece thus prepared in a crystal receptacle similarly shaped to the fish, and fill the former to the brim with very clear, melted jelly.

When dishing up, incrust the receptacle containing the fish in a block of clean ice which, in its turn, is laid on the dish to be sent to the table. Another way is to place the crystal utensil direct upon the dish and to surround the former with broken ice.

Saumon Froid ou Darne de Saumon Froid au Chambertin

Poach the salmon or the darne in a court-bouillon consisting of very clear fish fumet and Chambertin wine, in equal quantities, and leave to cool. Prepare an aspic jelly from the court-bouillon.

Skin and decorate the salmon or the darne and glaze it with white aspic jelly, exactly as directed above, in the case of the Belle-vue.

Dish in the same way, in a crystal receptacle, and fill the latter with the prepared aspic jelly. Serve on a block of ice, or with broken ice around the utensil.

Saumon Froid ou Darne de Saumon Froid à la Norvegienne

Skin and decorate the salmon or the darne, and glaze it with white aspic jelly precisely as in formula №804.

Let a coating of very clear jelly set on the bottom of the dish to be sent to the table. Upon this aspic jelly lay a cushion the same shape as the fish, of semolina, or of carved rice.

Set the piece (salmon or darne), decorated and glazed, upon this cushion, and lay thereon a row of fine prawns, cleared of their abdominal shell.

Surround with a garnish of small cucumber timbales, well parboiled, marinaded, and garnished dome-fashion, with a purée of smoked salmon; halved, hard-boiled eggs, glazed with aspic; very small tomatoes, or halved medium-sized ones, peeled, pressed in the corner of a towel to return them to their original shape, stuck with a bit of parsley-stalk, and decorated with leaves of green butter moulded by means of the piping-bag; and small barquettes of cooked and marinaded beetroot, garnished with shrimps’ tails cohered with mayonnaise.

Send a Russe sauce separately.

Cotelettes Froid de Saumon

Liberally butter some tin cutlet-shaped moulds. Line their bottoms and sides with a very red slice of salmon, as thin as a piece of cardboard. This slice should be long enough to project outside the brim of the mould to the extent of one-half inch.

Garnish the insides of the moulds with well-seasoned salmon meat, and draw the projecting lengths of salmon across this meat so as to enclose the latter and finish off the cutlets.

Arrange the moulds on a baking-tray; poach the cutlets, dry, in a moderate oven; turn them out of their moulds on to another tray as soon as they are poached, and let them cool. Then coat them with a half-melted aspic, and decorate them according to fancy, either with very green peas or a leaf of chervil with a bit of lobster coral in its centre—in a word, something simple and neat.

These cutlets, which are generally served at ball-suppers, may be dished on a tazza, on a cushion of rice, semolina, cornflour, or stearine, and laid almost vertically against a pyramid of vegetable salad cohered by means of mayonnaise with aspic. In this case the dish is finished of with a hatelet stuck into the middle of the pyramid.

The cutlets may also be arranged in a circle on a flat, shallow, silver or crystal dish, and covered with a delicate cold melted jelly.

Whatever be the selected method of dishing, always send to the table with the cutlet a sauceboat of cold sauce.

Médaillons de Saumon

These médallions have the same purpose as the cutlets already described, and are prepared thus:—

Cut some small slices, one-third inch thick, from a fillet of salmon.

Arrange them on a buttered tray; poach them, dry, in a moderate oven, and cool them under a light weight.

Now trim them neatly, with an even cutter, oval or round, in accordance with the shape they are intended to have.

Coat them, according to their purpose, either with mayonnaise sauce or one of its derivatives, thickened with jelly, or a white, pink, or green chaud-froid sauce. Decorate it in any way that may be fancied, and glaze them with cold melted aspic jelly.

Dish after the manner described under “Cotelettes” (see above).

Mayonnaise de Saumon

Garnish the bottom of a salad-bowl with moderately seasoned, ciseled lettuce. Cover with cold, cooked and flaked salmon, thoroughly cleared of all skin and bones.

Coat with mayonnaise sauce, and decorate with anchovy fillets, capers, stoned olives, small slices or roundels or quarters of hard-boiled eggs, small hearts of lettuce, a border of little roundels of radish, &c.

Salade de Saumon

This preparation comprises the same ingredients as the above, with the exception of the mayonnaise sauce. The decorating garnish is placed directly upon the salmon, and the whole is seasoned in precisely the same way as an ordinary salad.

Trout

From the culinary standpoint, trout are divided into two quite distinct classes, viz., large trout, whereof the typical specimen is Salmon-trout, and small or fresh-water trout.

Truite Saumonée (Salmon Trout)

In its many preparations, salmon-trout may be replaced by salmon, and all the recipes relating to the former may be adapted to the latter.

In any case, however, as its size is less than that of salmon, it is very rarely cut into darnes, being more generally served whole.

The few recipes that follow are proper to salmon-trout.

Truite à la Cambacérès

Select a male trout in preference; clean it, and remove its gills without opening it in the region of the belly.

Skin it on one side, starting at a distance of one inch from the head and finishing within two and one-half inches of the root of the tail.

Lard the bared portions with truffles and the red part only of carrots cut into rods.

This done, spread out a napkin, lay the trout thereon, belly under, and, with a sharp knife, separate the two fillets from the bones, beginning in the region of the head and proceeding straight down to where the body converges towards the tail.

The spine being thus liberated, sever it at both ends; i.e., from the tail and the head, and withdraw it, together with all the adhering ventral bones. The intestines are then removed, the inside of the fish is well cleaned, the fillets are seasoned on their insides, and the trout is stuffed with a mousseline forcemeat of raw crayfish. The two fillets are drawn together, and the trout, thus reconstructed, is covered with thin slices of bacon and laid on the drainer of the fish-kettle and braised in Sauterne wine.

When the fish is done, remove the slices of bacon, glaze it, and dish it up. Surround it with alternate heaps of morels tossed in butter and milt à la Meunière.

Send to the table, separately, a fine Béchamel sauce, combined with the braising-liquor of the trout, strained and reduced, and finished with crayfish butter.

Truite Saumonées Froides

We are now concerned with a whole series of unpublished “Trout” preparations, which are at once of superfine delicacy and agreeable aspect, and which admit of clean and easy dishing.

Cook a trout weighing from two to three lbs. in court-bouillon, and let it cool in the latter. Then drain it; sever the head and tail from the body, and put them aside. Completely skin the whole fish, and carefully separate the two fillets from the bones.

Deck each fillet with tarragon and chervil leaves, lobster coral, poached white of eggs, &c., and set them, back to back, upon a mousse of tomatoes lying in a special, long white or coloured porcelain dish about one and one-half to two inches deep.

Replace the head and tail, and cover the whole with a coating of half-melted, succulent fish aspic, somewhat clear. Let the aspic set, and incrust the dish containing the trout in a block of ice, or surround it with the latter broken.

Préparation De La Mousse De Tomates

This mousse, like those which I shall give later, is really a bavarois without sugar. Its recipe is exactly the same as that of the “bavarois of fruit”, except with regard to the question of sugar.

Cook one-half lb. of tomato pulp (cleared of skin and seeds, and roughly chopped) in one oz. of butter. When the pulp has thoroughly mingled with the butter, add thereto two tablespoonfuls of velouté thickened by means of eight leaves of gelatine per quart of the sauce.

Rub through tammy, and add to the preparation, when almost cold, half of its volume of barely-whipped cream. Taste the mousse; season with a few drops of lemon juice, and if it still seems flat, add the necessary salt and a very little cayenne.

N.B.—It will be seen that I prescribe cream only half-whipped. This precaution, however, does not apply to “Mousse de Tomates” alone, but to all mousses. Well-whipped cream imparts a dry and woolly taste to them, whereas, when it is only half-whipped, it renders them unctuous and fresh to the palate.

From the point of view of delicacy, the respective results of the two methods do not bear comparison.

Other Preparations of Trout after the same recipe

By proceeding exactly as directed in the foregoing recipe, and by substituting one of the following mousses for the “Mousse de Tomates”, it will be found that considerable variety may be introduced into menus:—

Crayfish Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with crayfish tails and tarragon leaves.
Lobster Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with slices of lobster, coral, and chervil.
Shrimp Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with crayfish tails and capers.
Capsicum Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with strips of grilled capsicum.
Physalia Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with chervil, tarragon, and bunches of physalia around the fillets.
Green Pimentos Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with strips of green pimentos.
Early-season Herb Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with chopped, hard-boiled eggs, and chopped parsley.
Volnay Mousse with fillets of trout, decked with anchovy fillets, capers, and olives.
Chambertin Mousse with fillets of trout decked like №8.

N.B.—In the making of “Mousse au Volnay” and “au Chambertin” the base of the preparations is supplied by cleared velouté, to which is added the reduced cooking-liquor of the trout.

All these recipes are equally suitable for sole or chicken-turbot.

Ondines aux Crevettes Roses

Prepare a very delicate trout mousse, mould it in egg-moulds, and garnish the centre with trimmed prawns’ tails. Let the mousse set; then speedily turn the undines out of their moulds, and lay them in a deep entrée-dish. Between each of them lay a few prawns, the tails of which should be shelled. Cover the whole, little by little, with some excellent, half-melted jelly here and there add a few sprigs of chervil, and then fill up the dish with jelly, so as to completely cover the mousses.

Fresh-water Trout

The best are those procured in mountainous districts, where the clear water they inhabit is constantly refreshed by strong currents.

The two leading methods of preparing them are called, respectively, “Au bleu” and “à la Meunière”. Having already described the latter, I shall now give my attention to “Truite au bleu”.

This preparation is held in very high esteem in Switzerland and Germany, where fresh-water trout are not only plentiful, but of excellent quality.

Truites au bleu

The essential condition for this dish consists in having live trout. Prepare a court-bouillon with plenty of vinegar (formula №163), and keep it boiling in a rather shallow basin.

About ten minutes before dishing them, take the trout out of water; stun them by a blow on the head; empty and clean them very quickly, and plunge them into the boiling liquid, where they will immediately shrivel, while their skin will break in all directions.

A few minutes will suffice to cook trout the average weight of which is one-third lb.

Drain them and dish them immediately upon a napkin, with curled-leaf parsley all round. Serve them with a Hollandaise sauce or melted butter.

N.B.—Fresh-water trout may also be served fried or grilled, but neither of these methods of preparation suits them so well as “à la Meunière” or “au bleu”, which I have given.

Soles

Sole may be served whole or filleted, and a large number of the recipes given for the whole fish may be adapted to its fillets.

As a rule, the fillets are made to appear on the menu of a dinner owing to the fact that they dish more elegantly and are more easily served than the whole fish, the latter being generally served at luncheons.

Nevertheless, in cases where great ceremony is not observed at a dinner, soles may well be served whole, inasmuch as no hard-and-fast rule has ever obtained in this matter.

Sole Alice

This sole is prepared, or rather its preparation is completed, at the table.

Have an excellent fish fumet (formula №11), short and very white. Trim the sole; put it into a special, deep earthenware dish, the bottom of which should be buttered; pour the fumet over it and poach gently.

Now send it to the table with a plate containing separate heaps of one finely-chopped onion, a little powdered thyme, and three finely-crushed biscottes.

In the dining-room the waiter places the dish on a chafer, and, taking off the sole, he raises the fillets therefrom, and places them between two hot plates. He then adds to the cooking-liquor of the sole the chopped onion, which he leaves to cook for a few moments, the powdered thyme and a sufficient quantity of the biscotte raspings to allow of thickening the whole.

At the last minute he adds six raw oysters and one oz. of butter divided into small pieces.

As soon as the oysters are stiff, he returns the fillets of sole to the dish, besprinkles them copiously with the sauce, and then serves them very hot.

N.B.—In order to promote the poaching of the soles, more particularly when they are large, the fillets on the upper side of the fish should be slightly separated from the bones. By this means the heat is able to reach the inside of the fish very quickly, and the operation is accelerated.

The sole is always laid on the dish with its opened side undermost—that is to say, on its back.

Sole Mornay

Lay the sole on a buttered dish; sprinkle a little fish fumet over it, and add one-half oz. of butter divided into small pieces. Poach gently.

Coat the bottom of the dish on which the sole is to be served with Mornay sauce; drain the fish, lay it on the prepared dish; cover it with the same sauce; sprinkle with grated Gruyère and Parmesan, and glaze at a Salamander.

Sole Mornay des Provençaux

This sole, which used to be served at the famous restaurant of the “Frères Provençaux”, was prepared, and always may be prepared, as follows:—

Poach the sole in fish fumet and butter, as directed in the preceding recipe; drain it, and place it on a dish; cover it with white-wine sauce; sprinkle liberally with grated cheese, and glaze quickly.

Sole au Champagne

Poach the sole in a buttered dish with one-half pint of champagne. Dish it; reduce its cooking-liquor to half; add thereto one-sixth pint of velouté, and complete with one and one-half oz. of best butter.

Cover the sole with this sauce; glaze, and garnish each side of the dish with a little heap of a julienne of filleted sole, seasoned, dredged, and tossed in clarified butter at the last moment in order to have it very crisp.

N.B.—By substituting a good white wine for the champagne, a variety of dishes may be made, among which may be mentioned: Soles au Chablis, Soles au Sauterne, Sole au Samos, Sole au Chateau Yquem, &c., &c.

Sole Colbert

On the upper side of the fish separate the fillets from the spine, and break the latter in several places. Dip the sole in milk; roll it in flour; treat it à l’anglaise, and roll the separated fillets back a little, so that they may be quite free from the bones.

Fry; drain on a piece of linen; remove the bones, and fill the resulting space with “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”.

Serve the sole on a very hot dish.

Sole à la Daumont

Bone the sole; i.e., sever the spine near the tail and the head; remove it, and leave those portions of the fillets which He on the remaining extremities of it intact. Garnish the inside with whiting forcemeat finished with crayfish butter, and rearrange the fillets in such wise as to give a natural and untouched appearance to the fish. Poach it on a buttered dish with one-sixth pint of white wine, the same quantity of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and one oz. of butter cut into small lumps.

Drain and dish the sole, and cover it with Nantua sauce. Place around it four mushrooms stewed in butter and garnished with crayfish tails in Nantua sauce; four small, round quenelles of whiting forcemeat with cream, decked with truffles; and four slices of milt treated à l’anglaise and fried at the last moment.

Sole Dorée

As I explained under “Fish à la Meunière” (formula №778), “Sole Dorée” is a sole fried in clarified butter, dished dry, and garnished with slices of carefully peeled lemon.

Sole Duglére

All fish treated after this recipe, with the exception of soles, should be divided up.

Put the sole in a buttered dish with one and one-half oz. of chopped onion, one-half lb. of peeled and concassed tomatoes, a little roughly-chopped parsley, a pinch of table salt, a very little pepper, and one-eighth pint of white wine. Set to poach gently, and then dish the sole.

Reduce the cooking-liquor; thicken it with two tablespoonfuls of fish velouté; complete with one oz. of butter and a few drops of lemon juice, and cover the fish with this sauce.

Sole Grillée

Season the sole; sprinkle oil thereon, and grill the fish very gently. Send it, garnished with slices of lemon, on a very hot dish.

Sole Grillée, aux Huîtres à l’américaine

This sole may be either grilled or poached, almost dry, in butter and lemon juice. With the procedure remaining the same, it may also be prepared in fillets. Whatever be the mode of procedure, serve it on a very hot dish, and surround it at the last moment with six oysters poached in a little boiling Worcestershire sauce.

Cover the sole immediately with very hot fried bread-crumbs, and add thereto a pinch of chopped parsley.

Sole à la Fermière

Put the sole, seasoned, on a buttered dish with a few aromatics. Add one-third pint of excellent red wine, and poach gently with lid on.

Dish up; strain the cooking-liquor, and reduce it to half; thicken it with a lump of manied butter the size of a hazel-nut, and finish the sauce with one oz. of butter.

Encircle the sole with a border of mushrooms sliced raw and tossed in butter. Pour the prepared sauce over the sole, and set to glaze quickly.

Sole à la Hollandaise

Break the spine of the sole by folding it over in several places. Put the fish in a deep dish; cover it with slightly salted water; set to boil, and then poach gently for ten minutes with lid on.

Drain and dish on a napkin with very green parsley all round. Serve at the same time some plainly boiled potatoes, freshly done, and two oz. of melted butter.

Sole Saint-Germain

Season the sole; dip it in melted butter, and cover it with fresh bread-crumbs, taking care to pat the latter with the flat of a knife, in order that they may combine with the butter to form a kind of crust. Sprinkle with some more melted butter, and grill the fish gently so that its coating of bread-crumbs may acquire a nice golden colour. Dish the sole, and surround it with potatoes turned to the shape of olives, and cooked in butter.

Send a Béarnaise sauce to the table separately.

Sole Florentine

Poach the sole in a fish fumet and butter. Spread a layer of shredded spinach, stewed in butter, on the bottom of a dish place the sole thereon; cover it with Mornay sauce; sprinkle with a little grated cheese, and set to glaze quickly in the oven or at a salamander.

Sole Montreuil

Poach the sole in one-sixth pint of fish fumet, one-sixth pint of white wine, and one-half oz. of butter.

Drain as Soon as poached, and surround with potato-balls the size of walnuts, cooked in salted water, and kept whole. Cover the sole with white-wine sauce, and lay a thread of shrimp sauce over the garnish.

Sole au Gratin

Partly separate the fillets from the bones on the upper side of the fish, and slip a lump of butter, the size of a walnut, under each.

This done, place the sole on a well-buttered gratin dish, on the bottom of which a pinch of chopped shallots and parsley has been sprinkled, together with one or two tablespoonfuls of Gratin sauce.

Lay four cooked mushrooms along the sole, and surround it with one oz. of raw mushrooms, cut into rather thin slices.

Add two tablespoonfuls of white wine; cover the sole with Gratin sauce; sprinkle with fine raspings followed by melted butter, and set the gratin to form in pursuance of the directions given under complete Gratin (formula №269).

When taking the sole from the oven, sprinkle a few drops of lemon juice and a pinch of chopped parsley upon it, and serve at once.

Sole au Chambertin

Season the sole and poach it on a buttered dish with one-third pint of Chambertin wine.

As soon as it is poached, drain it, dish it, and keep it hot. Reduce the cooking-liquor to half, add thereto a little freshly-ground pepper and two or three drops of lemon-juice, thicken with a lump of manied butter the size of a walnut, and finish the sauce with one and one-half oz. of butter.

Cover the sole with the sauce, set to glaze quickly, and garnish both sides of the dish with a little heap of julienne of filleted sole, seasoned, dredged, and tossed in clarified butter at the last moment so that it may be very crisp.

Remarks concerning “Soles aux Grands Vins”

Taking recipe №834 as a model, and putting into requisition all the good wines of Burgundy and Bordeaux, the following varieties are obtained, aviz.:—Soles au Volnay, au Pommard, au Romanée, au Clos-Vougeot, or soles au Saint-Estèphe, au Château-Larose, au Saint-Émilion, &c., &c.

Sole Montgolfier

Poach the sole in one-sixth pint of white wine and as much of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms. Drain, dish, and cover it with a white wine sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor of the sole and one tablespoonful of a fine julienne of spiny lobster’s tail, mushrooms, and very black truffles. Surround the sole with a border of little palmettes made from puff-paste and cooked without colouration.

Sole sur le Plat

Partly separate the fillets from the bones on the upper side of the fish, and slip a piece of butter the size of a walnut under each.

Lay the sole on a liberally buttered dish, moisten with one-fifth pint of the cooking-liquor of fish, and add a few drops of lemon-juice.

Cook in the oven, basting often the while, until the cooking-liquor has by reduction acquired the consistence of a syrup and covers the sole with a translucent and glossy coat.

N.B.—By substituting for the mushroom cooking-liquor a good white or red wine, to which a little melted pale meat glaze has been added, the following series of dishes may be prepared, viz.:—Sole sur le plat au Chambertin. Sole sur le plat au vin rouge, Sole sur le plat au Champagne. Sole sur le plat au Chablis, &c., &c.

Sole Régence

Poach the sole in a little white wine and two-thirds oz. of butter cut into small pieces.

Drain the sole, dish it, and surround it with six quenelles of whiting forcemeat finished with crayfish butter, moulded by means of a small spoon; four poached oysters (cleared of their beards); four small cooked and very white mushrooms; four small truffles, turned to the shape of olives; and four small poached slices of milt. Cover the sole and the garnish with a Normande sauce finished with a little truffle essence.

Sole Portugaise

Poach the sole in white wine and the cooking-liquor of fish. Drain, dish, and surround with a garnish consisting of two medium-sized tomatoes, peeled, pressed, minced, cooked in butter, and combined with minced and cooked mushrooms, and a large pinch of chopped chives.

Coat the sole with white wine sauce, plentifully buttered, and take care that none of the sauce touches the garnish.

Set to glaze quickly, sprinkle the garnish with a pinch of chopped parsley when taking the sole from the oven, and serve immediately.

Sole Cubat

Poach the sole in one-fifth pint of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms and one-half oz. of butter cut into small pieces.

Coat the bottom of the dish intended for the sole with a purée of mushrooms, place the drained sole on this purée, lay six fine slices of truffle along the fish, coat with Mornay sauce, sprinkle with cheese, and glaze quickly.

Sole aux Huîtres

Open and poach six oysters. Poach the sole in the liquor of the oysters, drain it, dish it, and surround it with the oysters (cleared of their beards).

Coat with a white wine sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor of the sole, and glaze quickly.

Sole à la Meunière

Proceed for this dish as directed under “Fish à la Meunière” (formula №778).

Sole Meunière aux Concombres otherwise Doria

Prepare a sole à la Meunière. Garnish it at both ends with little heaps of cucumber, turned and cooked in butter with a little salt and a pinch of sugar.

Sole Meunière aux Aubergines

Prepare a sole à la Meunière in the usual way. Surround it with a fine border of egg-plant roundels one-third inch thick, seasoned, dredged, and fried in clarified butter, just in time to be arranged round the sole when it is ready. The question of time is important, for if the fried roundels be allowed to wait at all they very quickly lose their crispness.

Sole Meunière aux Cèpes

Prepare the sole à la Meunière in the usual way and surround it with a border of sliced cèpes frizzled in butter just before dishing up.

Sole Meunière aux Morilles

Surround the sole with very fresh morels cooked in salted water and then tossed in butter just before dishing up. Sprinkle a pinch of chopped parsley over the morels.

Sole Meunière aux Raisins

The sole being ready, encircle it with fresh skinned Muscadel grapes prepared in advance.

Sole Meunière à l’Orange

When the sole is cooked and dished, lay thereon a row of orange slices, peeled to the pulp and thoroughly pipped, or some sections of oranges, likewise peeled to the pulp and carefully pipped. This done, cover the sole and the garnish with lightly-browned butter and serve instantly.

Sole Lutèce

Line the bottom of the dish intended for the sole with a coating of shredded spinach tossed in lightly-browned butter. Place the sole, prepared à la Meunière, upon this spinach; lay a few roundels of onion and slices of artichoke-bottom tossed in butter upon the fish; and on either side of the sole lay a border of potato-slices, freshly cooked in salted water and well browned in butter.

At the last moment cover the whole with lightly-browned butter.

Sole Murat

Toss in butter, separately

one medium-sized potato cut into dice;
two small raw artichoke-bottoms, likewise cut into dice. Prepare the sole à la Meunière, dish it, and surround it with the tossed potato and artichoke-bottom, mixed when cooked. Lay on the sole five slices of tomato, one-half inch thick, seasoned, dredged, and tossed in very hot oil; sprinkle a few drops of pale melted meat glaze, a little lemon-juice, and a pinch of concassed parsley over the sole, and cover the whole with slightly-browned butter.

Serve instantly.

Sole à la Provençale

Poach the sole in one-sixth pint of fish fumet, two tablespoonfuls of oil and a piece, the size of a pea, of garlic, well crushed. Drain and dish the sole. Coat it with Provençale sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor, and sprinkle a little concassed parsley over it.

Surround the sole with four little tomatoes and four medium-sized mushrooms stuffed with duxelles flavoured with a mite of garlic; these latter should be put in the oven just in time for them to be ready at the dishing up of the fish.

Sole Arlésienne

Poach the sole in a little fish fumet. Dish it, reduce the fumet, and add thereto the following garnish:—Cook a little chopped onion in butter, add two medium-sized, peeled, emptied, and concassed tomatoes, a bit of garlic, and some concassed parsley. Cook with lid on, add the reduced fumet and twelve pieces of vegetable-marrow, turned to the shape of olives and cooked in butter.

Cover the sole with this garnish and set a little heap of fried onion at each end of the dish.

Sole à la Royale

Poach the sole in a few tablespoonfuls of fish fumet and two-thirds oz. of butter cut into small lumps. Dish the sole and set upon it four small cooked mushrooms, four small quenelles of fish forcemeat, four crayfishes’ tails, and four slices of truffle.

Surround the sole with potato-balls, raised by means of the round spoon-cutter and cooked à l’anglaise, and coat the sole and garnish with Normande sauce.

Sole à la Russe

Prepare twelve grooved and very thin roundels of carrots, cut a small onion into fine slices. Put these vegetables into and cut a small onion into fine slices. Put these vegetables into one-seventh pint of white wine, and one-third pint of fish fumet. Cook and, in the process, reduce the moistening by half, and pour this preparation into a deep dish.

Partly separate the fillets from the bones on the upper side of the sole, slip a piece of butter, the size of a walnut, under each fillet, and put the fish into a deep dish containing the preparation. Poach and baste frequently the while.

As soon as it is poached, dish the sole, also the vegetables used in cooking, and keep the whole hot.

Reduce the cooking-liquor to one-eighth pint, add a few drops of lemon juice, and finish it away from the fire with one and one-half oz. of butter. Coat the sole and the garnish with this sauce.

Sole Richelieu

Prepare the sole exactly as directed under “Sole à la Colbert” (formula №822). When it is fried, remove the bones and dish it. Garnish the inside with butter à la maître-d’hôtel, and lay thereon a row of sliced truffles.

Sole Normande

Poach the sole on a buttered dish with one-sixth pint of fish fumet, and the same quantity of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms. Drain and dish the sole, and surround it with mussels, poached oysters (cleared of their beards), shrimps’ tails, and small cooked mushrooms. Put the sole in the oven for a few minutes, tilt the dish in order to get rid of all liquid, and coat the sole and the garnish with Normande sauce. Make a little garland of pale meat glaze on the sauce, and finish the garnish with the following articles:—Six fine slices of truffle set in a row upon the sole; six small crusts in the shape of lozenges, fried in clarified butter and arranged round the truffles; four gudgeons treated à l’anglaise and fried at the last moment; and four medium-sized trussed crayfish cooked in court-bouillon.

Set the gudgeons and the crayfish round the dish.

Sole Marguery

Poach the sole in white wine and fish fumet in the proportions already given.

Drain and dish the sole, and surround it with a border of mussels and shrimps’ tails. Coat the sole and the garnish with white wine sauce, well finished with butter, and set to glaze quickly.

Sole Marinière

Liberally butter a dish, sprinkle a coffee-spoonful of chopped shallots on the bottom, lay the sole thereon, and poach the latter with one-sixth pint of white wine and the same quantity of the very clear cooking-liquor of mussels. Drain and dish the sole, surround it with mussels (cleared of their beards), and keep it hot.

Reduce the cooking-liquor to half; thicken with a tablespoonful of velouté, and the yolks of two eggs, and finish it, away from the fire, with two and one-half oz. of butter and a pinch of chopped parsley.

Tilt the dish so as to rid it of the liquid accumulated on the bottom, coat the sole and the garnish with the prepared sauce, and glaze quickly.

Sole au Vin Blanc

Partly separate the fillets from the bones on the upper side of the sole, and slip a piece of butter, as large as a walnut, under each fillet. Lay the sole in a dish, the bottom of which should be buttered and garnished with a small onion, chopped. Moisten with one-quarter pint of ordinary white wine, as much fish fumet, and a few tablespoonfuls of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms. Poach gently with lid on.

Drain and dish the sole, and coat it with a white wine sauce, prepared in accordance with one of the methods given in the chapter on Sauces (formula №111). Glaze quickly, or serve without glazing.

N.B.—“Sole au Vin Blanc” may be prepared after the above recipe, but ordinary white wine may be replaced by one of the Rhine wines or Moselle, by some Johannisberg, or by a good white Burgundy or Bordeaux wine, such as Chablis-Moutonne, Savigny, Montrachet, Barsac, Sauternes, and even Château-Yquem or Château-Latour.

In any of these cases the name of the wine may be mentioned, and on the menu may be written Sole au Barsac, Sole au Chateau-Yquem, &c.

Sole Dieppoise

Poach the sole with one-sixth pint of fish fumet and a few tablespoonfuls of the cooking-liquor of mussels.

Drain and dish the sole, surround it with poached mussels (shelled and cleared of their beards) and shrimps’ tails, and coat the fish and the garnish with a white wine sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor.

Sole Diplomate

Poach the sole in very clear fish fumet.

Drain it, dish it, and coat it with Diplomate sauce.

Set upon it a row of six fine slices of black truffle; these should have been previously glazed with pale meat glaze.

Sole Bonne Femme

Butter the bottom of the dish intended for the sole, and besprinkle it with two chopped shallots, one pinch of parsley, and one and one-half oz. of raw minced mushrooms. Lay the sole upon this garnish, moisten with one-quarter pint of white wine and as much fish fumet, and poach gently, taking care to baste from time to time.

When the sole is poached, drain off the cooking-liquor into a vegetable-pan, and reduce it quickly to half; effect the leason with two tablespoonfuls of fish velouté, and finish the sauce with two oz. of butter. Coat the sole with this sauce and set it to glaze in a fierce oven or at a salamander.

Sole Parisienne

Poach the sole in white wine, the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and some butter. Drain it thoroughly, dish it, and coat it with white wine sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor of the sole. Garnish with a row of six slices of truffle and six fine roundels of cooked mushrooms kept very white, and finish with four medium-sized trussed crayfish.

Sole Nantua

Poach the sole in one-sixth pint of fish fumet and a few tablespoonfuls of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms.

Drain and dish the sole, surround it with twelve shelled crayfishes’ tails, and coat it with Nantua sauce.

Lay a row of very black truffle slices along the middle of the fish.

Fillets of Sole

Subject to the kind of dish required, fillets of sole are either kept in their natural state, they are stuffed and folded over, or they are simply folded over without being stuffed, each of which methods of preparation will be specially referred to in the recipes.

Whatever be the method adopted, always skin the fillets thoroughly; i.e., remove the thin membrane which lies beneath the skin, the tendency of which, during the cooking process, is to shrink and thereby disfigure the fillet.

This done, flatten out the fillets with the broad side of a wet knife, and trim them slightly if necessary. The poaching of fillets of sole must be effected without allowing the cooking-liquor to boil, the object being to prevent the pieces losing their shape. Fillets should also be kept very white.

In cases where the exact amount of the poaching-liquor is not given, allow one-quarter pint to every four fillets, i.e., to every sole.

Fillets de Sole Américaine

Arrange the folded fillets in a deep, buttered dish, and poach them in fish fumet.

Drain, and dish them in the form of an oval, letting them overlap one another with their tail-ends hidden. Garnish the centre of the dish with slices of lobster prepared à l’américaine (formula №939), and coat the whole with the lobster’s sauce.

Fillets de Sole Anglaise

Treat the fillets à l’anglaise with fresh and fine bread-crumbs. Pat the bread-crumbs over the egg with the flat of a knife, that the two may be well combined; and, with the back of a knife, criss-cross the coating of the fillets.

Cook them gently in clarified butter. Serve on a hot dish, and sprinkle the fillets with half-melted “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”.

Fillets de Soles Andalouse

Coat the upper sides of the fillets with fish forcemeat combined, per pound, with three oz. of chopped capsicum. Roll them up, after the manner of a scroll (see formula №914), and smooth the forcemeat on the top. Poach the fillets in butter and fish fumet.

The following should have been prepared beforehand:—

As many small half-tomatoes, stewed in butter and garnished by means of risotto with capsicums, as there are fillets of sole;
the same number of roundels of egg-plant, seasoned, dredged, and fried in oil.

When dishing, arrange the roundels of egg-plant round the dish; place a stuffed tomato on each roundel of egg-plant, and a poached fillet of sole upon each tomato. Sprinkle with lightly-browned butter, and serve at once.

Fillets de Soles Caprice

Dip the fillets in melted, seasoned butter, and then roll them in fresh and fine bread-crumbs. Pat the bread-crumbs with the flat of the knife, and with the back of the same instrument criss-cross the surface of the fillets. Sprinkle with melted butter, and set to grill gently, taking care that the coating of bread-crumbs acquires a nice, light-brown colour.

Lay each grilled fillet on the half of a peeled banana, cooked in butter, arid send to the table, separately, a Escoffier Roberts Sauce, finished with butter.

Fillets de Soles Catalane

Poach, in the oven, as many emptied and seasoned half-tomatoes as there are fillets of sole. Cook some very finely-minced onion in oil, without letting it acquire any colour, and allow one tablespoonful of the onion to each half-tomato.

Fold the fillets of sole, and poach them in fish fumet just a few minutes before dishing them. Garnish the half-tomatoes with onion; arrange them in a circle on a dish, and place a fillet of sole upon each. Quickly reduce the cooking-liquor of the fillets, and finish it with butter in the proportion of one oz. per one-eighth pint of reduced fumet.

Coat the fillets and set to glaze quickly.

Fillets de Soles Clarence

Fold the fillets, and poach them in fish fumet.

They may be dished after the two following methods:—

Put a preparation of Duchesse potatoes in a piping-bay fitted with a large, grooved pipe, and describe therewith an ornamental design containing as many divisions as there are fillets of sole. Lightly gild and brown in the oven. This design, consisting of scroll-work, should be prepared before poaching the fillets. Lay a fillet in each division of the design, and coat with American sauce, prepared with curry and combined with the meat of the lobster (cut into small dice) which has served in the preparation of the sauce. Take care that no sauce touches the scroll-work, which should remain well-defined.
Bake some large potatoes in the oven. Open them; remove their pulp, and put into each baked shell a tablespoonful of American sauce au currie referred to above. Add a poached fillet of sole; coat with American sauce; dish these garnished potatoes on a napkin, and serve very hot.

Fillets de Soles aux Champignons

Stew two oz. of small mushrooms in butter. Fold the fillets, and poach them in one-sixth pint of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and a piece of butter the size of a walnut. Arrange the fillets in an oval, and garnish the centre of the dish with the stewed mushrooms.

Reduce the cooking-liquor of the fillets to one-third; add thereto two tablespoonfuls of velouté; finish the sauce with one oz. of butter, and coat the fillets and the garnish.

Fillets de Soles aux Crevettes

Fold the fillets, and poach them in fish fumet.

Dish them in an oval; garnish the middle with one oz. of shrimps’ tails, kept very hot, and coat the fillets and the garnish with shrimp sauce.

Fillets de Soles Chauchat

Poach the fillets of sole, folded, in butter and lemon juice.

Coat the bottom of a dish with Mornay sauce, and set the fillets of sole thereon in the form of an oval. Surround the fish with roundels of cooked potatoes turned to the shape of corks.

Cover the fillets and the garnish with Mornay sauce, and glaze quickly in a fierce oven or at the salamander.

Fillets de Soles Bercy

Butter the bottom of the dish intended for the soles, and sprinkle it with two finely-chopped shallots. Lay the fillets lengthwise upon the dish, side by side; moisten with three tablespoonfuls of white wine and as much fish fumet, and add one-half oz. of butter cut into small pieces.

Cook in the oven, basting frequently the while, and glaze at the last minute. Besprinkle with a few drops of lemon juice, and when about to serve drop a pinch of chopped parsley upon each fillet.

Or, poach the fillets with chopped shallots, and increase the moistening. As soon as the fillets are ready, drain off their cooking-liquor into a vegetable-pan; reduce it speedily to one-third, and add a few drops of meat glaze, a little lemon juice, one-half oz. of butter, and one pinch of chopped parsley.

Coat the fillets, and set to glaze quickly.

N.B.—Sole à la Bercy may be prepared after either of the two methods.

Fillets de Soles Dejazet

Treat the fillets of sole à l’anglaise and grill them as explained under formula №860.

Dish them, cover them thinly with half-melted tarragon butter, and deck each fillet with five or six parboiled, tarragon leaves.

Fillets de Soles Grand Duc

Fold the fillets of soles over, and poach them in fish fumet and the cooking-liquor of mushrooms. Arrange them in an oval on a dish, with their tails pointing inwards; place a fine slice of truffle in the middle of each fillet, and between each of the latter three shelled crayfishes’ tails.

Coat with Mornay sauce, and set to glaze quickly.

When taking the dish from the oven, set in its centre a fine heap of very green asparagus-heads, cohered with butter at the moment of dishing.

Fillets de Soles Joinville

Select some fine fillets of soles; fold them, and poach them in the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and butter, taking care to keep them very white. Arrange them in an oval, with their tails pointing upwards and the carapace of a crayfish fixed on each fillet; and garnish the middle of the dish with a salpicon or a short julienne, consisting of one and one-half oz. of cooked mushrooms, one-half oz. of truffle, and one and one-half oz. of shrimps’ tails cohered by means of a few tablespoonfuls of Joinville sauce. Coat the fillets and the garnish with the same sauce, and deck each fillet with a fine slice of truffle coated with meat glaze.

They may also be served after the old-fashioned way, as follows:—

Set the garnish in the middle of the dish, shaping it like a dome; coat it with Joinville sauce, and surround it with the fillets of sole, which should slightly overlap one another and have their tails uppermost. Fix a carapace of crayfish on the tail of each fillet, and deck each with a slice of very black truffle.

With this method of dishing, the garnish alone is coated with sauce, the fillets thus forming a white, encircling border.

Fillets de Soles Judic

Fold, and poach the fillets in butter and lemon juice.

Arrange them in an oval round a dish, laying each upon a nice little braised and trimmed half lettuce, and place upon each fillet a quenelle of sole mousseline-forcemeat in the shape of a flattened oval, poached at the time of dishing up.

Coat with Mornay sauce and glaze quickly. When taking the dish out of the oven, encircle the fillets of sole with a thread of buttered meat glaze.

Fillets de Soles à la Hongroise

Fry in butter, without colouration, one small tablespoonful of chopped onion seasoned with a very little paprika; moisten with three tablespoonfuls of white wine and one-sixth pint of fish fumet; add two small peeled, pressed, and roughly-chopped tomatoes, and set to cook for seven or eight minutes.

Fold the fillets of sole; lay them on a buttered dish; pour the above preparation thereon, and poach them. Arrange them in a circle on a dish; reduce their cooking-liquor to a stiff consistence; add a few tablespoonfuls of cream and a few drops of lemon juice, and coat the fillets with this sauce.

Fillets de Soles Lady Egmont

Fold the fillets, and poach them in a few tablespoonfuls of excellent fish fumet.

Also for every four fillets (i.e., per sole) finely mince one oz. of well-cleaned mushrooms, and cook them quickly in butter, lemon juice, a little salt, and pepper. This done, add the cooking-liquor to the fish fumet, and keep the cooked minced mushrooms hot.

Reduce the combined cooking-liquor and fish fumet to half add thereto one oz. of butter and two tablespoonfuls of cream and to the resulting sauce add the reserved minced mushrooms and two tablespoonfuls of freshly-cooked and well-drained asparagus-heads, uncooled.

Serve the fillets of sole on an earthenware dish, coat them with the above garnish, and set to glaze quickly in a fierce oven or at the salamander.

Fillets de Soles Marinette

Poach a sole in fish fumet and the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and drain it on a napkin. When it is still lukewarm, carefully raise its fillets and trim them.

Break an egg into a bowl; beat it well, and add enough grated Gruyère and Parmesan to it (mixed in equal quantities) to produce a dense paste. Mix a dessertspoonful of cold Béchamel sauce with this paste; add salt and cayenne pepper; spread an even thickness of one inch of it over two of the fillets of sole; lay thereon the two remaining fillets, and put aside in the cool.

When the egg and cheese paste is very stiff, dip the fillets in a Villeroy sauce, and leave the latter to cool. Then treat the stuffed and sauced fillets à l’anglaise, and fry them, just before serving, in very hot fat.

Dish on a napkin with very green parsley all round.

Fillets de Soles Marie Stuart

Fold the fillets, and poach them in fish fumet. Arrange them in an oval on a dish; coat them with the sauce given under “Filets de soles à la New-burg” (formula №890), and place on each fillet a quenelle of fish forcemeat in the shape of a quoit and decked with a slice of truffle. These quenelles should, if possible, be poached just before dishing up, and well drained before being laid on the fillets of sole.

Fillets de Soles Mignonette

Cook the fillets in butter, and set them in a hot timbale.

Surround them with potato-balls the size of peas, raised by means of the round spoon-cutter, and cooked beforehand in butter.

Lay upon the fillets eight or ten slices of fresh truffle heated in one-sixth pint of very light meat glaze.

Lay upon the fillets eight or ten slices of fresh truffle heated in one-sixth pint of very light meat glaze.

Fillets de Soles Mimi

Divide a live lobster into two, lengthwise, and prepare it à l’américaine, taking care to keep the sauce short.

When the lobster is cooked, take the meat from the tail; put it into as many slices as there are fillets of sole, and keep them hot.

Remove all the meat from the claws, and that remaining in the carcass; pound all of it smoothly, add two tablespoonfuls of cream, and rub through a fine sieve. Prepare a garnish of spaghetti with cream, and add thereto the purée of lobster.

Fold the fillets of sole, and poach them in Chablis wine and butter. All this being done, lay the two emptied halves of the lobster on a napkin lying on a dish, setting them back to back. Fill these lobster shells to the brim with the prepared garnish of spaghetti. Upon this garnish lay the poached fillets of sole, sandwiching a slice of lobster between every two; besprinkle the whole with a short and fine julienne of very black truffle.

Send the lobster sauce, finished with a few tablespoonfuls of cream, to the table separately. Proceed as quickly as possible with the dishing up, in order that the dish may reach the table very hot.

Fillets de Soles Mexicaine

Coat the fillets with fish forcemeat, and roll them to resemble scrolls (see formula №914). Poach them in fish fumet as directed for the paupiettes. Lay each rolled fillet in a grilled mushroom garnished with one-half tablespoonful of peeled, pressed, and concassed tomato cooked in butter, and arrange them in an oval on a dish.

Coat them with Béchamel sauce combined with a purée of tomatoes and capsicums cut into small dice, in the proportion of two tablespoonfuls of the purée and two-thirds oz. of the capsicums per pint of the sauce.

Fillets de Soles Mirabeau

Poach the fillets, left in their natural state, in fish fumet.

Dish them and coat with white wine and Genèvoise sauces, alternating the two, white and brown. Lay a thin strip of anchovy fillet between each of the fillets of sole; deck those of the latter coated with white sauce with a slice of truffle, and those coated with brown sauce with a star of blanched tarragon leaves.

Fillets de Soles Miramar

Divide each of the fillets into slices; season them and cook them in butter. Cut fifteen roundels (one-third inch thick) of egg-plant; season, dredge, and toss them in butter, taking care to keep them very crisp.

Take a timbale of suitable size, and line its sides with a layer (three-quarters inch thick) of pilaff rice.

Put the roundels of egg-plant and the sliced fillets of sole (mixed and tossed together for a moment) in the middle of the dish.

Just before serving, sprinkle with one oz. of lightly-browned butter.

Fillets de Soles aux Huîtres

Open and poach twelve oysters. Poach the fillets of sole, folded, in the oyster liquor strained through linen, and a piece of butter as large as a walnut.

Arrange in an oval on a dish; garnish the centre with the poached oysters (cleared of their beards), and coat the fillets of sole and the oysters with Normande sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor of the fillets.

Fillets de Soles Nelson

Fold the fillets, and poach them in fish fumet.

Arrange them in a circle on a dish; coat them with white wine sauce, and glaze quickly.

Garnish the centre of the dish with a pyramid of potato-balls cooked in butter and of a light-brown colour. Surround the fillets with poached milt.

Fillets de Soles New-burg

Prepare a lobster à la New-burg, in accordance with one of the recipes given (formula №948 and formula №949). Cut the tail into as many slices as there are fillets of sole, and keep them hot.

Cut the remainder of the lobster meat into dice, and add these to the sauce. Fold the fillets of sole, and poach them in fish fumet. Arrange them in an oval on a dish; lay a slice of lobster upon each fillet, and coat with the lobster-sauce combined with the dice, prepared as directed above.

Fillets de Soles Orientale

Prepare the fillets exactly as those à la New-burg, but season the sauce with curry.

Having dished and sauced the fillets, set a pyramid of “Rice à l’Indienne” (formula №2254) in the middle of the dish, or send the rice to the table separately, in a timbale; either way will be found to answer.

Fillets de Soles Persane

Prepare the fillets as in the case of those à la New-burg, but season the sauce with Paprika, and add thereto one oz. of capsicums cut into large dice. Send some “Riz Pilaff à la Turque” to the table separately.

Fillets de Soles Orly

Season the fillets; dip them into batter and, a few minutes before serving, put them into very hot fat. Drain them; dish them on a napkin with fried parsley, and serve a tomato sauce separately.

N.B.—There are several ways of preparing these fillets of sole. Thus they may be simply dipped in milk, dredged, and impaled on a hatelet. They may also be marinaded, treated à l’anglaise, and twisted into cork-screw shape.

Always, however, dish them on a napkin with fried parsley and, in every case, send a tomato sauce to the table separately.

This last accompaniment is essential.

Fillets de Soles Olga, otherwise “Otero”

Bake beforehand, in the oven, as many fine, well-washed potatoes as there are fillets of sole. As soon as they are done, remove a piece of the baked shell, and withdraw the pulp in such wise as to leave nothing but the long, parched shells. Fold the fillets, and poach them with a little excellent fish fumet. Garnish the bottom of each prepared shell with a tablespoonful of shelled shrimps’ tails, cohered with a white wine sauce.

Put a poached fillet of sole upon this garnish; cover with sufficient Mornay sauce to completely fill the shell; sprinkle with grated cheese, and glaze quickly. Dish on a napkin the moment the fillets have been taken from the oven, and serve immediately.

Fillets de Soles Polignac

Fold the fillets, and poach them in one-quarter pint of white wine, a few tablespoonfuls of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and a piece of butter about the size of a walnut.

Dish the fillets in an oval. Reduce the cooking-liquor to half; thicken it by means of two tablespoonfuls, bare, of fish velouté; finish the sauce with one oz. of butter, and add thereto three small, cooked, finely-minced mushrooms, and one tablespoonful of a julienne of truffles.

Coat the fillets with sauce, and set to glaze.

Fillets de Soles Paysanne

For the fillets of soles, cut two small carrots, two new onions, a stick of celery, and the white of one leek in paysanne fashion. Season these vegetables with a very little table-salt and a pinch of sugar; stew them in butter; moisten sufficiently to cover them with lukewarm water; and add a few pieces of broccoli, a tablespoonful of peas, and the same quantity of French beans cut into lozenges.

Complete the cooking of the vegetables while reducing the cooking-liquor. Season the fillets of sole, and lay them on a buttered earthenware dish. Pour thereon the garnish of vegetables; put the cover on the dish, and gently poach the fillets.

When they are cooked, tilt the dish so as to pour all the liquor away into a vegetable-pan; this done, reduce the liquor to one-fifth pint, and add to it three oz. of butter.

Pour this sauce into the dish containing the fillets and the vegetable garnish, and serve immediately.

Fillets de Soles en Pilaw à la Levantine

Cut the fillets into collops, and toss these in butter. Prepare some pilaff rice after the usual recipe (formula №2255), and add thereto one oz. of capsicum cut into dice.

Also toss in butter one and one-half oz. of egg-plant, cut into dice and seasoned, and put these with the fillets of sole. Mould the rice into a border round the dish; put the fillets and the egg-plant in the middle, and coat the two with curry sauce without letting the latter touch the rice.

N.B.—N.B.—In the case of pilaff rice with fillets of sole, the rice should border the dish, and the fillets of sole, tossed in butter, should be laid in the middle and coated with brown butter.

Fillets de Soles Pompadour

Treat the fillets with butter and bread-crumbs, and grill them. Garnish them all round with a thread of very firm béarnaise tomatée. Dish and surround them with a border of Château potatoes (formula №2208).

Lay a fine slice of truffle, moistened with melted meat glaze, on each fillet.

Fillets de Soles Rachel

Coat the fillets with some delicate fish forcemeat; put four slices of truffle on the forcemeat of each of the fillets; fold the latter, and poach them in one-sixth pint of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, and a piece of butter the size of a walnut, cut into small pieces.

Arrange the fillets in an oval on a dish, and coat them with white-wine sauce combined with one tablespoonful of freshly-cooked and uncooled asparagus-heads, and one tablespoonful of truffle in dice per every one-half pint of the sauce.

Fillets de Soles Venitienne

Fold the fillets, and poach them in fish fumet.

Arrange them in a circle on a dish, alternating them with thin crusts, in the shape of hearts, fried in butter. Coat with Venetian sauce combined with the reduced cooking-liquor of the fillets.

Fillets de Soles Verdi

Prepare a garnish of macaroni cut into dice; cohere this with cream and grated Gruyère and Parmesan, and add three oz. of lobster meat and one and one-half oz. of truffles in dice per every one-half lb. of the macaroni.

Poach the fillets of sole in fish fumet, keeping the fillets in their natural state. Lay the macaroni very evenly on the dish set the poached fillets of sole upon it; coat with Mornay sauce, and set to glaze quickly.

Fillets de Soles Victoria

Fold the fillets, and poach them in fish fumet.

Arrange them in an oval on a dish, and garnish the centre with three oz. of the meat from the tail of the spiny lobster, and one oz. of truffle in dice per every four fillets.

Coat the fillets and the garnish with Victoria sauce, and set to glaze quickly.

Fillets de Soles Véronique

Raise the fillets of a fine sole; beat them slightly; fold and season them, and put them in a special earthenware, buttered dish.

With the bones, some of the trimmings of the fish, a little minced onion, some parsley stalks, a few drops of lemon juice, and white wine and water, prepare two spoonfuls of fumet.

This done, strain it over the fillets, and poach them gently.

Drain them carefully; reduce the fumet to the consistence of a syrup, and finish it with one and one-half oz. of butter. Arrange the fillets in an oval on the dish whereon they have been poached; cover them with the buttered fumet, and set to glaze quickly. When about to serve, set a pyramid of skinned and very cold muscadel grapes in the middle of the dish.

Put a cover on the dish, and serve immediately.

Fillets de Soles Walewska

Poach the fillets in fish fumet, keeping them in their natural state.

Dish, and surround them with three langoustines’ tails cut into two lengthwise, and stewed in butter (with lid on) with six fine slices of raw truffle.

Coat with a delicate Mornay sauce, and set to glaze quickly.

N.B.—Mornay sauce may, according to circumstances, be combined with one and one-half oz. of langoustine butter per pint.

Fillets de Soles Wilhelmine

Prepare some potato shells as directed under “Filets de soles Olga” (formula №894). Garnish them with a tablespoonful of cucumber with cream; put a fillet of sole into each garnished shell, a fine Zeeland oyster on each fillet, and cover with Mornay sauce.

Set to glaze quickly, and dish on a napkin.

Various Preparations of Soles and Fillets of Sole

Mousselines de Soles

The directions given under “Mousselines de Saumon” (formula №797) apply in all circumstances to Mousselines of Sole. I shall therefore refrain from repeating the recipe, since, the quantities remaining the same, all that is needed is the substitution of the meat of sole for that of salmon. Thus, I shall only state here, by way of reminding the reader, that these excellent preparations admit of all the fish sauces and garnishes, and that they may also be accompanied by all purées of fresh vegetables.

Turban de Filets de Soles à la Villaret

Raise the fillets of three soles; flatten them slightly with a moistened beater, and trim them very straight on either side.

Liberally butter a medium-sized savarin-mould. Lay the fillets aslant in this mould, with their tail-ends over-reaching its inner edge and their other ends projecting over its outer edge; slip a fine slice of truffle between each, and let them slightly overlap one another.

When the mould is completely lined with the fillets of sole, fill it up with lobster mousseline forcemeat. Gently tap the mould on a folded napkin lying on the table, with the object of settling the forcemeat, and then draw the overhanging ends of the fillets across the latter.

Set to poach in a bain-marie in a moderate oven.

This done, take the mould out of the bain-marie; let it stand for a few minutes, and then turn it upside-down upon the dish. Leave it to drain; soak up the liquid that has leaked out on to the dish; take off the mould, and moisten the surface of the fillets by means of a small brush dipped in melted butter. The object of this last measure is to glaze the fish and to remove therefrom the froth resulting from its poached albumen.

Now garnish the centre of the moulding with shrimps’ tails, mushrooms, poached milt, and slices of truffle, the whole cohered by means of Béchamel sauce finished with lobster butter.

Send a sauceboat of Béchamel sauce, finished with lobster butter, to the table at the same time as the fish.

Turban de Filets de Soles et Saumon Villaret

Proceed as in the preceding recipe, but alternate the fillets of sole with very red slices of salmon of the same size as the fillets.

The combination yields an excellent result, and the varying strips of white and orange which constitute the body of the moulded crown lend sightliness to the dish.

N.B.—The designation “à la Villaret”, relating to the crown alone, in no wise affects the constituents of the garnish; these may either remain the same as those of the preceding recipe, or may be replaced by something similar. The sauce alone remains unalterable, and this should be a good Béchamel finished with lobster butter.

Turban de Filets de Soles Cardinal

For ten people, prepare a timbale crust (formula №2394) the diameter of which should be greater than the height; line it with fine, short paste, and decorate it with noodle paste.

Raise the fillets of three medium-sized soles, flatten them slightly; coat them with whiting forcemeat prepared with crayfish butter, and roll them into scroll-form. Also prepare ten small slices of the meat of a medium-sized ordinary or spiny lobster’s tail, ten small grooved and cooked mushrooms, fifteen slices of truffle, and three-quarters pint of Cardinal sauce finished with a lobster butter.

When about to serve, lay the poached, rolled fillets of sole (well drained) in a circle round the bottom of the timbale; put the slices of lobster and the mushrooms in the centre, and cover the whole with Cardinal sauce.

Set upon the sauce, just over the centre of the timbale, a large, grooved mushroom (cooked and kept very white), and encircle the latter with fifteen slices of truffle.

Place the timbale, thus garnished, on a folded napkin lying on a dish, and serve at once.

Turban de Filets de Soles Carmélite

Prepare

a timbale crust as above;
a lobster à la New-burg made from raw lobster (formula №948);
twelve rolled fillets of sole stuffed with fish forcemeat finished with lobster butter;
three oz. of sliced truffles.

Poach the rolled fillets in fish fumet; slice the meat of the lobster’s tail, and put the poached fillets, the slices of lobster, and the slices of truffle into the lobster sauce. Heat the whole well, without boiling; pour the sauce and garnish into the timbale crust, and deck the top with twelve fine slices of truffle.

Dish the timbale on a folded napkin, and serve instantly.

Turban de Filets de Soles Grimaldi

Prepare:—

A rather deep timbale crust, and decorate it with noodle paste.
Cook, as for bisque, twenty-four small langoustines; wrench off their tails; cut them into two lengthwise, and keep them hot in butter.
Finely pound the langoustines’ carapaces, and add thereto one-third pint of fine Béchamel. Rub through a fine sieve first, and then through tammy. Put the resulting cullis into a saucepan, and heat without boiling it; intensify the seasoning; add a few tablespoonfuls of cream, little by little; put the prepared tails in the cullis, and keep the latter in the bain-marie.
Cut four oz. of blanched and somewhat stiff macaroni into pieces, and add thereto one-sixth pint of cream and three oz. of sliced truffle. Heat until the macaroni has completely absorbed the cream thicken with one-sixth pint of Béchamel sauce finished with fish fumet; add one and one-half oz. of butter cut into small lumps, and keep hot.
Coat sixteen fillets of sole with truffled fish forcemeat; roll the fillets into scroll-form, and, at the last minute, poach them in fish fumet.

To garnish the timbale, spread a layer of macaroni on the bottom thereof, lay half of the rolled fillets upon the macaroni, and cover these with half of the langoustines’ tails in the cullis.

Repeat the procedure, in the same order, with what is left of the garnishes, and finish the timbale with a layer of the langoustines’ tails.

Set the timbale on a folded napkin lying on a dish, and serve immediately.

Turban de Filets de Soles Carême

Flatten the fillets of three medium-sized soles, and trim them neatly.

Liberally butter a pound-cake mould, and line it with the fillets, placing them side by side with their tails lying round the centre of the bottom of the mould, and their opposite ends projecting above the brim. Press them well, that they may take the shape of the mould.

Completely coat the fillets with a layer, one-half inch thick, of fish forcemeat.

Put the mould in the front of the oven for a few minutes in order to poach the forcemeat, which, in adhering to the fillets, gives the required firmness to the timbale.

When the forcemeat has been poached and is stiff, withdraw the timbale from the oven, and cut off the pieces of fillet that project above the edges of the mould. Fill the timbale to within one-third inch of its brim with a garnish of shrimps and poached oysters and mussels, small button-mushrooms, and slices of truffle, all of which should be cohered with a thick and highly-seasoned Béchamel sauce. Cover this garnish with the projecting pieces of fillets, already cut off, and close the timbale by means of a thin layer of that forcemeat which served in coating the fillets. Poach for thirty minutes in a bain-marie and in a moderate oven. After taking the timbale out of the bain-marie, let it stand for a few minutes; overturn it on a round dish; take off the mould; deck it on top with a garland consisting of six little paupiettes of salmon, each stuffed with a crayfish tail, and surmounted by an encrusted crayfish carapace.

Serve a Nantua sauce separately.

Turban de Filets de Soles Marquise

For a timbale large enough for ten people, prepare:—

An even or fluted timbale crust.
A garnish consisting of twelve rolled or folded fillets of sole poached in fish fumet, twelve poached oysters (cleared of their beards), twenty-four small quenelles of salmon, and twenty slices of truffle.

Heat this garnish after having added a few drops of fish fumet to it, and then thicken it with one-half pint of white-wine sauce prepared with paprika.

Put the above garnish into the timbale, which should be very hot; set the latter on a folded napkin, and serve at once.

The preparation of Paupiettes of Fillets of Sole Salmon, &c.

The paupiettes (or fillets rolled after the manner of a scroll) are served either as entrées like fillets of sole, of which they are but a special kind, or as a garnish. For the second purpose, not only should they be smaller than for the first, but very small fillets are generally selected for the preparation of the paupiettes.

In order to make paupiettes, first remove the horny film from the outside surfaces of the fillets, and then slightly flatten the latter with the blade of a large knife; trim them on both sides, and coat them on their flayed side with a thin layer of fish forcemeat, truffled or not, in accordance with the requirements.

Now roll them into scroll-form; smooth the forcemeat that projects from the top end, and the paupiettes are done.

Stand them upright in a buttered sautépan to poach, and take care to place them snugly together lest they lose their shape while the operation is in progress. Moisten them with sufficient fish fumet (formula №11) to cover them; poach them in a moderate oven, and remember, as in the case of fillets of sole, not to let the poaching-liquor boil.

All the garnishes and sauces suited to fillets of sole likewise obtain with paupiettes, provided the difference in their shape be taken into account when dishing up.

For salmon paupiettes, cut slices two-thirds inch wide, one-half inch thick, and the length of a fillet of sole, from a skinned fillet of salmon. In view of the unusual fragility of salmon’s flesh, the slices of fillets should be carefully flattened in order to give them the width and thickness of a fillet of sole. This done, spread forcemeat on them, and roll them as explained above.

Soles and Fillets of Sole (Cold)

Aspic de Filets de Soles

An essential point in the making of an aspic is the clearness of the fish jelly. For a sole aspic, take some white fish aspic, which is at once succulent, limpid, and just sufficiently viscous to allow of its being turned out of a mould without breaking.

For the purpose under consideration, moulds with plain or decorated borders are generally used, and there are two modes of procedure:—

For a mould capable of holding one quart, fold twelve small fillets of sole and poach them in butter and lemon juice, taking care to keep them very white. This done, set them to cool under a light weight.

Pour a few tablespoonfuls of melted fish jelly into the mould, which should be lying amidst broken ice. As soon as the jelly begins to set, decorate it tastefully with pieces (lozenges, crescents, &c.) of very black truffle and the poached white of an egg. Capers, tarragon leaves, thin roundels of small radishes, &c., may also be used for the purpose of decoration.

When this part of the procedure has been satisfactorily effected, sprinkle a few drops of the same jelly over the decorating particles, in order to fix them and prevent their shifting during the subsequent stages of the process. Now add enough melted jelly to cover the bottom of the mould with a layer one inch thick, and leave this to set.

On this set jelly, arrange the six fillets of sole; let their tailends overlap, and cover them with jelly. Continue adding coat upon coat of jelly until the thickness covering the fillets measures about one-half inch.

Now arrange the remaining fillets in the reverse order, and fill up the mould with cold, melted jelly. Leave to cool for one hour.

When about to serve, quickly dip the mould in a saucepan of hot water; wipe it, and turn out the aspic upon a folded napkin lying on a dish.

Another Method of Preparing Aspic de Filets de Soles

Coat ten fine fillets of sole with a thin layer of truffled fish forcemeat finished with crayfish butter, and roll them round a little rod of truffle, twice as thick as an ordinary penholder. Tie these paupiettes, once or twice round, with cotton; poach them very gently in fish fumet and cool them on ice. Take a border-mould, even if possible; pour therein a few tablespoonfuls of melted fish jelly, and then rock it about on broken ice, with the object of evenly coating it with a thin layer of the jelly.

This operation is technically called “clothing the mould”.

Decorate the bottom of the mould as explained above; fix the decorating particles, and cover them with a layer one-half inch thick of fish jelly.

After having properly trimmed the ends of the paupiettes, cut them into roundels one-half inch thick; set these upright against the sides of the mould, keeping them close together; add a few drops of melted jelly to fix the roundels, and as soon as this has set, add a further quantity, sufficient to completely cover them.

As soon as this jelly sets, repeat the operation with the paupiette roundels and the jelly, and do so again and again until the mould is filled. For turning out the aspic, proceed as directed above.

Bordure de Filets de Soles à l’Italienne

Line a border-mould with jelly; i.e., coat its bottom and sides with a thin layer of fish jelly, rocking it upon ice as already explained.

Now fill it, two-thirds full, with a garnish consisting of a julienne of cold, poached fillets of sole, a julienne of truffles (two oz. per two filleted soles), and a julienne of capsicum (one and one-half oz. per two filleted soles). Fill up the mould with melted fish jelly, and leave the latter to set.

When about to serve, turn out the mould upon a little, low cushion of rice, lying on a dish, and set an “Salade Italienne” in the centre.

Serve a Mayonnaise sauce with this dish.

Filets de Soles Calypso

Flatten the fillets, and roll them into paupiettes around little rods of wood two-thirds inch thick. Lay the paupiettes in a buttered sautépan, with their joined sides undermost, and poach them in very clear fish fumet and lemon juice, taking care to keep them very white.

Let them cool, and remove the pieces of wood, whereupon they will have the appearance of rings.

Take as many small tomatoes as there are paupiettes; cut them in two at a point two-thirds of their height below their stem-end; empty, and peel them. Set a paupiette, upright, in each tomato; fill the centre with crayfish mousse combined with crayfishes’ tails in dice; lay a round piece of milt (stamped out with a cutter, poached, and cold) on each, and, finally, the shelled tail of a crayfish on each roundel of milt.

Arrange the tomatoes in a circle round a dish; surround them with little triangles of white fish jelly, and garnish the centre of the dish with the same fish jelly, chopped.

Filets de Soles Charlotte

Fold the fillets; poach them in fish fumet, and let them cool.

Trim them; coat them with pink chaud-froid sauce; decorate each fillet by means of a rosette of chervil leaves, in the centre of which rests a bit of lobster coral, and glaze them with fish jelly.

Set them, tail end uppermost, against a mousse of milt with horse-radish, moulded in a narrow dome-mould, which should have been coated with fish jelly and besprinkled with chopped coral.

Surround with a border of regularly-cut jelly dice.

Filets de Soles à la Moscovite

Prepare

some paupiettes of filleted sole, in rings, as explained under “Filets de Soles à la Calypso” (formula №918);
as many round, fluted cases made from hollowed cucumber as there are paupiettes.

The cucumber cases should be well blanched and marinaded inside. Set each paupiette in a cucumber case garnish their centre with caviare, and arrange them in a circle on a dish.

Send a sauce Russe to the table, separately, at the same time as the dish.

Dominos de Filets de Soles

Select some fine, fleshy fillets; slightly flatten them; poach them in a little of the cooking-liquor of mushrooms, some lemon juice and butter, and set them to cool under a light weight. When the fillets are cold, trim them and cut them into regular rectangles the size of dominoes.

Coat the rectangles with a maigre, white chaud-froid sauce decorate them in imitation of dominoes, with little spots of truffle; glaze them with cold, melted fish jelly, and put them aside.

Pound the trimmings of the fish together with their weight of caviare, and rub the whole through a fine sieve. Add to this preparation half its weight of highly-coloured jelly, and leave it to set in a somewhat deep and moderately-oiled tray, the thickness of the preparation on the tray being not greater than that of a fillet of sole.

When the jelly is set, cut it into rectangles exactly the same size as the prepared dominoes, and then, by means of a little melted, cold jelly, fix the dominoes of sole to the rectangles just prepared.

Put some chopped jelly in the centre of the dish, and on this lay the dominoes in a muddled heap.

Filets de Soles Froids Dressés sur Mousses

What I pointed out above, I repeat here for the reader’s guidance—namely, that fillets of sole may be prepared after all the recipes given for trout (formula №813).

As the fillets of sole in this dish remain very conspicuous, it is advisable to keep them very white in the poaching. Set them to cool under a light weight, and decorate them in a way that will be in keeping with the mousse on which they are dished. This mousse is set on a special dish, as already explained, and the decorated fillets are laid upon it and covered with melted jelly.

For the variation of mousses, see the table given under formula №814.

Turbot

Turbot is generally served boiled, accompanied by freshly-cooked, floury potatoes, and the cases are exceptional when, cooked in this way, it is dished with any other garnish.

All fish sauces may be served with turbot. When, for the sake of variety, or in pursuance of the consumer’s wishes, turbot has to be braised or garnished, it is best to select a medium-sized fish, i.e., one weighing from eight to twelve lbs., thick, very fleshy, and white.

Unless expressly ordered, it is best to avoid surrounding the piece with its garnish. Preferably, send the latter to the table in a separate dish, as also the sauce. By this means the service is expedited, and, more important still, the fish is quite hot when it reaches the table. It is granted that the sight of a dish containing a fine, richly garnished and tastefully arranged piece is flattering to the host, but it would be a pity that the quality of the fish should thereby suffer, more particularly as the gourmet is not satisfied with sightliness alone.

I explained at the beginning of this chapter, under “Boiled Fish” (formulas №776 and №779), the details relating to this method of cooking, especially with regard to its application to turbot. For the braising and garnishing of turbot, the reader is begged to refer to the recipes concerned with chicken-turbot. These recipes may be applied to turbot, provided the difference in the size of the fish be taken into account in reference to the time allowed for braising and the quantities of the garnishing ingredients.

Cold Turbot

Whether whole or sliced, cold turbot makes an excellent dish, if the fish have not been cooked too long beforehand. It will be found that turbot, especially when sliced, tends to harden, crumple, and lose its flavour while cooling. It is therefore of the greatest importance that the fish should have just cooled after cooking, and that the cooking-liquor should have barely time to set; otherwise the evil effects of cooling, mentioned above, will surely ensue. When served, just cooled, with one of the cold sauces suited to fish, turbot can vie in delicacy even with such fish as salmon or trout, which are usually served cold.

Turbotins (Chicken-Turbots)

Turbotins (chicken-turbots) may rank among the most delicate and nicest of fish. Their varying sizes allow of their being served either for three, four, or ten, or twelve people; they are, moreover, tender and white, and they lend themselves to quite a vast number of culinary preparations.

They may be served boiled, like the turbot; grilled; à la Meunière; fried; au gratin, like the soles; or braised, like the salmon and the trout. They are most often served whole, garnished and with sauce; but, in order to simplify the process, they may be filleted, the fillets being poached and dished with a garnish and the selected sauce.

Whatever be the method of preparing the chicken-turbot, whether it be boiled, poached, or braised, the spine should always be cut in one or two places. The gash should be just in the middle of the back where the flesh is thickest, and the fillets on either side of the gash should be partly separated from the bone. The object of this measure is to prevent deformation during the cooking process and, also, to precipitate the latter.

Turbotin à l’Admiral

Gash the back of the fish, and partly separate the under fillets from the bones. Lay it on a grill, and moisten, sufficiently to cover it, with previously-cooked court-bouillon with Sauterne wine. As soon as the court-bouillon boils, allow the fish to cook ten or twelve minutes for every two lbs. of its weight.

This done, drain it; dish it, and coat it twice with melted, red butter.

Now surround it with the following garnish, which should be in proportion to the size of the fish, viz., little heaps of large mussels and oysters, prepared à la Villeroy, and fried at the time of dishing; small patties of crayfish tails; large mushroom-heads grooved and cooked, and slices of truffle.

Serve, separately,

a timbale of potatoes à l’anglaise;
Normande sauce, combined with one-sixth pint of reduced court-bouillon per quart of sauce, finished with crayfish butter and seasoned with cayenne.

Turbotin à l’Andalouse

Cut it in the region of the back; season it, and lay it in a deep earthenware dish of convenient size, liberally buttered. In the case of a chicken-turbot weighing two and one-half lbs., moisten with one-third pint of white wine and one-quarter pint of fish fumet.

Finely mince two medium-sized onions, and toss them in butter until they have acquired a yellow colour.

Peel, press and mince three tomatoes, and add thereto three large, raw, sliced mushrooms. Cut two mild capsicums into strips.

Spread the onion on the chicken-turbot; put the tomatoes and the sliced mushrooms on top, and upon these arrange the grilled strips of mild capsicum. Besprinkle moderately with raspings; lay one oz. of butter, cut into small pieces, on the top, and set to cook gently in the oven.

Allow thirty minutes for the cooking. By reducing the moistening-liquor, which has perforce absorbed some of the gelatinous properties of the fish, the leason forms of itself.

Turbotin Bonne Femme

For a chicken-turbot weighing from two to two and one-half lbs. sprinkle on the bottom of a buttered tray one dessertspoonful of chopped shallots, one pinch of concassed parsley, and three oz. of minced mushrooms.

Cut the chicken-turbot in the back, and partly separate the fillets from the bone; lay it on a tray, and moisten with one-third pint of white wine and one-third pint of fish fumet. Cook gently in the oven, and baste frequently the while.

When the chicken-turbot is cooked, dish it and keep it hot. Pour the cooking-liquor into a sautépan; reduce it to half, and add three tablespoonfuls of fish velouté and three oz. of butter.

Cover the fish with this sauce and the garnish, and glaze quickly.

Turbotin Commodore

Poach the chicken-turbot in salted water.

Prepare the following garnish per one person:—Three large potatoes cut to the shape of hazel-nuts and cooked à l’anglaise one medium-sized, trussed crayfish; one quenelle of fish; one small lobster croquette; and one oyster prepared à la Villeroy.

All these products should be treated according to their nature, and just in time to be ready for the dishing up. A few moments before serving, drain the turbot; dish it, and surround it with the garnish detailed above, arranged in alternate heaps.

Serve a Normande sauce, finished with anchovy butter, separately.

Turbotin Daumont

Proceed exactly as directed under “Sole Daumont” (formula №823), taking into account the size of the fish, and increasing the sauce and the garnishing ingredients accordingly.

Turbotin Fermière

Sprinkle on the bottom of a buttered tray two minced shallots, a few roundels of carrot and onion, some parsley stalks, thyme, and bay.

Lay the chicken-turbot on these aromatics, and season moderately. For a fish weighing two lbs. moisten with two-thirds pint of excellent red wine; add one-half oz. of butter, cut into small pieces, and poach gently, taking care to baste frequently.

Meantime toss three oz. of minced mushrooms in three oz. of butter. When the turbot is ready, drain it; dish it; surround it with the tossed mushrooms, and keep it hot.

Strain the cooking-liquor into a vegetable-pan, and reduce it to half. Thicken it with a piece of manied butter the size of a walnut; add three oz. of butter; pour this sauce over the chicken-turbot and its garnish, and set to glaze quickly.

Turbotin à la Mode de Hollande

Poach the chicken-turbot in salted water. Drain it, dish it, and upon it lay a lobster cooked in court-bouillon. The shell of the lobster should have been opened along the top of the tail, and the meat of the tail should have been quickly sliced and returned to its place.

Send to the table at the same time

a timbale of floury potatoes, freshly cooked à l’anglaise;
a sauceboat containing egg sauce with melted butter (formula №117).

Turbotin Mirabeau

Poach the fish in court-bouillon with Sauterne wine, as directed under “Turbotin à l’Amiral” (formula №926).

Drain it; dish it, and coat it in alternate bands with white wine and Genèvoise sauces. Along the lines formed by the meeting of the sauces lay thin strips of anchovy fillets placed end to end. Decorate the bands of white sauce with slices of truffle, and the bands of brown sauce with blanched tarragon leaves.

Turbotin Parisienne

Poach the fish in court-bouillon with Sauterne wine. Drain it, dish it, and round it arrange a border composed of alternate slices of truffles and mushrooms. Coat the fish with white-wine sauce, and surround it with trussed crayfish cooked in court-bouillon.

N.B.—For fish à la Parisienne, the garnish of sliced truffles and mushrooms may be set on the dish, either conspicuously or the reverse; i.e., it may be laid round the fish and covered by the sauce, or arranged in the form of an oval on the fish after the latter has been sauced. In either case the slices of truffles and mushrooms should be laid alternately.

Turbotin Régence

Poach the chicken-turbot in a sufficient quantity of previously-prepared court-bouillon with Chablis wine.

For a fish weighing three lbs. (enough for ten people), prepare the following garnish:—Twenty small spoon-moulded quenelles of whiting forcemeat with crayfish butter; ten poached oysters (cleared of their beards); ten small mushroom-heads (very white); ten truffles in the shape of olives, and ten poached slices of milt.

Drain the chicken-turbot just before dishing it, and slip it on to a dish. Surround it with the garnish detailed above, arranged in alternate heaps, and serve a Normande sauce, finished with two tablespoonfuls of truffle essence per pint, separately.

Turbotin Soufflé à la Reynière

Lay the chicken-turbot on its belly, and make two gashes in its back, on either side of the spine, from the head to the tail. Completely separate the fillets from the bones; cut the spine at both ends; carefully raise it from the underlying, ventral fillets, and entirely remove it.

Season the inside of the fish, and garnish it with enough fish mousseline forcemeat to give it a rounded appearance. Close in the forcemeat by drawing the two separated fillets over it; turn the piece over, and lay it on a well-buttered, deep, oval dish, the size of which should be in proportion to that of the chicken-turbot.

Poach it gently, almost dry, with lid on, in fish fumet and the cooking-liquor of mushrooms mixed, i.e., two-thirds pint of the one and one-third pint of the other. This done, dish it carefully, and lay a row of grooved and white mushroom-heads down the centre of it. On either side put some very white, poached milt, alternating the latter with whole anchovy fillets, in such wise as to form an oval enframing the row of mushrooms.

Send to the table, separately, a sauce composed of Soubise cullis and white-wine sauce, in the proportion of one-third and two-thirds respectively, combined with the reduced cooking-liquor of the chicken-turbot.

Turbotin Feuillantine

Stuff the chicken-turbot after the method described in the preceding recipe, but substitute lobster mousseline forcemeat for that mentioned above.

Poach as directed above, and dish.

Coat the fish with lobster butter, made as red as possible, from the carcass of the lobster whose meat has been used for the forcemeat.

From head to tail and down the centre of the fish lay a row of fine slices of truffle, letting them overlap each other slightly.

Frame the row of truffle with two lines of very white, poached oysters, so placed as to form a regular oval.

Send to the table, separately, a fine Béchamel sauce seasoned with cayenne.

Cold Chicken-Turbot

My remarks relative to cold turbot apply here with even greater force, for chicken-turbots are particularly well suited to cold dishing.

The chicken-turbots to be served cold should not be too small; the best for the purpose would be those weighing four lbs. or more.

In dismissing the subject I can but recommend cold chicken-turbot as a dish admitting of the most tasteful arrangement and decoration

Lobster (Homard)

Whereas the ordinary lobster is a very favourite dish with English gourmets, the spiny kind has scarcely any vogue. This is no doubt accounted for by the fact that the former is not only very plentiful, but also of excellent quality, while the latter is comparatively scarce.

Homard à l’américaine

The first essential condition is that the lobster should be alive. Sever and slightly crush the claws, with the view of withdrawing their meat after cooking; cut the tail into sections split the carapace in two lengthwise, and remove the queen (a little bag near the head containing some gravel). Put aside, on a plate, the intestines and the coral, which will be used in the finishing of the sauce, and season the pieces of lobster with salt and pepper.

Put these pieces into a sautépan containing one-sixth pint of oil and one oz. of butter, both very hot. Fry them over an open fire until the meat has stiffened well and the carapace is of a fine red colour.

Then remove all grease by tilting the sautépan on its side with its lid on; sprinkle the pieces of lobster with two chopped shallots and one crushed clove of garlic; add one-third pint of white wine, one-quarter pint of fish fumet, a small glassful of burnt brandy, one tablespoonful of melted meat glaze, three small, fresh, pressed, and chopped tomatoes (or, failing fresh tomatoes, two tablespoonfuls of tomato purée), a pinch of concassed parsley, and a very little cayenne. Cover the sautépan, and set to cook in the oven for eighteen or twenty minutes.

This done, transfer the pieces of lobster to a dish; withdraw the meat from the section of the tail and the claws, and put them in a timbale; set upright thereon the two halves of the carapace, and let them lie against each other. Keep the whole hot.

Now reduce the cooking-sauce of the lobster to one-third pint; add thereto the intestines and the chopped coral, together with a piece of butter the size of a walnut; set to cook for a moment, and pass through a strainer.

Put this cullis into a vegetable-pan; heat it without letting it boil, and add, away from the fire, three oz. of butter cut into small pieces.

Pour this sauce over the pieces of lobster which have been kept hot, and sprinkle the whole with a pinch of concassed and scalded parsley.

Homard à la Bordelaise

Section the live lobster as directed above.

Stiffen the meat and colour the carapace in a sautépan with two oz. of clarified butter. When the meat is quite stiff and the carapace is red, pour away two-thirds of the butter. Then add two tablespoonfuls of chopped shallots, a crushed piece of garlic the size of a pea, one-sixth pint of white wine, three tablespoonfuls of burnt brandy, and reduce the whole to half. Complete with one-half pint of fish fumet, one-third pint of maigre Espagnole, one-quarter pint of tomato sauce, one small faggot, one pinch of salt, and a very little cayenne.

Put the lid on, and set to cook for one-quarter hour.

Take the meat from the sections of the tail and the claws, as in the case of the preparation à l’américaine; put these into a small sautépan, and keep them hot. Add the intestines and the chopped coral, reduce the sauce to one-third pint; pass it through a strainer, and pour it over the pieces of lobster.

Heat the whole without boiling; add a few drops of lemon juice, two and one-half oz. of butter cut into small pieces, and one-half tablespoonful of chopped chervil and tarragon, and stir over the stove with the view of thoroughly mixing the whole.

Dish as directed in the preceding recipe.

Homard Bouilli à la Hollandaise

Cook the lobster in a court-bouillon (formula №163), allowing twenty minutes for a specimen weighing two lbs.

As soon as the lobster is cooked, drain it; split it in two lengthwise without completely severing the two halves; lay it on a long dish covered with a napkin, and surround it with very green, curled-leaf parsley.

Serve with it, at the same time, a timbale of floury potatoes freshly cooked à l’anglaise, and a sauceboat of melted butter.

Homard à la Broche

Select a lobster that seems full of life, and, after killing it, fix it on the spit. Put into the dripping-pan six oz. of butter, one-half bottle of champagne, salt, and peppercorns. In order to cook it to perfection, frequently baste it with this mixture, and allow one hour before a red fire for a specimen weighing three lbs. It may be dished with two accompaniments:—

A hot ravigote sauce combined with the gravy of the lobster, from which all grease has been removed.
Strain the contents of the dripping-pan (cleared of all grease) through a fine sieve; reduce it by a quarter over a brisk fire; add three tablespoonfuls of meat glaze, two tablespoonfuls of Worcestershire sauce, and a little chopped parsley, and finish this sauce with three oz. of butter and a few drops of lemon juice.

Homard Cardinal

Plunge the live lobster into boiling court-bouillon, and cook it after the manner directed under “Homard à la Hollandaise” (formula №941).

The moment it is cooked, cut it in two lengthwise; withdraw the meat from the tail, slice it, and keep it hot in a little Cardinal sauce. Disconnect the claws; open them sideways, and withdraw all their meat without breaking them. Cut the withdrawn meat into dice, as also the creamy parts from the carapace, and add thereto their weight of cooked mushrooms and half that quantity of truffles—both of which products should also be in dice. Thicken this salpicon with a few tablespoonfuls of lobster sauce, and spread it in even layers on the bottom of each half-carapace.

Reserve, however, two tablespoonfuls of it for garnishing the emptied claws.

Upon the salpicon lay the slices of lobster, kept hot, alternating these with fine slices of truffles. Set the two half-carapaces, thus garnished, on a dish, and wedge them upright by means of the two claws.

Coat the slices and the claws with Cardinal sauce; sprinkle with grated cheese and melted butter; set to glaze quickly in a fierce oven or at the salamander, and serve instantly.

Homard Clarence

Cook the lobster in court-bouillon, and drain it as soon as it is done.

When it is only lukewarm, split it open lengthwise; take the meat from the tail; slice it, and keep it hot in a vegetable-pan with a few drops of fish fumet or the cooking-liquor of mushrooms.

Remove the remains of meat and the creamy parts from the carapace; pound the two former together with two tablespoonfuls of cream; strain through a fine sieve, and add to the resulting cullis one-half pint of Béchamel sauce with curry.

Garnish the two half-carapaces, two-thirds full, with “Rice à l’Indienne” (formula №2254); set the slices of lobster on this rice, intercalating them with slices of truffle; coat thinly with the prepared Béchamel sauce, and set the two garnished and sauced half-carapaces on a long, hot dish.

Send to the table, at the same time, a sauceboat containing Béchamel with curry.

Homard à la Crème

Proceed as for “Homard à la New-burg à cru” (formula №948), but swill with brandy only; and add, immediately, four oz. of fresh, peeled truffles cut into slices.

Moisten, almost sufficiently to cover, with very fresh, thin cream; season with salt and cayenne, and cook the lobster. Then take the meat from the carapaces, and put it into a timbale; reduce the cream to one-third pint, and mix therewith three tablespoonfuls of melted, white meat glaze and a few drops of lemon juice.

Strain this sauce through muslin, and pour it over the pieces of lobster.

Homard Grillé

For this purpose, the lobster may be taken raw, but it is better, first, to have it three-parts cooked in court-bouillon.

Now split it into two lengthwise; sprinkle it with melted butter, and set it on the grill for its cooking to be completed.

Treated thus, the meat of the lobster does not harden as when it is grilled raw. Dish the grilled lobster on a napkin or on a drainer, after having broken the shell of the claws in order to facilitate the withdrawal of the meat, and surround with curled-leaf parsley.

Serve a “Devilled sauce Escoffier”, or any other sauce suited to grilled fish, with the lobster, but remember that the first-named sauce is the fittest that could be found for this particular dish.

Homard à la Mornay , otherwise au Gratin

Proceed in all points as directed under “Homard Cardinal” (formula №943), but substitute Mornay sauce for Cardinal.

Homard à la New-burg

This dish may be prepared in two ways—with raw lobster and with the latter cooked sometime beforehand. The second way is the more correct, but the first, which is less troublesome to prepare, is more suited to the work of large establishments.

Homard à la New-burg (with raw lobster)

Cut up the live lobster, and fry it in oil and butter as explained under “Homard à l’Américaine”. When the pieces of lobster are stiffened and coloured, clear them of all grease; swill the sautépan with one tablespoonful of burnt brandy and one-half pint of Marsala.

Reduce by a third; season, and add two-thirds pint of cream and one-sixth pint of fish fumet. Cover and set to cook for fifteen minutes.

Take out the pieces of lobster; withdraw the meat there-from, and keep it hot in a covered timbale. Thicken the sauce with the reserved intestines and coral of the lobster, which should be chopped in combination with one oz. of butter.

Set to boil a second time; rub the sauce through tammy, and pour it over the pieces of lobster.

Homard à la New-burg (with the lobster cooked)

Cook the lobster in court-bouillon. Remove the shell from the tail; take the meat therefrom, and cut it into regular slices. Lay these slices in a liberally-buttered sautépan, season strongly, and heat the slices on both sides until the outside membrane acquires a fine red colour.

Moisten with enough Madeira to almost cover the slices, and reduce the moistening almost entirely. When dishing up, pour a leason, composed of one and one-quarter pints of cream and two egg-yolks, over the slices. Stir gently on the side of the fire until the thickening has been effected by the cooking of the egg-yolks, and serve in a lukewarm timbale.

Homard à la Palestine

Cut up the live lobster and toss it in butter with a mirepoix prepared in advance, as for crayfish intended for potage bisque.

Moisten with two-thirds pint of white wine, one pint of fish fumet, and three tablespoonfuls of burnt brandy. Cover and cook for fifteen minutes.

Now detach the sections of the tail and the claws; withdraw the meat from them, and keep them hot in a small covered saucepan with a little butter. Pound the carapace and remains of the lobster in a mortar; fry them in four tablespoonfuls of very hot oil, and add thereto an ordinary mirepoix, cut very fine. Moisten with the cooking-liquor of the lobster, and set to cook for one-quarter hour. Strain through muslin; leave to stand for five minutes, that the oil may rise to the surface, and then completely remove it. Reduce this liquid to one-quarter pint; thicken it with the reserved creamy parts of the lobster, rubbed through tammy, and two tablespoonfuls of fish velouté, and finish this sauce with two and one-half oz. of curry butter.

Arrange a border of pilaff rice (formula № 2255) on the dish intended for the lobster; set the pieces of lobster, kept hot, in the centre, and coat these with a few tablespoonfuls of curry sauce.

Serve the remainder of the sauce separately.

Mousselines de Homard

In the matter of crustaceans, the term mousse stands, as a rule, for a cold preparation, whereas the term mousseline is only applied to warm dishes. The special mousselines or quenelles of lobster are made with a mousseline forcemeat, the recipe for which I gave under formula №195. This forcemeat is prepared with the raw meat of the lobster.

As with the other crustaceans, their meat produces forcemeat which is somewhat too flimsy to be spoon-moulded, and it is preferable to poach it in special well-buttered quenelle- or dariole-moulds.

Mousselines are poached under cover in a moderate oven.

All the garnishes and sauces given in respect of salmon mousselines may be applied here. The reader will therefore refer to:—

Mousselines de Saumon Alexandra (formula №798).

Mousselines de Saumon à la Tosca (formula №799).

Soufflés de Homard

For lobster soufflés the same forcemeat is used as for the mousselines; but, unlike the latter, it is poached in the half-carapaces of the lobster, the meat of which has served in its preparation. The procedure is as follows:—First cook the two half-carapaces carefully, that they may not lose their shape in the process.

After having drained and dried them, fill them with mousseline forcemeat and surround them with strong, buttered paper, which should be tied on with string, and should overreach the edges of the carapaces by one inch.

The object of this measure is to prevent the forcemeat from spilling during the poaching.

Lay the two garnished carapaces on a tray containing just enough boiling water to moisten its whole surface. Put the tray in a moderate oven or in a steamer, and allow from fifteen to twenty minutes for the soufflé to poach.

This done, carefully drain the two carapaces; remove the paper holding in the forcemeat; dish them on a napkin, and surround them with bunches of very green, curled-leaf parsley. Serve separately a sauce in keeping with the preparation; i.e., a Normande, a White-wine, a Diplomate, or a Béchamel finished with lobster butter, &c.

N.B.—The above constitutes the model-recipe of lobster soufflé, and I need scarcely point out that the latter may be varied almost indefinitely in accordance with the fancy of the cook and the taste of the consumer.

Thus the forcemeat may be garnished with truffles in dice, slices of lobster, milt, or poached oysters, &c., which garnishes may also be laid on the soufflé when it is finished. I therefore leave to the operator, who should now see his way quite clearly, the task of imagining the various possible combinations, a description of which would but unnecessarily delay the progress of this work.

Cold Lobster with Various Sauces

Cook the lobster in court-bouillon, and let it cool in the latter. Drain it, sever the claws, and break them open in order to withdraw their meat. Split the lobster into two lengthwise, remove the intestines and the queen, and dish it on a napkin. Lay the claws on either side of it, and surround it either with curled-leaf parsley or with a few hearts of lettuce.

Send to the table separately one of the derivative sauces of the Mayonnaise (formula №123 to 132).

Aspic de Homard

Under “Aspic de filets de soles” (formula №915), I pointed out the preparatory principles of an aspic; in this case, therefore, I shall only refer to the various details very cursorily.

Let a thin coating of white fish jelly set on the bottom of an aspic-mould incrusted in ice. The reader is reminded of the great care that must be observed in the preparation of an aspic jelly, that the latter be limpid, succulent, and just sufficiently firm hot to break when withdrawn from the mould. Decorate the bottom of the mould with bits of truffle, poached white of egg, lobster coral, capers, and tarragon leaves.

The decorative design cannot be described; it must be left to the taste and fancy of the operator; all I can urge is that it be as regular and symmetrical as possible.

Fix the decoration by means of a few drops of jelly; then cover the whole with a thickness of one  inch of the same jelly, and leave the latter to set. Upon this layer of jelly arrange rows of thin slices of lobster meat and slices of truffles placed alternately and slightly overlapping. Now add enough jelly to cover these slices, and continue filling up the mould with varying layers consisting respectively of jelly (one inch thick) and the slices above described.

When about to serve, dip the mould in hot water; dry it, and turn out the aspic upon a dish covered with a napkin.

Côtelettes de Homard Arkangel

Prepare a salpicon of lobster meat in dice combined with its weight of caviare, the whole quantity being in proportion to the number of côtelettes required.

Thicken the salpicon with an equal quantity of lobster mousse (formula №956), and at once garnish some moderately oiled cutlet-moulds with the preparation. As soon as the latter has set, turn out the cutlets; coat them with a fish chaud-froid sauce, finished with lobster butter; and deck each with a fine, grooved slice of truffle. Glaze them with cold melted jelly, and keep them in the cool until required to be served.

Arrange them in a circle on a round dish; garnish the centre with chopped white jelly, and serve a Russian salad separately.

Mousse de Homard

Cook the lobster in a few tablespoonfuls of previously-prepared fine mirepoix, one half-bottle of white wine, and a small glass of burnt brandy. Leave to cool in the cooking-liquor. Now split the lobster in two, with the view of withdrawing its meat. Finely pound the latter while adding thereto, little by little, one-third pint of cold fish velouté per lb. of meat. Rub through a sieve; put the resulting purée in a vegetable-pan lying on ice, and stir for a few minutes. This done, add a little good fish jelly, melted and cold, and one-third pint of barely-whipped cream. Taste; rectify the seasoning, and warm it slightly with cayenne.

Mousse de Homard Moulée

When the mousse is intended for moulding, it is well to decorate and “clothe” the mould with fish jelly some time in advance. I have already explained that to “clothe” a mould with jelly, all that is needed is to pour therein a few tablespoonfuls of melted jelly, and then to rock the utensil on ice. By this means a thin even coating sets on the bottom and sides of the mould, which, when the moulding is turned out, swathes the latter in a transparent film.

This “clothing” of jelly may be made more or less thick, according to the requirements, by simply using more or less jelly, and by proportionately lengthening or shortening the time for rocking the mould.

When the mould is clothed, decorate the sides with large slices of very black truffle dipped in melted jelly, that they may stick.

This done, fill the receptacle with the prepared mousse (see the preceding recipe), and leave to set in the cool.

For the turning out of the mould and the dishing of the moulding, proceed as for the aspic.

Petites Mousse de Homard

For these small mousses, use little cassolettes or silver timbales. First let a thin layer of jelly (one or two tablespoonfuls, according to their size) set on the bottom of each utensil, and then surround the latter with bands of white paper, the ends of which should be stuck together, and should reach one inch above the brims of the cassolettes. The preparation of mousse may now be placed in the cassolettes in a sufficient quantity to overflow the brims, so that, when the paper is removed, their appearance is that of small soufflés.

When the cassolettes have been garnished, put them aside on ice or in a refrigerator until they are served.

Homard à la Grammont

Split the lobster open lengthwise down the middle. Withdraw the meat from the tail; trim it, and cut it into regular collops. Coat the latter again and again with aspic jelly, that they may be well covered with it; decorate each with a slice of truffle, and glaze it with the same aspic.

Also coat with jelly as many very white poached and dried oysters as there are collops.

Now take the creamy parts and the meat of the claws, and pound them finely with one tablespoonful of cold Béchamel sauce; rub through a sieve, and, with the resulting purée combined with melted fish jelly and cream (see lobster mousse formula №956), prepare a mousse “au paprika” of a decided pink colour.

Fill the two half-carapaces to their edges with this mousse, and leave it to set on ice.

When about to serve, lay the collops, glazed with jelly, upon this mousse, and place an oyster between each pair. Dish the two garnished half-carapaces, back to back, upon a napkin, and put the heart of a lettuce in the middle, and a bunch of curled-leaf parsley at either end.

Serve a mayonnaise or other cold sauce separately.

Homard à la Parisienne

Tie a lobster to a little board; stretch out its tail to the fullest extent; cook it in court-bouillon, and leave it to cool in the latter.

When it is quite cold, with the help of scissors, carefully cut a strip of the shell from the back of the head to the tail. The aperture left by the removed strip of shell ought to be sufficiently wide to allow of the meat of the tail being removed without breaking it. Having emptied the tail, refill it with salad leaves, and return the strip of shell (upside down) to its place. Cut the meat of the tail into even collops, and lay on each a roundel of truffle stamped out with the fancy-cutter, and dipped in half-melted jelly. Then coat these slices, which should be on a dish, again and again, with cold melted jelly until they are well covered with it.

Now break the claws and remove their meat, as also that remaining in the carapace, and cut both meats into dice. Take the creamy parts, and rub them through a sieve.

Prepare a small vegetable salad; add thereto the meat dice, and cohere the two with a mayonnaise sauce combined with melted jelly and the creamy parts rubbed through a sieve. When the salad begins to set, owing to the jelly contained in the mayonnaise, garnish twelve small artichoke-bottoms with it, arranging the salad in them in pyramid form. Set a bit of truffle on each pyramid, and sprinkle the salad with melted fish jelly in order to make it glossy.

Dishing

Dish the lobster on a cushion of buttered bread on which a julienne of lettuce has been stuck, or on one of carved rice. The cushion should have the shape of a wedge, in order that the lobster may lie at an angle of about 45°, with its head raised, when laid upon it. Arrange the slices (slightly overlapping one another) along the back of the lobster, beginning at its head with the smallest of them, and progressing down towards the tail, gradually increasing their size.

Surround the lobster alternately with artichoke-bottoms garnished with salad, and quartered hard-boiled eggs, or halved hard-boiled eggs (set upright with their yolks facing outwards).

Border the dish with very clear jelly in large cubes or triangles, &c.

Homard à la Russe

Proceed exactly as above with regard to the cooking of the lobster, the extraction of the meat, and the cutting of it into slices. Coat the slices with mayonnaise sauce combined with melted jelly; or, better still, with a white fish chaud-froid sauce combined with the lobster’s creamy parts rubbed through a sieve.

Decorate each slice with a bit of coral and two little chervil leaves; coat them again and again with cold melted aspic, and put them aside in the cool. “Clothe” ten dariole-moulds, and decorate the bottom of each with a slice of truffle. Also prepare ten hard-boiled eggs.

Prepare a “Salade Russe” (without meat); add to this the remains of the lobster meat cut into dice, and thicken with mayonnaise and melted aspic, mixed. With this thickened salad fill the dariole-moulds, and leave to set in the cool.

Dishing

Set the lobster on a cushion, after the manner of the preceding recipe. Trim the slices, and lay them, as before, on the lobster’s back, taking care to graduate their sizes. Surround the lobster with the small moulded salads, and alternate these with the hard-boiled eggs. The latter should be cut in two at a point one-third of their height above their base; their yolks should be removed, the space filled with caviare moulded to the form of a pyramid, and, this done, the eggs should be set upright.

Border the dish with roundels of very clear fish jelly, stamped out by a fancy-cutter, and lay a bit of truffle upon each.

N.B.—

The moulds of salad must, of course, be dipped in hot water before being turned out.
The lobster may also be served “à la Néva”, “à la Moscovite”, “à la Sibérienne”, &c., but these preparations are only minor forms of “Homard à la Russe” under different names.

Changes may be effected in the preparation by altering the constituents of the salad and its dishing. It may, for instance, be made in small cucumber or beetroot barquettes, while the caviare, instead of being laid in hard-boiled eggs, may be served in little pleated cases.

As these preparations, however, are based neither on fixed principles nor on classical rules, I shall refrain from giving them.

Mayonnaise de Homard

Proceed as for Mayonnaise de Saumon—that is to say, garnish the bottom of a salad-bowl with ciseled lettuce leaves, and season them moderately.

Upon this salad lay the remains of the lobster, and upon the latter place the thin slices of the tail. Cover with mayonnaise sauce, and decorate with strips of anchovy fillets, capers, olives, hard-boiled eggs, roundels of pink radishes, the hearts of lettuce, &c.

N.B.—I have already pointed out the futility of prescribing a decorative design. As a rule, the matter is so intimately connected with the taste and fancy of the individual, and the products used for the purpose lend themselves to such indefinite variation, that I prefer merely to enumerate these products, and to leave the question of their arrangement to the artistic ingenuity of the operator.

Salade de Homard

See “Salade de Saumon” (formula №810). As the preparation and seasoning of the latter are identical with those of the dish under consideration, all that is needed is to replace the salmon of recipe №810 by the collops of lobster.

Spiny Lobsters (Langouste).

All culinary preparations dealing with lobsters may be adapted to spiny lobsters. There is, therefore, no need to repeat them here. Of the cold recipes, two are much better suited to the spiny than to the ordinary kind, though, as they are used for both specimens, I gave them earlier in the book. The two recipes referred to are:—

Langouste à la Parisienne; see Lobster, recipe 960.

Langouste à la Russe; see Lobster, recipe 961.

Crayfish (Écrevisses).

When crayfish are prepared after one of the recipes most commonly used on the Continent, i.e., whole, they are not much relished in England. This is doubtless accounted for by the fact that ladies, dining in evening dress, find them somewhat difficult to manage.

They are therefore only served in the form of an aspic, a mousse, mousselines, timbales, &c., or as the garnish of some other fish; for in all these cases they are shelled.

Be all this as it may, I give below the various recipes relating to them, and from among these it ought to be possible to choose one which will meet the requirements of any particular case.

Écrevisses à la Bordelaise

N.B.—Whatever be their mode of preparation, crayfish should always be thoroughly cleansed and cleared of their intestines, the extreme end of which is to be found under the middle of the tail. In order to remove the intestines, take the telson or tail-segment between the point of a small knife and the thumb, and pull gently. If this were not done, the intestines, especially in the breeding season, might render the crayfish disagreeably bitter.

As soon as their intestines have been removed, the crayfish should be set to cook, otherwise, i.e., if they be left to wait, their juices escape through the anal wound, and they empty.

For twelve crayfish, after having cleaned and eviscerated them, put them into a vegetable-pan with one tablespoonful of very fine mirepoix, completely cooked beforehand, and two-thirds oz. of butter. Toss them over an open fire until the shells have acquired a fine, red colour. Moisten with three tablespoonfuls of burnt brandy and one-quarter pint of white wine; reduce by a third, and complete with one tablespoonful of Espagnole, two tablespoonfuls of fish fumet, the same quantity of tomato purée, and one spoonful of special mirepoix (formula №229).

Put the lid on, and set to cook for ten minutes.

Dish the crayfish in a timbale; reduce the sauce by a quarter, and finish it with a few drops of meat glaze, one oz. of butter, a very little cayenne, chopped chervil, and tarragon. Pour this over the crayfish, and serve instantly.

Écrevisses à la Marinière

In the case of twelve crayfish, toss them in two-thirds oz. of butter over an open fire, until the shells are of a fine red. Season with salt and pepper; add two finely chopped shallots, a bit of thyme and a bit of bay; moisten with one-third pint of white wine; cover; cook for ten minutes, and dish in a timbale.

Reduce the cooking-liquor to half; thicken with two tablespoonfuls of fish velouté; finish the sauce with one oz. of butter, and pour it over the crayfish.

Sprinkle with a pinch of chopped parsley, and serve at once.

Écrevisses à la Nage

For twelve crayfish, ten minutes beforehand prepare a court-bouillon of one-half pint of white wine, one-quarter pint of fish fumet, a few roundels of carrot and onion, one stalk of parsley cut into dice, a small pinch of powdered thyme and bay, and a very little salt and cayenne pepper.

Put the crayfish into the boiling court-bouillon; cover, and leave to cook for ten minutes, taking care to toss the crayfish from time to time.

When about to serve, pour the crayfish with the court-bouillon and the aromatics into a timbale.

Écrevisses à la Liégeoise

Cook the crayfish in court-bouillon as explained in the preceding recipe. Dish them in a timbale, and keep them hot. Strain the court-bouillon; reduce it by a quarter; add one oz. of butter, and pour it over the crayfish.

Sprinkle with a pinch of concassed parsley

Mousselines d’Écrevisses

What I said with reference to “Mousseline de Homard” (formula №951) applies perfectly here, and my remarks relative to the variation of the garnishing ingredients, which are the same as those in №951, also hold good.

Timbale de Queues d’Écrevisses à la Nantua

For ten people prepare

a shallow timbale crust, and a cover decorated with a design of leaves or some other ornamental treatment;
toss sixty crayfish in butter with two tablespoonfuls of very fine mirepoix cooked in butter beforehand. When the crayfish are of a distinct red, moisten with one glass of white wine and three tablespoonfuls of burned brandy; season with salt and cayenne pepper; cover them, and keep them on the side of the fire for ten minutes, taking care to toss them again from time to time;
shell the tails and put them into a small saucepan with twenty small quenelles of whiting forcemeat, finished with crayfish butter; fifteen small, grooved mushrooms, cooked and very white, and three oz. of truffles in slices. Add a few drops of the mushroom cooking-liquor to this garnish, and keep it hot;
pound the remains and carcasses of the crayfish very finely; add two-thirds pint of cream sauce to the resulting purée; rub it through tammy, and add it to the garnish;
when about to serve, pour this garnish into the timbale crust, which should be very hot, and deck the top with a crown of fine slices of very black truffle. Close the timbale with its cover, and dish it on a napkin.

Soufflé d’Écrevisses à la Florentine

Make a preparation of “Soufflé au Parmesan” (formula №2295) combined with two tablespoonfuls of crayfish cream per pint. The cream is prepared after the manner of lobster cream (formula №295).

Put this preparation in a buttered timbale in alternate layers separated by litters of sliced truffle and crayfish tails. Cook the soufflé after the manner of an ordinary one.

Soufflé d’Écrevisses Léopold de Rothschild

Prepare a soufflé as above, and add thereto a bare tablespoonful of freshly-cooked asparagus and slices of truffle, and crayfish tails placed between the layers of the soufflé preparation. Cook as above.

Soufflé d’Écrevisses à la Piémontaise

This is identical with formula №972, except that the ordinary truffles are replaced by shavings of Piedmont truffles.

Aspic de Queues d’Écrevisses à la Moderne

Cook twelve fine crayfish in accordance with the directions under formula №996, but substitute champagne for the white wine.

Shell the tails; trim them evenly; cut them in two lengthwise, and keep them in the cool until they are wanted. Remove the creamy parts from the carapaces of the crayfish; add the trimmings of the tails, the meat from the claws, and the mirepoix in which the crayfish have cooked.

Pound the whole very finely in a mortar, and rub it through a sieve. Put the resulting purée in a receptacle; add thereto one-quarter pint of very cold, melted aspic, and three tablespoonfuls of barely beaten cream. Leave this preparation to settle.

Trim the crayfish carapaces; fill them with a little prepared mousse, and decorate each carapace with a small roundel of truffle.

Put the remainder of the mousse in the middle of a little crystal bowl, and mould it to the shape of a cone, narrow towards the base, and as high as possible.

Arrange the garnished crayfish carapaces on their backs in the bowl around the cone of mousse, and set some crayfish tails in superposed rings up the cone. The crayfish tails should be dipped in half-melted jelly, that they may stick fast to the cone. Lay a small, very round truffle on the top of the cone to complete the decoration. This done, coat the whole again and again by means of a spoon with half-melted, succulent, clear fish jelly, and incrust the timbale in a block of ice, or set it amidst the latter broken up.

Mousse d’Écrevisses

For ten people cook thirty crayfish as for potage Bisque. This done, remove the tails, and reserve a dozen fine carapaces. Finely pound the remainder, together with the mirepoix in which the crayfish have cooked, and add thereto one-half oz. of butter, one oz. of red butter (formula №142), one-quarter pint of cold fish velouté, and six tablespoonfuls of melted fish jelly. Rub through tammy, and put the resulting purée in a saucepan; stir it over ice for two or three minutes; add three-quarters pint of half-beaten cream, and the crayfish tails cut into dice or finely sliced.

Before beginning to prepare the mousse, line the bottom and side of a Charlotte-mould with paper, that the mousse may be moulded as soon as ready.

Pour the preparation into the mould, taking care to reserve enough for the twelve carapaces already put aside, and put the mousse on ice or in a refrigerator until dishing it. Fill the twelve trimmed carapaces with the reserved mousse, and decorate each with a round slice of truffle. When about to serve, turn out the mousse on a small, round cushion of semolina or rice, one-half inch thick, lying on a dish. Remove all the paper, and decorate the top of the mousse with a crown of fine slices of truffle dipped in melted jelly, that they may be glossy.

Surround the semolina or rice cushion with a border of chopped jelly, and arrange the garnished carapaces upon this jelly, setting them almost upright.

Instead of being served on a cushion, the crayfish mousse may be sent to the table in a deep silver dish with a border of chopped jelly, and surrounded by the garnished carapaces. The utensil is then laid on a flat dish in a bed of broken ice, or it is incrusted direct in a block of carved ice.
For the moulding of crayfish mousse, the mould may be “clothed” with fish jelly and decorated with slices of truffle, as directed under “Mousse de Homard moulée” (formula №957).

A mousse prepared in this way may be either dished on a semolina or rice cushion, or in a deep silver entree dish, as described above.

Suprêmes d’Écrevisses au Champagne

Select forty medium-sized crayfish that seem full of life; cook them quickly in a highly-seasoned mirepoix, moistened with one half-bottle of dry champagne. This done, shell them trim their tails, and keep them in the cool in a small bowl. Pound their shells as finely as possible with one-quarter lb. of fresh butter, and put the resulting purée in a saucepan, together with one-half pint of boiling velouté containing four or five leaves of gelatine, and the cooking-liquor of the crayfish passed through a fine strainer.

Set to boil for a few minutes, that the remains may exude all their flavour; rub through tammy over a basin lying on ice, and whisk the preparation in order to accelerate its cooling. As soon as it begins to thicken, add one pint of half-whipped cream to it. Then pour the whole into a silver or porcelain timbale, taking care that the utensil be not more than three-quarters full.

When the mousse has set, decorate the surface with the reserved crayfish tails, to which are added, as a finish, bits of truffle and chervil leaves. Cover the decoration with a thin coating of easily-melting and amber-coloured fish jelly, and put the timbale on ice. When about to serve, incrust it in a block of carved ice, or place it on a silver dish with broken ice all round.

Mousse d’Écrevisses Cardinal

For ten people cook the crayfish as explained in formula №976, but take forty instead of thirty. Shell the tails; trim them and cut them into dice. Prepare the mousse in the same way, but use twice as much red butter. Garnish twelve carapaces after the same manner, and decorate each with a slice of truffle.

Clothe a dome- or Charlotte-mould somewhat thickly with jelly; garnish its bottom and sides with crayfish tails, previously dipped in half-melted jelly, and arranged in superposed rows; and place the crayfish so that the tails of the first row lie to the left, those of the second row to the right, and so on. As often as possible, do this work before preparing the mousse, in order that the latter may be put into the mould as soon as ready.

When about to fill the mould, add twenty fine slices of truffle to the mousse. Dish after one of the two methods directed in the appended note to formula №970, and take care to dip the mould quickly into hot water before attempting to turn out its contents.

Petits Soufflés Froids d’Écrevisses

Prepare the crayfish mousse as directed under formula №976, and replace the fish velouté by cold Béchamel. The addition of sauce is even unnecessary in this case, and the preparation may be all the more delicate for consisting only of the crayfish cullis and two tablespoonfuls of fish jelly.

For the moulding of these small soufflés I can only repeat what I said under “Petites Mousses de Homard” (formula №958). Let a thin coating of jelly set on the bottom of the small cassolettes or timbales used; garnish their insides with a band of white paper, reaching one inch above their brims; stick the end of this band with a little batter.

Now garnish the timbales with mousse, letting it project above their edges to the extent of two-thirds of an inch, and leave it to set in the cool. When about to serve, remove the band of paper, holding in the projecting mousse, and the appearance of the garnished timbales is exactly that of small, hot soufflés. Allow one soufflé for each person.

Shrimps and Prawns (Crevettes Grises et Crevettes Roses)

Prawns are chiefly used for hors-d’œuvres, but they may, nevertheless, be prepared in Aspics; Mousses; small cold Soufflés, &c.

As regards shrimps, their use is entirely limited to garnishes, hors-d’œuvres, and to the preparation of soups, shrimp butters, and creams.

Oysters (Huîtres).

Though oysters are nicer raw, there are so many culinary preparations of which they form the leading constituent, and such a number of garnishing uses to which they may be put, that I feel compelled to mention some of these.

Huîtres à la Favorite

Poach the oysters (cleared of their beards) in their own liquor, which should have been carefully collected when opening them. Clean their hollow shells, and place them on a tray covered with a layer of salt one-half inch thick. Garnish them with Béchamel; upon the latter, in each shell, lay an oyster decked with a slice of truffle; cover with the same sauce; besprinkle with grated Parmesan and melted butter, and set to glaze quickly. Serve immediately.

Huîtres au Gratin

Open the oysters; cut them free, and lay them in the hollow halves of their shells, which should be incrusted in a layer of salt covering a tray. On each oyster put a drop of lemon juice, a pinch of fried bread-crumbs, a little melted butter, and a piece of fresh butter the size of a pea.

Set the gratin to form in a fierce oven or at the salamander, and serve immediately.

Huîtres à la Mornay

Poach the oysters, and allow two per shell.

Set the hollow shells, thoroughly cleansed, on a tray covered with salt. Cover the bottom of the shells with Mornay sauce; put two poached oysters into each; cover with the same sauce sprinkle with grated cheese and melted butter, and set to glaze quickly. Serve instantly.

Huîtres Soufflées

Make a preparation of “Soufflé au Parmesan” (formula №2295). Slightly poach the oysters, clean their hollow shells, and set these on a tray covered with kitchen salt. Spread a layer of the preparation on each shell; put an oyster thereon, and cover the latter with the soufflé au Parmesan.

Heat the base of the tray on the stove, and, when the soufflé begins to rise, put the tray in the oven, that the soufflé may cook and colour at the same time. Serve at once.

Huîtres à la Florentine

Poach the oysters. Set their hollow shells on a tray as above; garnish the bottom of each of these with shredded spinach stewed in butter; lay an oyster on the spinach in each shell; cover with Mornay sauce, and set to glaze quickly. Serve immediately.

Huîtres Grillées

Open the oysters, and leave them in their hollow shells; lay them (very straight) on a tray covered with salt, incrusting them in the latter; besprinkle with a drop of lemon juice and a little mignonette pepper and put them in a fierce oven, that their top surfaces may be speedily poached.

Dish them on a napkin; pour a coffee-spoonful of “Sauce Diable Escoffier” over each, and serve directly.

Quenelles d’Huîtres à la Reine

With four oz. of chicken fillets and six raw oysters, prepare a mousseline forcemeat in accordance with the directions given under formula №195. Mould this forcemeat, by means of a tablespoon, into large quenelles, in the centre of which lay two cold poached oysters.

Poach these quenelles after the manner of ordinary mousselines. This done, drain them on a piece of linen; arrange them in a circle on a round dish, and cover them with highly-seasoned Supreme sauce. Decorate each quenelle with a fine slice of truffle, and garnish the middle of the dish with some asparagus-tops, cohered with butter.

Bass (Bar)

This excellent fish is very little known, and, consequently, rarely sought after in England.

The large specimens are served, boiled, with the same kind of sauce as for turbot. The smaller ones are chiefly served à la Meunière or fried.

Brill (Barbue)

Served whole, brill may be looked upon as the understudy, as it were, of the chicken-turbot, and all the preparations given for the latter may be adapted to the former.

If it be preferred filleted, it may be treated after the recipes given for fillets of sole. Hence for brill cooked whole refer to chicken-turbot and the recipes №925 to №938, and for filleted brill see recipes №865 to №922.

Bloaters

Bloaters, or herrings partially dried in smoke, form one of the nicest breakfast dishes. As a rule, they are simply grilled over a moderate fire. It should be borne in mind that, as these fish are only partially salted and smoked, they will not keep very long.

Cod (Cabillaud)

If cod were less common, it would be held in as high esteem as salmon; for, when it is really fresh and of good quality, the delicacy and delicious flavour of its flesh admit of its ranking among the finest of fish.

Cabillaud Bouilli

Fresh cod is mostly served boiled, either whole, in sections, or in dames, and the directions given under “The Boiling of Fish“(formula №766) apply particularly to this fish.

Boiled fresh cod is always accompanied by its liver, poached in salted water, and very floury potatoes, boiled at the last minute, must always be sent to the table with it.

Served thus with an oyster sauce, a Hollandaise sauce, or melted butter, fresh cod constitutes a Relevé which would satisfy the most exacting of gourmets.

Cabillaud Grillé

Cut the fish into slices one inch or two inches thick. Season these slices; dredge them; sprinkle them copiously with melted butter, and set them to grill, remembering to baste them frequently the while with melted butter.

Serve them on a hot dish; garnish them with slices of lemon, and surround with bunches of parsley.

Send a Maître-d’Hôtel or Anchovy butter, or a grilled-fish sauce to the table with the dish.

Cabillaud Frit

Cut some slices of fresh cod, from one inch to one and one-half inches thick. Season them, treat them à l’anglaise, and fry them sufficiently to allow of their being well cooked all through. Dish them on a napkin with fried parsley and lemon, and send a butter sauce (formula №66), a tartare sauce, or a tomato sauce to the table at the same time as the fish.

Cabillaud Crème Gratin

For ten people take two lbs. of boiled fresh cod divided into small pieces; clear these of all bones and skin, and keep them hot in a little of their cooking-liquor.

Now, with the necessary quantity of Duchesse potatoes (formula №221), and by means of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe, lay a border, one and one-half inches high, round a dish, shaping it in such wise that it is thickest at its base. The dish may be either round or oval. Carefully gild this border with egg-yolks.

This done, pour a few tablespoonfuls of Mornay sauce on the dish; lay thereon the drained pieces of cod, and cover the latter with enough Mornay sauce to reach within one-third of an inch of the brim of the border. If more sauce were used, it would flow over the border during the process of glazing.

Sprinkle with grated Parmesan and melted butter; set to glaze, and see that the border gets evenly coloured.

Serve the moment the dish is withdrawn from the oven.

N.B.—This mode of preparation is not restricted to fresh cod. It may be applied to all other boiled fish—turbot, chicken-turbot, brill, bass, salmon, &c..

Cabillaud à la Flamande

Cut the fresh cod into slices one inch thick; season them with salt, pepper, and nutmeg, and put them in a sautépan or a deep, liberally-buttered tray. Moisten with white wine to the height of the slices; add chopped shallots and “fines herbes”, and garnish the fish with roundels of pipped lemon, peeled to the pulp.

Set to boil, and then poach in the oven for twelve minutes. Place the slices on a dish; thicken their cooking-liquor with crushed biscotte; cook it for five minutes; pour it over the slices, and serve.

Cabillaud à La Portugaise

For ten people, cut five slices of fresh cod, each weighing one-half lb., and season them with salt and pepper. Put these slices into a sautépan containing the following garnish, Into which they should be pressed:—Three oz. of butter and one-sixth pint of oil; one large onion, chopped and lightly coloured in butter; a bit of crushed garlic the size of a pea; one faggot two pinches of concassed parsley; eight medium-sized, peeled, pressed, and minced tomatoes, and one-third pint of white wine.

Cover the sautépan, and set to boil on an open fire for five minutes.

Now take the lid off the saucepan, and leave it to cook for twelve minutes on the side of the fire, in order that the liquid may be reduced and the fish cooked at the same moment of time.

Set the slices on a long dish; withdraw the faggot, and pour the garnish and the cooking-liquor over the fish.

Laitances de Carpe (Carp’s Milt)

The milt of a carp makes a very delicate dish. It is served either as a second fish at a dinner; as a garnish to large fish Relevés, after having been poached in salted water; or cut while raw into slices which are generally treated à la Meunière.

Laitances à la Meunière

Prepare them whole or in collops, in pursuance of the directions given under “The Cooking of Fish à la Meunière” (formula №778).

Barquettes de Laitances à la Florentine

Poach the milts in salted water; cut them into small, long slices, and set them in barquette crusts prepared in advance.

Cover the sliced milts with a “Soufflé au Parmesan” (formula №2295), and shape the latter slightly after the manner of a dome. Arrange the barquettes on a dish, and put them in a moderate oven, that they may cook and the soufflé be glazed at the same time. When taking them out of the oven, dish them on a napkin and serve immediately.

Caisses de Laitances à la Nantua

Poach the milts in salted water. Drain them, and cut them into small slices thicker than their length.

Place these slices in small pleated porcelain cases with two crayfish tails in each. Fill up the cases with Nantua sauce, and lay a fine slice of truffle over the centre of each case.

John Dory (St Pierre)

This fish, which is in the highest degree unsightly, is possessed of flesh whose firmness, whiteness, and delicacy are of the rarest excellence; and, when quite fresh, its fillets are certainly equal in quality to those of the chicken-turbot and the sole.

Albeit the dory is not as popular as it deserves to be, and this is owing either to its unsightliness, which may prejudice the opinion of gourmets against it, to people’s indifference with regard to it, or to a mere trick of fashion.

While I admit its unpopularity, however, I should strongly recommend all lovers of fish to give it a trial. Let them prepare the dory’s fillets after the recipes given under Fillets of Sole and Chicken-turbot, and, provided the directions be properly carried out, I venture to believe that the prevailing aversion to dory will very soon be found to have no warrant in fact.

Fresh Haddock (Eglefin)

This fish is chiefly eaten smoked, under the name of haddock.

When it is fresh, it may be prepared after the recipes given for cod, to which it is quite equal in the matter of delicacy.

Smelt (Éperlans)

Owing to their small size, smelts only lend themselves to a very limited number of preparations. They are usually served either on little skewers or dished in a heap on a napkin, with fried parsley and grooved half-lemons; those on skewers are dished flat with the same garnish.

Large smelts may be treated after the recipes immediately following.

Éperlans à l’anglaise

Open the smelts down the back and carefully bone, without disfiguring them. Treat them à l’anglaise with fine breadcrumbs, and pat them lightly with the flat of a knife, that the bread-crumbs may adhere well.

Cook them in clarified butter; set them on a long hot dish, and besprinkle them with half-melted “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”.

Éperlans au Gratin

Proceed as for “Merlans au Gratin“(formula №1018), but allowing for the difference between the sizes of the two fish, put the smelts in a fiercer oven than the whiting, in order that they may be cooked simultaneously with the formation of the gratin.

Éperlans Grillés

Open them down the back, and remove the bulk of their spine, leaving a small piece only in the region of the tail, and another small piece at the head. Season, dredge, and sprinkle them with melted butter, and grill them quickly.

Set them on a long, hot dish; surround them with slices of lemon and bunches of fried parsley, and serve separately either some half-melted butter “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”, or a sauce suited to grilled fish.

Mousselines d’Éperlans

Proceed exactly as for Mousselines de Saumon (formula №797). To prepare the forcemeat, follow the directions under formula №195 but note the following changes:—Of the whole quantity of the meat of fish, that of the smelt should only measure one-third; the other two-thirds should be supplied by the sole, dory, or whiting.

The object of this disproportion has already been explained under “Velouté d’Éperlans” (formula №680). The flesh of the smelt is of a much too decided flavour to be used alone, and when this flavour dominates, it becomes positively disagreeable; hence the need of a fish whose flesh is almost neutral in so far as taste is concerned. But this addition of a fish foreign to the base of the preparation fulfils a double purpose; for, while it effectually weakens the pungency of the smelt’s flesh, it also enables the whole preparation to absorb a much larger quantity of cream, and this last circumstance can only allow of the mousselines being lighter and mellower.

Mousse Chaude d’Éperlans à la Royale

Take a Charlotte-mould, of a size in proportion to the number of people to be served, and butter its bottom and sides. Cover the bottom of the mould with a round piece of buttered kitchen paper, and do the same on the sides.

Prepare the required quantity of smelts’ fillets; slightly flatten them in order to break their fibres, and trim them all to the same length and width.

Then garnish the bottom of the mould with the fillets of smelt, placing them so that their skin-sides are against the mould. Between each of the fillets set a small strip of truffle, one quarter of the width of the former.

Garnish the sides in the same way, putting a strip of truffle between each; but take care to place the fillets aslant instead of upright. Having thus lined the mould with fillets of smelt and truffle, cover the whole with a layer of mousseline forcemeat, one-half inch thick.

Now fill the mould in the following way:—On the layer of forcemeat covering the fillets at the bottom of the mould set as many slices of truffle as will cover it; spread another layer of forcemeat on the truffle, and over that lay, alternately, a sufficient quantity of fillets of smelt and anchovy. Follow with a fresh layer of forcemeat, slices of truffle, &c., until the mould is full, and finish with a layer of forcemeat.

Poach the mousse (covered) in a moderate oven, and allow fifty minutes for one prepared in a quart-mould. It is very easy, however, to tell when the mousse is done, by simply thrusting a small knife into it; if the blade of the knife withdraws quite clean, the mousse is cooked.

As soon as it is ready, turn the mould upside-down on a dish, and raise it a little in order to allow the liquid, which always accumulates in more or less large quantities, to drain away. Soak up this liquid; gently draw off the mould; take oft" the paper, and remove the froth which may have formed on the fillets by means of a wet brush.

Lay a fine, grooved mushroom on the top of the mousse surround it with mousseline sauce (formula №92), finished with crayfish butter, and send a sauceboat of the same mousseline sauce to the table with the dish.

N.B.—This mousse may also be prepared with fillets of sole, of salmon, or of trout, &c.

Haddock

Sometimes the fish is grilled, but, after having boned it and removed its fins and the greater part of its belly, it is more often cooked in water or milk, either of which moistening is usually short.

It is plunged in slightly salted boiling water, and then it is moved to the side of the fire to poach, with lid on. Allow about fifteen minutes for a fish weighing one and one-half lbs.

Dish it with a few tablespoonfuls of its cooking-liquor, and, subject to the consumer’s taste, serve some fresh or melted butter separately.

When haddock is served at lunch, send to the table with it an egg-sauce and a timbale of potatoes, freshly cooked à l’anglaise.

Mackerel (Maquereau)

Maquereau Bouilli, Sauce aux Groseilles

Cut the mackerels into three, crosswise, and poach them in court-bouillon with vinegar (formula №163), seasoned with a pinch of fennel per pint. Drain them on a napkin; skin them, and dish them with curled-leaf parsley all round.

With the mackerels serve a gooseberry sauce prepared as follows:—

Green Gooseberry Sauce proper to Mackerel

Cook one lb. of green gooseberries in a copper sugar boiler with three oz. of sugar and enough water to cover them, and then rub them through tammy.

Maquereau Grillé

Cut off the extremity of the mackerels’ mouths; open them down the back, without dividing them into two.

Season them; sprinkle them with melted butter, and grill them gently, taking care to baste them by means of a brush with melted butter while they are cooking.

Set them on a round, hot dish, and sprinkle them with half-melted “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”, after having drawn their halves together, that they may seem natural and untouched.

Or surround them with grooved slices of lemon, and send a “Sauce Diable Escoffier” to the table separately. This sauce constitutes an excellent adjunct to grilled mackerel.

Filets de Maquereau aux Fines Herbes

Raise some mackerels’ fillets in such wise as to leave the bones quite clean. Arrange the fillets on a buttered dish, and poach them in white wine and the cooking-liquor of mushrooms in equal quantities. Take care to cover them while they are being poached.

This done, drain them; skin them; set them on a long dish, and cover them with a herb sauce (formula №83), combined with their cooking-liquor strained through linen and reduced.

Filets de Maquereau au Persil

Raise the fillets as before, and poach them in a white-wine court-bouillon with one-half oz. of parsley leaves per pint. Drain them; skin them; set them on a long dish, and cover them with a parsley sauce. This latter is an English butter sauce (formula № 113a) referenced recipe is non-extant in the original manuscript to which some freshly-chopped parsley is added at the last moment.

Filets de Maquereau à la Vénitienne

Poach the fillets in a court-bouillon with white wine. Drain them; skin them; set them on a long dish, and cover them with a Venetian sauce (formula №107).

Whiting (Merlan)

Merlan à l’anglaise

Open the whitings down the back; loosen the spine, and completely remove it. Season them inside, and treat them à l’anglaise with very fresh and fine bread-crumbs.

Cook the whitings very quickly in clarified butter; set them on a long dish, and sprinkle them with half-melted “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”.

N.B.—Whitings a l’anglaise may also be grilled, but it is preferable to cook them in clarified butter.

Merlan à la Bercy

Slightly open the whitings down the back, with the view of promoting their cooking process. Lay them on a buttered dish sprinkled with finely-chopped shallots, and moisten them with white wine and fish fumet. Add one-half oz. of butter per whiting, and cook in the oven, basting often the while. The moment when the whitings are quite done should be coincident with the almost complete reduction of their cooking-liquor.

Set to glaze at the last moment.

When taking the whitings out of the oven, sprinkle them with a few drops of lemon juice and a little chopped parsley.

Merlan à la Colbert

Open the whitings down the back, and bone them. Season them; dip them in milk; roll them in flour; and treat them à l’anglaise. Fry them; drain them; set them on a long dish garnish the openings in their backs with “Butter à la Maître d’Hôtel”, and border the dish with grooved slices of lemon.

Mousselines de Merlan

For the preparation of the mousseline forcemeat, refer to formula №195. The moulding and poaching of these mousselines are the same as for salmon mousselines, and the preparations suited to the latter may likewise be applied to mousselines de merlans. (See Mousselines de Saumon, formula №797 to №799.)

Filets de Merlan au Gratin

Raise the fillets from some whitings, and leave the bones quite clean. Lay them on a buttered dish besprinkled with chopped shallots, the bottom of which should have been covered with a few tablespoonfuls of gratin sauce. Surround the fillets with slices of raw mushrooms; set two small, cooked mushrooms upon each fillet; pour a few tablespoonfuls of white wine into the dish, and cover the whole with gratin sauce.

Sprinkle with fine raspings and melted butter, and put the dish in a sufficiently fierce oven to

reduce the sauce;
allow the gratin to form; and
cook the fillets at the same moment of time.

In respect of this operation, refer to Complete Gratin, formula №269.

When taking the dish from the oven, sprinkle a little chopped parsley and a few drops of lemon juice over it.

N.B.—If the whiting be treated whole, the procedure remains the same.

Paupiettes de Merlan au Gratin

Raise some fillets of whiting; coat them with a fish forcemeat combined with fine herbs, and roll them into scrolls. Set these rolled fillets on a round, buttered gratin dish sprinkled with chopped shallots, the bottom of which should have been covered with gratin sauce.

Surround them with a border of sliced, raw mushrooms; place a small, cooked mushroom on each fillet, and proceed for the rest of the operation exactly as explained under “Filets de Merlan au Gratin”.

Merlan en Lorgnette au Gratin

Separate the fillets from the bones, proceeding from the tail to the head, and completely remove the spine near the head. Cover the fillets with fish forcemeat “aux fines herbes”, and roll them into scrolls with their tail-ends inside.

Set them on a round dish sprinkled with chopped shallots and covered with gratin sauce, placing them side by side, all round the dish, with the whitings’ heads in the centre; and proceed for the rest of the operation as explained under formula №1018.

N.B.—Whitings prepared in this way may be treated with white wine, Dieppoise, Bercy, fried, &c.

Filets de Merlan Orly

Raise the fillets and proceed as for “Filets de Soles Olga”, formula №893.

Merlan sur le Plat

Proceed as for “Sole sur le Plat”, formula №837.

Merlan à la Richelieu

Prepare six “Merlans à l’anglaise”, formula №1014. Lay thereon a few slices of truffle. Or dish them simply on their sides; garnish their top surfaces with the butter prescribed above, and put a row of truffle slices on the butter.

Morue and Salted Cod (Morue et Cabillaud Salé)

Salted cod bought in England has generally been fished somewhere along the English coast, and is, as a rule, of recent salting. It has not the peculiar flavour of the Icelandic morue, or that of the Newfoundland specimens, and it does not lend itself to such a large variety of preparations as these two.

At the end of each of the following recipes, I indicate the kind of cod to which the procedure may be applied.

Morue, especially the Newfoundland kind, should be set to soak at least twelve hours before being used, and the water during that time should be frequently changed.

When about to cook it, suppress its fins, and cut it up in a way befitting the selected mode of preparation.

Allow four oz. gross of the fish for each person.

Salted Cod And Morue à l’anglaise

Put the fish into cold water; set to boil, and as soon as this point is reached, leave the fish to poach on the side of the fire for fifteen minutes.

Drain, skin, dish on a napkin, and serve, separately, a timbale of parsnips and an egg-sauce à l’Écossaise.

Both kinds of cod may be used for this dish.

Morue à la Bénédictine

Poach one and one-half lbs. of morue as above; drain it and cut into small pieces, cleared of all skin and bone. Pound it quickly while it is still hot, and add to it half its weight of potatoes cooked as for a purée, drained, and dried in the oven for a few minutes. When the whole has been reduced to a fine paste, add one-sixth pint of oil, and one-quarter pint of boiled milk. The oil and the milk should be added little by little, and the paste should be more mellow than stiff.

Serve in a buttered gratin dish; arrange the preparation in the form of a dome; sprinkle with melted butter, and set to colour in the oven.

Icelandic and Newfoundland morue.

Morue au Beurre Noir ou au Beurre Noisette

Cut the morue into squares or rectangles; roll these into paupiettes or scrolls, and bind these with a piece of string. Poach them in the usual way; drain them; scrape their skins, and dish them. Sprinkle with concassed parsley; add lemon juice, and cover with brown or lightly-browned butter. Either kind of cod may be used.

Brandade de Morue

Cut one lb. of morue into pieces, and poach these for eight minutes. The eight minutes should be counted from the time the water begins to boil.

Drain on a sieve, and clear the pieces of all skin and bones. Heat in a sautépan one-sixth pint of oil until the latter smokes; throw the cleaned pieces of morue into the oil; add a piece of crushed garlic the size of a haricot-bean, and stir over a brisk fire with a wooden spoon until the morue is reduced to shreds.

Then take the saucepan off the fire, and, without ceasing to stir the paste, add thereto, little by little, as for a mayonnaise, about one-half pint of oil. When the paste begins to stiffen through the addition of the oil, now and again add a tablespoonful of milk. For the amount of morue used, one-quarter pint of boiling milk should thus be added by degrees.

When the Brandade is finished, it should have the consistence of an ordinary potato purée. When about to serve, taste the preparation, and rectify its seasoning.

Dish the Brandade in a hot timbale, building it up in the shape of a pyramid, and set thereon a crown of bread-crumb triangles fried in butter just before dishing up.

N.B.—The triangles of fried bread may, with advantage, be replaced by lozenges made from puff-paste, which are baked without colouration. For the Brandade use only well-soaked Icelandic or Newfoundland morue.

Brandade de Morue à la Crème

Follow the directions given above, but instead of oil and milk, use two-thirds pint of cream, which should be added to the morue paste by spoonfuls.

Morue à la Créole

Finely mince an onion, and cook it gently in butter until it is of a nice golden colour. Spread it on the bottom of a little oval earthenware dish, and set three tomatoes prepared à la Provençale (formula №2268) upon it.

Poach one lb. of morue; drain it as soon as ready, and flake it while clearing it of all skin and bones. Lay this flaked morue on the slices of tomato; cover it with three mild capsicums, split and broiled; sprinkle the whole with a few drops of lemon juice and one oz. of lightly-browned butter, and put the dish in the oven for a few minutes. Serve very hot.

Icelandic or Newfoundland morue may be used.

Cabillaud Sale, or Morue à la Hollandaise

Proceed exactly as for “Sole à la Hollandaise” (formula №829). Both kinds suit this preparation.

Cabillaud Sale, or Morue à l’indienne

Poach one lb. of salted cod or morue, and flake it while clearing it of all skin and bones. Mix this flaked fish with two-thirds pint of Indienne sauce formula for referenced sauce not provided in original manuscript, and dish it in a hot timbale.

Serve some “Rice à l’Indienne” (formula №2254) separately.

Both kinds of fish are suited to this dish.

Morue à la Lyonnaise

Poach one lb. of morue, and flake it as explained above. Finely mince a medium-sized onion, and toss it in butter. Also toss three medium-sized potatoes cut into roundels. Heat one oz. of butter and two tablespoonfuls of oil in a frying-pan; put therein the flaked morue and the potatoes, and toss the whole over a brisk fire for a few minutes.

When about to dish up, add a few drops of vinegar.

Dish in a hot timbale, and sprinkle the morue with a pinch of chopped parsley. Use either the Icelandic or the Newfoundland fish for this preparation.

Soufflé de Morue

Finely pound one-quarter lb. of freshly poached and flaked morue, and add thereto, little by little, two tablespoonfuls of hot and very thick Béchamel sauce. When the paste is very smooth, season it; put into a saucepan, heat it, and add the yolks of three eggs, and four whites beaten to a stiff froth.

Put the whole into a buttered soufflé-saucepan, and cook after the manner of an ordinary soufflé. Take either Icelandic or Newfoundland morue for this dish.

Char (Ombre-Chevalier)

The char is a fish of the salmon family, which is culinarily treated in exactly the same way as the trout. When it is large, the recipes given for salmon trout may be adapted to it, but it is mostly used small—that is to say, from five inches to ten inches long. The fishing of char is restricted chiefly to lake countries, such as Scotland and Switzerland, and it is only in season during two months of the year. Moreover, as this fish loses much of its quality in transit, its scarcity on the market will be easily understood. The lake of Zug, in Switzerland, supplies the most famous specimens, which are called Rothel by the people of the locality. The delicacy of the fish is remarkable, and in this it may vie even with the best river trout.

The char of the Scotch lakes may be treated after the same recipes as the Swiss specimens, but they are more often used in the preparation of potted char, the recipe for which is as follows:—

Potted Char

Cook the chars in a fine mirepoix with white wine, exactly after the manner of trout. When the fish are cooked, leave them to cool completely in their cooking-liquor. Drain them skin them; separate their fillets, and thoroughly bone them. Set the fillets in a special earthenware pot; entirely cover them with clarified butter, and put them in a moderate oven for one quarter of an hour.

Leave them to cool until the next day, and add sufficient clarified butter to cover them with a layer one-third inch thick.

If Potted Char be left in the cool, it will keep for some considerable time.

Red Mullets (Rougets)

Red mullet, especially the Mediterranean rock kind, is one of the greatest fish delicacies known; and the surname “Sea Woodcock”, which gourmets sometimes give it, is quite justified, not only by its quality, but by the fact that, except for its gills, it is generally left whole, and not even emptied.

It is best grilled.

Grilled Red Mullet

Carefully wipe the mullet; cisel it on either side to a depth in proportion to the thickness of its flesh and at closer intervals the thicker the latter is, in order to facilitate the cooking; season it with salt and pepper; sprinkle it with a little oil and a few drops of lemon juice; spread a few slices of lemon and a few parsley stalks upon and beneath it; and let it marinade for an hour or two, turning it over frequently the while.

Twenty minutes before serving, set the red mullet on a double fish grill, and cook it over a rather fierce fire, sprinkling it often the while with its marinade. Dish and serve it as soon as it is ready, and serve a little half-melted maître-d’hôtel butter separately.

Rouget à la Bordelaise

Grill or sauté the red mullet. At the same time serve a sauce Bordelaise Bonnefoy (formula №67).

Rouget à la Bordelaise

Cisel and marinade the red mullet as directed under formula №1035a, and add a certain quantity of chopped fennel to the aromatics. Twenty minutes before serving, add two oz. of roughly-chopped raw pork fat and a little parsley to the marinade; wrap the red mullets in strong, oiled paper, together with its marinade, grill it gently, and serve it as it stands.

Rouget à la Niçoise

Grill it as directed above, and serve it with the garnish given under “Sole à la Niçoise” referenced recipe not given in original manuscript.

Rouget en Papillote

Grill and wrap it in strong, oiled paper between two layers of somewhat thick Duxelle sauce referenced recipe not given in original manuscript. When about to serve, put the papillote for five minutes in the oven, that it may be souffléd.

Whitebait

Thames whitebait, which has many points in common with the “Nonat” of the Mediterranean, is one of the riddles of ichthyology; for, while it is generally admitted that it is the fry of one of the many species of fish, its real parentage is quite unknown principally juvenile sprat and herring.

At dinners in London it usually stands as a second fish-course, and, fried after the customary manner, it constitutes a dish the delicacy of which is incomparable. Whitebait, like the nonat, are extremely fragile, and ought to be cooked as soon as they are caught. They are always served fried, and the frying-medium used in their preparation should be fresh, abundant, and just smoking when the fish are plunged into it. Previous to this operation, however, the whitebait ought to be thoroughly dredged with flour and placed in a special sieve or frying basket, either of which should be well shaken, in order to rid the fish of any superfluous flour.

They are then plunged into the smoking frying-medium, in small quantities at a time, and one minute’s stay therein suffices to render them sufficiently crisp.

Draining is the next operation, effected upon a spread piece of linen, that the fish may be easily seasoned with table-salt and cayenne, mixed. This done, the whitebait are dished upon a napkin and sent to the table with very green, fried parsley.

Various Preparations of Fish

Matelote au Vin Rouge

The fish used for the Matelote are eel, carp, tench, bream, perch, &c.

It may be prepared from one or many kinds of fish.

Put the fish, cut into sections, into a sautépan. For two lbs. of it, add one minced onion, one faggot, two cloves of garlic, one pint of red wine, a pinch of salt, and another of pepper or four peppercorns.

Set to boil; add three tablespoonfuls of heated and burnt brandy; cover the sautépan, and complete the cooking of the fish.

This done, transfer the pieces to another saucepan; strain the cooking-liquor, reduce it by a third, and thicken it with manied butter (consisting of one and one-half oz. of butter and one tablespoonful of flour), cut into small pieces.

When the leason has been properly effected, pour the resulting sauce over the pieces of fish; heat, and dish in a timbale.

Matelote au Vin Blanc

Prepare the fish as above, but use red wine instead of white, and burn the brandy as before. When the pieces of fish are cooked, transfer them to another saucepan with small onions, previously cooked in butter, and small, cooked mushrooms. Strain the cooking-liquor, reduce it to a little less than half, thicken it with fish velouté, and finish with one oz. of butter.

Pour this sauce over the fish and the garnish; dish the whole in a timbale or a deep dish, and surround with crayfish, cooked in court-bouillon, and little crusts in the shape of hearts, fried in butter.

Bouillabaisse à la Marseillaise

The fish for Bouillabaisse are rascasse, chapon, dory, whiting, fielas, boudreuil, spiny lobster, red mullet, gurnet, &c.

Cut the larger fish into slices; leave the smaller ones whole, and with the exception of the whiting and the red mullet, which cook more speedily than the others, put them all into a saucepan.

For two lbs. of fish, add one small onion, the chopped white of one leek, one small, peeled, pressed and chopped tomato, two crushed cloves of garlic, a large pinch of concussed parsley, a pinch of powdered saffron, a bit of bay, a little savory and fennel, and two tablespoonfuls of oil.

Moisten the fish with just enough cold water to cover it, and season with one-third oz. of salt and a pinch of pepper per quart of water.

Set to boil, and cook over a brisk fire. At the end of eight minutes add the pieces of whiting and red mullet, and leave to cook for a further seven minutes.

Pour the liquor of the bouillabaisse over some slices of household bread lying on the bottom of a deep dish; set the fish on another dish with the sections of spiny lobster all round, and serve.

Quenelles de Brocket à la Lyonnaise

Pound separately one lb. of the meat of pike, cleared of all skin and bones, and one lb. of the fat of kidney of beef, very dry, cleaned, and cut into small pieces. If desired, half of the weight of the fat of kidney of beef may be replaced by one-half lb. of beef marrow.

Put the pounded meat of the pike and the kidney fat on separate plates. Now pound one lb. of frangipane Panada (formula №192) and add thereto, little by little, the white of four little eggs. Put the pike meat and the fat back into the mortar, and finely pound the whole until a fine, smooth paste is obtained. Rub the latter through a sieve; put the resulting purée into a basin, and work it well with a wooden spoon in order to smooth it.

With this forcemeat mould some quenelles with a spoon, and poach them in salted water.

If these quenelles are to be served with an ordinary fish sauce, put them into it as soon as they are poached and drained, and simmer them in it for ten minutes that they may swell.

If the sauce intended for them is to be thickened with egg-yolks, and buttered at the last moment, put them into a saucepan with a few tablespoonfuls of fumet, and simmer them as directed in the case of an ordinary fish sauce, taking care to keep the saucepan well covered that the concentrated steam may assist the swelling of the quenelles. In this case they are added to the sauce at the last moment.

N.B.—Slices of truffle may always be added to the sauce. The quenelles are dished either in a silver timbale, in a shallow timbale-crust, or in a fine vol-au-vent crust, in accordance with the arrangement of the menu.

Fish Cakes

Fish cakes or balls, which are greatly appreciated in both England and America, are made from any boiled fish. Salted cod, however, is best suited to their preparation, and is therefore used much more often than other kinds of fish.

Flake one lb. of cooked cod, and clear it of all skin and bones; pound it with one-half lb. of freshly-cooked, floury potatoes, two tablespoonfuls of reduced Béchamel sauce, and two whole eggs. Season with salt and pepper. When the paste has been well beaten and is smooth, take it out of the mortar and divide it into portions weighing about two oz. Roll these portions into balls upon a flour-dusted mixing-board, flatten them out to the shape of thick quoits, and treat them à l’anglaise.

Fry them at the last moment in very hot fat, and dish them on a napkin with fried parsley all round.

Waterzoi

In order to prepare Waterzoi, it is best, when possible, to have live fish at one’s disposal, not only because these are better able to resist the cooking process, but also owing to the fact that they are richer in gelatine in the live state.

The fish more generally used are the eel, the perch, the tench, the carp, the pike, &c.

After having scaled and emptied them, trim them and cut off their heads and tails. Cut the fish into sections; moisten these with just enough cold water to cover them; add a piece of butter, sufficient parsley roots or stalks to produce a decided taste, a few peppercorns, and some salt.

Set to cook on a brisk fire, and take care that the cooking-liquor be reduced and sufficiently thickened when the fish are cooked.

Serve in a timbale or on a dish, and send some slices of bread and butter to the table at the same time.

Chapter XV Relevés and Entrées of Butcher’s Meat

Beef

Fillet of Beef (Relevé)

Fillet of beef for a Relevé may consist either of the whole piece, trimmed, studded, or larded, or a more or less large piece cut from the whole, and treated after one of the methods suited to the whole fillet. The fillet may be braised, poëled, or roasted; but the last two modes of preparation suit it best, as it is generally preferred underdone and somewhat red towards the centre.

The garnishes for a Relevé of fillet of beef are as numerous as they are varied; and, as they are applicable not only to fillet of beef but to all Relevés of butcher’s meat, I give them here in preference, since fillet of beef may be considered the choicest of Relevés.

Filets de Bœuf Andalouse

Having removed all the connective tissue from the fillet, lard it with thin strips of bacon, and poële or roast it. Glaze it at the last moment; set it on a long dish, and surround it with:

Some grilled half-capsicums, filled with “Riz à la Grecque”;
roundels of egg-plant, two inches in diameter and one inch thick, hollowed out to form cases, fried in oil, and garnished with concassed tomatoes tossed in oil. Arrange the half-capsicums and the egg-plant alternately round the fillet, and place a grilled chifolata sausage between each.

Sauce to be sent separately.—The gravy taken from the poëling-stock, strained, cleared of all grease, and thickened.

Filets de Bœuf Bouquetière

Having larded the fillet and poeled or roasted it, set it on a long dish and surround it with:—

Small heaps of carrots and turnips, turned by means of a small grooved spoon, and cooked in consommé;
small heaps of little potatoes turned to the shape of olives and cooked in butter;
small heaps of peas and of French beans, cut into lozenges and cohered with butter;
five bunches of cauliflower.

Arrange these different products in such wise as to vary their colours and throw them into relief.

Serve the gravy of the fillet separately, after having cleared it of all grease and strained it.

Filets de Bœuf Camargo

Trim the fillet; suppress the long muscle lying on its thicker side (French: chaîne), and open the meat lengthwise from the same side. Withdraw the meat from the inside of the fillet so as to leave a wall of meat only one-half inch thick all round. Finely chop the withdrawn meat and combine with it, per lb., little by little, from four to five tablespoonfuls of cream and four oz. of fresh foie gras. Season with salt and pepper, rectify the consistence of the paste, and add thereto, per lb., two oz. of chopped truffles.

Fill the hollow fillet with this forcemeat, thereby returning it to its original shape, and stud its top surface with pointed pieces of truffle one inch long by one-quarter inch wide, stuck into the meat aslant. In order to facilitate this operation, bore the meat, before the insertion of the pieces of truffles, by means of a small knife.

Now cover the fillet with slices of bacon and string it laterally, leaving a space of one inch between each strand.

Poële the meat carefully, and take care that the forcemeat inside be well, but not over-done. This may be ascertained by thrusting a braiding needle into the thickest part of the fillet, as soon as the meat seems resisting and elastic to the touch. If the needle withdraws clean, the fillet is ready.

Sauce to be sent to the table separately.—The reduced poëling-liquor of the fillet, cleared of all grease, and added to a Périgueux sauce.

Filets de Bœuf Châterlaine

Lard the fillet, poele it, and glaze it just before dishing up. Set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish:—

Medium-sized artichoke-bottoms garnished with thick Soubise;
fine, peeled chestnuts cooked in the poeling-liquor;
small heaps of lightly browned potatoes, cooked in butter at the last moment.

Sauce to be sent separately.—The reduced poëling-liquor of the fillet, cleared of all grease and added to a Madeira sauce.

Filets de Bœuf Clamart

Lard the fillet and roast it.

Set it on a long dish and surround it with:—

Little tartlet-crusts garnished with peas, prepared à la Française, combined with the ciseled lettuce used in their cooking-process, and cohered with butter;
small quoits of “Pommes de Terre Macaire”. Arrange the tartlet-crusts and the quoits alternately.

Sauce to be sent separately.—The gravy slightly thickened.

Filets de Bœuf Dauphine

Lard the fillet and poéle it.

Glaze it at the last moment; set it on a long dish, and surround it with a garnish of potato croquettes à la Dauphine, moulded to the shape of corks, and fried just before dishing up.

Sauce to be sent separately.—Pale half-glaze with Madeira.

Filets de Bœuf Dubarry

Lard the fillet with bacon, and roast it.

Set it on a long dish, and surround it with small heaps of cauliflower moulded to the shape of balls, coated with Mornay sauce, besprinkled with grated cheese, and put in the oven for the gratin to form just in time for the dishing up.

Send a thickened gravy to the table separately.

Filets de Bœuf Duchesse

Either roast or poéle the larded fillet. If it be poéled, glaze it at the last moment.

Set it on a long dish and surround it with potatoes à la Duchesse (the shape of which may be varied according to fancy), lightly browned and coloured in the oven for a few minutes before the dishing.

Sauce to be sent separately.—Half-glaze with Madeira.

Filets de Bœuf Financière

Poéle the larded fillet.

Glaze it at the last moment and set it on a long dish. Surround it with a garnish consisting of

quenelles of ordinary forcemeat;
grooved and cooked button-mushroom heads;
cocks’ combs and kidneys;
turned and blanched olives.

Each garnish should be placed on the dish in distinct heaps.

Cover the garnish with a little financiere sauce, and send the same sauce separately.

Filets de Bœuf Gastronome

Insert truffles, cut to the shape of ordinary larding-bacon, into the fillet, and set the latter to marinade for four or five hours in one-quarter pint of Madeira.

This done, thoroughly wipe it; cover it with slices of bacon, and braise it in Madeira. When about to serve it, remove the slices of bacon glaze it slightly, and set it on a long dish.

Surround it with a garnish consisting of

large and thick slices of truffle, cooked in a fine mirepoix with champagne;
fine chestnuts cooked in consommé and glazed;
fine cocks’ kidneys, rolled in pale, thin meat-glaze;
noodles tossed in butter. These different garnishes should be arranged in alternate heaps, and connected by means of medium-sized truffles cooked in Madeira.

Sauce to be sent separately.—Half-glaze combined with the cooking-liquor of the truffles, strained through linen and reduced to two-thirds.

Filets de Bœuf Godard

Lard the fillet with alternate strips of bacon and salted tongue, and poële it. Glaze it a few minutes before serving; set it on a long dish, and surround it with a garnish consisting of

quenelles of ordinary forcemeat with chopped mushrooms and truffles added thereto, moulded by means of a coffee-spoon, and poached just before dishing up;
turned and cooked button-mushroom heads;
glazed lamb sweetbreads;
cocks’ combs and kidneys;
truffles fashioned like olives.

Slightly coat these garnishes, which should be arranged in heaps, with sauce; finish the dish with four oval quenelles decked with tongue and truffle, and place one of these at either end and side of the dish.

Sauce to be sent separately.—A Godard sauce combined with the cooking-liquor of the fillet, cleared of all grease and reduced.

Filets de Bœuf Hongroise

Lard the fillet and roast it.

Set it on a long dish and surround it with a garnish consisting of medium-sized onions, cooked in white consommé, and glazed in butter at the last minute.

Sauce to be sent separately.—Thin Soubise with paprika.

Filets de Bœuf Japonaise

Lard the fillet and poéle it.

Glaze it just before dishing; set it on a long dish, and surround it with a garnish consisting of

small croustades cooked in grooved brioche-moulds and garnished with Japanese artichokes cohered by means of velouté;
potato croquettes moulded to the shape of eggs and fried just before dishing up. Arrange the croustades and the croquettes alternately.

Send the gravy of the fillet, strained and cleared of all grease, to the table separately.

Filets de Bœuf Jardinière

Lard the fillet and roast it.

Set it on a long dish and surround it with the following garnishes, which should be arranged in distinct heaps in such wise as to alternate their colours:—Carrots and turnips, raised by means of a grooved spoon-cutter and cooked separately in consommé; peas, French beans in lozenge-form and small flageolets, each of which vegetables should be cooked in a manner in keeping with its nature, and separately cohered with butter; portions of freshly-cooked cauliflower, kept very white and of tight growth.

Send some Hollandaise sauce for the cauliflower, and some clear gravy, to the table, separately.

Filets de Bœuf Lorette

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it at the last moment; set it on a long dish, and surround it with a garnish as follows:—

A small pyramid of Lorette potatoes (№2226) at either end of the fillet;
fine heaps of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter, on either side.

Send some tomated half-glaze separately.

Filets de Bœuf Macédoine

Prepare the fillet as directed under “Filet de Bœuf Jardinière”. Set it on a long dish and surround it with a Macédoine garnish. The latter comprises the same ingredients as the “Jardinière”; but, instead of their being heaped separately, they are mixed together and cohered by means of butter.

Filets de Bœuf au Madère et aux Champignons

Lard and poële the fillet.

Glaze it; dish it as before, and surround it with fine mushroom-heads, turned and grooved.

Send to the table, separately, a Madeira sauce finished with the poëling-liquor, cleared of all grease and reduced.

Filets de Bœuf Moderne

Lard the fillet alternately with bacon and tongue, and poële it.

Glaze it just before dishing; set it on a long dish, and surround it with garnish as follows:—On either side of the fillet lay a row of small “chartreuses”, made in small, hexagonal moulds.

To make these “chartreuses”, butter the moulds and deck the bottom of each with a slice of truffle, big enough to almost entirely cover it. Now line the sides of the moulds with various vegetables, such as carrots, turnips, peas, and French beans; each of which vegetables should be cooked as its nature requires.

Arrange them in such wise as to vary their colours, and spread over the whole a thin layer of rather flimsy forcemeat.

Fill up the moulds with braised cabbage, which should be well pressed with the view of ridding it of all its moisture, and put the chartreuses in a bain-marie ten minutes before dishing the fillet.

At either end of the fillet set some braised half-lettuces, arranging them so that they frame the ends of the fillet in half-circles.

Between the lettuce and the chartreuses set four round quenelles, decorated with salted tongue and poached in time to be ready for the dishing of the meat.

Send to the table, separately, the poeling-liquor of the fillet, cleared of all grease, strained, and slightly thickened with arrowroot.

Filets de Bœuf Montmorency

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it just before dishing up, and set it on a long dish.

Send to the table, separately, a Madeira sauce finished with the poëling-liquor of the fillet, to which add (per pint of the sauce) three tablespoonfuls of red-currant jelly; two tablespoonfuls of finely-grated horse-radish, or the latter finely grated first, and then chopped; thirty moderately-sweetened cherries, set to soak in tepid water seven or eight minutes beforehand, and drained just before being added to the sauce.

Filets de Bœuf Nivernaise

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it at the last moment; set it on a long dish, and surround it with garnish as follows:—

Heaps of small carrots, shaped like elongated olives, cooked in white consommé and a little butter and sugar, and rolled in their cooking-liquor (reduced to the consistence of syrup), with the view of glazing them.

Send the poëling-liquor (cleared of all grease and strained) to the table separately.

Filets de Bœuf Orientale

Roast the fillet “plain”, i.e., without previously larding it.

Set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish, taking care to alternate the ingredients, viz.,

timbales of “Riz à la Grecque” moulded in buttered dariole-moulds, each timbale being placed on a medium-sized half-tomato, seasoned and tossed in butter;
croquettes of sweet potatoes, moulded to the shape of corks, and fried just before dishing up.

Send to the table, separately, a highly seasoned tomato sauce.

Filets de Bœuf Périgourdine

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it just before dishing up; set it on a long dish, and surround it with medium-sized truffles, freshly cooked in Madeira and fine mirepoix, and glazed. Send a Périgueux sauce separately.

Filets de Bœuf Petit Duc

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it in good time; set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish:—

crisp, small patties of puff paste garnished with asparagus-heads cohered by means of cream sauce;
medium-sized artichoke-bottoms, prepared in the usual way, and garnished with slices of truffle.

Send, separately, a light, meat glaze, combined with four oz. of butter per one-half pint.

Filets de Bœuf Portugaise

Lard the fillet and roast it.

Set it on a long dish, and garnish it as follows:—

A row of medium-sized, stuffed tomatoes on either side.
At either end a nice heap of potatoes, shaped like long olives, and cooked in butter just before dishing up.

Send a light, Portugaise sauce separately.

Filets de Bœuf Provençale

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it at the last minute; set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following, alternated:—Tomatoes and mushrooms stuffed à la Provençale (№2266 and №2075).

Send a tomatéd half-glaze sauce, separately.

Filets de Bœuf Régence

Marinade the fillet in Rhine wine two or three hours in advance; cover it with a Matignon (№227); envelop the fillet and the Matignon in slices of bacon, and set the whole to braise with its marinade.

A few minutes before dishing up, remove the slices of bacon and the Matignon, and glaze the fillet.

Set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish, which, except for the decorated quenelles, which are left plain, should be arranged in distinct heaps, and slightly coated with sauce:—

quenelles of ordinary forcemeat, combined with chopped tongue, moulded by means of a coffee-spoon, and poached at the last minute;
collops of foie gras tossed in butter;
fine cocks’ combs;
very white, cooked mushroom-heads, and truffles shaped like large olives.

Send, separately, the braising-liquor of the fillet, cleared of all grease, strained with pressure, reduced, and added to a half-glaze sauce.

Filets de Bœuf Renaissance

Lard the fillet and poële it.

Glaze it at the last minute; set it on a long dish, and surround it with a garnish of early-season vegetables, comprising carrots and turnips, raised by means of a large, round, grooved spoon-cutter, cooked in consommé and glazed; very green peas; small French beans; small faggots of asparagus-heads; portions of cauliflowers, and small potatoes cooked in butter.

Renaissance garnish is, however, subject to no fixed rules, and it may consist of all the available early-season vegetables, small artichoke-bottoms included.

Send a clear gravy separately.

Filets de Bœuf Richelieu

Lard the fillet, and either poële or roast it.

If it be poëled, glaze it in good time; set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish, which should be arranged in distinct heaps and in such wise as to contrast its colouring:—

Small tomatoes and medium-sized mushrooms, stuffed;
small or half-lettuces, braised and well trimmed;
potatoes, the size of pigeons’ eggs, cooked in butter and prepared just in time for the dishing up.

Send the cooking-liquor, cleared of all grease, and slightly thickened, separately.

Filets de Bœuf Saint-Florentin

Lard the fillet and roast it.

Set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish:—

At either end, a heap of cèpes, prepared à la Bordelaise at the last minute;
croquettes of potatoes à la Saint-Florentin, on either side. These croquettes are prepared from the same potato-paste as “Pommes Duchesse”, but in this case the paste receives a copious addition of chopped tongue. Mould them to the shape of lozenges, and treat them a l’anglaise, using for the purpose very fine vermicelli instead of bread-crumbs.

Fry the croquettes just before dishing up.

Send, separately, a Bordelaise sauce with white wine, kept somewhat light.

Filets de Bœuf Saint-Germain

Lard the fillet and roast it.

Set it on a long dish, and surround it with the following garnish:—

At either end of the fillet a nice heap of glazed carrots, cut to the shape of olives;
a heap of very small potatoes, cooked in butter, on either side of the carrots;
a row of small timbales of very green peas purée on either side of the fillet.

Filets de Bœuf Talleyrand

Cut up the necessary number of raw truffles for the garnishing of the fillet. The pieces of truffle should be one inch long and one-quarter inch wide, and so pointed as to enable them to be easily stuck into the meat.

To stick them in, make small incisions in the fillet, and in these set the bits of truffle. Marinade the fillet for three hours in Madeira; wrap it in slices of bacon; string it, and set it to braise with its marinade.

This done, remove the slices of bacon glaze it, and set it; on a long dish. Send the following garnish separately:— Poached macaroni, cut into pieces one and one-half inches long, and combined per lb. with three oz. of grated Gruyère and Parmesan, one and one-half oz. of butter, three oz. of a julienne of truffles, and three oz. of cooked foie gras, cut into large dice.

As an adjunct, send a Périgueux sauce with a fine julienne of truffles instead of the latter chopped.

Filets de Bœuf Froid (Relevé)

Fillet of beef, when properly dished, makes an excellent cold Relevé.

For this purpose lard it, roast it (keeping it somewhat underdone towards the centre), and, when it is quite cold, trim, and coat it with half-melted jelly.

Then set it either directly upon a dish or upon a cushion of bread or carved rice, which makes the dish more sightly when the garnish is added.

Before setting the fillet on the dish or on the cushion of rice, it is well to cut a slice one-fifth inch thick from the whole of its base; leave this slice under the fillet when dishing; by this means, when the carving is proceeded with, each slice will be found to be neatly trimmed.

Cold fillet of beef allows of every possible cold vegetable garnish.

The vegetables should be cooked with the greatest care and be left to cool naturally.

When they are quite cold, either cohere them by means of jelly, or set them round the fillet in neat heaps, taking care to alternate their shades, and coat them with almost melted aspic.

Finally, between each heap of vegetables lay a little chopped and very clear aspic, and, round the whole, arrange a border consisting of bits of aspic (round, oval, square, lozenge-shaped, &c.) very regularly cut.

I see no reason for devoting any further space to this subject. What has been said should, I think, suffice to show how varied and numerous are the possible ways of dishing cold fillet of beef, the minute details of which may, with advantage, be left to the ingenuity of the operator.

Fillet of beef for entrées

Châteaubriand, Fillet Steak, Tournedos

By fillet steaks are understood those pieces of meat cut laterally from the thickest part of the fillet of beef.

They ought to be about one and one-half inches thick, and weigh from six to seven oz. Tournedos are half-fillets in respect of their weight, and might well be called the “kernels” of the fillet of beef. The usual thickness of a tournedos is about one and one-quarter inches, and they should be cut to a nice, round shape. With the object of preserving their shape, they may be tied round with string.

Châteaubriand is also procured from the centre of fillet of beef, and its weight is often twice, thrice, and sometimes more than thrice as much as that of the ordinary fillet steaks.

As a rule, especially when grilled, it constitutes a special roast for luncheons; when it is cooked in the saucepan, i.e., sautéd, it is more often served as a Relevé.

The same garnishes suit fillet, Châteaubriands, and tournedos, the only necessary modifications being in respect of size and arrangement, which should be subject to the size of the piece of meat.

The garnishes detailed hereafter are for the tournedos, which supply the greatest number of the dishes prepared from the three different cuts of fillet. If a fillet steak be prepared after one of the following recipes, the garnish should be made a little stronger, and its constituents modified in the dishing, neither of which changes need in any way alter the formula.

The same holds with regard to a Cháteaubriand. Thus, for example, if it be required to prepare a fillet steak or a Châteaubriand, after the recipe “Tournedos à l’Algérienne”, the number of croquettes and tomatoes should be half as much again, and they should be arranged alternately round the meat, instead of the latter being placed on the croquettes, as in the case of the tournedos.

If the fillets are to be treated “à l’Alsacienne”, after the recipe for tournedos, the sauerkraut should be dished in a timbale instead of in tartlet-crusts, &c.

All that is needed, therefore, is a change in the method of arrangement, and this can be decided upon at a glance, without necessarily interfering with the principle of the recipe.

It should be borne in mind that nearly all the garnishes given under fillet of beef, served whole, may be applied to Châteaubriands, fillet steak, and tournedos, provided they be made in proportion to the size of the different pieces. I see no need, therefore, to repeat these vegetable recipes in so far as they relate to the various cuts of fillet of beef.

It is only necessary to add that for the fillet of beef, as well as for tournedos, noisettes, &c., a large number of plain vegetable garnishes may be used, the details of which I prefer to omit for fear of unduly lengthening this work.

Whole fillets, fillet steak, and tournedos may thus be served with garnishes of braised celery, tuberous fennel, cardoons with gravy, chow-chow and endives, braised lettuce, various purées, &c., and, generally, with all the vegetable preparations given in Chapter XVII.

Important Remarks relative to the Sauces suited to Entrées of Butcher’s Meat, Garnished with Vegetables

The derivative sauces of the Espagnole are not, as a rule, suited to entrées garnished with vegetables. Thickened gravy is better.

The finest adjunct, however, is meat-glaze, which should receive an addition of four oz. of butter per pint, and should be slightly acidulated by means of a few drops of lemon juice. This glaze ought to be so light as not to impaste the vegetables.

Such vegetables as asparagus-heads, peas, French beans, macédoines, &c., have a disintegrating action upon the sauces, and this is owing either to their natural moisture or to their leason. As a result of this action the preparation has an unsightly appearance when served upon the diner’s plate.

With Châteaubriand sauce (№71) or buttered meat-glaze this objection does not obtain, seeing that this sauce does not decompose, but combines admirably with the garnish, and lends the latter a certain noticeable mellowness.

I therefore emphasise this point, viz., that the derivative sauces of the Espagnole and tomato sauces should be exclusively used with such preparations garnished with truffles, cock’s combs and kidneys, quenelles and mushrooms, as “la Financière”, “la Godard”, &c.

Tournedos

Tournedos Algerienne

Season the tournedos, and fry them in clarified butter. Arrange them in the form of a crown on a round dish, andset a croquette of sweet potato, moulded to a round shape, uponeach.

Around the whole lay some small, emptied, and seasoned half-tomatoes, stewed in oil.

Tournedos Alsaciennes

Season and grill the tournedos.

There should have been prepared in advance as many small tartlet-crusts as there are tournedos.

Garnish these tartlets with well-drained, braised sauerkraut, and set on each a roundel of the lean of ham, stamped out with an even cutter. Arrange them in the form of a crown on adish, and set a tournedos upon each tartlet.

Tournedos Arlésienne

Fry the tournedos in butter and oil.

When about to serve, set the tournedos on a dish, and surround them with fried roundels of egg-plant and tossed tomatoes, alternating the two garnishes, and placing roundels of fried onions on the tournedos.

Tournedos Baltimore

Season the tournedos, and fry them in clarified butter.

Set them in the form of a crown on small tartlets garnished by means of maize with cream.

Upon each tournedos set a roundel of tomato, seasoned and tossed in butter, and a smaller slice of green capsicum, alsotossed in butter, on each roundel of tomato.

Accompanying sauce: a Châteaubriand.

Tournedos Béarnaise

Season the tournedos, and grill them.

Set them on round crusts, half an inch thick, fried inclarified butter; slightly coat the surface of the tournedos with meat-glaze, and surround them with a thread of Béarnaise Sauce.

In the centre arrange a heap of small potatoes cooked inbutter and kept very soft, and sprinkle thereon a pinch ofchopped parsley.

N.B.—The tournedos may be simply coated with glaze and the Béarnaise Sauce served separately.

Tournedos Belle-Hélène

Prepare as many small croquettes of asparagus-tops, shaped like quoits, as there are tournedos, and fry them while the latterare being cooked. Season the tournedos, and fry them in clarified butter.

Arrange them, in the form of a crown, on a dish; place a croquette on each tournedos, and a large, glazed slice of truffleon each croquette.

Tournedos Bercy

Grill the tournedos, and coat them lightly with pale meat-glaze.

Dish them in the form of a crown, and serve a half-melted “Bercy Butter” separately.

Tournedos Bordelaise

Grill the tournedos, and dish them in the form of a crown.

Set a large slice of poached marrow on each, and serve a Sauce Bordelaise separately.

Tournedos Brabançonne

Prepare as many tartlet-crusts as there are tournedos.

Garnish them with very small parboiled Brussels sprouts, stewed in butter; cover these with Mornay Sauce, and set to glaze a few moments before dishing.

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter; set them on the prepared tartlets of sprouts, and surround with a border of small “Pommes de Terre Fondantes”.

Tournedos Castillane

Prepare

as many tartlet-crusts as there are tournedos;
peeled, pressed, and seasoned tomatoes, cooked in butter; these should be in the proportion of one tablespoonful per tartlet;
rings of onion, fried in oil as for “Tournedos Arlésienne”;
a garnish of one tablespoonful of small French beans, cohered with butter, per tartlet.

Season the tournedos; fry them in butter, and dish them in the form of a crown on fried crusts.

Place a tartlet, garnished with a fondue of tomatoes, on each tournedos; all round arrange a border of the fried roundels of onion, and serve the French beans, either in the middle of the dish or separately in a timbale.

Tournedos Cendrillon

Prepare

>as many fine artichoke-bottoms as there are tournedos;
a Soubise purée, combined with chopped truffles, and well buttered.

A few moments before the tournedos are ready, garnish the artichoke-bottoms with the Soubise, and set them to glaze in a fierce oven.

Season the tournedos; fry them in clarified butter, and set them on the artichoke-bottoms, which should be arranged in acircle round the dish.

Tournedos aux Champignons

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter.

Dish them in the form of a crown; drain the butter fromthe sauté-pan; swill the latter with some mushroom cooking-liquor, and add there to a proportional quantity of mushroom sauce. Set to boil for a few minutes, and pour the sauce, with the mushrooms, in the midst of the circle of tournedos.

Tournedos Chasseur

Season the tournedos; fry them in butter, and dish them inthe form of a crown.

Drain the butter away; swill the sauté-pan with white wine, and add to this a quantity of Chasseur Sauce, which should bein proportion to the number of tournedos.

Set to boil for a moment or two, and pour the sauce over the tournedos.

Tournedos Choron

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter.

Set them on crusts fried in butter; round the top of each lay a thread of Choron sauce (№64), and in the middle of each set a medium-sized artichoke-bottom garnished with peas or asparagus-heads cohered with butter.

All round, arrange a border of potatoes, lightly browned inbutter, or heap them in the middle of the crown of tournedos.

N.B.—The sauce may be served separately.

Tournedos Coligny

With a preparation of sweet potatoes, made after the manner of “Duchesse potatoes”, make as many small galettes as there are tournedos, and of the same size as the latter.

Place them on a tray; gild them, and set them to brown inthe oven a few minutes before the tournedos are ready.

Cut some chow-chows in thick, paysanne fashion; par-boil them; stew them in butter, and add thereto an equalquantity of Provençale sauce.

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter; dish them in the form of a crown, on the galettes of potato, and cover them with the paysanne of chow-chow.

Tournedos à l’Estragon

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter.

Dish them in the form of a crown, and on each set either aspray of parboiled tarragon leaves or a lattice composed of the latter. Send separately a thickened gravy with tarragon.

Tournedos Favorite

Season the tournedos; fry them in clarified butter, and dish them, in the form of a crown, on crusts stamped out with anindented cutter and fried in butter.

On each tournedos place a round collop of foie gras, a little smaller than the piece of meat; the collop should be seasoned, dredged, and tossed in butter. On each collop of foie gras puta fine, glazed slice of indented truffle. Garnish the centre of the dish with a fine heap of asparagus-tops cohered with butter, or merely set these in small heaps round the tournedos.

Serve separately a timbale of potatoes (of the size of hazel-nuts) cooked in butter, rolled in pale meat-glaze, and slightly sprinkled with chopped parsley.

Tournedos à la Florentine

Prepare

as many subrics of shredded spinach as thereare tournedos; make them of the same size as the latter, andcook them at the same time as the tournedos;
small, round croquettes of semolina the size of walnuts; these should befried a few minutes before the tournedos are ready.

Grill the tournedos, and dish them, in the form of a crown, on the spinach subrics. The croquettes of semolina may bearranged either in the middle or all round.

Tournedos Forestière

Season the tournedos, and sauté them. Set them on crusts fried in butter. Surround them with alternate heaps of noodlesand potatoes cut into large dice and tossed in butter.

The potatoes may also be placed in the midst of the tournedo swith the noodles all round, or vice versa.

Tournedos Gabrielle

Make a preparation from the white meat of a chicken and truffles—both cut into dice and cohered with the necessary quan-tity of somewhat light “Duchesse-potatoes” paste.

With this preparation make as many small quoit-shaped croquettes as there are tournedos, and fry them while the latter are being cooked.

Season the tournedos, and fry them with oil and butterin equal quantities. Dish them, in the form of a crown, on the prepared croquettes, and on each tournedos set a fineroundel of poached marrow and one slice of truffle.

Around the tournedos arrange some very small, braised, and well-trimmed lettuces.

Tournedos Henri IV

Grill the tournedos, and set them on crusts fried in butter. Round the edge of each tournedos lay a thread of Béarnaise Sauce, and on top of each an artichoke-bottom garnished with very small potatoes (of the size of hazel-nuts) cooked in butter.

N.B.—Instead of putting the sauce on the edge of the tour-nedos, it may be served separately.

Tournedos Judic

Season the tournedos; fry them in butter, and dish them inthe form of a crown on crusts fried in butter. On each tournedos set a crown of truffle slices, with a cock’s kidney in the centre, and surround with braised, trimmed, and quartered lettuces.

Tournedos Lackmé

Prepare

as many small tartlet-crusts as there are tournedos;
the same number of grilled, medium-sized mushrooms;
a garnish of one tablespoonful of broad beans with cream per tartlet.

Season the tournedos, and fry them in clarified butter.

Dish them in the form of a crown, each on a tartlet garnished with broad beans, and set a grilled mushroom on each tournedos.

Tournedos Lesdiguiéres

Select onions sufficiently large to admit of placing the tournedos upon them, and let their number equal that of the tournedos.

Trim their tops, and parboil them almost long enough to cook them.

Then, by means of a small knife, cut out their insides so that they may form little cases. Fill the latter, two-thirds full, with spinach prepared with cream, cover the spinach with Mornay Sauce, and set them to glaze in a fierce oven a few moments before the tournedos are ready.

Grill the tournedos; dish them in the form of a crown, each on an onion.

Tournedos Lili

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter.

Dish them, in the form of a crown, each on a crust of “Pommes de terre Anna”, stamped out with around, even cutter of the same size as the tournedos.

On each tournedos set an artichoke-bottom garnished witha roundel of foie gras tossed in butter, and on the foie gras placea slice of truffle. Send, separately, a reduced and well-buttered Périgueux sauce.

Tournedos Lucullus

Season the tournedos; fry them in clarified butter, and dish them, in the form of a crown, on fried crusts. Surround them with a garnish consisting of quenelles of chicken forcemeat, cocks’ combs, truffles, and blanched olives, and coat the whole with half-glaze sauce prepared with truffle essence.

Tournedos Madeleine

For ten tournedos prepare

ten timbales of a purée of haricot beans. For these timbales the purée of haricot beans must be cohered per lb. with one egg and three yolks, finished with two oz. of butter, put into well-buttered dariole-moulds, and set these to poach fifteen minutes in advance.
Ten small artichoke-bottoms garnished with reduced Soubise.

Season the tournedos; fry them in butter; dish them, andsurround them with the timbales and the artichoke-bottoms, alternating the two garnishes.

Tournedos Maréchale

Season the tournedos; fry them in butter, and dish themupon fried crusts. On each of the tournedos set a large, glazed slice of truffle, and surround them with little heaps of asparagus-heads cohered with butter.

Tournedos Marie-Louise

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter.

Dish them, in the form of a crown, upon crusts one-third inch thick, fried in butter. On each tournedos set a small artichoke-bottom, stewed in butter, garnished in the shape of a dome, by means of a piping-bag, with a purée of mushrooms combined with a quart of very reduced Soubise.

Tournedos Mascotte

Season the tournedos, and fry them in butter.

Have a garnish ready consisting of raw, quartered artichoke-bottoms fried in butter; small, olive-shaped potatoes, also cookedin butter; and olive-shaped truffles.

When about to serve, dish the tournedos in a cocotte with the garnish above described.

Swill the sauté-pan with white wine; add thereto a little gravy; reduce the whole, strain it into the cocotte, and put thelatter in the front of the oven for a minute or two.

Tournedos Masséna

Season the tournedos and fry them in butter; dish them onfried crusts of the same size, and, in the middle of each tour-nedos, set a large slice of poached marrow.

Surround with a row of small artichoke-bottoms, garnished with very stiff Béarnaise Sauce.

Tournedos à la Ménagère

Put into an earthenware cocotte the following vegetables, which should be in proportion to the number of tournedos:—Haricot butter or “Princesse” cut into small pieces, minced new carrots, very small new onions, and very fresh peas.

All these vegetables should be equally apportioned.

Add salt, butter, and a very little water, for the cooking ofthe vegetables should be effected mainly by the concentrationof steam inside the cocotte, which, for the purpose, shouldtherefore be well closed.

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them upon the vegetables in the cocotte at the last moment.

Tournedos à la Mexicaine

Prepare

a fondue of peeled and pressed tomatoes, cookedin butter, well reduced, and in the proportion of one table-spoonful per mushroom;
as many large grilled mushroomsas there are tournedos, while the latter are being fried;
some grilled or fried capsicums in the proportion of half a one pertournedos.

Season the tournedos, and fry them in oil and butter in equal quantities. Dish them each on a mushroom garnished withthe fondue of tomatoes, and cover them with the grilled or fried capsicums.

Tournedos Mikado

Select some fine, rather firm tomatoes—“Mikados”, as they are called—and cut them in two laterally. Squeeze them withthe object of expressing all their juice and seeds; season theminside, and grill them so that they may be ready at the same time as the tournedos.

Season the latter and fry them in butter.

Dish them in the form of a crown, each on a grilled half-tomato, and garnish the centre of the dish with Japaneseartichokes tossed in butter.

Tournedos Mirabeau

Grill the tournedos.

Lay eight fine strips of anchovy fillets upon each, crossing the former after the manner of a lattice. Cover the edges witha crown of blanched tarragon leaves, and set a large stoned olivein the middle of each tournedos.

Send some half-melted anchovy butter separately, and allow two-thirds oz. of it for each tournedos.

Tournedos Mireille

For ten tournedos, prepare in advance,

five croustades from the preparation used for “pommes Duchesse”. To make these croustades, fill some buttered dariole-moulds with the preparation referred to, taking care to press it snugly into them. Dip the moulds into tepid water, turn out, treat the mouldings à l’anglaise, fry them, hollow out their centres, and keep them hot.
A fondue of tomatoes in the proportion of one heapedtablespoonful per croustade.
Five timbales of pilaff rice, made after the same manner as the croustades, and kept hot until required for dishing.

Season the tournedos, fry them in butter, and dish them as soon as they are ready.

Surround them with timbales of rice, and the croustades garnished with the fondue, the two garnishes to be alternated.

Tournedos Mirette

Prepare as many small timbales of “Pommes de Terre Mirette” as there are tournedos.

Turn them out on a dish, sprinkle with grated Parmesan and a few drops of melted butter, and set them to glaze a few minutes before the tournedos are ready. Grill the tournedos, dish them in the form of a crown, and set a timbale of pommes Mirette upon each.

Swill the sauté-pan with white wine; add thereto a little meat-glaze, finish with butter, and pour the resulting sauce over the tournedos.

Tournedos à la Moëlle

Grill the tournedos and dish them in the form of a crown. Lay on each of them a large slice, of poached marrow, and either surround them with Bordelaise Sauce or send the latter to the table separately.

Tournedos Montgomery

Season the tournedos and fry them in butter.

Dish them upon a pancake of spinach, cooked in a tartlet-mould. Deck each tournedos with a rosette of reduced Soubise, made by means of a piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe, and put a fine slice of truffle in the centre of the rosette.

Tournedos Montpensier

Prepare

as many tartlet-crusts as there are tournedos;
a garnish of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter, in the proportion of one heaped tablespoonful per tartlet.

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them upon fried crusts.

On each of them set a tartlet garnished with asparagus-heads, with a slice of truffle in the middle.

Tournedos aux Morilles

Grill the tournedos or fry them in butter.

Dish them in the form of a crown; in the centre arrange aheap of morels tossed in butter, and besprinkle them moderately with chopped parsley.

Tournedos à la Niçoise

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them in the form of acrown.

In the centre of each tournedos set a small heap, consistingof one half-tablespoonful of peeled, pressed, and concassed tomatoes, tossed in butter, together with a little crushed garlic and chopped tarragon.

Surround with small heaps of French beans cohered with butter, and other heaps of small potatoes, cooked in butter, alternating the two garnishes.

Tournedos Ninon

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them upon crusts of pommes Anna, stamped out with a round fancy-cutter of the same size as the tournedos. On each of the latter set a small patty, garnished with asparagus-heads, cohered with butter and combined with a fine and short julienne of truffles.

Tournedos Parmentier

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them in the form of a crown.

In the middle of the dish or round it set a fine heap of potatoes, cut into regular cubes of two-thirds inch side, or raisedby means of an oval, grooved spoon-cutter. The potatoes should be cooked in butter and kept very soft.

Slightly sprinkle the potatoes with chopped parsley.

Tournedos Persane

Prepare as many green capsicums, stuffed with rice moulded to the shape of balls and braised, and as many grilled half-tomatoes as there are tournedos. Also have some fried slices of banana ready, and allow three for each tournedos.

Fry the tournedos in butter and dish them, in the form of a crown, on the grilled half-tomatoes. On each tournedos set a stuffed and braised capsicum.

In the centre of the dish arrange the fried slices of banana in a nice heap. Send separately to the table a Châteaubriand sauce, combined with the reduced braising-liquor of the capsicums.

Tournedos Peruvienne

Prepare, after the manner described below, as many oxalis roots as there are tournedos.

Peel the oxalis roots; cut a slice from underneath them, in order to make them stand upright, and hollow them out to form little cases.

Chop up the pulp extracted from them in the last operation, and add it to a preparation of duxelles, made as for stuffed mushrooms.

Fill the oxalis cases with this preparation, shaping it above their edges after the manner of a dome; besprinkle with raspingsand oil, and put them in the oven in good time for them to beready at the same time as the tournedos.

Grill the tournedos, dish them in the form of a crown, and surround them with the oxalis cases.

Tournedos Piémontaise

Butter as many tartlet-moulds as there are tournedos; fill them with Rizotto à la Piémontaise, combined with white truffles cut into dice, and keep them hot.

Fry the tournedos in clarified butter; dish them, in the formof a crown, on the rizotto tartlets, turned out at the last minute.

Tournenos Provençale

For ten tournedos, prepare

ten medium-sized mush-rooms, stuffed with duxelles, slightly flavoured with garlic, andput in the oven in good time;
ten half-tomatoes à la Provençale.

Fry the tournedos in equal quantities of butter and oil; dish them, in the form of a crown, on fried crusts, with a half-tomato upon each, and around them set the stuffed mushrooms.

Tournedos Rachel

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them, in the form of a crown, on fried crusts one-third inch thick.

On each tournedos set a small artichoke-bottom, garnished with a large slice of poached marrow.

Send a Bordelaise sauce separately.

Tournedos Rossini

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them, in the form of a crown, upon fried crusts.

On each tournedos set a round slice of foie gras, just a little smaller than the former; the slices should be seasoned, dredged, and fried in butter.

On each slice of foie-gras, set a fine slice of truffle.

Tournedos Roumanille

Cut the tournedos a little smaller than usual. Season them; fry them in butter, and dish them in a circle on grilled half-tomatoes.

Coat the tournedos with Mornay sauce, and set them to glaze quickly.

In the middle of each tournedos set a large stuffed and poached olive, encircled by a ring consisting of an anchovy fillet.

In the centre of the dish arrange a fine heap of egg-plant roundels, seasoned with salt and pepper, dredged, fried in oil, and kept very crisp.

-Tournedos Saint Mandé

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them, in the form ofa circle, each on a little cushion of “Pommes de Terre Macaire”, moulded in ordinary tartlet-moulds.

In the centre of the dish set a garnish consisting of peas cohered with butter.

Tournedos à la Sarde

Prepare a garnish of

hollowed, parboiled, and braisedsections of cucumber, stuffed with duxelles, and gratified;
small tomatoes, similarly treated;
small round croquettes of rice flavoured with saffron, thickened with egg-yolks, treateda Vanglaise, and fried.

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them in the form of a crown.

Set a croquette of rice upon each tournedos, and framethe whole with the stuffed cucumber cases and the stuffed tomatoes, laid alternately.

Tournedos Soubise

Grill the tournedos and dish them in the form of a crown.

Serve a light Soubise purée separately.

Tournedos Tivoli

For ten tournedos, prepare ten small grilled mushrooms, and allow one half-tomato tossed in butter for each mushroom.

Fry the tournedos in butter and dish them, in the form of a crown, upon fried crusts. On each tournedos set a grilled mushroom, garnished with a tossed half-tomato, and all round set some fine “pommes souffles” made in ribbon-form, of around shape, and in the proportion of one potato to each tournedos. .

Send a Béarnaise sauce separately.

Tournedos Tyrolienne

For ten tournedos, prepare the following sauce:— Gently cook one chopped onion in butter; add two peeled, pressed, and roughly-chopped tomatoes, salt, pepper, chopped parsley, anda little crushed garlic.

When the tomatoes are sufficiently cooked, add thereto a few tablespoonfuls of poivrade sauce, and set to boil for fiveminutes.

Fry the tournedos in butter; dish them in the form of acrown, and cover them with the prepared sauce.

>133—Tournedos Valençay

Fry the tournedos in butter; dish them in the form of acrown, each on a small, round, and flat croquette of noodles and ham, fried just before dishing up.

Send a Châteaubriand sauce separately.

Tournedos Valentino

Prepare as many pieces of turnips, of the same diameter as the tournedos and one and one-half inch thick, as there are tournedos. Cut them neatly round, stamp them with an even and round cutter, and parboil them until they are almost completely cooked. Hollow them out, by means of a spoon, inside the mark left by the fancy-cutter, and stuff them with a preparation of semolina with Parmesan.

Put these stuffed pieces of turnip in a sauffipan; add a littlewater, butter, and sugar, and glaze them while finishing theircooking-process.

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them in a circle, eachon a stuffed case of turnip.

Tournedos Vert-Pré

Grill the tournedos, and dish them simply with half-melted butter à la Maître-d’Hôtel upon them.

Surround them with alternate heaps of water-cress and freshly-fried straw potatoes.

Tournedos Victoria

Fry the tournedos in butter.

Dish them in a circle, each on a little round and flat croquette of chicken-meat. On each tournedos set a half-tomato tossed in butter.

Tournedos Villaret

Prepare

as many tartlet-crusts as there are tournedos;
a sufficient quantity of very smooth flageolet purée to garnish the tartlets;
a fine grilled tomato per each tournedos.

Grill the tournedos, and dish them on the garnished tartlets. On each tournedos set a grilled mushroom, the hollow of which should have been filled with Châteaubriand sauce.

Tournedos Villeneuve

Fry the tournedos in butter, and dish them in a circle on little quoit-shaped croquettes of chicken-meat, fried at the last moment.

On each tournedos set a crown of small roundels of tongue and truffle, laid alternately, and a small grooved mushroom in the middle.

Send a Châteaubriand sauce separately.

Tournedos Villemer

Grill the tournedos, and dish them in a circle, each on a fried, hollowed-out crust, garnished with truffled Soubise.

On each tournedos set a large slice of truffle coated with meat-glaze.

Filets en Chevreuil

For the “en chevreuil” treatment, the meat used is generally cut from the narrowest end of the fillet of beef. The weight of the pieces cut should average about three oz. each.

After having slightly flattened and trimmed them, lard them with very thin strips of bacon, and marinade them for a few hours in the raw marinade given under №169. When about to cook them, dry them thoroughly, and fry them quickly in hot oil, taking care that the latter be smoking, and therefore hot enough to set the meat and to cause its external moisture to evaporate.

The fillets may be accompanied by all vegetable purées and highly-seasoned sauces, the most suitable of the latter being the Poivrade and the Chasseur.

Sirloin of Reef (Relevé)

Sirloin of beef is that part of the bullock’s back reaching from the haunch to the floating ribs, which is equivalent to the saddle in veal and mutton. This piece, however, cannot properly be called “sirloin”, except when it comprises the fillet or undercut, and the upper fillet (Fr.: contrefilet), so-called to distinguish it from the undercut. If this joint be treated whole, it need only be shortened by suppressing the flank, andby sectioning the ligament lying alongside of the chine on the upper fillet, in different places.

A little fat is left on the undercut, but none whatever mustbe removed from the upper fillet. As a rule, when sirloin of beef is braised, it is cut laterally into pieces weighing from

six to seven lbs. If it is to be roasted, it is best to keep it whole.

When served as a relevé, it is braised or roasted, and is kept under done if so desired. Unless it be of excellent quality, however, braised sirloin generally turns out to be dry.

All garnishes given for “Filet de Bœuf” may be served with sirloin; but, as a rule, the bulkiest, such as the “Richelieu”, the “Provençale”, the “Godard”, &c., are selected.

The accompanying sauce is that indicated for the abovegarnishes.

Porterhouse-Steak (Grill)

Porterhouse-steak is a slice from the sirloin of beef, which may be more or less thick. It is cleared of the flank and of the bones of the chine, and it is always grilled.

It may be served with any of the various garnishes and sauces suited to grills; but it is more often served plain.

Upper Fillet and Ribs of Beef (Relevé)

The upper fillet is that part of beef which lies between the top of the haunch and the floating ribs, alongside of the chine. It may be treated like the fillet, and all the garnishes suited to the latter may also be applied here.

If the piece is to be braised, it should be completely boned; if intended for roasting, it is best to retain the bones. In the latter case, the large ligament should be cut at various pointswith the view of preventing distortion, while the bones constituting the spinous process should be broken close to the point where they join the body of the vertebræ, that they may be easily removed when the meat is being carved.

The upper fillet, especially when it is of good quality, is best roasted.

Ribs of beef may likewise be braised or roasted.

In either case, the meat should be properly trimmed and cleared of all the bones of the spinous process.

This piece should only be used after having been well hung, in order that it may be as tender as possible.

Grilled Sirloin Steaks and Ribs of Beef

The sirloin steak may be cut either from the upper fillet or the ribs of beef, i.e., between two rib-bones. In order that its cooking may be regular, it should not weigh more than from two to three lbs.

Ribs of beef may also be grilled, provided they be sufficiently tender.

They may be braised, too, and in this case they are served with any of the various garnishes given under Fillet of Beef.

Pièce de Bœuf Braisee (Relevé)

The piece of beef called rump is the one preferred for boiling and braising. Whatever be the use for which the meat is intended, the weight of the pieces should not be more than six or eight lbs. at the most, and they should be cut in the length rather than in the thickness, that the cooking process may be facilitated.

All the garnishes of braised sirloin of beef are suited to braised pieces of beef.

Boiled beef is generally accompanied by the vegetables used in its cooking-process, by purées, green or dry vegetables, pastes, macaroni, &c., &c.

Pièce de Bœuf à la Bourguignonne

Lard the piece of beef, and marinade it for three hours in brandy and red wine. Braise it after the manner described under №247; moisten first with the wine of the marinade, and, when the latter is reduced, with some veal gravy and one-half pint of Espagnole sauce per quart of liquid, taking care that the whole moistening reaches the top of the piece of meat. Add a faggot and some mushroom parings; set to boil, andcook gently in the oven.

When the meat is two-thirds cooked, transfer it to another saucepan, and surround it with mushrooms cut into two or four, according to their size, and tossed in butter; breast of bacon, out into dice, blanched and tossed in butter, and some smallonions half-glazed with butter.

Strain the sauce through a sieve over the piece of beef and its garnish, and complete the cooking gently.

A few minutes before serving, put the meat on a dish and glaze it in the oven. Transfer the meat to the dish intended for the table; quickly reduce the sauce if necessary, and pour it over the piece of beef and the garnish.

Pièce de Bœuf à la Cuiller

Select a very square or oval piece of beef, and bear in mind, in selecting it, that it will have to be fashioned to the shape of a case when it has been cooked.

String it, and braise it after the manner described under №247, almost entirely covering it with moistening liquor.

Set it to cook gently; withdraw the piece when the meat is still somewhat firm, and let it cool under slight pressure.

This done, cut out the meat from the inside; leave a thickness of about half-inch round the sides and on the bottom, and the piece thus emptied should constitute a square or oval case, in accordance with the shape originally adopted.

Coat the outside of the whole piece with a mixture of beaten eggs and fine bread-crumbs, combined with Parmesan; sprinkle melted butter over it with a brush, and put the case into a sufficiently hot oven to allow of a crust forming round it.

Meanwhile chop up the meat extracted from the inside of the piece; add thereto a little salted tongue, some braised slices of sweet-bread, and mushrooms; put the whole into a sauté-pan with an Italian or a half-glaze sauce, according to the requirements, and heat this garnish.

N.B.—This preparation was quite common in old-fashioned cookery, but though it is still served occasionally, it is now looked upon more as a curiosity than anything else. As a curiosity, therefore, I chose to include it among these recipes; but it does not follow from this that I in any way recommend it.

Pièce de Bœuf à la Flamande

Lard the piece of beef, and braise it as explained under №247.

Meanwhile prepare the following garnish:—

Cut a nice firm cabbage into four, remove the heart, and parboil it for seven or eight minutes. Drain it; cool it; divide up the quarters, leaf by leaf, so as to remove the hard ribs, and seasonwith salt and pepper.

Mould them to the shape of balls by pressing them in the corner of a towel into balls weighing about three oz. each, or simply put them into a saucepan with a quartered carrot, anonion stuck with a clove, a faggot, six oz. of blanched breast of pork, and a little raw sausage with garlic, which latter must be withdrawn after cooking has gone on for one and one-half hours.

Moisten the cabbage with just sufficient consommé to coverit; add a few tablespoonfuls of good stock-fat; set to boil, andcook gently in the oven for one and one-half hours.

Cut the required quantity of carrots and turnips to theshape of olives; cook them in consommé, and reduce the latterfor the purpose of glazing.
Prepare some potatoes à l’anglaise.

Set the piece of beef on a dish large enough to allow of the former being surrounded with the moulded or plainly-heaped cabbages, the glazed carrots and turnips, and the potatoes à l’anglaise. The last two vegetables should be set in alternate heaps with the cabbages and the bacon (cut into small rectangles) and the sausage (cut into roundels) should be distributed all round.

Serve separately the gravy of the piece of beef, cleared of all grease, reduced to a half-glaze and strained.

Pièce de Bœuf à la Mode Chaude

Lard the piece of beef, which should not, if possible, weigh more than from four to five lbs. The strips of bacon used for larding ought to have been prepared fifteen or twenty minutes in advance, marinaded in a few tablespoonfuls of brandy, and sprinkled with parsley just before being used.

Rub the piece with salt, pepper, and nutmeg, and put it into a basin with one bottle of red wine and one-fifth pint of brandy, and set it to marinade for four or five hours, taking care to turn it over from time to time.

Then set it to braise after the manner described under №247; add its marinade to the moistening, and surround it with three small, boned, blanched, and strung calf’s feet.

When the cooking is three-quarters done, transfer the piece of beef to another saucepan, and surround it with the following garnish:—

About one-quarter lb. of carrots turned to the shape ofelongated olives, and already two-thirds cooked.
Small onions coloured in two-thirds lb. of butter.
The calf’s feet cut into small, square, or rectangular pieces.

Strain the braising-liquor over the whole, and complete the cooking gently. When about to serve, either glaze the piece of beef, or dish it plain; coat it lightly with sauce, and send what remains of the latter, with the garnish, in a timbale.

Pièce de Bœuf à la Mode Froide

Bœuf à la mode is very rarely prepared specially for cold dishing, the remains of a fine piece being generally used forthat purpose. The piece of meat must first be well trimmed. If the quantity of sauce do not seem enough, or if the sauce itself seem too stiff, add a third of its volume of aspic jelly to it.

For moulding, take a terrine, a pâté, a mould, or other utensil capable of holding the piece of meat, its garnish, and its sauce. Deck the bottom of the utensil in any suitable way with thecarrots and the onions, and surround the piece with what remains of the latter and the dice of calf’s foot.

Add the sauce, combined with the jelly, after having passed it through a strainer, and put the whole in the cool for a few hours. Turn out just before serving, and surround with very light, chopped jelly.

Pièce de Bœuf à la Noailles

Lard the piece of beef, and marinade it in brandy and red wine.

This done, dry it thoroughly, and brown it evenly in butter all over; moisten it with its marinade and an equal quantity of veal gravy, and set to cook gently.

When the meat is half-cooked, surround it with two lbs. of minced onions, tossed in butter, and three oz. of rice. Complete the cooking of the piece with onions and rice.

Now withdraw the piece of beef, and quickly rub the onions and the rice through tammy. Reduce this Soubise with rice for a few moments.

Neatly trim the piece of beef; cut it into even slices; reconstruct it on a dish, and between each slice pour a tablespoonful of Soubise purée.

Cover the reconstructed piece of beef with the remainder of the Soubise; sprinkle the surface with two tablespoonfuls of bread-crumbs fried in butter, and some melted butter, and putthe whole in the oven, that the gratin may form speedily.

The Rump

Rumpsteak and Beefsteak.

The rump is that portion of the sirloin of beef which touches the top of the haunch.

It may be braised, but it is more often grilled in slices from one inch to one and one-half inches thick, which are called “rumpsteaks.”

With reference to this subject, it is as well to point out that the term “Beefsteak”, so hackneyed in France, is scarcely used in England, owing to its want of precision.

In France, beefsteak is either a cut from the fillet, the upper-fillet, or the rump, according to the standing of the catering-house which supplies it. But the nature of the piece cannot very well be mistaken, inasmuch as the term beefsteak, which designates it, is generally followed by other French words which reveal its origin, whereas in England the term “Beefsteak” does not convey any particular meaning.

Rumpsteak is either grilled or sautéd, but whatever be themethod of cooking it, it is generally served plain.

All garnishes suited to fillets, however, may be served with it, as also the various butters and sauces generally used with grills.

Langue de Bœuf

Ox tongue is served fresh or salted, but, even when it is to be served fresh, it is all the better for having been put in salt a few days previously. In order to salt it, put it into a special brine, as explained under №172. When salted, it is cooked in boiling water; when fresh, it is braised exactly after the manner of any other piece of meat.

Ox tongue may be served with almost all the garnishes suited to relevés of fillet of beef, but more particularly with the following:—Bourgeoise; Flamande; Milanaise; Noodles or Macaroni with cream, cheese or tomatoes; and all vegetable purées.

The most suitable sauces are:—Madeira sauce, Piquante sauce, Tomato sauce, or their derivatives.

Langue de Bœuf Choucroute

Braise the tongue as described under №247, and glaze it at the last moment. Dish it, and send to the table separately

a timbale of well-braised sauerkraut;
a timbale of potato purée;
a Madeira sauce, combined with the braising-liquor of the tongue, cleared of all grease, and reduced.

Langue de Bœuf Bourgeoise

Braise the tongue in the usual way.

When it is two-thirds cooked, surround it with carrots fashioned to the shape of olives and already two-thirds cooked, and small onions browned in butter.

Complete the cooking gently, and for the rest of the operation, proceed as for “Pièce de Bœuf à la Mode Chaude”.

Langue de Bœuf aux Fèves

Tongue intended for this preparation should be put in salt a few days in advance.

Boil it in the usual way and very gently; glaze it whenabout to serve, and dish it. Send to the table separately (1) atimbale of very fresh, skinned, broad beans, cooked in saltedwater with a spray of savory, and cohered with butter at thelast moment.

(2) A Madeira sauce.

LANGUE de Bœuf FLAMANDE

Braise the tongue, and glaze it at the last moment. Sur-round it with the garnish “à la Flamande” given under the beef

recipe of that name, i.e., braised cabbages, glazed carrots andturnips, potatoes a Vanglaise, rectangles of lean bacon, androundels of sausage.

LANGUES de B(EUF FROIDES

Ox tongues intended for cold dishing should be kept inbrine (№172) for eight or ten days. When about to use them, put them to soak in cold water for a few hours, and then cookthem plainly in water for three hours.

This done, withdraw them from their cooking-liquor; skinthem; cover them with buttered paper, and let them cool. Theobject of the paper is to keep off the air, the tendency of whichis to blacken the surface of the meat.

When quite cool, coat the tongues with a glaze composed ofcne-half lb. of gelatine dissolved in one pint of water; the latteris given a scarlet tint by means of carmine and caramel.

Cold ox tongues are dished amidst aspic jelly dice and curled-leaf parsley.

N.B.—The gelatine glaze described above will be found agreat improvement upon the coating of reddened gold-beaters’skin.

OX TAILS.

Ox tails, sectioned or unsectioned, are usually braised, andonly the thicker half of the caudal appendage is ever used.

QUEUE de Bœuf A d’AUVERGNATE

Section the tail, and braise it in white wine, after recipeNo. 247.

Prepare a garnish of rectangles of lean bacon, large chestnutscooked in consommé and glazed, and small onions cooked inbutter.

Put the sections of the tail in an earthenware cocotte withthe garnish.

QUEUE de Bœuf à la CAVOUR

Section the tail, and braise it in a moistening two-thirds ofwhich is brown stock and one-third white wine. It is well forthe moistening to be somewhat abundant. Set to cook verygently, until the meat falls from the bones, i.e., for a matter ofabout four and one-half or five hours.

This done, dish the sections of the tail in a cocotte; addsome small, cooked mushrooms; clear the cooking-liquor ofgrease; reduce it, and thicken it slightly with fecula. Strain

this thickened cooking-liquor over the sections of the tail andthe mushrooms, and set to boil very gently for ten minutes.

Serve thus in the cocotte set on a dish, and send a timbaleof chestnut purée to the table at the same time.

QUEUE de Bœuf FARCIE

Choose a large ox tail, and bone it carefully without burst-ing it.

Lay it on a napkin, and stuff it with a forcemeat consistingof the following ingredients:—Three-quarters lb. of very leanbeef and one-half lb. of chopped fat bacon, the two mixed withfour oz. of bread-crumbs soaked in milk and pressed; two wholeeggs; three oz. of truffle peel; one-half oz. of salt, a pinch ofpepper, and a very little spice.

Sew up the tail, cover it with a piece of linen after themanner of a galantine, and cook it gently for three hours in avery light stock with vegetables as for boiled beef.

At the end of the three hours take it out of the linen; put itinto a sautepan, the bottom of which should be garnished asfor a braising; add a little of the cooking-liquor of the tail, andcomplete the cooking, basting often the while. Take care tobaste more frequently towards the close of the operation with theview of properly glazing the meat.

When about to serve, dish it, after having removed allstring, and lightly coat the bottom of the dish with a sauceconsisting of the cooking-liquor, reduced and thickened witharrow-root. Send what remains of the cooking-liquor in asauceboat.

Serve separately either a purée, a garnish of braised vege-tables, or one of the sauces suited to pieces of beef.

QUEUE de BGEUF GRILLEE

Cut the tail into sections twice the usual length, and cookthese in a stewpan for five hours with salted water and aromatics.

Drain the sections; dry them well; dip them in meltedbutter, and roll them in very fine bread-crumbs. Sprinkle withmelted butter, and set to grill gently.

Grilled ox tail may be served with any vegetable purée. Anordinary Soubise, or one prepared la Noailles,” as ex-plained under the piece of beef of that name, also suits verywell.

In any case, the Soubise should be sufficiently thick.

Such sauces as à la Diable, Hachée, Piquante, Robert, Tomato, Italienne, &c., are also suited to grilled ox tail.

N.B.—When the adjunct to grilled ox tail is a highly-

c c

386 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

seasoned sauce, the sections should first be covered with a coatof mustard, then dipped in melted butter, and finally rolled inbread-crumbs.

QUEUE de Bœuf en HOCHEPOT

Cut the tail into sections, and put these into a stewpan ofconvenient size, with two pig’s trotters, each of which mustbe cut into four or five pieces, and one pig’s ear. Cover thewhole with cold water; add salt to the extent of one-third oz.per quart of the liquid; set to boil; skim, and leave to cookgently for two hours.

This done, add one small cabbage, cut into quarters, par-boiled and cooled; ten small onions; five oz. of carrots, and thesame weight of turnips, cut to the shape of large, garlic cloves.Set the whole to cook for a further two hours at least.

When about to serve, dish the sections of tail in a circle;put the vegetable garnish in the centre, and surround the latterwith the pig’s ear cut into small, narrow strips, and ten grilledchipolata sausages.

Serve, separately, a timbale of potatoes cooked a I’anglaise.

Various Preparations of Beef.

STEWED STEAKS and ONIONS

Select some steaks one and one-third inches thick; fry themin butter on both sides, and set them to braise in short moisten-ing, with a sufficient quantity of quartered and browned onionsto constitute an abundant garnish.

Leave the whole to cook gently for three hours.

Dish the steak, and surround it with the onions and thebraising-liquor cleared of all grease and reduced.

SALT BEEF

The pieces of beef chiefly selected for salting are brisket, silver side, and round of beef, and these are always boiled fora more or less lengthy period, according to their size.

To the cooking-liquor is added a copious garnish of carrotsand turnips. These are served with the meat, together with asauceboat of cooking-liquor and a suet dumpling, prepared asfollows: —

SUET DUMPLING

Finely chop up some suet; add to it an equal quantity offlour and about one-quarter oz. of salt per lb. of suet and flour.Moisten with just enough water to make a thick paste of

about the same consistence as brioche-paste. Cut this pasteinto portions weighing about one oz., and roll them into smallballs. Put the latter in a sauté-pan containing some boilingbeef cooking-liquor, which need not have been cleared of grease, and let them poach for one and one-half hours.

Now drain the dumplings, and arrange them around themeat with the garnish of carrots and turnips, as explained above.

COLD SALT BEEP

Salt beef, served cold, constitutes an excellent sideboard dishfor luncheons.

It need only be neatly trimmed all round, care being takento preserve all the fat so highly esteemed by some. Indeed, apiece of cold salt fat is sometimes added to that already existingaround and in the meat, in which case the extra quantity isfixed to the beef by means of a hatelet.

PRESSED BEEF

Salt beef also serves in the preparation of “Pressed Beef,”but, for this purpose, the breast is generally used.

After having thoroughly cooked the salted breast of beef inaccordance with the procedure indicated for salt beef, cut it intolarge pieces of the same size as the moulds into which the meatis going to be pressed. Lay the pieces of beef one on top ofanother in a square or rectangular mould, and cover with athick board, cut flush with the inside edge of the mopld. Nowapply pressure, either by means of a strong press or heavyweight, and leave the beef to cool under the applied pressure.

When the meat is quite cold, turn it out; trim it carefullyon all sides, and glaze it, i.e., cover it entirely with a coatingof rather firm, clarified gelatine, brought by means of carmineend caramel to a nice red-brown colour.

STEAK and KIDNEY PUDDING

Cut three lbs. of very lean beef into slices one-third inchthick.

Season these slices with salt, pepper, and nutmeg, and adda little chopped onion and parsley. Take a pudding-basin;line it with a firm layer of suet-dough (№1166), and garnishthe bottom and sides of the basin with the slices of beef.

In the middle put one lb. of kidney of beef, of veal, or ofmutton, cut up as for tossing, and seasoned like the steaks.Moisten with just sufficient water to cover.

Now close up the basin with a layer of the same paste asthat used in lining, pinching it with the latter, all round, thatit may adhere thoroughly. In order to effect this with greater

C C 2

certainty, the respective edges of the two layers of paste maybe moistened.

This done, cover the basin with a buttered and dredgednapkin, fastened on by means of string tied round just beneaththe lip of the utensil. Cook for five hours, either in boilingwater or in steam, and, after having removed the napkin, servethe pudding as it stands.

STEAK PUDDING

Make some rather stiff paste with two lbs. of flour, one andone-quarter lbs. of the chopped fat of kidney of beef, a pinchof salt, and one-quarter pint of water.

With the rolling-pin, roll out this paste to a round layerone-quarter inch thick, and put it into a buttered dome-mouldor pudding-basin.

Cut the lean beef into pieces, and season them, exactly asfor steak and kidney pudding. Fill up the basin with thepieces arranged in layers; moisten with just enough water tocover, and close up the basin with a layer of the same pasteas that used for its lining.

Carefully join the edges of the two layers of paste, assistingthe operation with a little moisture applied by means of a brush;swathe the basin in a buttered pudding-cloth, and fasten thelatter firmly with string.

Put the pudding in a saucepan of boiling water or a steamer, and leave it to cook for three hours if the beef has been cutfrom the fillet, and for four hours if cut from any other piece.

At the end of the required time take the pudding out of thesaucepan and remove the cloth.

Dish on a folded napkin.

II7,_STEAK and oyster pudding

Proceed exactly as for steak and kidney pudding, but takeonly two lbs. of beef, and replace the odd pound by forty fineoysters.

Daube Chaude à la Provençale

Cut four lbs. of shoulder or cushion of beef into cubesweighing about four oz. each. Lard each piece of meat witha strip of bacon two inches long by one-half inch wide, andput the cubes or pieces into a bowl with salt, pepper, a verylittle spice, five or six tablespoonfuls of vinegar, and a glassof red wine. Leave to marinade for two or three hours, andtoss the pieces, from time to time, in the marinading liquor, inorder that each may be well saturated with it. Heat six oz. of

grated bacon in an earthenware stewpan, and brown thereintwelve small onions, fifteen carrots in the shape of olives, twosticks of celery cut into pieces of the same size as the carrots, and four cloves of garlic. Add the marinaded pieces of meat, which should have been properly dried; fry the whole, meatand vegetables, for a further seven or eight minutes, andmoisten with the marinade and two glasses more of red wine.

Complete with one-half lb. of fresh bacon rind, blanched andcut into square pieces of two-thirds inch side; a faggot madeup of parsley stalks, thyme, bay, and, in the centre, a smallpiece of dry lemon rind. Set to boil, completely close the stew-pan, and leave to cook in a moderate oven for six or seven hours.

When about to serve, remove the faggot, clear all greasefrom the gravy, and dish in a hot timbale, or serve the “daube”in the stewpan itself.

Daube à la Provençale Froide

A daube is rarely prepared specially for cold dishing; gene-rally the remains of one already served hot are used.

Take the pieces, one by one, with a fork, and place them ina terrine a ■pâté with the carrots, onions, and squares of baconrind, which have remained almost untouched.

Strain the gravy over them through an ordinary strainer, pressing lightly the while, and leave to cool.

When about to serve, turn out the daube on a cold dish, andsurround with chopped aspic jelly.

CARBONNADES à la FLAMANDE

Cut three lbs. of lean shoulder or cushion of beef into thin, short slices. Season the latter with salt and pepper, and brownthem quickly on both sides in stock fat. At the same time tossone and one-quarter lbs. of minced onions in butter, until theyare well browned.

Put the slices of beef and the onions in alternate layers intoa saucepan, and in their midst place a faggot.

Drain the grease from the sauté-pan in which the slices werefried; swill with one and one-half pints of beer (old Lambic inpreference); add the same quantity of brown stock, thicken withfour oz. of brown roux; finish the seasoning with one and one-half oz. of powdered sugar; set to boil, stirring the while, andstrain this sauce over the slices of beef and the onions.

Cover and cook gently in the oven for from two and one-halfto three hours.

N.B.—Carbonades are served thus, mingled with theonions; but they may also be dished in a timbale and covered

with a Soubise consisting of the onion and the sauce rubbedthrough tammy.

EMINCE de B(EUF

Cold roast or boiled meats may be warmed up in manydifferent ways.

In their preparation, however, the reader should follow onerule, the non-observance of which invariably leads to failure.

Whatever the meat be, it should first be cut into the thinnestpossible slices; set on a dish, and covered with a boiling sauceor garnish, which should effect its warming up. If the meatboil in the sauce or garnish, it toughens, and this, above all, should be avoided when roast meat is used.

Sauces suited to Eminces are the Bordelaise, the Piquante, the Italienne, the Chasseur, the Poivrade, the Périgueux, and the Tomato.

EMINCE de Bœuf en MIROTON

For one lb. of beef mince two fine onions somewhat finely, and toss them in butter until they are evenly and well gilded.

Sprinkle with one-half tablespoonful of flour; set to cookfor a moment, and then moisten with one-half glassful of whitewine and one-half pint of consommé; season with a pinch ofpepper; boil, and leave to cook gently for seven or eight minutes.

The flour may be dispensed with, but, in this case, the whitewine is reduced to two-thirds, one-half pint of half-glaze isadded, and the whole is cooked for seven or eight minutes.

Cut the beef into very thin slices, and set these on a dish.

A minute before serving, add a few drops of vinegar to theonions; cover the meat with the onions and the sauce; standthe dish for a moment on the hob, and sprinkle it slightlywith chopped parsley.

N.B.—When the miroton is prepared with boiled beef, theslices should be cut somewhat more thickly, and left to simmergently in the sauce for as long as possble—an hour or more ifnecessary.

The miroton is then dished with some minced gherkins, sprinkled with raspings, and placed in the oven at the lastmoment for the gratin to form.

, ,77—GOULASH de Bœuf à la HONGROISE

Cut three lbs. of ribs or shoulder of beef into squares weigh-ing about three oz. each. Fry these pieces on a moderate firein four oz. of lard, together with one-half lb. of onions cut intolarge dice, until the latter acquire a nice, even, golden colour.

Season with one-third oz. of salt and the necessary quantity ofpaprika; add one and one-quarter lbs. of peeled, pressed, andquartered tomatoes, and one-sixth pint of water.

Cover and cook in the oven for one and one-half hours.

This done, add one-third pint of water and one and one-quarter lbs. of quartered potatoes to the Goulash.

Continue the cooking in the oven, basting often the while, and do not stop the operation until the moistening-liquor isentirely reduced. When about to serve, dish the Goulash ina timbale.

HACHIS de BGEUF A d’AMERICAINE

Cut the meat into small cubes.

Also cut into dice the same weight of potatoes as of meat.

Season these potatoes and toss them in butter.

This done, put half their quantity into a saucepan with themeat dice, and cohere the whole with a few tablespoonfuls oftomato sauce and reduced veal gravy. Heat without allowingto boil; dish in a hot timbale; distribute the remainder of thepotatoes, which should be crisply fried, over the hash, andsprinkle with a pinch of freshly-chopped parsley.

HACHIS de Bœuf PARMENTIER

Bake some fine potatoes in the oven.

The moment they are done, slice off a piece of their bakedshell, and remove the pulp from their insides by means of aspoon handle.

Crush this pulp with a fork, and toss it in butter as for “Pommes de Terre Macaire”. Then add to it as much beefin dice as there is pulp; two tablespoonfuls of chopped onioncooked in butter per lb. of the preparation; a pinch of choppedparsley, and a few drops of vinegar. Now toss the wholetogether for a few minutes, and then fill the empty potato shellswith the preparation.

Sprinkle with Lyonnaise sauce rubbed through tammy, andadd as much of it as the hash will absorb.

Replace the portion of shell cut off at the first, that thepotatoes may seem untouched; arrange them on a dish, and putthe latter in the oven for ten minutes. When about to serve, dish the stuffed potatoes on a napkin.

TRIPES à la MODE de CAEN

In the preparation of this culinary speciality of Normandy, a very common mistake is often made; to wit, that of usingcalves’ feet instead of those of the ox, an innovation to whichthere are many objections.

In the first place, the gravy of the tripe cannot absorb somuch gelatine, and is indifferently thickened in consequence;secondly, since calves’ feet are much more tender than thoseof the ox, the former get boiled to shreds before the cooking ofthe tripe has been properly effected. This supposed improve-ment on the old method is thus seen to actually run counter tothe end in view; but means there are, nevertheless, wherebythose who insist upon the use of calves’ feet may be satisfied.It is only necessary to braise a number of calves’ feet before-hand, the number being in proportion to the quantity of tripe, and to add these to the latter a quarter of an hour beforeserving.

Another mistake which obtains somewhat widely in respectof this dish is the serving of it in a silver utensil—a methodquite as unreasonable as that of serving a Chaudfroid in anearthenware dish.

By virtue of its simplicity, tripe should be served in eithersandstone or special earthenware stewpans, wherein heat is bestretained; and the operator should rather direct his attention tothe serving of tripe as hot as possible, than to this or thatfanciful method of dishing, which really has no raison d’etrein this case.

The Preparation of Tripe.—Under the head of “beef tripe”are understood: (i) The feet; (2) tripe proper, which comprisesthe Paunch, the Honey-comb Bag, the Manyplies, and theReed.

First soak the tripe in cold water for some considerabletime; then cut it into squares of two inches side.

For the seasoning and flavouring of tripe, complete in allits parts, take: (Seasoning) one-quarter oz. of salt and a pinchof pepper per lb.; (flavouring) four lbs. of onions stuck withfour cloves; three lbs. of carrots; one faggot, comprising twolbs. of leeks, one-third lb. of parsley stalks, a sprig of thyme, and a bay leaf.

Moisten with two quarts of good cider (not likely to turnblack while cooking, otherwise use water); one-half pint ofbrandy or liqueur-cider.

The quantity of the moistening-liquor largely depends uponthe shape of the utensil; a little less will be needed in the caseof a narrow one, and a little more in the case of a wide one.

In any case, however, the tripe should be just covered.

Treatment and Cooking-process.—Take a stewpan or brais-ing-pan, just large enough to hold the tripe and the garnish.

On the bottom of this lay carrots, onions, seasoning, andthe four ox feet, bound and cut into fair-sized pieces.

Add the tripe, placing the faggot in its midst; upon thetripe lay the bones of the feet, broken lengthwise; some slicesof beef-fat, well soaked in cold water; and, finally, themoistening.

Cover the whole with a kind of galette of paste, consistingof flour mixed with hot water and kept somewhat stiff, and fix the paste well on to the edges of the utensil.

Place in the oven, and, when about two hours have elapsedand the paste is well baked, close the utensil with its own cover.

In a regular and moderate oven, allow about ten hours forthe cooking.

The Dishing and Serving.—After taking the tripe out ofthe oven, remove the cover of paste, the bones, the fat, thecarrots, the onions, and the faggot, and by means of a slicewithdraw the pieces of tripe and set them in the special earthen-ware bowls, taking care to distribute the pieces, coming fromdifferent portions of tripe, in such wise as to meet the demandsor fancies of the various consumers.

When the tripe has been transferred to the bowls, clear thegravy of all grease, and dole it out evenly among the numberof receptacles. It is best, now, to put the latter in a bain-marie, for they must only be served quite hot, on chafers orotherwise.

N.B.—(i) To make the dish to perfection, the tripe shouldbe put into special earthenware pots (wherein the heat is moreeffectively concentrated), and cooked in a baker’s or pastry-cook’s oven.

I dealt with the alternative of cooking tripe in a stewpanin order to make provision for those who can avail themselvesof neither special pots nor a baker’s oven.

(2) The measures I prescribe, namely, those of first layingthe slices of beef-fat upon the tripe, and then covering thewhole with a lid of paste, are intended to stop a too rapidevaporation of the liquid—a contingency that must be guardedagainst, more particularly in a kitchen oven—and to preservethe whiteness of the tripe.

The cover of paste would be quite useless if a baker’s ovenwere available, for the latter not only ensures perfectly regularheat, but also wanes regularly.

2. VEAL.

With the exception of veal sweetbreads, it cannot be deniedthat this meat is considerably less popular in England thanabroad, nor does it ever seem to appear on important menus inthis country.

Of course, and the fact must not be lost sight of, Englishveal is admittedly inferior in quality—badly fattened, andmostly red, soft, and dry. Probably, therefore, its unpopularitymay be the indirect cause of its poor quality; for it is incon-ceivable that a country so famous for cattle-rearing as Englandundoubtedly is could not produce veal equal in quality to itsbeef, mutton, and pork, if rearers thought it worth their whileto perfect that special branch of their business. Be this as itmay, almost all the best veal consumed in England comes fromthe Continent, principally from France, Belgium, and Holland;and, in this respect, I not only refer to the larger joints, butto those odd parts such as the head, the liver, the sweetbreads,&c., the continental quality of which is likewise very superiorto that of the English produce.

SELLE de VEAU (Relev<5)

Saddle of veal is the only Relev£ of this meat which issometimes allowed to appear on an important menu, and it is, in fact, a splendid and succulent joint.

It may be roasted, but I should urge the adoption of thebraising treatment, not only as a precaution against dryness, but because of the fine stock yielded by the operation.

Whatever be the method of cooking, trim the saddle on oneside, flush with the bones of the pelvis, and up to the firstribs on the other side. Then cut out the kidneys, leaving athick layer of fat on the under fillets or “filets mignons”;pare the flank on either side, in such wise that what is left ofit, when drawn under the saddle on either side, may just coverthe fillets above referred to. This flank should only be drawnover the fillets after the inside of the joint has been salted;then cover the top surface of the joint with slices of bacon, and tie round with string, five or six times, that the baconand the flank may not shift.

When the saddle is intended for only a small number ofpeople, half of it may be used at a time; that is to say, onefillet, in which case the joint may be cut in two, lengthwise.

The procedure for braising this piece is in pursuance of thedirections given under “The Braising of White Meats” (№248).

The process of braising, whether it be in respect of thesaddle or other veal Relevés, such as the cushion, the loin, theneck, &c., demands particular care, must be accompanied byfrequent basting, and should always be carried on with shortmoistening.

SELLE de VEAU à la CHARTREUSE

Braise the saddle, and glaze it at the last moment, after

having removed the slices of bacon. Set it on a long dish, and, at each end of the latter, place a chartreuse of vegetables.

Round the joint put a few tablespoonfuls of the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease, reduced, and well-strained; andserve what remains in a sauceboat.

Chartreuses of Vegetables.—Take two dome- or Charlotte-moulds, capable of holding two-thirds of a quart. Butter themliberally; line them with buttered paper, and on the latter, overthe bottom and sides of the utensil, lay carrots, turnips, peas, and French beans; each of which vegetables should be cookedin a way suited to its nature. This operation, which is some-what finicking, may either be effected on the plan of a draught-board, or the different vegetables may be superposed in alter-nate row’s of varying colours.

When the moulds are garnished in this way, spread thereon, over the vegetables, a layer of forcemeat softened w’ith beatenwhite of egg; the object of this measure is to keep the vegetabledecoration in position, and this is effected by the poaching ofthe forcemeat before the chartreuse is filled with ifs garnish.

This done, fill the moulds to within one-third inch of theirbrims with a Macedoine of vegetables cohered by means ofstiff Bechamel and cream, and cover with a layer of forcemeat.

Set these chartreuses to poach thirty-five minutes beforeserving, and take care to let them rest for five minutes beforeunmoulding them on either side of the saddle.

SELLE de VEAU à la METTERNICH

Braise the saddle, and, when it is ready, put it on a dish.

Now draw a line within one-half inch of its extreme edge oneither side and end, pressing the point of a small knife alongthe meat in so doing.

Proceed in the same way on either side of the chine, andremove the fillets from the joint, severing them from the bonewith care.

Cut the fillets into regular collops, keeping the knife some-what at a slant.

In the double cavity left by the fillets spread a few table-spoonfuls of Bechamel with paprika; return the colloped fillets

to their respective places in the joint, reconstructing them insuch wise as to make them appear untouched; and betweenthe collops pour one-half tablespoonful of Bechamel and laytwo slices of truffle.

This done, cover the whole surface of the joint withBechamel sauce with paprika, and set to glaze quickly at thesalamander. Now, with a large slice, carefully transfer thesaddle to a dish.

Serve separately (i) the braising-liquor of the saddle, clearedof all grease and reduced; (2) a timbale of pilaff rice.

SELLE de VEAU à la NELSON

Braise the saddle. When it is ready, remove the fillets, proceeding exactly as described under “Selle à la Metternich,”and cut the fillets in a similar manner.

In the cavities left by the fillets spread a few tablespoonfulsof Soubise; return the colloped fillets to their place, and, between the collops, place a thin slice of ham, of the same sizeand shape as the adjacent piece of meat, and a little Soubisesauce.

Having reconstructed the joint, cover its surface with alayer, about one inch thick, of “Soufflé au Parmesan,” com-bined with one quart of truffle purge.

Bind the joint with a strong band of buttered paper, for thepurpose of holding in the soufflé, and set it to cook in amoderate oven for fifteen minutes. After having taken thesaddle out of the oven, remove the paper band, and send it tothe table without changing the dish.

Send the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease, reduced andstrained, to the table separately.

SELLE de VEAU A d’ORIENTALE

Braise the saddle; remove the fillets, and cut them intocollops as for “Selle à la Metternich.” Garnish the cavitieswith Soubise sauce “au currie”; reconstruct the fillets, puttinga little of the same sauce between the collops, and coat thesurface of the piece with the sauce already referred to.

Surround the joint with braised celery, and serve its cooking liquor and a timbale of pilaff rice separately.

SELLE de VEAU à la PIEMONTAISE

Braise the saddle, and cut the fillets into collops as before.When reconstructing the fillets, between the collops put a littleBgchame! sauce, combined with three and one-half oz. of gratedParmesan and three and one-half oz. of grated white trufflesper quart of the sauce.

Coat the surface of the joint with the same sauce, and setto glaze quickly.

Serve the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease and strained, separately; as also a timbale of rizotto & la Piémontaise (№2258).

SELLE de VEAU PRINCE ORLOFF

Braise the saddle and proceed as above, placing betweenthe collops of fillet a little Soubise sauce and a fine slice oftruffle.

Coat the surface of the joint with Mornay sauce, combinedwith one quart of highly-seasoned Soubise, and set to glazequickly.

N.B.—This saddle may be accompanied either by a garnishof asparagus-heads or by cucumbers with cream.

SELLE de VEAU à la ROMANOFF

Braise the saddle; remove the fillets, and cut the latter intocollops as for “Selle à la Metternich.” Reconstruct the fillets, placing a small quantity of minced mushrooms, cohered bymeans of a few tablespoonfuls of cream, between the collops, and coat the surface of the joint with highly-seasoned Bechamelsauce, finished with four oz. of crayfish butter per quart.

Surround the piece with a border of braised half-fennels.Serve the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease, reduced andstrained, separately.

SELLE de VEAU à la TOSCA

Braise the saddle, and then prepare it as for №1183.Almost completely fill the cavities left by the fillets with agarnish of macaroni, cut into short lengths, cohered with cream, and combined with a julienne of truffles.

Reconstruct the fillets upon this garnish and coat the collopswith Mornay sauce, placing a slice of truffle between the collops.The reconstructed fillets thus appear raised on either side of thechine.

Coat the surface of the joint with the same sauce as thatalready used, and set to glaze quickly. Send the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease and strained, to the table separately.

SELLE de VEAU à la RENAISSANCE

Braise the saddle, and glaze it at the last moment. Dish itand surround it with a large heap of cauliflower at either end;on either side, nice heaps of carrots and turnips, raised bymeans of an oval, grooved spoon-cutter, cooked in consommé and glazed; peas; French beans in lozenge-form; asparagus-

heads cohered with butter; and some small potatoes cooked inbutter.

Send the braising-liquor of the joint, cleared of grease andstrained, separately.

SELLE de VEAU à la TALLEYRAND

Prepare twenty studs of truffle, about one inch long andone-third oz. in weight. Stick them upright and symmetricallyinto the meat of the joint, making way for them by means oflittle incisions cut with a small knife. Now envelop the jointin slices of larding bacon, string it, braise it, and glaze it atthe last moment.

Dish it with some of its braising-liquor, cleared of all greaseand reduced.

Serve separately (1) what remains of the braising-liquor;(2) a garnish of macaroni, cut into half-inch lengths, coheredwith one and one-half oz. of butter, three oz. of grated Gruy&reand Parmesan, combined with three oz. of foie gras, cut intolarge dice, and three oz. of a julienne of truffles, per lb. ofmacaroni.

SELLE de VEAU FROIDE

Cold saddle of veal makes an excellent sideboard dish whichadmits of all cold-dish garnishes, such as Macedoines of vege-tables cohered with jelly or mayonnaise sauce; artichoke-bottoms and tomatoes, variously garnished; small, mouldedvegetable salads, &c.

Decorate it with fine, regular, jelly dice; but its usual andessential adjunct is its own braising-liquor, cooked, cleared ofgrease poured carefully away, and served in a sauceboat withouthaving been either clarified or cleared.

All the pieces of veal given as relevés, the cushion, the loin, the fillet, and the fricandeau, may be served cold like the saddle, and are generally much appreciated, more particularly insummer.

LOIN of VEAL

NECK of VEAL

SHORT LOIN of VEAL

CHUMP of VEAL or QUASI

CUSHION of VEAL (Releves)

I have grouped these various Releves together owing tothe identicalness of their garnishes.

The directions I give below for cushion of veal are, with avery few exceptions which I shall point out, applicable to allother large veal joints. In the circumstances, therefore, itwould be quite unnecessary to repeat the recipe in each case.

Loin of Veal is that piece which corresponds with the sirloinin beef. It extends from the floating ribs to the extreme endof the haunch, the latter being cut flush with the pelvic boneat its junction with the femur, and following the direction ofthe former bone. The loin thus consists of two distinct parts: —(i) the caudal region (called the chump end; Fr. quasi), whichcomprises the bones of the pelvis and the haunch, up to thelevel of the latter, and is one of the best pieces of veal forbraising; and (2) the region extending from the haunch to thefloating ribs, comprising the fillet and the upper fillet. Thislast portion also constitutes a choice joint, to which the kidneysare generally left attached, after all their superfluous fat hasbeen removed.

Neck or Best End of Veal consists of the first eight or nineribs, cut two inches above the kernel of meat. The ends of therib-bones are cleared of meat to a height of about two-thirdsinch, and the naked bone is then called the “handle” of thecutlet, which ultimately holds the ornamental frill of paper.

The vertebræ are then suppressed, so that the bones of theribs alone remain; the yellow ligament is cut away; and thebared parts are covered with slices of bacon, tied on by meansof string.

Cushion of Veal consists of an enormous muscle, whichrepresents almost half of the haunch and all the inside part ofit, from the pelvis to its junction with the tibia. A certainquantity of white fat will always be found to lie over the cushion, and it should be carefully reserved.

If the cushion is to be larded, a procedure which I do notadvise, it should be done on the bared part adjoining the fat-covered region.

The various pieces of veal enumerated above may be roasted, but, as in the case of the saddle, I prefer braising, owing tothe greater succulence of the dish resulting from this process, and its accompanying gravy, which has an incomparableflavour. (See Braising of White Meats, №248.)

ADJUNCTS TO CUSHION of VEAL

Cushion of veal, like the other large pieces of veal, admitsof an almost unlimited number of vegetable garnishes, simpleor compound, as also garnishes of various pastes.

From among these garnishes the following may be quoted, viz.:—Bouquetiére, Bourgeoise, Chartreuse, Choisy, Chicorde, Cardoons, Clamart, Braised Celery, Japanese Artichokes, Chow-chow, Endives, Spinach, Braised Lettuce, à la Vichy, à la Nemours, &c.; Jardiniere, Macedoine, Renaissance, &c.

Among the paste garnishes:—Noodles, Macaroni, Spa-ghetti, variously prepared; various Gnocchi, &c.

And, in addition to all these, the garnishes already givenunder Beef Relevés, which need not be repeated here.

I shall, therefore, give only three recipes which are properto cushion of veal; though even these should be regarded asmere curiosities, seeing that, far from recommending them, Iconsider them rather as gastronomical mistakes. But someprovision must be made for outlandish tastes, and, for thisreason alone, I include the following recipes.

NOIX de VEAU en SURPRISE

Braise the cushion of veal, keeping it somewhat firm. Thisdone, set it on a dish, and let it almost cool.

Then cut a slice from it laterally, at a point one-third inchof its height from the top; and, within one-half inch of itsedges, make a circular incision, pressing the point of a sharpknife into the meat, and withdraw the centre of the cushion.Take care to leave the same thickness of meat on the sides ason the bottom, that is to say, about one-half inch. The cushionof veal, thus emptied, should have the appearance of a roundor oval case.

If the meat withdrawn from the centre of the cushion is toserve for the garnish, or is to be used sliced to surround thecase, cut it from out the whole in the largest possible pieces, inorder that slices may easily be cut therefrom.

The inside of the emptied cushion of veal is then garnishedaccording to fancy; the top of the piece that was cut off at thestart is returned to its place, with the view of giving the piecean untouched appearance, and the whole is put in the oven fora few minutes that it may be hot for serving.

The braising-liquor, cleared of grease and strained, shouldbe sent to the table separately.

NOIX de VEAU en SURPRISE à la MACEDOINE

Braise the cushion of veal, and hollow it out as explained

above.

Meanwhile (i) prepare a Macedoine garnish, or mixed Jar-diniere (cohered with butter or cream), the quantity of whichshould be in proportion to the size of the case; (2) cut themeat, withdrawn from the centre of the cushion, into thinrectangles.

Garnish the bottom of the case with a layer of Macedoine, and set thereon a litter consisting of the rectangles of meat.Cover with Macedoine; set thereon another litter of the pieces

of meat, and renew the operation until the case is filled. Finishup with a layer of Macedoine.

Replace the slice cut from the cushion at the start; put thecase in the oven for a few minutes; serve, and send the braising-liquor separately.

-NOIX de VEAU en SURPRISE à la PITHIVIERS

Braise the cushion of veal, and prepare the case as directedabove.

Stuff fifteen larks without boning them; that is to say, puta lump of stuffing about the size of a hazel-nut into each. Frythem in butter with one-half lb. of mushrooms and three oz.of truffles, each of which vegetables should be raw and minced.Cohere the whole with the necessary quantity of half-glaze sauce, flavoured with game essence; put this garnish in the case;return the sliced piece to its place; seal the cover to the caseby means of a thread of almost liquid forcemeat, and set in theoven for seven or eight minutes.

When taking the case out of the oven, surround with thewithdrawn meat, which should have been cut into thin slicesand kept warm until required for the dressing.

The larks may be replaced by quails or thrushes, or othersmall birds, but the name of the particular bird used must bereferred to in the title of the dish.

NOIX de VEAU en SURPRISE à la TOULOUSAINE

Braise the cushion and cut it to the shape of a case asexplained above. Pour therein a garnish consisting of quenellesof chicken forcemeat; lamb sweetbreads, or collops of vealsweetbreads, braised without colouration; cocks’ combs; smallmushrooms, cooked and very white; and slices of truffle; thewhole to be cohered by means of an Allemande sauce, flavouredwith mushroom essence.

Return the piece sliced off at the start to its place, and sur-round with slices of the meat withdrawn from the inside ofthe cushion.

N.B.—All the garnishes suited to Vol-au-vent and timbalesmay be served with cushion-of-veal case, which latter thus stands in the stead of the Vol-au-vent and Timbale crusts.

Finally, I must ask the reader to bear in mind that methodslike those described above have no place in really good cookery, the ruling principle of which should always be simplicity.

NOIX de VEAU FROIDE à la CAUCASIENNE

Cut a cold cushion of veal into slices two inches long byone-half inch wide by one-sixth inch thick.

D D

On each slice spread a little butter seasoned with salt andpepper, combined with finely-chopped chives and anchovy filletscut into dice.

Couple the slices together as for sandwiches; round off theirangles and put them under slight pressure. Prepare a Purée of tomatoes with jelly; mould it in a dome- or Bombe-mould, and let it set on ice.

When this moulding of tomatoes is quite firm, turn it outin the middle of a round, cold dish; arrange the meat slices allround, and border the dish with cubes of very clear veal jelly.

NOIX de VEAU FROIDE à la SU^DOISE

(1) From the widest part of a cold cushion of veal, cut alateral slice one and one-third inch thick, and trim it nicelyround.

(2) Let a coating of aspic jelly set on the bottom of a rounddish, and upon this jelly, when it is quite firm, lay the sliceof veal.

(3) Cut what remains of the piece of veal into slices twoinches long, by one and one-half inch broad, by one-eighth inchthick. Prepare the same number of rectangles of salted tongue, of the same size, though slightly thinner than those of veal.

(4) Cohere a nice vegetable salad with cleared mayonnaise ;mould it in an oiled, Bombe-shaped or narrow pyramid mould, and put it on ice to set.

Coat the rectangles of veal with horse-radish butter; placea rectangle of tongue on each, and finish off these sandwichesby rounding their corners.

For Dishing.—By means of a piping-bag fitted with agrooved pipe, garnish the edges of the slice of veal with athread of previously softened butter.

Turn out the vegetable salad in the centre of the piece ofmeat; set on it the heart of a small lettuce (nicely opened), andarrange the veal and tongue sandwiches all round.

Serve a cold sauce, derived from the mayonnaise, separately.

LONQES, CARRES et NOIX de VEAU FROIDS

What was said in respect of cold saddle of veal likewise

applies to the different pieces mentioned in the above title.They may be coated with aspic jelly and dished with Mace-doines of vegetables, cohered with jelly; small salads, coheredwith cleared mayonnaise; garnished artichoke-bottoms, &c.

The dishes should always be bordered with cubes of veryclear jelly.

FRICANDEAU (Relev6)

Fricandeau is a lateral cut from the cushion of veal; that isto say, a piece cut with the grain of the meat. It should not bethicker than one and one-half inches.

After beating it with a beater or the flat of a chopper, tobreak the fibres of the meat, finely lard the piece of meat on thecut side with strips of bacon, somewhat smaller than those usedfor fillet of beef. Only when the piece is larded may it becalled “Fricandeau for, when not treated thus, it is nothingelse than an ordinary piece of veal. Fricandeau is invariablybraised; but it differs from other braisings of white meat in this, namely, that it must be so cooked as to be easily cut with aspoon. Connoisseurs maintain that Fricandeau should neverbe touched with a knife.

It is glazed at the last moment, like other braisings, and, in view of its prolonged cooking, should be dished with greatcare.

All the garnishes enumerated for cushion of veal may beadapted to Fricandeau.

FRICANDEAU FROID

Cold fricandeau constitutes an excellent luncheon dish. Itis dished and surrounded with its braising-liquor, cleared ofgrease and strained. This braising-liquor sets to a jelly, andis the finest adjunct to fricandeau that could be found.

The piece may be glazed with half-melted jelly, smearedover it by means of a brush.

POITRINE de VEAU FARCIE

This is really a family dish, admirably suited for a luncheonrelev£. It is accompanied chiefly by vegetable purées, but allthe vegetable and other garnishes given under Cushion of Vealmay be served with it.

Breast of veal is prepared thus:—After having boned thepiece, open it where it is thickest, without touching the ends. A kind of pocket is thus obtained, into which put the previously-prepared stuffing, taking care to spread it very evenly.

Now, with coarse cotton, sew up the opening, and rememberto withdraw the cotton when the piece is cooked.

Stuffing for Breast of Veal.—For a piece weighing fourlbs., add to one lb. of very fine sausage-meat (№196), twooz. of dry duxelles, two oz. of butter, a pinch of choppedparsley, tarragon and chives, a small beaten egg, and a littlesalt and pepper.

Cooking.—Breast of veal is usually braised; the moistening

D D 2

should be short and the cooking process gentle. For a pieceweighing four lbs. when stuffed, allow three hours in a moderateand regular oven. Glaze breast of veal at the last moment, asin the case of other braised meats.

TETE de VEAU (Relevd and Entree)

Nowadays, calf’s head is rarely served whole, as was thecustom formerly. Still more rarely, however, is it served ata dinner of any importance; and it has now, by almost generalconsent, been relegated to luncheon menus where, indeed, ithas found its proper place.

After having boned the head, soak it or hold it under arunning tap, for a sufficiently long time to allow of its beingentirely cleared of blood. Then, blanch it for a good half-hour;cool it in cold water; drain it, and rub it with a piece of lemonto avoid its blackening.

If it is to be cooked whole, as sometimes happens, wrap it ina napkin, that it may be easily handled; if not, cut it into pieces.In either case, plunge it immediately into a boiling blanc (№167).

With a view of keeping the calf’s head from contact withthe air, which would blacken it, cover it with a napkin, orcover the liquid with chopped suet. A layer of chopped suetis the best possible means of keeping the air from the calf’shead.

Whatever be the method of serving calf’s head, it is therule to send slices of tongue and collops of brain to the tablewith it.

The tongue may be cooked simultaneously with the head, andthe brain is poached as described under №1289.

TfeTE de VEAU A d’ANGLAISE

Calf’s head a Vanglaise is cooked in a blanc, as explainedabove; but in halves and unboned.

Dish it on a napkin with sprays of very green parsley anda piece of boiled bacon.

Send a sauceboat of parsley sauce (№119a) to the table atthe same time.

TETE de VEAU à la FINANCIERE

Cook the calf’s head in a blanc as already directed. Sup-press portions of the meat, where the latter is thick, in such wiseas to leave only a very little on the skin.

Cut of pieces into squares of one, two or three in. side;

put them in a timbale, and cover them with a financi&re garnish ;adding a few small slices of tongue and brain.

TETE de VEAU à la POULETTE

Cook the calf’s head in a blanc.

Cut the pieces of the head into small slices, somewhat aslant, and toss them into a previously-prepared poulette sauce (№101).

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle with a pinch of choppedparsley.

TETE de VEAU en TORTUE

With a round cutter one, two, or three in. in diameter, cutup the pieces of calf’s head, the meat of which must be entirelysuppressed. For this preparation, only the skin of the headshould be used.

Put the pieces of head in a timbale or on a dish, and coverthem with a Tortue garnish.

Tortue garnish consists of: Small quenelles of veal force-meat with butter; cock’s combs and kidneys; small mushrooms;stoned, stuffed and poached olives; slices of truffle; gherkinscut to the shape of olives (these should only be put into thesauce at the last moment); and Tortue sauce.

This garnish comprises, besides, among unsauced ingre-dients: Slices of tongue and calf’s brain; small, trussed cray-fish, cooked in court-bouillon; fried eggs, the half of whose rawwhites should be suppressed; and small croutons of bread-crumb, fried in butter at the last moment.

T^TE de VEAU à la VINAIGRETTE OU A d’HUILE

Set the boiling pieces of calf’s head on a napkin, lying ona dish. Surround them with slices of tongue, collops of brain, and sprigs of very green, curled-leaf parsley.

Serve separately, on a hors-d’oeuvre dish, without mixingthem, capers, chopped onion and parsley.

Send to the table at the same time a sauceboat of vinai-grette or sauce & l’huile, prepared by mixing one part ofvinegar, two parts of oil, and one part of the calf’s-headcooking-liquor, together with the necessary salt and pepper.

ESCALOPES de VEAU

Collops of veal may be cut from either the fillet or thesaddle; but they are more often cut from the cushion. Theirweight varies from three to four oz., and they should alwaysbe cleared of all connective tissue. They may be fashionedto the shape of ovals, or curve-based triangles, and they should

406 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

be more or less flattened, according to their use. Thus, whenthey are to be plainly tossed, to be afterwards served with asauced garnish or with a sauce, they are simply beaten in orderto break the fibres of the meat, without flattening the lattertoo much; but if, on the contrary, they are to be treated aVanglaise, they should be beaten very thin with the moistenedbeater.

In either case, they should be cooked somewhat quickly inclarified butter; for, if their cooking lag at all, their meathardens.

All the garnishes of veal cutlets, and a large number ofthose of the cushion, may be served with the collops. Thesegarnishes may be set on the same dish with the collops whenthe latter are plainly tossed; but, in the case of collops treateda Vanglaise, the garnish or sauce which accompanies themshould be served separately, lest its moisture soften the crispcoating of the collops.

GRENADINS

Grenadins are veal collops larded with rows of very thinbacon strips, and cut somewhat thicker than ordinary collops.They are really small fricandeaux, the braising of which is acomparatively lengthy operation; for their cooking must be thesame as that of the fricandeaux, and needs quite as much atten-tion. In order that the grenadins be not too dry, they shouldbe frequently basted with their braising-liquor.

When they are cooked, glaze them -rapidly, and dish themwith one of the garnishes given for the cushion of veal.

GRENADINS FROIDS en BELLEVUE

This dish may be prepared in several more or less compli-cated ways; here is a simple way:—

Take as many shell-shaped hors-d’oeuvre dishes as there aregrenadins. Let a thin coat of jelly set on the bottom of each, and set thereon a slight decoration composed of bits of carrot, turnip, peas, French beans in lozenge-form, &c. Put a gren-adin, larded side undermost (i.e., upside down) into each hors-d’oeuvre dish; add enough melted aspic jelly to reach half-wayup the thickness of the grenadin.

When this jelly has set, lay on it, all round the grenadin, a border consisting of carrots, turnips, French beans and peas.Sprinkle these vegetables with a few drops of jelly, so as tofix them, and keep them from floating, and then fill up thehors-d’oeuvre dishes with jelly.

When about to serve, dip the hors-d’oeuvre dishes into hot

water; turn out the grenadins on a very cold dish, and arrangethem on it to form a crown.

Surround with a border of very clear, chopped aspic jelly.

RIS de VEAU (Sweetbreads)

Veal sweetbreads may be looked upon as one of the greatestdelicacies in butchers’ meats, and may be served at any dinner, however sumptuous. Select them very white, entirely free ofblood stains, and leave them to soak in fresh water, whichshould be frequently changed, for as long as possible; or, betterstill, place them under a running tap.

To blanch them (an operation the purpose of which is toharden the surface) put them in a saucepan with enough coldwater to cover them completely, and bring to the boil gently.Let them boil for ten minutes; withdraw them and plunge theminto a basin of fresh water.

When the sweetbreads are cold, trim them; that is to say, cut away all cartilaginous and connective tissue; lay thembetween two pieces of linen, and put them under a light weightfor two hours.

Now lard them with fine bacon, tongue or truffle, subject tothe way in which they are to be served. They may also bestudded with either tongue or truffles, or they may be leftunlarded and unstudded, and plainly braised, just as they are.

Certain it is, that neither studding nor larding enhances in any way whatsoever their quality or sightliness.

Veal sweetbread consists of two parts, as unequal in qualityas in shape. They are: the “kernel” or heart sweetbread, which is the round and most delicate part, and the “throat,”or throat sweetbread, which is the elongated part, and not ofsuch fine quality as the former.

In a well-ordered dinner, heart sweetbreads only should beused, as far as possible.

There are three ways of cooking sweetbreads, viz.:—Braising(№248), poaching (№249), and grilling (№259). In thefollowing recipes, therefore, the reader will kindly refer to thedirections given under one of the numbers just mentioned, according as to whether the dish is to be a braising, a poaching, or a grill.

ATTEREAUX de RIS de VEAU à la VILLEROY

Cut some veal sweetbreads (preferably the throat kind) intoroundels one and one-third in. in diameter and one-third in.thick. Prepare an equal number of mushrooms and truffleroundels, somewhat thinner than those of sweetbread.

Impale these roundels on little wooden skewers, the size ofmatches, and about four in. long; alternating the differentproducts in so doing. Dip these skewers into a Villeroy sauce, and set them on a dish. When the sauce is quite cold, removethe attereaux; clear them of any superfluous sauce that mayhave fallen on to the dish; dip them in an anglaise (№174);roll them in very fine and fresh bread-crumbs, and turn themwith the fingers, so as to shape them like small cylinders.Plunge them into plenty of hot fat eight minutes before serving-, drain them on a piece of linen; carefully withdraw the woodenskewers and put little silver ones in their place. Dish theattereaux on a folded napkin, with fried parsley in the centre;or set them upright in a circle, on a rice or semolina cushionlying on a dish, and put some very green, fried parsley in themiddle.

Serve a Périgueux sauce separately.

CHARTREUSE de RIS de VEAU

Prepare (1) one and one-quarter lbs. of fine forcemeat withcream (№194); (2) two poached, veal throat sweetbreads, cutinto slices; (3) one-half lb. of cooked mushrooms, cut intolarge slices, and three oz. of sliced truffles; (4) a garnish ofcarrots and turnips, raised by means of a tube- or spoon-cutter, or cut into grooved roundels two-thirds inch in diameter; andpeas and French beans. Each of these vegetables should becooked in a way befitting its nature, and kept somewhat firm.

Liberally butter a quart Charlotte-mould. Line its bottomand sides with the vegetables, arranged in alternate and vari-coloured rows, and spread thereon a layer of forcemeat, one-half inch thick.

This done, set upon the layer of forcemeat just spread, another of slices of sweetbread, mushrooms, and truffles; coverthe whole with a coat of forcemeat; start the operation againwith a litter of sweetbread, mushroom, and truffle slices, andproceed as before until the mould is filled. Finish with a layerof forcemeat. Cover with a round piece of buttered paper, andset to poach in a bain-marie and in the oven, for from forty-fiveto fifty minutes.

When taking the chartreuse out of the bain-marie, let itstand for seven or eight minutes, that the ingredients insidemay settle a little, and then turn it out in the middle of around dish; place a large, cooked, grooved, and very whitemushroom on the top of it, and encircle its base with a crownof small braised and well-trimmed half-lettuces.

Send to the table, separately, a sauceboat of Velouté flavoured with mushroom essence.

RIS de VEAU BONNE MAMAN

Cut the vegetables intended for the braising stock into ashort and coarse julienne, and add thereto an equal quantityof similarly-cut celery.

Braise the veal sweetbreads with this julienne, after themanner described under №248, and moisten with excellentveal stock. Take particular care of the vegetables, that theydo not burn.

When the sweetbreads are ready, glaze them and dish themin a shallow, round cocotte with the julienne of vegetables andthe braising-liquor all round.

Cover the cocotte, and serve it on a folded napkin,

Crepénette de Ris de Veau

For this dish take either some white throat sweetbreads,

or some remains of the latter, from which slices have alreadybeen cut.

Chop up the throat sweetbreads or the remains, togetherwith their weight of raw calf’s udder.

Season with one-half oz. of salt and a pinch of pepper; addfive oz. of chopped truffles and two whole eggs per lb. of themince-meat. Mix the whole well; divide it up into portionsweighing three oz., and wrap each portion in a piece of verysoft pig’s caul.

Sprinkle with melted butter and bread-crumbs, and grillgently.

Dish in the form of a crown, and serve a Périgueux sauceat the same time.

RIS de VEAU à la CEVENOLE

Braise the veal sweetbreads and glaze them at the last

moment.

Dish them with a heap of small glazed onions at either end, and serve, at the same time, a purée of chestnuts and a sauce-boat of thickened gravy.

RIS de VEAU DEMIDOFP

Lard the sweetbreads with bacon and truffles; braise thembrown, and only half-cook them. Then place them in a shallowcocotte, and surround them with the following garnish:—Twooz. of carrots and the same weight of turnips, both cut intogrooved crescents; an equal quantity of small onions, cut intolarge roundels, and some celery cut paysann e-fash ion. Allthese vegetables should be first stewed in butter.

Add the braising-liquor of the sweetbreads, and one oz. ofminced truffles, and complete the cooking of the former. Clearof all grease and serve in the cocotte.

ESCALOPES de RIS de VEAU BERENGERE

Braise the veal sweetbreads and cut each piece into fourmedium-sized slices. Trim each slice with an even, oval fancy-cutter; and, by means of a piping-bag fitted with an even pipe, one-sixth inch in diameter, garnish the edge of each slice witha thick border of mousseline forcemeat, combined with choppedsalted tongue. Set the slices on a tray, and put them in amoderate oven to poach the forcemeat.

Now, by means of another piping-bag fitted with a groovedpipe, garnish the centre of the slices with a nice rosette of fineand very white Soubise purée; and, in the middle of eachrosette, place a little ball of very black truffle.

Set each slice on a thin, oval crouton of the same size as theformer and fried in butter. Serve at the same time, in a sauce-boat, the braising-liquor of the sweetbreads, cleared of allgrease, and a timbale of fresh peas.

ESCALOPES de RIS de VEAU à la FAVORITE

Blanch the veal sweetbreads; cool them under pressure, andcut them into slices. Season the latter and toss them inclarified butter.

At the same time, toss an equal number of slices of foie grasof the same size as those of the sweetbread, after havingseasoned and dredged them.

Dish in a circle, alternating the foie gras and the sweet-bread slices; put a crown of sliced truffle on the circle alreadyarranged; and, in the centre, pour a garnish of asparagus-headscohered with butter.

Send, separately, a Madeira sauce flavoured with truffleessence.

ESCALOPES de RIS de VEAU GRAND DUC

Blanch and cool the sweetbreads, and cut them into slices.Season the latter and cook them in butter without colouration.Dish them in the form of a crown, placing a large slice oftruffle between each; coat with Mornay sauce, and glazequickly.

When taking the dish out of the oven, arrange a heap ofasparagus-heads cohered with butter, in the middle of the dish, and serve instantly.

4”

ESCALOPES de RIS de VEAU JUDIC

Blanch and cool the sweetbreads, and cut them into slices.

Prepare and poach a roll of chicken forcemeat, large enoughto allow of slices being cut therefrom of the same size as thoseof the sweetbreads.

Season, dredge, and toss the slices of sweetbread in butter, and dish them in the form of a crown, each on a roundel of thepoached chicken forcemeat.

On each slice place a very small, braised, and well-trimmedlettuce, a slice of truffle, and a cock’s kidney.

Send a sauceboat of thickened gravy separately.

ESCALOPES de RIS de VEAU à la MARECHALE

Braise the veal sweetbreads, keeping them somewhat firm, and cut them into slices.

Treat the latter a Vanglaise; brown them in clarified butter, and dish them in a circle, placing a fine slice of truffle betweeneach.

In the middle of the dish arrange a fine heap of asparagus-heads cohered with butter.

RIS de VEAU GRILLES

After having blanched, cooked, and trimmed the sweet-breads, set them to get quite cold under pressure. Then cutthem in two, laterally, at their thickest point; dip each pieceinto melted butter, and grill gently, basting frequently the whilewith melted butter.

The sweetbreads may also be grilled whole, but the processis perforce a more lengthy one.

RIS de VEAU GRILLES CARMAGO

Cook a brioche, without sugar, in a fluted mould, the aper-ture of which is a little larger than the veal sweetbreads. Care-fully remove the top of the brioche, following the direction ofthe fluting, and withdraw all the crumb from the inside.

Fill this kind of croustade, two-thirds full, with a garnishconsisting of peas, prepared la française,” and carrots “hla Vichy,” in equal quantities.

Set the grilled veal sweetbreads on this garnish, and coverit with slices of grilled bacon.

Dish on a napkin and serve at once.

RIS de VEAU GRILLE GISMONDA

Prepare a shallow croustade, without colouration, in an oval

flawn ring of the same length as the veal sweetbread. Grill theveal sweetbread after the manner already described.

Garnish the bottom of the croustade with equal quantities ofartichoke-bottoms and mushrooms, minced raw, tossed in butter, and cohered with cream sauce.

Set the grilled sweetbread on the garnish, and place thecroustade on a folded napkin.

Serve, separately, a slightly buttered meat-glaze.

RIS de VEAU GRILLE JOCELYNE

Cut some potatoes into roundels one and one-half inch thickand of the same size as the veal sweetbread. Stamp the roundels, close up to their edges, with a round, even cutter, and cook themin butter. Grill the sweetbread at the same time.

When the potatoes are cooked, withdraw all their inside insuch wise as to give them the appearance of cases, and fill themwith Soubise prepared with curry.

Dish them and set the grilled sweetbread upon them. Onthe sweetbread lay a small half-tomato and a green half-capsicum, both grilled.

RIS de VEAU GRILLES SAINT-GERMAIN

Blanch, prepare, and grill the veal sweetbreads as alreadyexplained. Set them on a long dish, and surround them withalternate heaps of small potatoes cooked in butter and of anice golden colour, and carrots cut to the shape of elongatedolives, cooked in consommé and glazed.

Serve a Béarnaise Sauce and a purée of fresh peas, separately.

RIS de VEAU DES GOURMETS

Braise the veal sweetbreads, and, as soon as they are ready, set them in a round, flat cocotte, just large enough to hold them.Cover them with raw truffles, cut into thick slices; strain thebraising-liquor over the whole; cover the cocotte, and seal thecover to the edges of the utensil by means of a thread of softpaste, made simply from a mixture of flour and water.

The object of this last precaution is to prevent any escapewhatsoever of steam, and to hold the aroma of the truffleswithin.

Put the cocotte into a very hot oven for ten minutes; set iton a dish, and serve it as it stands. The cover should be re-moved only when the dish reaches the table.

RIS de VEAU aux QUEUES d’^CREVISSES

Stud the sweetbreads with truffle and braise them withoutcolouration. Dish them, and, on either side, set a heap of cray-fishes’ tails (in the proportion of four to each person), coheredwith cream.

4U

At either end place some crayfishes’ carapaces (in the pro-portion of two to each sweetbread), garnished with chickenforcemeat combined with crayfish butter, and poached.

Serve, separately, an Allemande sauce prepared with cray-fish butter.

RIS de VEAU à la REGENCE

Stud the sweetbreads with truffles, and braise them withoutcolouration.

Dish them; pour their reduced braising-liquor round thedish, and surround them with a R^gence garnish, arranged inalternate heaps representing the constituents of the former, which are: quenelles of fine truffled chicken forcemeat; smallgrooved mushrooms; curled cocks’ combs, and truffles cut tothe shape of olives. Serve separately an Allemande sauce, flavoured with truffle essence.

RIS de VEAU SOUS la CENDRE

Stud the veal sweetbreads with truffles and tongue, andthree-parts braise them.

Cut some slices of salted tongue of the same size as thesweetbreads, garnish them with slices of truffle, and set a sweet-bread on each.

Cover each sweetbread with a layer of short paste (№2358); set them on a tray; gild; flute; make a small incisionon the top of the paste to allow the escape of steam, and bakein a hot oven for thirty minutes.

When withdrawing them from the oven, pour in some half-glaze sauce with Madeira, and dish them on a napkin.

RIS de VEAU à la TOULOUSAINE

Stud the sweetbreads with truffles and braise them withoutcolouration.

Dish them with the Toulousaine garnish, arranged in heapsall round, and surround the latter with a thread of meat-glaze.

Toulousaine garnish comprises small chicken-forcemeatquenelles; cocks’ combs and kidneys; very white button-mush-room heads, and slices of truffle.

Serve, separately, an Allemande flavoured with mushroomessence.

CROUSTADE de RIS de VEAU à la FINANClfeRE

Prepare (1) the required number of small, fluted croustades, baked without colouration in rather large tartlet moulds. (2)The same number of slices of braised veal sweetbread as thereare croustades, and of the same size. (3) A financi&re garnish, consisting of very small chicken-forcemeat quenelles; grooved

44

button-mushrooms, and sliced cocks’ combs and kidneys. Thewhole covered by half-glaze with Madeira, in the proportion ofone tablespoonful per croustade. (5) As many fine slices oftruffle as there are croustades.

Put a tablespoonful of the garnish into each croustade; setthereon a slice of sweetbread; put a slice of truffle upon that, and dish the croustades on a folded napkin.

Pâté CHAUD de RIS de VEAU

Butter an ordinary round hot raised pie, or a Charlotte-mould. Take about one and one-half lbs. of short paste androll it into galettes, one-third inch thick; fold the paste overafter having dredged it slightly; draw the two ends gentlytowards the centre, to form a kind of skullcap, which, whenplaced in the mould, immediately lines the latter. Avoid makingfolds in the paste while preparing the skullcap, for they wouldspoil the look of the patty when turned out.

Press the paste on the bottom and sides of the mould, thatthe latter may impart its shape to its lining, and cut the pro-jecting paste to within half inch of the brim. Now coat thebottom and sides of the mould with a layer of chicken force-meat, of an even thickness of two-thirds of an inch.

Pour into the centre of the mould a garnish composed ofslices of poached veal sweetbread; sliced and cooked mush-rooms and sliced truffles; the whole covered with reduced andsomewhat stiff Allemande sauce, flavoured with mushroomessence.

Cover the garnish with a coating of forcemeat, and closethe patty with a layer of paste, the edges of which should bemoistened and sealed down all round the brim of the mould.Pinch the rim of paste inside and outside, and finish off withleaves of paste stamped out with a fancy-cutter, ribbed by meansof the back of a knife, and laid upon the paste cover. Gild withbeaten egg; make a central slit for the escape of steam, and setto bake in a hot oven, for from forty-five to fifty minutes.

When taking the patty out of the oven, turn it out and dishit on a napkin.

TIMBALE de RIS de VEAU

Butter a timbale mould and decorate its sides with thin piecesof noodle paste, in the shape of lozenges, crescents, indentedrings, discs and imitation-leaves. Excellent ornamentalarrangements may be effected thus; but the reader should bearin mind that the simplest are the best.

Prepare a skullcap of paste as explained under №1241;

Relevés and ENTREES

slightly moisten the ornamental work in the mould, that it maycling to the paste of the timbale, and line the latter with pastewhich should be well pressed in all directions, that it may takethe shape of the mould.

Then pierce the paste on the bottom, to prevent its blisteringduring the baking process; line the bottom and sides withbuttered paper, and fill the timbale, three-quarters full, withsplit peas or lentils.

Cover the latter with a round piece of paper, and close thetimbale by means of a round layer of paste, which should besealed down round the edges. Make and trim the crest of thetimbale; pinch it inside and out, and finish the cover, by meansof applied imitation-leaves of paste, superposed to form a kindof dome.

Set in a moderate oven, and when the timbale is baked, remove its cover with the view of withdrawing the lentils orpeas and the paper, the sole object of which was to providea support for the cover. Besmear the inside of the timbale witha brush dipped in the beaten white of an egg; keep it for aminute or two in front of the oven, with the view of dryingit inside; turn it out, and spread upon its bottom and sides avery thin coat of chicken or ordinary forcemeat, the purposeof which is to shield the crust from the softening effects of thejuices of the garnish.

Put the timbale in the front of the oven for a moment ortwo, that this coating of forcemeat may poach.

Garnish.—Veal sweetbreads, braised without colourationand cut into collops; small mushrooms; cocks’ combs andkidneys; small quenelles of chicken, mousseline forcemeat, orroundels of chicken forcemeat rolls one-third inch thick, trimmedwith the fancy-cutter; and slices of truffles, half of which shouldbe kept for the purposes of decoration.

Cover this garnish with Allemande sauce, prepared withmushroom essence. Pour it into the timbale, just beforeserving; upon it set the reserved slices of truffle, in the form ofa crown; replace the cover; dish upon a folded napkin, andserve.

N.B. (1) As already stated the garnish of the timbale may becohered with a half-glaze sauce, flavoured with Madeira ortruffle essence.

(2) In this garnish, whether it be cohered by means of awhite or brown sauce, the slices of veal sweetbreads are alwaysthe principal ingredient; but, subject to the circumstances, theother details may be altered or modified.

VOL au VENT de RIS de VEAU

Vol au vent, which formerly held the place of honour onbourgeois menus, has now fallen somewhat into the back-ground; nevertheless, I wished it to appear among the recipesin this work.

The preparation of the paste: Make the vol au vent crustas explained under №2390.

Garnish.—Prepare it exactly as explained under “Timbalede ris de Veau.” This garnish may also be cohered with abrown sauce, and its minor ingredients may be modified; butthe slices of veal sweetbread must always stand as the domin-ating element.

Whatever be the selected kind of garnish, vol au vent shouldalways be accompanied by medium-sized, trussed crayfish, cooked in court-bouillon.

Dishing.—Set the vol au vent crust upon a dish covered witha napkin; pour the garnish into it; decorate with slices oftruffle; arrange the crayfish round the edge, and lay the coverupon the crayfish.

RIS de VEAU à la RICHELIEU

Braise the veal sweetbreads exactly as described under “Risde Veau Bonne Maman,” taking care to keep the braising-liquor sufficiently plentiful to well cover the sweetbreads in thecocotte.

When the sweetbreads are in the cocotte, together with thejulienne of vegetables and a julienne of truffles, strain thebraising-liquor over the whole; leave to cool well, and, whenthe liquid has turned to a jelly, remove the grease that hasrisen to the surface.

Dish the cocotte on a napkin.

RIS de VEAU à la SUEDOISE

Poach the veal sweetbreads without colouration, and, whenthey are quite cold, cut them into thin and regular collops.Spread some horse-radish butter over the latter, and cover witha slice of tongue of the same size as the underlying collop.

Bake a crust without colouration in a Hawn ring, of a sizein proportion to the number of slices, and garnish it with avegetable salad cohered with mayonnaise. This crust mustnecessarily be made in advance.

Upon the salad now set the collops, either in the form of acrowm or in that of a small turban; in the middle place a finelettuce heart, the leaves of which should be slightly opened out.

relevés and entries

PALETS de RIS de VEAU A d’ECARLATE

Poach the sweetbreads; when they are cold, cut them intocollops half-an-inch thick, and trim them with a round, evencutter. Stamp out some roundels of salted tongue with thesame cutter, but let them be only one-eighth inch thick, andtwice as many as the collops of veal sweetbread.

Coat the latter, on either side, with butter prepared withmustard; and cover with a roundel of tongue.

Set the prepared collops on a tray; let the butter harden, coat with jelly, and deck the middle of each quoit with a fineslice of truffle.

Arrange the quoits in a circle on a round dish; put somechopped jelly in the centre, and border the dish with veryregularly-cut jelly dice.

Serve a horse-radish sauce and an Italian salad separately.

Calf’s Liver.

Calf’s liver is served chiefly as a breakfast or luncheonentree.

Nevertheless, in ordinary menus, it is sometimes served asa relev6, braised and whole.

FOIE de VEAU BRAISE à la BOURGEOISE

Lard the piece with large, seasoned strips of bacon, as for “Bœuf à la Mode.” Brown it slightly in the oven, and thenput it into a saucepan garnished for braising. (№247.)

Moisten with one pint of white wine, and reduce it com-pletely. This done, moisten again with brown stock, addingone pint of Espagnole sauce per quart of the moistening.

It is sufficient if the moistening and the sauce reach a littleabove the middle of the piece of liver.

When the cooking is two-thirds completed, transfer the liverto another saucepan; surround it with carrots, shaped like elon-gated olives and half-cooked in consommé; and some smallonions, half-cooked in butter.

The amount of this garnish of carrots and onions shouldnaturally be in proportion to the size of the piece of liver.

Strain the sauce over the whole, and complete the cookinggently in the oven. Dish the liver with the carrots and onionsall round; reduce the sauce if necessary, and pour it over thegarnish.

N.B. The latter need not be arranged symmetrically.

On the contrary simplicity should be made a feature of thesebourgeois dishes.

E E

FOIE de VEAU A d’ANGLAISE

Cut the calf’s liver into fairly thin slices, from two-and-a-halfoz. to three oz. in weight. Season them with salt and pepper;dredge them, and toss them in butter. Grill an equal numberof rashers of bacon.

Dish the slices of liver and the rashers of bacon alternately, and sprinkle them with the butter in which the liver was cooked, or with a brown butter.

BROCHETTES de FOIE de VEAU

Select a pale piece of calf’s liver and cut it into square piecestwo-thirds of an inch thick. Season with salt and pepper, andtoss the pieces in butter, just to stiffen them.

Put them into a basin with an equal quantity of blanchedsalted breast of pork, cut into squares, and of slices of cookedmushrooms. Add a few tablespoonfuls of stiff Duxelles sauce, and toss the whole together, that each particle of the various in-gredients may become coated with Duxelles.

This done, impale the squares of liver and pork and theslices of mushrooms upon a ringed skewer, alternating themin so doing; sprinkle copiously with fine raspings and meltedbutter, and set to grill gently.

These brochettes are served, either on a maître-d’hôtel butter, or on a Duxelles, Fines Herbes, an Italian or other sauce.

,250—FOIE de VEAU A d’ESPAGNOLE

Cut the calf’s liver into slices weighing three and a half oz.;season these with salt and pepper; dredge them; sprinkle themwith oil, and grill them gently.

•Meanwhile, prepare:—(1) As many grilled half-tomatoes asthere are pieces of liver; (2) onions cut into thin roundels, sea-soned, dredged, and fried in oil; (3) a proportionate quantityof fried parsley.

Arrange the grilled slices of liver along the centre of anoval dish; place a half-tomato upon each; and, on one side, set the fried onions, on the other, the fried parsley.

- FOIE de VEAU Sauté aux FINES HERBES

Cut the calf’s liver into slices, as above; season these withsalt and pepper; dredge them, and toss them in butter.

Arrange the slices in a circle on a round dish; and eitherpour the herb sauce over the slices, or serve it separately.

PAIN de FOIE de VEAU

For a calf’s liver loaf made in a quart mould: Cut one lb. ofcalf’s liver into dice, and finely pound these together with one-

third oz. of salt, a pinch of pepper, and a little nutmeg. Add, little by little, five oz. of very cold frangipane panada, and twoeggs.

Rub through a sieve; put the forcemeat in a bowl; workit over ice, and finish it with two tablespoonfuls of choppedonions, cooked in butter, without colouration; the yolks of twoeggs, and quarter pint of thick cream, added by degrees.

Pour this forcemeat into a well-buttered quart Charlotte-mould; knock the latter gently on a folded serviette, with theview of settling its contents, and put it to poach in the ovenin a bain-marie, for about forty-five minutes.

When taking the loaf out of the oven, let it stand for fiveminutes, that the forcemeat inside may thoroughly settle;turn it out on a round dish, and cover it with a Duxelles, Italienne, Bordelaise, brown caper, or other sauce.

COTES de VEAL

Veal cutlets may either be grilled or sautéd, but the secondmethod of cooking them is, in most cases, preferable.

When they are sautéd, the cutlets should be cooked in clari-fied butter, over a somewhat fierce fire and in a utensil largeenough to hold them without crowding.

This done, dish them; pour away the butter in which theyhave been cooked; swill the saucepan, i.e., dissolve the concen-trated gravy adhering to the sides and bottom of it with a liquidin keeping with the garnish; either mushroom cooking-liquor, white or red wine, or Madeira, &c.; and add this swilling-liquor, reduced, to the accompanying sauce. The latter isgenerally a buttered half-glaze, but the best adjunct to vealcutlets is a pale meat glaze, moderately buttered.

All vegetable and paste garnishes, given under Cushion ofVeal, suit veal cutlets. I must therefore beg the reader torefer to those recipes, as circumstances may dictate; and restrictmyself to a few formulae which, in my opinion, are suited moreparticularly to veal cutlets.

COTE de VEAU à la BONNE FEMME

Put the veal cutlet into an earthenware saucepan, with oneand one-half oz. of butter, and brown it well on both sides. Addsix small onions cooked in butter, three oz. of potatoes cutinto roundels; and complete the cooking gently in the oven, keeping the saucepan covered.

Serve the preparation in the saucepan as it stands.

*255—COTE de VEAU en CASSEROLE

Heat one oz. of butter in an earthenware saucepan; insertthe veal cutlet, seasoned, and cook it gently, taking care to turnit over from time to time.

At the last moment, add a tablespoonful of excellent vealgravy, and serve in the saucepan.

COTE de VEAU en COCOTTE à la PAYSANNE

Toss the veal cutlet in butter, in the cocotte, with two smallslices of blanched salted breast of pork. Add four small onions, and two small, long potatoes, cut paysanne-fashion; and com-plete the cooking of the cutlets and the garnish very gently inthe oven.

Send the preparation to the table in the cocotte.

—Côte de Veau à la Dreux

Stud the kernel of the veal cutlet with tongue, ham andtruffle, and cook it gently in butter. This done, trim it to thequick on both sides, that the studding may be clean and neat;dish it with a frill on the bare bone, and, beside it, arrange asmall garnish of quenelles, mushrooms, cocks’ combs andkidneys, and turned and blanched olives.

Pour a little half-glaze sauce, flavoured with truffle essence, over the garnish.

Côte de Veau Milanaise

With a moistened butcher’s beater, flatten the meat in such-wise as to reduce it to half its normal thickness. Dip the vealcutlet into beaten egg; roll it in bread-crumbs, mixed with halfas much grated Parmesan, and cook it in clarified butter, 01butter and oil in equal quantities.

Dish it with a frill on the bare bone, and the garnish besideit.

Milanaise garnish consists of cooked macaroni, seasonedwith salt, pepper and nutmeg, and cohered with butter, grated Gruyère and Parmesan cheeses, and very red tomato purée; andcombined with a julienne of very lean cooked ham, saltedtongue, mushrooms and truffles, heated in Madeira.

1259—COTE de VEAU PAPILLOTE

Toss the veal cutlet in butter, and prepare, meanwhile:—

(1) Two tablespoonfuls of Duxelles sauce, combined witha cooked and sliced mushroom.

(2) Two heart-shaped slices of ham, of about the same sizeas the cutlet.

(3) A doubled sheet of strong paper, cut to the shape ofa heart and well-oiled.

Spread out the sheet of paper, and, in the middle thereof, lay a slice of ham; spread a tablespoonful of Duxelles on thelatter; put the cutlet on the sauce; cover it with the remainderof the Duxelles, and finish with the other slice of ham.

Fold the sheet of paper so as to enclose the whole; pleatthe edges nicely; put the cutlet on a tray, and blow out thepapillote in a fairly hot oven. When taking it out of the oven, transfer it to a dish, and serve instantly.

COTE de VEAU POJARSKI

Completely separate the meat of the veal cutlet from thebone; clear it of all skin and gristle, and chop it up with half itsweight of butter, salt and pepper. Mass this mince-meat closeup to the bone, shaping it like a cutlet, and cook the whole inclarified butter, turning it over very carefully in the process.

Dish with a suitable garnish.

COTE de VEAU ZINGARA

Cook the veal cutlet in butter; at the same time prepare a sliceof raw ham, cut to the shape of the cutlet, and likewise tossedin butter.

Dish the cutlet; set the slice of ham upon it, and surroundwith a few tablespoonfuls of Zingara sauce.

Zingara sauce is prepared thus: Reduce a few tablespoonfulsof white wine and mushroom cooking-liquor to half. Addone-fifth pint of half-glaze, two tablespoonfuls of tomato sauce, one tablespoonful of veal stock, one oz. of a julienne of tongue, mushrooms and truffles; and set to boil for a few seconds.

COTE de VEAU FROIDE en BELLE VUE

Let a little jelly set in a utensil somewhat resembling a cutletin shape. Trim the veal cutlet; decorate it with various littlevegetables, and sprinkle the latter with half-melted jelly, so asto fix them.

Put the cutlet on the layer of set jelly, inside the utensil, and let it lie with its decorated side undermost.

Add enough jelly to cover the cutlet, and let the formeiset.

This done, pass the blade of a small knife (dipped in hotwater) round the cutlet; set the utensil for a moment upon anapkin dipped in hot water, turn out the cutlet with care, andset it on a cold dish, with a border of chopped aspic, and afrill on the bone.

COTE de VEAU FROIDE RUBENS

Trim the veal cutlet; coat it with half-melted aspic, and coverit with young hop shoots, cohered with tomato sauce cleared bymeans of aspic.

Let the sauce thoroughly set, and then put the cutlet betweentwo layers of aspic as explained above.

N.B. Cold veal cutlets may also be served Belle-vuefashion, after the very simple manner described under “Gren-adins en Belle-vue” (№1217).

ROQNON de VEAU

When sautéd after the usual manner, veal kidney admits ofall the preparations given for sheep’s kidney. (See the chapteron Mutton.)

* shall now, therefore, only give those recipes which areproper to veal kidney.

ROQNON de VEAU en CASSEROLE

Trim the veal kidney and only leave a very slight layer offat all round it.

Heat one oz. of butter in a small, earthenware saucepan, alsocalled “cocotte put the seasoned kidney into the latter, andcook it gently for about thirty minutes, taking care to turn itoften the while.

At the last minute sprinkle it with a tablespoonful of goodveal gravy. Serve it in the cocotte as it stands.

ROQNON de VEAU en COCOTTE

Prepare the veal kidney and fry it in butter, as in the case ofthe “en casserole” dish. Surround it with one and one-halfoz. of small pieces of blanched bacon, tossed in butter; one andone-half oz. of raw, quartered mushrooms, also tossed, andone and one-half oz. of small blanched potatoes, of the sizeand shape of garlic cloves, and the same quantity of small, glazed onions. Complete the cooking of the whole gently.

At the last minute, add a tablespoonful of good, veal gravy, and serve the cocotte as it stands.

ROGNON de VEAU GRILLE

Trim the veal kidney, and leave a slight layer of fat all roundit. Cut it in half lengthwise, without completely separating thetwo halves, and impale it on a small skewer, with the viewof keeping it in shape.

Season with salt and pepper, and grill it gently; basting itoften the while with melted butter.

Send separately, either a Maître-d’hôtel, a Bercy, or otherbutter suited to grills.

ROGNON de VEAU à la LIEGEOISE

Prepare the veal kidney as for " en casserole.” One minutebefore serving, add one small wineglassful of burned gin, twocrushed juniper berries, and one tablespoonful of good vealgravy. Serve in the cooking-utensil.

ROGNON de VEAU à la MONTPENSIER

Trim the veal kidney, leaving a slight coating of fat all roundit, and cut into five or six slices. Season the latter, toss themin butter over a brisk fire, and transfer them to a plate.

Swill the saucepan with one tablespoonful of Madeira, andadd thereto three tablespoonfuls of melted meat glaze, a fewdrops of lemon juice, one and one-half oz. of butter, and a pinchof chopped parsley.

Dish the pieces of kidney, or set them in a timbale;sprinkle them with the sauce, and in their midst set a heapof asparagus-heads, cohered with butter, and one and one-halfoz. of truffle slices.

Rognon de Veau Portugaise

Cut up the veal kidney, and toss it in butter, after the mannerdescribed under №1269.

Dish the pieces in a circle on a dish; set a very small, stuffedhalf-tomato upon each, and garnish the centre of the dish witha very reduced tomato fondue. Surround the kidney with asauce prepared as directed above.

ROGNON de VEAU à la ROBERT

Heat one oz. of butter in a small cocotte-, put the seasonedveal kidney therein; fry it over a brisk fire, and set it to cookin the oven for about fifteen minutes. Serve the kidney as itleaves the oven, and complete the procedure, at the table, inthe following manner:—

Transfer the kidney to a hot plate. Place the cocotte on aspirit lamp; pour into the former one glassful of excellentliqueur brandy, and reduce to half. Meanwhile, quickly cutthe kidney into extremely thin slices, and cover these with anoverturned plate.

Add to the reduced liqueur brandy one coffeespoonful ofmustard, one oz. of butter cut into small pieces, the juice of aquarter of a lemon, and a pinch of chopped parsley; and workthe whole well with a fork, with the view of effecting the leason.

Put the sliced kidney into this sauce, together with the

gravy that has drained from it; heat the whole well, withoutboiling, and serve on very hot plates.

TENDRONS de VEAU

The tendrons are cut from breast of veal. They are, in fact, the extreme ends of the ribs, including the cartilage of thesternum.

If the tendrons are braised, treat them after the mannerdescribed under “The Braising of White Meats” (№248); or, simply stew them in butter; moisten them with excellent vealstock, and baste them frequently while cooking them. Theymay also be treated like an ordinary veal sauté, from which theyonly differ in shape, and the various preparations of which maybe adapted to them.

The garnishes best suited to them are those of early-seasonvegetables, and, as a matter of fact, the latter, together withsuch pastes as noodles, macaroni, spaghetti, &c., are the gar-nishes most often served with them.

BLANQUETTE de VEAU A d’ANCIENNE

Cut the veal tendrons into pieces weighing about three oz.Then, slightly blanch them; cool them, and put them into asaucepan with enough white stock to cover; add a very littlesalt; set to boil, and skim.

For two lbs. of tendrons, add one small carrot; one fair-sized onion, stuck wdth a clove; a faggot, consisting of oneleek, parsley stalks, and a fragment of thyme and bay; and setto cook gently for one and one-half hours.

Prepare a white roux from one and one-half oz. of butterand one and one-half oz. of flour; moisten with one pint ofveal cooking-liquor; add one oz. of mushroom parings, andcook for a quarter of an hour, despumating the sauce the while.

Transfer the pieces of tendron, one by one, to a sauté-pan withtwelve small onions cooked in consommé, and fifteen small, cooked and very white mushrooms. Finish the sauce with aleason of two egg-yolks, mixed with three tablespoonfuls ofcream and a few drops of lemon juice; strain it over the vealand its garnish; heat without boiling; dish in a timbale, andsprinkle with a pinch of chopped parsley.

N.B. This blanquette may also be prepared with noodlesor ckpes, instead of with ordinary mushrooms.

BLANQUETTE de VEAU aux CELERIS,

CARDONS, ETC.

Prepare the blanquette exactly as explained above, and set itto cook with the veal and the vegetable selected for the garnish,

i.e., either small heads of celery cut into two or four, or car-doons, cut into pieces and well blanched. The endives are notblanched; they need only be well washed and put with the veal.

When cooked, drain the vegetables, trim them, and dishthem in a timbale with the veal and the sauce; the latter pre-pared as directed and strained over the meat.

BLANQUETTE de VEAU aux NOUILLES

Proceed as for “Blanquette & l’ancienne,” but suppress thegarnish of onions and mushrooms.

When the blanquette is dished, set thereon heaps of noodles, parboiled and cohered with butter, and cover these with rawnoodles tossed quickly in butter; allow three oz. of tossednoodles per lb. of those cohered.

FRICASSEE de VEAU

Fricassee differs from blanquette in this, namely, that thepieces of veal in the former are stiffened in butter without colour-ation.

When the meat has been well stiffened, besprinkle it withabout one oz. of flour per lb.; cook this flour with the meat fora few minutes; then moisten the fricassee with white stock;season, and set to boil, stirring the while. All the garnishesof mushrooms and vegetables given for blanquette may beserved with fricassee; but in the case of the latter, both the meatand the garnish are cooked in the sauce, the leason of whichis effected by means of egg-yolks and cream, as for blanquette.

FRICADELLES

Fricadelles are a kind of meat balls, somewhat like thosecommonly prepared in private households. They are madefrom raw or cooked meat, in the following manner: —

Fricadelles with Raw Meat.—For ten fricadelles, eachweighing three and one-half oz., chop up one lb. of very leanveal, cleared of all fat and gristle, together with two-thirds of alb. of butter. Put the whole into a bowl, and add theretofive oz. of soaked and well-pressed crumb of bread, two eggs, half an oz. of salt, a pinch of pepper and a little nutmeg, andtwo oz. of chopped onion cooked in butter without colouration.

Mix the whole well, and divide it up into portions weighingthree and one-half oz.

Fashion these portions to the shape of quoits, by first rollingthem into balls on a flour-dusted board, and afterwards flatteningthem out with the flat of a knife.

Heat some butter or very pure fat in a sauté-pan; put the

fricadelles therein; brown them on both sides, and then com-plete their cooking in the oven.

This done, set them on a round dish, and serve them, either with a vegetable purée, a Piquante or a Robert Sauce.

Fricadelles with Cooked Meat.—For ten fricadelles, eachweighing two and one-half oz., chop one lb. of cooked veal, fat and lean, somewhat finely.

Put it into a bowl with a large pinch of salt, another ofpepper, and a little nutmeg. Add the pulp of three fair-sizedpotatoes, baked in the oven; three oz. of chopped onions, cookedin butter without colouration; one large egg, and one table-spoonful of chopped parsley. Mix well; divide up into portionsof the weight already given, and shape and cook them as inthe previous case.

These fricadelles are served with vegetable purées and thesauces suited to those prepared from raw meat.

PAUPIETTES de VEAU

Paupiettes or scrolls are made from extremely thin slices ofveal, four in. long by two in. wide. After having seasoned them, cover them with forcemeat or very fine mincemeat; roll them, with their forcemeat-coat inside, into scrolls, and tie themround, once or twice, with string, that they may keep theirshape while cooking. They are sometimes covered with thinrashers of bacon. Paupiettes are always braised, gently andprotractedly.

They are generally garnished with vegetable purées; butthey may be served just as well with all vegetable garnishes.

By making them half the usual size, they may, after havingbeen braised, serve as the garnish for a timbale, together withnoodles, gniokis, spaghetti, or with Financi&re, Milanaise orNapolitaine garnish, &c.

Sautés de Veau

The pieces best suited to veal sautés are: the breast and the shoulder, as also those parts of the haunch other than thecushion and undercushion.

Sauté de VEAU à la MARENGO

Heat one pint of oil in a sauté-pan, until it smokes. Puttherein two lbs. of veal, cut into pieces, each weighing two oz., and fry until the latter are well set. Add a chopped half onionand a crushed half-clove of garlic, and fry again for a fewmoments.

Drain away the oil, tilting the sauté-pan with its lid on, for

the purpose; moisten with a quarter of a pint of white wine;reduce, and add two-thirds of a quart of thin Espagnole sauce, one and one-half lbs. of tomatoes, pressed and cut into pieces(or one pint of tomato sauce), and a faggot.

Set to boil, and cook in the oven gently for one and one-halfhours.

At the end of that time, transfer the pieces of veal, one byone, to another saucepan with fifteen small glazed onions, andfive oz. of mushrooms. Reduce the sauce; strain it over theveal and its garnish, add two large pinches of concassed parsley, and cook for a further quarter of an hour.

When about to serve, clear of all grease, dish in a timbale, and surround with small heart-shaped croutons of bread-crumb, fried in oil.

SAUT6 de veau chasseur

Cut the veal into pieces as above, and fry these well inbutter or oil.

Drain away the grease; moisten with one quart of brownstock, add two tablespoonfuls of tomato purée, and a faggot;set to boil, and cook in the oven gently for one and one-halfhours.

Transfer the pieces to another saucepan; strain; reduce their cooking-liquor by a quarter, and add it to one-quarter of a pint of Chasseur sauce.

Pour this sauce over the pieces of veal, and cook againfor a quarter of an hour. Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle withchopped parsley.

Sauté de VEAU PRINTANIER

Fry the pieces of veal in butter. Moisten with two-thirds ofa quart of brown stock and one-fifth of a pint of half-glaze; adda faggot; boil, and cook in the oven gently for one hour.

This done, transfer the pieces to another saucepan; addthereto a garnish of carrots, new turnips, and small, new pota-toes; strain the sauce over the veal and the garnish, and cookfor a further three-quarters of an hour.

Dish in a timbale and distribute over the sauté a few table-spoonfuls of peas and French beans in lozenge-form, bothcooked a Vanglaise.

Sauté de VEAU à la CATALANS

Cut up, sauté, and cook the veal gently for one and one-halfhours, as for №1280.

Transfer the pieces of veal to another saucepan, and add

to them three small peeled and pressed tomatoes, quarteredand tossed in butter; ten small onions cooked in butter; six oz. of raw, quartered mushrooms; ten chestnuts, three-parts cookedin consommé, and eight Chipolata sausages.

Reduce the sauce to one-third of a pint; strain it over theveal and its garnish; cook for a further quarter of an hour, and dish in a timbale.

Sautés de Veau Divers

Veal sauté may also be prepared with mushrooms, finesherbes, egg-plant, tomatoes, or “Currie h l’lndienne,” &c.

PAIN de VEAU

Prepare “Pain de Veau” exactly as directed; but substitute for the liver some very white veal.

Pain de veau is generally accompanied by a white sauce, such as velout£ prepared with mushroom essence, Allemande sauce prepared with mushrooms, Supreme sauce, &c.

CALF’S FEET

Calf’s feet serve chiefly in supplying the gelatinous elementof aspics, and the body of braising stock. They are rarelyused in the preparation of a special dish; but, should they beso used, they may be cooked and served after the mannerdirected in the recipes treating of calf’s head.

CALVES’ TONGUES

Provided the difference of size be allowed for, calf’s tonguemay be prepared like ox tongue, and served with the samegarnishes. (See Ox Tongue, Nos. 1153 to 1158 inclusive.)

CALF’S BRAINS and AMOURETTES

Calf’s brains form the most wholesome and reparative dietfor all those who are debilitated by excessive head-work; andthe same remark applies to the brains of the ox and the sheep.

The amourettes mentioned here, which almost alwaysaccompany ox brains, are only the spinal marrow of the ox orthe calf. This may be used in the preparation of a few specialdishes; but all the recipes dealing with brains may be appliedto it.

THE COOKING of BRAINS

Carefully remove the membrane enveloping the brains or theamourettes, and put them to soak in fresh water, until they arequite white. Put the brains in a saucepan with enough boiling

court-bouillon (№163) to cover them well; skim and then setto cook gently.

Brains have this peculiarity, namely, that prolongedcooking only stiffens them; thus, calf’s brains only take halfan hour to cook; but they may cook for two hours more withoutharm, seeing that the process only tends to make them firmer.

CERVELLE à la BEAUMONT

Cut the brains into slices; on each slice put a layer of gratinforce-meat (№202) prepared from foie gras and softened bymeans of a little cold, brown sauce, and a slice of truffle. Re-construct the brains by putting the coated slices together again.

Roll some puff-paste remains into a galette one-fifth of aninch thick, the diameter of which should be in proportion tothe size of the brains under treatment. Put the brains in themiddle of the galette, and cover them with the same forcemeatas that laid on the slices; sprinkle with chopped truffles; moistenthe edges of the paste, and draw these over the brains so as toenclose the latter completely.

Gild; make a slit in the top for the escape of steam, andbake in a hot oven for fifteen minutes. After taking thepie out of the oven, pour a few tablespoonfuls of Périgueuxsauce into the former, and dish on a napkin.

CERVELLE au BEURRE NOIR

Slice the brains; set the slices on a dish, and season themwith salt and pepper.

Cook two oz. of butter in the frying-pan until it is slightlyblackened; throw therein a pinch of parsley pluches, andsprinkle the brains with this butter. Pour a few drops ofvinegar into the burning frying-pan, and add it to the brains.

CERVELLE au BEURRE NOISETTE

Slice and season the brains as above. Cook the butter untilit has acquired a golden colour and exhales a nutty smell; pourit over the brains, and finish with a few drops of lemon juiceand a pinch of chopped parsley.

CERVELLE à la MARECHALE

Cut the brains into regular slices, one-third of an inch thicktreat them a Vanglaise with very fine bread-crumbs, and brownthem in clarified butter.

Dish them in the form of a circle, with a slice of truffle oneach, and garnish the centre of the dish with a fine heap ofasparagus-heads cohered with butter.

CERVELLE à la POULETTE

Prepare half a pint of poulette sauce (№101), combinedwith three oz. of small, cooked, and very white mushrooms.

Add the brains, cut into slices; toss them gently in the sauce, taking care lest they break; dish them in a timbale, andsprinkle with a pinch of chopped parsley.

CERVELLE à la VILLEROY

Cut the raw brains into slices; season them, and poach themin butter.

Dip the slices into an almost cold Villeroy sauce, in suchwiseas to cover them with a thick coating of it. Leave to cool, andtreat them a Vanglaise. Set to cook for a few minutes beforeserving, and dish on a napkin with fried parsley.

Serve a light Périgueux sauce separately.

VOL au VENT de CERVELLE

Prepare a vol-au-vent crust, as explained under №2390.Slice the brains, and put the slices into half-a-pint of Allemandesauce, with twelve quenelles of ordinary forcemeat, poached justbefore dishing up; four oz. of small, cooked mushrooms, andone oz. of truffle slices, five or six of which should be reserved.

Pour the garnish into the vol au vent; set upon the latter thereserved slices of truffle, and dish on a folded napkin.

AMOURETTES à la TOSCA

Poach one lb. of amourettes, as explained above, and cutthem into lengths of one in.

Prepare a garnish of macaroni cohered with butter and gratedParmesan, and add thereto four tablespoonfuls of a crayfishcullis per four oz. of macaroni; three crayfishes’ tails for eachperson, and two-thirds of the pieces of amourettes. Toss well, in order to thoroughly mix the whole; dish in a timbale; coverthe macaroni with what remains of the pieces of amourettes, andcover them slightly with crayfish cullis.

MUTTON, GRASS LAMB and HOUSE LAMB

Releves and Entrees.

From the culinary standpoint, the ovine species suppliesthree kinds of meat, viz: —

Mutton—properly so-called when the meat is derived fromthe adult animal.

Lamb—the young, weaned sheep, not yet fully grown, themeat of which is the more highly esteemed the younger theanimal is.

House Lamb—the sheep’s unweaned young that has not yetgrazed.

The “Pauillac” lamb, which is imported from France, isthe most excellent example of the last kind. Good house lambsare also killed in England; they are quite equal to Pauillaclamb, but their season is short. As regards ordinary Englishmutton and lamb, however, the delicacy and quality of thesemeats are unrivalled.

But for its greater delicacy and tenderness, grass lamb, which corresponds with what the French call “agneau de pr£-sal6” is scarcely distinguishable from mutton. The recipessuited to it are the same as those given for mutton; and all thatis necessary is to allow for differences of quality in calculatingthe time of cooking.

House lamb, the white flesh of which is quite different, admits of some of the mutton recipes; but it is generally pre-pared after special formulae, the details of which I shall givehereafter.

When served roasted, hot or cold, mutton and grass andhouse lamb are always accompanied by mint sauce, the recipefor which I gave under №136.

In view of the similarity of their preparations, and in orderto avoid finicking repetitions, I have refrained from giving sepa-rate recipes for lamb and mutton respectively. The reader willtherefore bear in mind that the formula relating to mutton alsoapply to grass lamb.

SADDLE of MUTTON

BARON or PAIR of HIND-QUARTERS of MUTTON

DOUBLE or PAIR of LEGS of MUTTON

FILLETS of MUTTON

NECK of MUTTON (Relevés)

Saddle of mutton is that part of the sheep which reaches fromthe bone of the haunch to the floating ribs.

Baron of mutton comprises the saddle and the two legs, i.e., a pair of hind-quarters.

Double consists of the two unseparated legs, minus thesaddle.

The Baron and the Double are almost always cuts of lamb.

The fillet is one half of the saddle, when the latter is cutinto two, lengthwise; that is to say, divided down the middle insuchwise as to bisect the spinal column. These fillets are some-times boned, rolled over with the kernel of meat in the centre, and strung, in which case the skin should be removed beforerolling. Saddle of mutton, before being roasted, should becleared of all its superfluous underlying fat; and the flanksshould be so shortened as to just meet when drawn over thefillets. The overlying skin should be removed, and the saddleshould be strung in five or six places to keep it in shape.

In the case of a saddle of lamb, the skin need not be com-pletely removed, but slit in various places. As to neck ofmutton, this should be shortened as for the cutting of ordinarycutlets; the skin and the bones of the chine should be removed, as also the meat at the end of the rib-bones, down to two-thirdsin. from the extremity of each. The cushion is then coveredwith slices of bacon, tied on with string.

When the piece is roasted and dished, a frill should beplaced on the end of each bared bone. Neck of mutton oughtnever to comprise more than nine to ten ribs, counting from thefloating ones; it should consist of rather less if anything.

Mutton Relevés allow more particularly of vegetable and ricegarnishes.

Garnishes with sauces do not suit them so well, even whenthe pieces are braised. As for paste garnishes, such asmacaroni, noodles, gniokis; they are seldom used.

Garnishes for mutton relevés should therefore be chosen, inpreference, from among the following, the details of which Igave under “Filet de Bœuf” (Nos. 1044 to I074) and which Irecall hereafter: —

Andalouse, Bouquetiere, Chatelaine, Clamart, Dauphine,

Dubarry, Duchesse, Japonaise, Jardiniere, Lorette, Macedoine, Montmorency, Moderne, Nivernaise, Orientate, Petit-Due, Provençale, Renaissance, Richelieu, St. Germain.

Apart from these compound garnishes, the following simplegarnishes also suit admirably, either alone, or separated bysome kind of potato preparation: —

Braised Lettuce, stuffed with ordinary forcemeat or rice.

Cabbages, moulded to the shape of small balls, braised andstuffed with fine mince-meat or rice.

Haricot-beans, Peas and Broad-beans, cohered with butter,

Asparagus-heads, white or green, cooked and cohered with butter.

Celery, Endives, and Chicory, all braised. Brussels Sprouts, Cauliflowers, Brocoli, &c.

Finally, the garnishes and modes of preparation termed: à l’Anglaise, a la Boulangere, Braises, Marine en Chevreuit, which I give below for the leg and the shoulder, may be appliedperfectly well to other large pieces of mutton.

Large Cold Joints of Mutton

Refer to Cold Beef; in all cases keep the dishing simple.

The garnishing is optional.

LEG and SHOULDER of MUTTON

Legs of mutton or lamb ought never to appear on any butan ordinary luncheon menu. Although, strictly speaking, theyshould always be served after one of the ways described here-after, all the garnishes given above may be applied to them.

Shoulders may be roasted whole; but they may also beboned, seasoned inside, rolled up, and firmly strung. Theymay be treated like the legs, and the same garnishes are suitedto them.

GIGOT BOUILLI A d’ANGLAISE

Trim the leg, shorten it in the region of the tibia bone, andplunge it into a stewpan of boiling water, salted in the propor-tion of one-third oz. of salt per quart of water.

For an ordinary leg, add: three medium-sized carrots, twoonions, each stuck with a clove, a faggot, and two cloves ofgarlic.

Let the leg cook for a quarter of an hour for each two lbs. ofits weight.

Dish with vegetables all round, and serve at tht same timea butter sauce with capers.

N.B.—Leg of mutton a Vanglaise may be accompanied by

F F

purees of turnips, celery, &c., and these vegetables should cookwith the meat. A purée of potatoes or of haricot beans may besent to the table with the meat; but, in this case, of course, thevegetables would be served separately.

BRAISED LEG of MUTTON

Suppress the pelvic bone, shorten the end bone and brownthe leg in the oven.

Now, put it in an oval utensil, garnished for braising; addjust enough white stock to barely cover the joint, and cookgently, allowing forty minutes per lb. of meat.

Transfer the leg to a tray; strain the braising-liquor; clearit of all grease, and reduce it to half. Sprinkle the meat witha few tablespoonfuls of this reduced gravy, and set it to glazein the oven.

Serve at the same time: —

(1) Either a purée of potatoes, of turnips, of haricot-beans, ofcauliflower,*&c., or

(2) The reduced braising-liquor.

GIGOT à la BOULANGERE

The leg may either be boned, seasoned inside and strung; orthe end-bone may simply be shortened and that of the pelvisremoved.

In either case, put it in an earthenware dish, and brown itwell in the oven, on both sides; then complete its cooking, allbut a third.

This done, set round the joint four large, sliced onions, justtossed in butter, that they may acquire some colour, and eightlarge, peeled potatoes cut into roundels one half in. thick.Sprinkle this garnish with the grease of the joint, and then com-plete the cooking of the leg and its garnish.

Serve in the dish in which the joint has cooked.

GIGOT MARINE en CHEVREUIL

Shorten the end-bone; remove the bone of the pelvis, andskin the top of the leg, leaving the meat in that region quitebare. Lard with very small strips of bacon, and put the meatinto a marinade prepared after the manner described under №170. The length of its stay in the marinade should be basedupon the tenderness of the meat and atmospheric conditions.In winter the time averages about three or four days, and insummer two days.

To Roast the Joint.—Withdraw it from the marinade anddry it thoroughly; set it on a stand in the baking-tray; and put

it into a very fierce oven, that the meat may set immediately.The object of the very fierce oven is to prevent the juicesabsorbed from the marinade escaping in steam and therebyhardening the meat.

Towards the close of the operation, rissole the larding baconwell.

Set on a long dish; fix a frill to the bone, and serve a Chev-reuil sauce separately.

Chevreuil Sauce a la Frangaise.—With the marinade of thejoint and a Mirepoix with ham, prepare a sufficient quantity ofPoivrade sauce (№49) to obtain two-thirds of a pint of it afterit has been strained through a colander—an operation whichshould be effected with the application of great pressure to thearomatics.

Despumate this sauce for thirty minutes, and add, little bylittle, half a wine-glassful of excellent red wine. Finish the sea-soning with a little cayenne and a pinch of powdered sugar, and once more rub the whole through tammy or a fine strainer.

QIQOT à la SOUBISE

Braise the leg of mutton as shown under №247. When itis two-thirds done, transfer it to another utensil; strain thebraising-liquor over it, and add thereto three lbs. of sliced onionsand two-third lb. of rice.

Gently complete the cooking of the joint, together with theonions and the rice. This done:—(1) put it on a baking-trayand glaze it in the oven; (2) quickly rub the onions and the ricethrough a fine sieve or tammy.

Set the leg of mutton on a long dish; put a frill on thebone, and serve, separately, the well-heated Soubise, finishedwith one oz. of butter.

N.B.—This Soubise may be prepared separately; but in thiscase it has much less flavour than when it is made from theonions and the rice which have cooked in the braising-liquor. I therefore urge the adoption of the recipe as it stands.

COLD LEG of MUTTON

Dish it very simply, like other cold large joints of mutton.

CUTLETS

Mutton and lamb cutlets are sometimes sautéd; but grillingis the most suitable method of cooking them. When the natureof their preparation requires that they should be treated dVanglaise, fry them in clarified butter. All the garnishes, given

f r 2

*36

under “Tournedos,” except those served with sauces, may beapplied to cutlets.

The latter also allow of a few special garnishes, and these Igive in the following recipes.

Côtelettes à la Champvallon (10 Cutlets)

Take some cutlets from the region underlying the shoulder;that is to say, those uncovered by the removal of this joint. And do not clear the bone-ends of their meat, as when frills areto be fixed to them.

Season them with salt and pepper, and brown them in butteron both sides. This done, put them in an earthenware dish withhalf lb. of sliced onions, tossed in butter without colouration;moisten with enough white stock to almost cover the cutlets andthe onions; add the quarter of a clove of garlic, crushed, and afaggot; boil, and set in the oven. At the end of twentyminutes, add one and one-half lbs. of potatoes, fashioned tothe shape of corks, and cut into thin roundels; season, andcomplete the cooking, basting often the while.

When the cutlets are cooked, the moistening should be almostentirely reduced.

C^TELETTES LAURA

Grill the cutlets, and, meanwhile, prepare a garnish (thequantity of which should be such as to allow two and one-halfoz. of it per cutlet) of parboiled macaroni, cut into half-inchlengths, cohered with cream, and combined, per lb., with threeand one-half oz. of peeled, pressed, and concassed tomatoes, tossed in butter.

Or, when white truffles are in season, prepare some macaroniwith cream, as above, combined with the peelings of raw, whitetruffles.

Cut some very soft pig’s caul into triangles, proportionate insize to the cutlets; spread a little macaroni on each triangle; onthe latter set a cutlet; cover the cutlets with some more macaroni, and enclose the whole in the caul. Lay the cutlets on a dish.

Sprinkle with fine raspings and melted butter, and set togrill at the salamander, or in a fierce oven, for seven or eightminutes.

Dish the cutlets in the form of a crown, and surround themwith a thread of clear half-glaze sauce, combined with tomatoes.

cOtelettes a la maintenon

Fry the cutlets in butter, on one side only. This done, puta heaped tablespoonful of a Maintenon preparation (№226)

on each; shape it like a dome, by means of the blade of a smallknife dipped in tepid water, and put the cutlets, one by one, on a tray. The Maintenon preparation should be laid on thecooked side of each cutlet and sprinkled with fine raspings andmelted butter. Now put the cutlets in a rather hot oven forseven or eight minutes in order to: —

(1) Allow a gratin to form over the surface of the garnish.

(2) Finish the cooking of the cutlets.

Dish the latter in the form of a crown, and serve, separately, a sauceboat of meat glaze finished with butter.

COTELETTES à la MURILLO

Fry the cutlets in butter, on one side only; and garnish thecooked side, dome-fashion, with a fine hash of mushrooms, cohered with a little very reduced Bechamel sauce.

Set them on a tray; sprinkle with grated Parmesan and afew drops of melted butter, and glaze in a fierce oven. Dishthe cutlets in the form of a crown; fix a frill to each, and sur-round them with mild capsicums and tomatoes, both of whichshould be sliced, tossed in butter, and mixed.

Côtelettes a la Provençale

For ten cutlets:—(1) Reduce one-half pint of Bechamel sauceto a third, and add thereto the third of a garlic clove, crushed, and the yolks of three eggs; (2) prepare at the same time asthe cutlets, ten grilled mushrooms; and ten stoned, stuffed andpoached olives, girded by a strip of anchovy fillet.

Fry the cutlets in butter, on one side only. Cover thecooked side of each with the preparation described above; setthem on a tray; sprinkle them with a few drops of melted butter, and put them in the oven, that their garnish may be glazedand that their cooking may be completed.

Dish in the form of a circle; place a grilled mushroom(convex side uppermost) in the middle of each cutlet, and, on each mushroom, a stuffed olive.

Côtelette5 de Mouton à la Réforme

Trim six mutton cutlets; season them; dip them in meltedbutter, and roll them in bread-crumbs, combined with finely-chopped ham in the proportion of a third of the weight of thebread-crumbs. Now cook them gently in clarified butter.

Dish them in a circle on a hot dish, and send the followingsauce to the table with them: —

Take a small saucepan, and mix therein three tablespoon-fuls of half-glaze sauce, the same quantity of Poivrade sauce,

43«

and one coffeespoonful of red-currant jelly; add one coffee-spoonful of each of the following short julienne garnishes tothe sauce; viz.: hard-boiled white of egg; very red, saltedtongue; gherkins; mushrooms, and truffles.

Côtelette5 à la Séivigné

Have ready a preparation of mushroom and artichoke-bottom croquettes, in the proportion of one heaped tablespoonfulfor each cutlet.

Fry the cutlets in butter, on one side only. Garnish thefried side of each, dome-fashion, with the above preparation;treat them a. Vanglaise, and sprinkle them with melted butter.

Put them in the oven to complete their cooking, and, atthe same time, to colour their coating of egg and bread-crumbs.

Dish in the form of a crown.

Côtelettes à la Suédoise

Place the cutlets on a dish, and drop thereon some mincedonions and shallots, bits of parsley stalks, thyme and bay.Sprinkle them with the juice of a lemon and a few drops ofoil, and leave them to marinade for thirty minutes, turningdiem over the while, from time to time.

This done, dry them; dip them in melted butter, sprinklethem with bread-crumbs, and grill them.

Dish them in the form of a crown, and garnish the centreof the dish with the following, which may also be sent separ-ately: one-half lb. of peeled and finely-sliced apples, quicklystewed to a purée with the third of a wineglassful of whitewine. When about to serve, add to this purée two and one-half oz. of finely-grated horse-radish, or the latter grated andafterwards finely chopped.

Côtelettes en Belle Vue

Proceed after one of the recipes given for veal cutlets andgrenadins “en Belle Vue.”

Côtelettes en Chaudfroid

Cut some very regular cutlets from a neck of mutton orlamb, which should have been trimmed as explained, braised, and left to cook in its braising-liquor. Clear all grease fromthe latter; strain it; reduce it, and add to it a brown chaud-froid sauce (№34).

Dip the cutlets in the sauce when it is almost cold; setthem on a tray; deck the kernel of meat in each with a fine slice

of truffle, and sprinkle with cold, melted aspic. When thesauce has set well, pass the point of a small knife round thecutlets, with the view of removing the superfluous sauce; andeither dish them round a vegetable salad, cohered and moulded, or simply dish them in the form of a circle and place a pyramidof cohered, vegetable salad in their midst.

NOISETTES de MOUTON

Mutton noisettes, and especially those of lamb, may beclassed among the choicest of entries. They are cut from eitherthe fillet or the neck; but, in the latter case, only the first sixor seven ribs are used.

Noisettes are grilled or sautéd, and all the recipes given forTournedos (Nos. 1077 to 1139) and for cutlets, may be appliedto them.

MINION FILLETS

The minion fillets of mutton or lamb consist of the twomuscles which lie under the saddle. Their mode of preparationchanges according to their size. Thus, if they are small, theyare served whole, after having been trimmed, sometimes larded;and sautéd.

If they are large, they are divided into two or three parts, cut laterally and aslant; they are flattened, trimmed to the shapeof ellipses, seasoned, dipped in melted butter, sprinkled withfine bread-crumbs, and finally, gently grilled.

Minion fillets of beef, obtained from the narrow extremityor head of the fillet, are also used occasionally; and these aregenerally flattened, dipped in butter and fine bread-crumbs, andgrilled.

These fillets are served chiefly with vegetable purées or with macedoines of fresh vegetables.

The sauces best suited to them are the Béarnaise and the Robert Escoffier.

SHEEP’S TONGUES

Salted or fresh sheep’s tongues make an excellent luncheonentree.

They are cooked after the manner of ox and calf’s tongues, due allowance being made for the difference of size.

The various garnishes given for ox and calf’s tongues mayalso be used in this case.

SHEEP’S TROTTERS

Sheep’s trotters, as they reach us from the purveyor, shouldfirst be well singed over spirits of wine, and then rubbed witha clean piece of linen. The little tuft of hair in the cleft of

the hoof is next removed, the hoof itself is suppressed, andthe trotters are split open lengthwise and boned. Sheep’strotters are cooked like calf’s feet, in the special court-bouillonor blanc, given under №167.

*325—FRITOT of SHEEP’S TROTTERS

Fifteen minutes before frying them, put the sheep’s trottersinto a receptacle with lemon juice, a few drops of oil and somechopped parsley; keeping the quantity of these ingredients inproportion to the number of trotters. Be careful to toss thelatter from time to time in the marinade.

A few moments before serving, dip the half-trotters intobatter (№232) and plunge them into an abundant and hotfrying-medium.

Drain them when the batter is nicely dry and golden; anddish on a napkin with a border of very green fried parsley.

Serve a tomato sauce separately.

PIEDS de MOUTON POULETTE

For this dish the trotters should, as far as possible, befreshly cooked. For twenty trotters prepare two-thirds of a pintof poulette sauce; add the trotters thereto, well drained; tossthem in the sauce, and dish them in a timbale with a sprinklingof chopped parsley.

PIEDS de MOUTON ROUENNAISE

Instead of cooking the sheep’s trotters in a blanc, braisethem; add a little Madeira to their braising-liquor, and cookthem thoroughly.

Prepare a forcemeat, consisting of one and one-half lbs. ofvery fine sausage-meat; three oz. of chopped onions, cooked inbutter without colouration, and a large pinch of parsley.

When the trotters are cooked, transfer them to a dish;almost entirely reduce their braising-liquor; add to this twoliqueur-glassfuls of burnt brandy, for each ten trotters, and addthis reduced braising-liquor to the forcemeat. Cut ten rect-angles six inches long by four inches wide out of pig’s caul.

Spread a tablespoonful of forcemeat over each; set twotrotters on the forcemeat of each rectangle; cover up with force-meat, and draw the ends of the caul together in suchwise asto enclose the whole.

Sprinkle with bread-crumbs and melted butter; grill gently, and serve.

PIEDS de MOUTON TYROLIENNE

Cook a fair-sized chopped onion in butter, together withthree peeled, pressed, and roughly-chopped tomatoes. Seasonwith salt and pepper; add a pinch of chopped parsley, a littlecrushed garlic, one-sixth of a pint of Poivrade sauce, and twentyfreshly-cooked and well-drained sheep’s trotters.

Simmer for ten minutes and dish in a timbale.

MUTTON KIDNEYS

Mutton kidneys are either grilled or sautéd. When they areto be grilled, first remove the fine skin enveloping them, cutthem in halves, without completely severing them on their con-cave side, and impale them on a small skewer, with the viewof keeping them open during the grilling operation. Beforegrilling they may or may not be dipped in melted butter androlled in bread-crumb.

When they are to be sautéd, clear the kidneys, as before, of the thin skin which envelops them; cut them into halves, and then into slices one-quarter in. thick.

Kidneys, of what kind soever, should be cooked very quickly, otherwise they harden. After having seasoned them, put theminto very hot butter, and toss them over a fierce fire in orderto stiffen them. This done, drain them; and let them standfor a few minutes, that they may exude the blood they contain, which sometimes has a distinct ammoniacal smell.

Meanwhile, swill the utensil in which they have been sautéd, and finish the sauce, to which they are added when dishingup. Never let the kidneys boil in the sauce, for they wouldimmediately harden.

Rognons 5AUTES BERCY

Slice, season, and quickly toss the mutton kidneys in butter, and drain them.

For six kidneys put one tablespoonful of finely-choppedshallots into the saucepan, and just heat it. Moisten with one-sixth of a pint of white wine; reduce to half; add two table-spoonfuls of melted meat glaze, and a few drops of lemon-juice, and put the kidneys in this sauce. Add two and one-half oz. of butter, cut into small pieces; melt this on the cornerof the stove, tossing and rolling the pan the while; dish in atimbale, and sprinkle a pinch of chopped parsley over thekidneys.

Rognons Sautés Bordelaise’ Fry the mutton kidneys, and drain them as above.

Put into the saucepan one-third of a pint of Bordelaise sauce

combined with poached dice of marrow, a pinch of choppedparsley, and three oz. of sliced cbpes, tossed in butter and oiland well drained.

Return the kidneys to the saucepan; toss them in the sauce, and dish in a timbale.

Rognons Sautés Carvalho

Fry the skinned, halved and seasoned mutton kidneys inbutter, and dish them, each on a small crouton of bread-crumb, cut to the shape of a cock’s comb and fried in butter. On eachhalf-kidney, set a small cooked mushroom and a slice of truffle.

Swill the saucepan with Madeira; add a little half-glaze; putin a small quantity of butter, away from the fire, and pour thissauce over the kidneys.

Rognons Sautés au Champagne

Remove the outer skin from the mutton kidneys; cut themin two lengthwise; season them; fry them quickly in butter, anddish in a timbale.

Swill the saucepan with one-half pint of champagne per sixkidneys; reduce almost entirely; add two tablespoonfuls ofmelted meat glaze; add a small quantity of butter, and pourthis sauce over the kidneys.

N.B.—The preparation of kidneys sautéd with wine alwaysfollows the same principle; that is to say, the saucepan in whichthe kidneys have cooked is always swilled with a quantity ofwine, in proportion to the number of kidneys; a proportionateamount of meat glaze is then added, and after the sauce has beenslightly buttered, the kidneys are tossed in it.

Rognons Sautés HONQROISE

Remove the outer skin from the mutton kidneys; cut theminto halves; slice and season them; fry them in butter, anddrain them.

In the saucepan that has served in the cooking of thekidneys, fry a chopped onion with butter, and add thereto apinch of paprika.

Moisten with a tablespoonful of cream, and reduce; addone-sixth of a pint of velout6, boil for a moment, and rubthrough tammy.

Heat this sauce; put the kidneys into it, toss them for aminute, so as to heat without boiling them, and dish in atimbale.

Rognons Sautés Chasseur

Quickly fry the sliced mutton kidneys in butter and drainthem.

Swill the saucepan with white wine and almost entirelyreduce; add one-third of a pint of Chausseur sauce for each sixkidneys; put the kidneys in this sauce, toss them for an instant;dish them in a timbale, and sprinkle with a pinch of choppedparsley.

Rognons Sautés à d’Indienne

For six mutton kidneys: fry a chopped onion in butter andadd a large pinch of curry thereto. Moisten with one-sixth pintof velout6; cook for a few minutes, and rub through tammy.

Clear the kidneys of their outer skin; slice and season them, and fry them quickly in butter. Put them into the sauce; dishthem in a timbalej and serve some rice “k l’lndienne” sepa-rately.

Rognons Sautés TURBIGO

Clear the mutton kidneys of their outer skin and cut them inhalves; season them; fry them quickly in butter, and dish themin a circle in a timbale.

In their midst set a garnish of small, cooked mushrooms, andgrilled chipolata sausages; and pour thereon a highly-seasoned, tomatéd half-glaze sauce.

CROUTE aux ROGNONS

Cut some crusts two and one-half in. in diameter and oneand one-third in. thick, from a tin-loaf, and allow one for eachperson. Remove the crumb from their inside, leaving only aslight thickness at the bottom; butter them, and dry them inthe oven.

Garnish these crusts with mutton kidneys sautéd with mush-rooms, and combined with small, ordinary forcemeat quenelles, and slices of truffle.

Dish on a napkin, and serve very hot.

•339—TURBAN de ROGNONS à la PIEMONTAISE

Garnish a border or a Savarin-mould with “rizotto à la Pidmontaise,” press the latter lightly into the utensil, and keepthe mould hot.

Clear the mutton kidneys of their outer skin; cut them intohalves; season them, and fry them quickly in butter.

Turn out on a round dish, set the half-kidneys in a circleon the “Turban,” alternating them with fine slices of truffle, and pour a tomatéd half-glaze sauce, flavoured with truffleessence, in the middle.

ROGNONS à la BROCHETTE

Cut the mutton kidneys into halves, as explained, withoutdividing them; impale them two or four at' a time, on a skewer;

season them, and grill them in a somewhat fierce oven. Setthem, with the skewers withdrawn, upon a hot dish, and put intothe cavity of each a piece of softened, Maître-d’hôtel butter, thesize of a hazel nut.

,34I_ROGNONS BROCHETTE A d’ESPAGNOLE

Prepare the mutton kidneys as above.

Grill the same quantity of small, pressed and seasoned half-tomatoes. Garnish these tomatoes with a piece, the size ofa walnut, of Maître-d’hôtel butter, combined with two-thirds oz.of chopped capsicum per three oz. of butter. Dish these toma-toes in a circle; set a kidney on each, and surround with a borderconsisting of rings of onion, seasoned, dredged and crisply friedin oil.

ROGNONS BROCHETTE au VERT PRI*

Prepare the mutton kidneys exactly as explained under thefirst of this kind of recipes, and surround them with smallheaps of straw potatoes and bunches of very green parsley.

BROCHETTES de ROGNONS

Remove the outer skin from the mutton kidneys, and cutthem into roundels one-third in. thick. Season these roundelsand stiffen them in butter over a very fierce fire. Impale themon skewers, alternating them with squares of blanched leanbacon and slices of sautéd mushrooms. Sprinkle with meltedbutter and raspings, and grill.

These brochettes are generally served as they stand.

Various Preparations of Mutton.

%

C ASSO U LET

(1) Set one quart of haricot beans to cook with two quartsof water, one-third oz. of salt, one carrot, one onion stuck witha clove, one faggot, six garlic cloves, and two-thirds lb. of freshpork rind, blanched and strung together. Boil; skim; cover, and cook gently for one hour. At the end of this time, addtwo-thirds lb. of breast of pork, and a sausage with garlic, ofthe same weight as the pork. Salt the beans very moderately, allowing for the reduction which they have ultimately toundergo.

Complete the cooking of the whole gently.

(2) Fry gently in lard one lb. of shoulder, and the sameweight of breast, of mutton; both cut into pieces one and one-half oz. in weight.

This done, drain away half the grease; add two chopped

onions and two crushed cloves of garlic, and fry again untilthe onions have acquired a slight colour. Now pour in one-sixth pint of good tomato purée; moisten the meat, enough tocover, with the cooking-liquor of haricot beans, and cook gentlyin the oven for one and one-half hours at least.

(3) Garnish the bottom and sides of some cocottes or deepdishes with bacon rind; fill these with alternate layers of thepieces of mutton, the beans, the bacon cut into dice, and thesausage cut into roundels.

Sprinkle the surface with raspings, and set the gratin toform in a moderate oven for one hour; taking care to bastefrom time to time with some reserved haricot-beans cooking-liquor.

>345—CURRIE A d’INDIENNE

Cut two lbs. of lean mutton into cubes of one and one-thirdin. side, and fry these in three oz. of lard, with one choppedonion, salt, and a pinch of powdered curry. When the meatis frizzled and the onions begin to colour, sprinkle with oneand one-third oz. of flour; cook the latter a while; moistenwith one and one-third pints of water or stock; boil, stirringthe while, so as to dissolve the roux, and then cook gently inthe oven for one and one-half hours. When about to serve, clearof all grease and dish in a timbale.

Send a timbale of rice & 1’indienne separately.

DAUBE A d’AVIGNONNAISE

Bone a medium-sized leg of mutton, and cut the meat intosquares, three oz. in weight. Lard each square with a large, seasoned strip of bacon, inserted with the grain of the meat.Put the pieces into a daubiere with a sliced half-carrot andonion, three cloves of garlic, a little thyme, bay, and parsleystalks. Moisten with one and one-third pints of good, red wineand four tablespoonfuls of oil, and marinade in the cool for twohours.

Prepare:—(1) Three chopped onions mixed with twocrushed garlic cloves; (2) one-half lb. of lean bacon, cut intodice and blanched; (3) one-half lb. of fresh, bacon rind, blanched and cut into squares of one in. side; (4) a large bunchof parsley, containing a small piece of dry, orange peel. Gar-nish the bottom and sides of a daubiere with thin slices ofbacon; set the pieces of mutton in layers inside, and alternatethem with layers of onion, bacon and bacon rind; sprinkle apinch of powdered thyme and bay on each layer of meat. Putthe faggot in the middle.

Moisten with the marinade, strained through a sieve, andone-fifth pint of brown stock; cover with slices of bacon; closethe daubihe, and seal down the lid by means of a threadof soft paste, in order that the steam may be concentrated inside.

Boil on the side of the stove; put the daubihe in an ovenof regular heat (a baker’s oven if possible) that the cookingprocess may be gentle and steady, and cook for five hours.

When about to serve, uncover the daubihe; remove theoverlying slices of bacon; clear of grease; remove the faggot, and dish the daubihe on a napkin.

N.B.—According to the household method, the “Daube”is served in the daubihe itself; but, subject to the demands ofthe service and in order that the preparation may keep itsbucolic character, it may be served in small earthenwareutensils.

>347—DAUBE FROIDE

Cold Daube constitutes an excellent luncheon dish. Allthat is needed is to put what is left into a small daubihe, where, as a result of the binding properties of the pork rinds, it willset in a mass.

When about to serve, turn out on a round dish; surroundwith very light, chopped jelly; and carve into very thin slices.

EMINCES et HACHI5

An unalterable principle governs the preparation of eminc^sand hashes, which is that the meats constituting these dishesshould never boil if it be desired that they be not hard.

They should, therefore, only be heated in their accom-panying garnish or sauce, and in the case of eminc^s, cut asfinely as possible.

For the various recipes under this head, see the Chapter onBeef. (Nos. 1175, 1178 and 1179.)

HARICOT de MOUTON

Heat three oz. of lard in a sauté-pan. Put therein one-halflb. of lean bacon, cut into dice and blanched, and twenty smallonions. When the bacon is frizzled and the onions haveacquired a good colour, drain both on a dish. In the same fat, fry three lbs. of breast, neck and shoulder of mutton, all threebeing cut into pieces weighing about three oz. Keep the meatin the fat until each piece of it has acquired a frizzled coat.

Drain away half of the grease; add three crushed cloves ofgarlic; dust with two tablespoonfuls of flour, and cook the latter, stirring the while.

Moisten with one quart of water; season with one-third oz.

of salt and a pinch of pepper; boil and stir; add a faggot, andcook in the oven for thirty minutes.

This done, transfer the pieces to another saucepan; add thebacon and the onions and a quart of half-cooked haricot beans;strain the sauce over the whole, and complete the cooking in theoven for one hour.

Dish in a timbale or in small cocottes.

IRISH STEW

Cut two lbs. of boned breast and shoulder of mutton intopieces, as above.

Slice two lbs. of potatoes and chop four medium-sizedonions.

Take a saucepan just large enough to hold these ingredientsand the moistening; line the bottom of the utensil with a layerof the pieces of meat, and season the latter with salt and pepper.Upon the meat spread a litter of sliced potatoes and Choppedonions; repeat the operation, again and again, until all theingredients are used up, and remember to place a faggot in themiddle.

Moisten with one and one-third pint of water, and cookgently in the oven for one and one-half hours. The potatoesin this preparation answer the double purpose of garnish andleason.

Dish in a timbale and serve boiling.

135*— MOUSSAKA

(1) Cut six fine egg-plants into halves, lengthwise; cisel thepulp somewhat deeply with the point of a small knife, and frythem until their pulp may be easily removed. Do this with aspoon, and put the pulp aside with the skins of the egg-plants.

(2) Peel two fair-sized egg-plants; cut them into roundelsone-third in. thick; season them, dredge them; fry them inoil, and put them aside.

(3) Chop up the pulp withdrawn from the egg-plants, andput it into a basin with one and one-half lbs. of very lean, cooked mutton, chopped or cut into very small dice; two table-spoonfuls of very finely-chopped onion, fried in butter; a pinchof parsley; a piece of crushed garlic as large as a pea; threeoz. of roughly-chopped raw mushrooms, fried in butter; twoeggs; two tablespoonfuls of cold Espagnole sauce; one table-spoonful of tomato purée; a pinch of salt, and another ofpepper. Mix the whole well.

(4) Butter a low-bordered quart Charlotte mould; line it allover with the egg-plant skins, and lay these black side upper-

most. Garnish the bottom of the mould with a layer of mince-meat, one in. thick; on this layer place a few fried roundels ofegg-plant, and continue thus with alternate layers of mince andegg-plant. Cover the last layer of mince-meat with the remainsof the egg-plant skins, and cook in a bain-marie for one hour.

When taking the mould out of the oven, let it stand for fiveminutes in order that the ingredients may settle; turn out ona round dish, and besprinkle the surface of the Moussaka withchopped parsley.

MUTTON PUDDING

Follow the directions given under beefsteak pudding (№1170) exactly. The preparation is just the same, but for thesubstitution of mutton for the beef.

•353—NAVARIN PRINTANIER

Heat four oz. of clarified fat in a sauté-pan, and put into itfour lbs. of breast, neck and shoulder of mutton; all three cutinto pieces weighing two and one-half oz. Fry over a verybrisk fire; season with one-third oz. of salt, a pinch of groundpepper, and another of sugar.

The sugar settles slowly on the bottom of the sauté-pan, where it turns to caramel; it is then dissolved by the moistening, and thus gives the sauce the required colour.

When the meat is well fried, remove almost all the fat;sprinkle with one and one-half oz. of flour; cook the latterfor a few minutes, and moisten with one and one-half quarts ofwater or stock.

Boil, stirring the while, and add two-thirds lb. of freshconcassed tomatoes or one-fifth pint of tomato purée; onecrushed clove of garlic, and a large faggot. Cover and cookin the oven for one hour.

This done, transfer the pieces of mutton, one by one, toanother saucepan with twenty small, new onions; twentypieces of new trimmed carrots; twenty pieces of new turnips, cut to the shape of long olives and tossed with butter in afrying-pan; twenty small, new potatoes, cut into two, andtrimmed, or whole; one-sixth pint of fresh peas, and an equalquantity of raw French beans, cut into lozenges. Strain thesauce over the whole; set to boil, and continue cooking slowlyin the oven for one hour; taking care from time to time to bastethe overlying vegetables with sauce.

Dish in a timbale and serve very hot.

N.B.—When put into the sauce, the vegetables cook muchless quickly than in boiling water. In the Navarin, moreover,

they are cooked by means of gradual penetration; thus, byslackening the cooking speed of the Navarin, they are cookedto the required extent.

*354—PILAW de MOUTON à la TURQUE

Mutton Pilaff is, in fact, nothing but a Navarin in whichthe tomatoes dominate the other ingredients; it is flavoured with ginger or saffron, according to circumstances, and the usualvegetables are replaced by rice. Prepared in this way, it doesnot lend itself very well to the exigencies of a restaurant service.

More often, therefore, it is treated like curried mutton; but, instead of serving it with rice & l’lndienne, it is dished in themidst of a pilaff-rice border. Sometimes, too, the rice is servedseparately, after the manner of a curry dish.

HOUSE LAMB.

*355—BARON (or PAIR of HIND-QUARTERS) of LAMB*356—DOUBLE (or PAIR of LEGS) of LAMB*357—QUARTER of LAMB*358—FILLET of LAMB*359—SADDLE and NECK of LAMB

Large joints of lamb for Relevés are cut like those of mutton.

One joint, however, should be added, which is “TheHaunch”; and this consists of one leg and half the loinattached.

Large joints of house lamb should be poeled or roasted.Their most suitable adjunct is either their own stock, or athickened, highly seasoned and clear gravy.

House Lamb Relevés are chiefly garnished with early-seasonor new vegetables; but all the garnishes given under Mutton Relevés may also be served with them, provided the differencein size be taken into account. In addition to these garnishes, saddle of lamb admits of all the preparations given under saddleof veal (Nos. 1181 to 1191).

SELLE d’AGNEAU de LAIT EDOUARD VII.

Completely bone the saddle from underneath, in suchwise asto leave the skin intact; season it inside, and place in the middlea fine foie gras, studded with truffles and marinaded in Marsala.

Reconstruct the saddle, and wrap it tightly in a piece ofmuslin; put it in a saucepan just large enough to hold it, on alitter of pieces of bacon rind, cleared of all fat and blanched.

G G

Moisten, enough to cover, with the braising-liquor of a cushionof veal; add thereto the Marsala used in marinading the foiegras, and poach for about forty-five minutes.

Before withdrawing the saddle, make sure that the foie grasis sufficiently cooked. Remove the muslin, and put the saddlein an oval terrine a pâté just large enough to hold it. Strainthe cooking-liquor over it, without clearing the former of grease, and set it to cool.

When the saddle is quite cold, carefully clear away the greasethat lies upon it, first by means of a spoon and then by meansof boiling water. Serve it very cold, in the terrine as it stands.

CARRE d’AGNEAU BEAUCAIRE

Having trimmed the neck of lamb, as explained, brown itin butter; surround it with eight small, Provence half-artichokes, and cook gently in the oven. The artichokes in question haveno chokes and are very tender.

Meanwhile, peel, press, concass and season four or five toma-toes, and fry them in butter. When they are ready, add a largepinch of chopped tarragon to them.

Dish the tomatoes; set the neck upon them, and surroundit with the stewed half-artichokes.

CARRE d’AGNEAU en COCOTTEA la BONNE FEMME

Fry a shortened and well-trimmed neck of lamb, in butter.

This done, transfer it to an oval cocotte with ten small onionsbrowned in butter, and two medium-sized potatoes, cut into largedice, shaped like garlic cloves, and blanched. Sprinkle thewhole with melted butter and cook gently in the oven.

Serve the preparation as it stands, in the cocotte, placing thelatter on a folded napkin.

CARRE d’AGNEAU à la BOULANGERE

Fry the neck of lamb with butter, in an earthenware dish, and surround it with sliced onions, tossed in butter, and slicedpotatoes; both of which vegetables should be in quantities inproportion to the size of the piece of meat. The “à la Boul-ang&re” procedure is always the same, and was explained underNo. 1307, but allowances should always be made for the par-ticular size and tenderness of the piece.

CARRE D AGNEAU GRILLE

Having shortened and well trimmed the neck, season it;sprinkle it with melted butter, and grill it gently.

45»

When it is almost cooked, sprinkle it again with meltedbutter and bread-crumbs, and let it acquire a golden colourwhile completely cooking it.

Serve very hot with mint sauce and a suitable garnish.

*365—CARRE d’AGNEAU MIREILLE

Prepare some Anna potatoes (№2203) in an oval earthen-ware dish, and add a third of the quantity of potatoes of raw, minced artichoke-bottoms.

When the potatoes are three-parts cooked, stiffen the neckin butter; place it on the potatoes, and complete the cooking ofthe two, basting often the while with melted butter.

Send the preparation to the table on the dish that hasserved in the cooking process.

CARRE d’AGNEAU PRINTANIER

Prepare the following garnish: eight small onions, half-cooked in butter; ten carrots of the size and shape of garliccloves, cooked in consommé and glazed; and ten turnips ofthe same shape and size, similarly treated.

Put these vegetables into a cocotte with three tablespoonfulsof fresh peas; the same quantity of raw, French beans, cut intolozenge form; two or three tablespoonfuls of good and veryclear stock, and complete the cooking of the whole.

Meanwhile, poele the neck of lamb, which should have beenshortened and trimmed in the usual way. Dish the neck oflamb and serve the vegetables in the cocotte.

CARRE d’AGNEAU SOUBISE

Having shortened and trimmed the neck of lamb, stiffen itin butter; surround it with one-half lb. of finely-minced andwell-blanched onions, and complete the cooking of both bystewing.

This done, transfer the neck to a dish and keep it hot. Addone-quarter pint of boiling Bechamel sauce to the onions, andrub them quickly through tammy or a fine sieve. Heat this Soubise; finish it with one and one-half oz. of butter, and pourit over the neck.

Border the dish with a thread of rather light meat glaze, and serve.

CARRE d’AGNEAU à la TOSCANE

Shorten the neck of lamb; suppress the cartilaginous portionsand stiffen it in butter. Garnish the bottom of an oval earthen-ware dish, of the same size as the neck, with a layer of Annapotatoes (№2203). Set the neck on this layer, and cover it

G G 2

over with a second layer of the same potato preparation.Sprinkle with grated Parmesan; cook in the oven as for Annapotatoes, and take care that the bottom be so well set as toprevent any of the juices of the joint from exuding and deposit-ing on it.

Serve the dish as it stands.

LEG and SHOULDER of LAMB

All the recipes given under Haunch and Double (pair oflegs), may be applied to the legs and shoulders of house lamb.

The shoulders are often grilled, the operation being effectedover a moderate fire after the joints have been incised lattice-fashion, and the same applies to the breast. The “& laBoulang&re” treatment (№1307) admirably suits the legs andshoulders of house lamb.

CUTLETS

According to custom, lamb cutlets are usually served like“Noisettes,” i.e., two are allowed for each person.

As a rule, when they are to be grilled, they are previouslydipped in melted butter and sprinkled with fine bread-crumbs.

When they are to be sautéd they are treated a Vanglaise (eggand bread-crumbs) except when, subject to their mode of pre-paration, they have to be served plain or stuffed.

Côtelettes d’AGNEAU de lait a la buloz

Prepare:—(1) a rizotto (№2238) with truffles, in propor-tion to the number of cutlets; (2) some very reduced Bechamelsauce, combined with one-half oz. of grated Parmesan per one-fifth pint of the sauce, and allowing one small tablespoonful of itfor each cutlet.

Half-grill the cutlets; dry them, and cover them, on bothsides, with the reduced sauce. As soon as the cutlets havereceived their coat of sauce, dip them, one by one, into beatenegg (anglaise); roll them in very fine bread-crumbs mixed withgrated Parmesan. Thoroughly press this coating of bread-crumbs with the flat of a knife, that it may adhere well to theegg and produce a crust at the close of the operation. Thisdone, set the cutlets in a sauté-pan of very hot, clarified butter, and brown them on both sides.

Dish the rizotto in a very even layer; set the cutlets in acircle on the rice, and fix a frill to the bone of each.

Côtelettes d’AGNEAU de LAITMARECHALE

Treat the cutlets d l’anglaise, and cook them in clarifiedbutter.

Dish them in a circle, with a fine slice of truffle upon each;

and, in their midst, set a nice heap of asparagus-heads coheredwith butter.

>373—COTELETTES d’AGNEAU de LAIT

MILANAISE

Treat the cutlets & Vanglaise, but add to the bread-crumbsthe quarter of their weight of grated Parmesan.

Cook the cutlets in clarified butter. Dish them in a circle, and, in their midst, arrange a garnish “à la milanaise” (seeCote de Vau à la Milanaise,” №1258.)

COTELETTES d’AQNEAU de LAIT

MORLAND

Slightly flatten the cutlets, dip them in beaten egg, and rollthem in finely-chopped truffle, which in this case answers thepurpose of bread-crumbs. Press the truffle with the flat of aknife, that it may thoroughly combine with the egg, and cookthe cutlets in clarified butter. Dish them in a circle; garnishthe centre of the dish with a mushroom purée (№2059), andsurround the cutlets with a thread of buttered meat glaze.

*375—COTELETTES d’AQNEAU de LAIT

NAVARRAISE

For twelve cutlets, make a preparation consisting of fouroz. of ham, four oz. of cooked mushrooms, and one-half oz. ofchopped, red capsicums; the whole being cohered by means ofa very reduced Bechamel sauce, flavoured with truffle essence.

Grill the cutlets on one side only, and garnish them on theirgrilled side with a tablespoonful of the above preparation, whichshould be shaped like a dome upon them.

Set the cutlets upon a tray as soon as they are garnished;sprinkle the surface of the preparation, covering them withgrated cheese and melted butter, and place them in the oven, that their cooking may be completed and the gratin formed.Meanwhile, toss twelve seasoned half-tomatoes in oil. Dishthese tomatoes in a circle; set a cutlet upon each, and borderwith a thread of tomato sauce.

“COTELETTES d’AQNEAU de LAIT

NELSON

Grill the cutlets, and, at the same time, prepare as manybread-crumb croutons as there are cutlets, and of exactly thesame shape as the latter. Fry the croutons in butter, and coatthem with foie-gras purée.

Place a grilled cutlet on each coated crouton, and a sliceof truffle on the kernel of each cutlet. Now, by means of a

piping-bag, fitted with an even pipe, cover the cutlets with somesouffle au Parmesan (№2295A); dish them in a circle, andput them in the oven for five minutes, that the soufflé maypoach.

After withdrawing them from the oven, garnish the centreof the dish with a heap of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter.

COTELETTHS d’AGNEAU de LAIT FARCIESA la PERIGUEUX

Cook the cutlets in butter on one side only, and cool themunder slight pressure.

Garnish the cooked side of each with a tablespoonful offorcemeat with butter (№193), which should have received acopious addition of chopped truffles. Shape this forcemeatdome-fashion, by means of the flat of a small knife, dipped intepid water, and set the cutlets, one by one, on a tray. Nowput them in the front of the oven for seven or eight minutesthat the forcemeat may be poached.

Dish them in a circle, and pour a Périgueux sauce in theirmidst.

EPIGRAMMES d’AGNEAU

A lamb “epigram” consists of a cutlet, and a piece ofbraised breast, cooled under slight pressure and cut to the shapeof a heart of the same size as the cutlets. The cutlets and thepieces of breast must be treated a Vanglaise, and sautéd orgrilled according to circumstance.

Epigrams should be dished in a circle, the cutlets and thepieces being alternated.

They are usually garnished with braised chicory, or mace-doines of early-season vegetables.

RIS d’AGNEAU

Lamb sweetbreads are, according to circumstances, eitherused as the principal constituent of various preparations, or theyanswer the purpose of a garnish.

Due allowance having been made for their particular size, they may be treated after the same manner as veal sweetbreads;that is to say, once they have been cleared of blood, they areblanched and braised according to the nature of the selectedmode of preparation.

If they are to form part of a large garnish, cohered by meansof a brown sauce, they are braised brown and glazed. If theystand as an adjunct to poached fowl, they may be either studdedor left plain, and braised white.

Apart from their two uses as principal and garnishing con-

stituents, the undermentioned methods of preparation, explainedin the various preceding series, may be applied to them; viz.:—

Attereaux, Brochettes, Croustades, Pâté chaud, Vol au vent,&c.

Sauté d’AGNEAU PRINTANIER

Prepare the following garnish:—Twenty new carrots, cut tothe shape of large olives, cooked in consommé and glazed;twenty pieces of turnip, similarly treated; fifteen small, newonions, cooked in butter; twenty very small new potatoes, cooked in butter (or d I’anglaise if desired); three tablespoonfulsof peas; the same quantity of French beans cut into lozenge-form, and an equal quantity of small flageolet beans. Thethree last vegetables should be cooked a Vanglaise, and keptrather firm.

Cut two lbs. of shoulder and breast of lamb into piecesweighing two oz., and completely cook them in butter withoutany moistening.

This done, transfer them to a dish. Swill the saucepan withthree tablespoonfuls of water; add five tablespoonfuls of palemeat glaze; heat without boiling, and finish with two and one-half oz. of butter.

Put the pieces of lamb and the vegetables into this sauce, and gently rock the saucepan, that all the ingredients may par-take of the sauce.

Serve in a hot timbale.

PILAW d’AGNEAU

Proceed exactly as explained under “Pilaw de Mouton”(№1354), only bear in mind that the time allowed for cookingshould be proportionately shortened in view of the greater ten.derness of lamb’s meat.

CURRIE d’AGNEAU

Proceed as for “Currie de Mouton,” after duly allowing, as above, for the greater tenderness of the meat.

PORK

Releves and Entrees.

FRESH LEG of PORK

FRESH PORK FILLETS*385—FRESH NECK of PORK

Releves of fresh pork are only served at family and bourgeoismeals. They are always roasts and allow of all the dry or freshvegetable garnishes, as wrell as the various vegetable purées, and the pastes, such as macaroni, noodles, polenta, gnochi, &c. Ishall, therefore, give only a few recipes, and shall select FreshNeck of Pork as the typical joint.

FRESH NECK of PORK à la CHOUCROtiTE

Roast the neck of pork and withdraw it from the oven a fewminutes before it is done.

Keep it in the stove for an hour, that its cooking may becompleted gently; but remember, that if a stove is not avail-able, the cooking of the piece should be well finished in theoven; for pork is indigestible when it is not thoroughly wellcooked.

Meanwhile, prepare a garnish of sauerkraut (№2097), and, during the last hour of its cooking, sprinkle it frequently withthe fat of the neck.

Dish the neck; clear the sauerkraut of any superfluous fat, and set it round the piece of meat in spoonfuls; slightly pressingit in so doing.

FRESH NECK of PORK with BRUSSELS SPROUTS

Roast the neck of pork. Three-parts cook the Brusselssprouts; completely drain them, and put them round the pieceof meat, that they may complete their cooking in its gravy andfat, being frequently basted the while.

For this preparation it is well to roast the neck in an earthen-ware dish, in which it may be served with its garnish—a muchbetter plan than that of transferring it to another dish.

FRESH NECK of PORK with RED CABBAGEA la FLAMANDE

Roast the neck of pork; dish it and surround it with agarnish of red cabbages, prepared à la Flamande (№2098).

Sprinkle the garnish of vegetables with the gravy of thejoint, three-parts cleared of grease.

FRESH NECK of PORK with STEWED APPLES

Roast the neck of pork and see that it is well done.

Meanwhile, peel and mince one lb. of apples; put them ina saucepan with one oz. of sugar and a few tablespoonfuls ofwater; seal the lid of the saucepan well down, so as to con-centrate the steam inside, and cook quickly. When about toserve, thoroughly work the apple purée with a wire whisk, inorder to smooth it. Dish the neck with its gravy, three-partscleared of grease, and serve the apple purée separately in atimbale.

FRESH NECK of PORK à la SOISSONNAISE

Roast the neck on a dish that may be sent to the table.

When it is three-parts done, set one quart of cooked andwell-drained haricot beans round it, and complete the cookinggently. Serve the dish as it stands.

BOILED SALTED PORK A d’ANGLAISE

Cook plainly in water three lbs. of shoulder, breast, orgammon of bacon, and add thereto a garnish of vegetables asfor boiled beef, and six parsnips.

Serve the vegetables round the piece of meat, and send apease-pudding (prepared as directed below) separately.

Pease-pudding: put one lb. of a purée of yellow or green, split peas into a basin, and mix therewith three oz. of meltedor softened butter, three eggs, a pinch of salt, another of pepper, and a little nutmeg. Pour this purée into a pudding basin, andpoach it in steam or in a bain-marie.

This preparation may also be put into a buttered and flour-dusted napkin; in which case, close the napkin up purse-fashion, tying it up securely with string, and cook the pudding in thesame stewpan with the pork. This procedure is simpler thanthe first and quite as good.

Very often a purée prepared from split, yellow or green peas, is used instead of the pudding given above.

PORK PIE

Completely line the bottom and sides of a pie-dish with thinslices of raw ham, and prepare, for a medium-sized dish:—(1)one and one-half lbs. of fresh pork in collops, seasoned with saltand pepper, and sprinkle with two tablespoonfuls of dryDuxelles (№223), a pinch of parsley and another of chopped

sage; (2) one and one-half lbs. of raw, sliced potatoes, and onelarge, chopped onion.

Garnish the bottom of the dish with a litter of collops; coverwith potatoes and onions; spread another litter of collops, andbegin again in the same order. Add one-quarter pint of water;cover with a layer of fine paste or puff-paste trimmings, whichshould be well sealed down round the edges; gild with beatenegg; streak the paste with the prongs of a fork; make a slit inthe centre of the covering of paste for the escape of steam, andbake in a moderate oven for about two hours.

Fresh-pork Cutlets.

*393—FRESH-PORK CUTLETS à la CHARCUTIERE

Season the cutlets; dip them in melted butter, and sprinklethem with fine raspings. Grill them gently, and baste themfrom time to time.

Dish them in a circle; pour a Charcuti&re sauce in theirmidst, and serve a timbale of potato purée separately.

Charcutiere sauce for eight or ten cutlets: prepare one pint of Robert Sauce and mix with it, just before dishingup, two oz. of gherkins, cut in short julienne fashion or minced.

FRESH-PORK CUTLETS à la FLAMANDE

Season the cutlets, and fry them on both sides in butteror fat.

Meanwhile, peel and slice some eating apples, allowing threeoz. of the latter for each cutlet, and put them in an earthenwaredish. Set upon them the half-fried cutlets; sprinkle with fat, and complete their cooking, as well as that of the apples, in theoven.

Serve the dish as it stands.

Côtes de porc Frais à la Milanaise

Treat the cutlets a Vanglaise, but remember to add one quartof grated Parmesan to the bread-crumbs. Cook them gently inbutter.

Dish in a circle; set a milanaise garnish (№1258) in thecentre, and serve a tomato sauce separately.

FRESH-PORK CUTLETS with PIQUANTEOR ROBERT SAUCE

Season and grill or sauté the cutlets. Dish them in a circle, with Piquante or Robert Sauce in their midst.

N.B.—(1) Cutlets accompanied by either of the two above-mentioned sauces, may be treated with melted butter and bread-

crumbs and grilled or sautid; but, in this case, the sauce shouldbe served separately.

(2) For cutlets with Piquante sauce, border the dish on whichthey are served with gherkins, and send the sauce either separ-ately or on the dish.

(3) All the garnishes given under fresh neck of pork mayaccompany grilled or sautéd pork cutlets.

SUCKING PIG

Stuffed or not stuffed, sucking pigs are always roasted whole, and the essential point of the procedure is that they should bejust done when their skin is crisp and golden.

While cooking, they should be frequently basted with oil;the latter being used in preference to any other fatty substanceowing to the greater crispness it gives to the skin of the suckingPig-

Serve a sauceboat of good gravy at the same time.

ROAST STUFFED SUCKING PIG A d’ANGLAISE

For a sucking pig of medium weight, prepare the followingforcemeat:—Cook three lbs. of large onions with their skins, and let them cool. This done, peel and finely chop them, andput them in a basin with one lb. of the chopped fat of kidneyof beef, one lb. of soaked and well-pressed bread-crumb, fouroz. of parboiled and chopped sage, two eggs, one oz. of salt, a pinch of pepper and a little nutmeg.

Mix the whole well, and put this stuffing inside the suckingpig. Sew up the latter’s belly; put it on the spit, and roast asdirected above.

Serve separately, either a timbale of apple sauce or of mashedpotatoes. Four oz. per lb. of selected raisins, washed andswelled in tepid water, are sometimes combined with the applesauce.

ZAMPINO de MODfeNE

Zampino, or stuffed leg of pork, is a product of Italianpork-butchery.

It is cooked like a ham, after having been tied in a napkinlest its skin burst.

Served hot, it is accompanied by a Madeira or tomato sauce, a garnish of boiled, braised, or gratined cabbages; of Frenchbeans, or of potato purée.

ZAMPINO FROID

Zampino is served cold, alone or mixed with other meats;but it is used more particularly as a hors-d’oeuvre. For thispurpose, cut it into the thinnest possible slices.

460 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

OREILLES à la ROUENNAISE

After having singed and well cleaned the inside of the pig’sears, cook them in water, salted to the extent of one-third oz.of salt per quart, together with a garnish of vegetables as forpot-au-feu. This done, cut them across in suchwise as to havethe end where the flesh is thickest on one side, and the thinnestend on the other side of the strips.

Chop up the thick portion; cut the other into collops, and putthe whole into a saucepan with one-quarter pint of half-glazewith Madeira.

Cook gently for thirty minutes. This done, add to theminced ears, one and one-half lbs. of sausage meat and a pinchof chopped parsley. Divide up the whole into portions, weighingthree oz; wrap each portion in a piece of pig’s caul, insert acollop of ear into the wrapping, and give the latter the shape ofordinary crepinettes. Grill gently, until the cooking is three-parts done; sprinkle with butter and raspings, and complete thecooking of the crepinettes, colouring them in so doing.

Dish in a circle, and serve a Madeira sauce at the same time.

OREILLES à la SAINTE MENEHOULD

Cook the ears as explained above, and let them cool.

Cut them in two, lengthwise; coat them with mustard;sprinkle them with melted butter and raspings, and grill themgently.

Ears are usually served plain, but they may be accompaniedby apple sauce.

PIEDS de PORC TRUFFES

Truffled pig’s trotters may be bought already prepared; allthat remains to be done, therefore, is to grill them.

Sprinkle them with melted butter; grill them very gently, basting them from time to time the while, and serve them with aPérigueux sauce.

PIEDS de PORC PANES

Sprinkle the pig’s trotters copiously with melted butter, andput them on the grill, which should be very hot.

Grill them very gently, turning them with care; and servethem plain, or with a tomato purée separately.

Boudins.

BOUDIN BLANC ORDINAIRE

Chop and afterwards pound one-half lb. of very lean freshpork, and three-quarters lb. of fat fresh bacon. Add one andone-half oz. of foie gras, and rub through a fine sieve.

Put this forcemeat into a basin, and finish it with two fresheggs; one and one-half oz. of chopped onion, cooked in butterwithout colouration; one-sixth pint of thick cream; one-half oz.of salt, a pinch of white pepper, and a little nutmeg.

Mix the whole well; put it into the gut, without overfillingthe latter, and tie round with string at regular intervals. Nowset the boudins on a willow lattice, and plunge them into areceptacle full of boiling water. From this moment keep thewater at 203°F., and let the boudins poach for twelve minutes.This done, withdraw them, and let them cool.

Before serving them, grill them very gently, and, as a pre-cautionary measure, wrap them in buttered paper. Do notcisel them, but prick them with a pin.

Serve a purée of potatoes with cream at the same time.

BOUDINS BLANCS de VOLAILLE

Pound separately one lb. of raw chicken fillets and three-quarters lb. of fresh fat bacon.

Combine the two products in the mortar; pound again withthe view of thoroughly mixing them, and add three oz. ofchopped onion, cooked in butter without colouration, togetherwith a little thyme and bay; one-half oz. of salt, a pinch ofwhite pepper, and a little nutmeg.

Mix the whole well, and add four eggs, one by one, workingthe forcemeat vigorously the while with the pestle.

Rub through a fine sieve; return the forcemeat to the mortar, and add thereto, little by little, one pint of boiled and verycold milk.

Put the forcemeat into the gut; poach it in the bain-marie, and set it to grill, observing the same precautions as in thepreceding recipe.

Serve a purée of potatoes with cream at the same time as theboudins.

BOUDINS NOIRS

Make the following preparation, putting the various in-gredients into a basin:—One lb. of very fresh pork fat, cut intolarge dice, and half-melted; one sixth pint of thick cream; twoeggs; six oz. of chopped onions, cooked in lard without coloura-

tion; two-thirds oz. of salt, a pinch of pepper, and a little spice;a pinch of wild-thyme leaves, and a leaf of bay, both chopped.

Mix the whole well with one pint of blood of pork, and put itinto the gut without over-filling it, for it should be borne inmind that the preparation swells in poaching.

Set the boudins on willow lattices or baskets; plunge theminto boiling water, and, from that time, keep the latter at203°F.

Let them poach for twenty minutes, and remember to prickall those that, by rising to the surface, show they contain air, which might burst their skins. When about to serve them, cisel them on both sides, and grill them very gently.

They are generally accompanied by a potato purée withcream.

BOUDINS NOIRS A d’ANGLAISE

Have ready the same preparation as for black boudins, givenabove, and add to it three-quarters lb. of rice, cooked in con-somm£ and kept somewhat firm. Poach as before, and leave tocool. Cisel the boudins, and grill them over a moderate fire.

Serve very hot with an apple purée.

BOUDINS NOIRS à la FLAMANDE

Have ready the same preparation as for black boudins, andadd to it three oz. of moist sugar, two oz. of raisins, and thesame quantity of currants, washed and swelled in lukewarmwater.

Put the preparation into the gut, and poach in the usualway.

When about to serve, grill these boudins gently, after themanner of black boudins, and send them to the table with asugared apple sauce.

Crepinettes and Sausages.

CREPINETTES TRUFFEES

Add to two lbs. of very good sausage-meat, four oz. ofchopped truffles, and two tablespoonfuls of truffles cooking-liquor. Mix the whole well; divide into portions weighing twoand one-half oz., and wrap each portion in a square of pig’scaul. Shape the crepinettes thus formed rectangularlySprinkle with melted butter, and grill gently.

Dish them in a circle; pour a Périgueux sauce in their midst, and serve a potato purée with cream separately.

CREPINETTES à la CENDRILLON

Prepare the crepinettes as above; wrap them in a doublesheet of buttered paper; over them set a heap of cinders coveredwith burning embers, and keep the latter alive for a space oftwenty minutes, when the cooking operation should be com-pleted.

Formerly, the above was the mode of procedure, but now-adays the crepinettes are merely enveloped, each in an ovallayer of paste. They are then gilded, their tops are streaked, and, after having been laid on a tray, they are baked in a warmoven for twenty minutes.

This done, they are dished on a napkin.

SAUCISSES ANGLAISES

The most well-known of English sausages are those ofCambridge.

They are cooked like the French kind, and they are oftenserved at breakfasts as an adjunct to bacon. Sometimes, too, they serve as a garnish to roast fowls, young turkeys, &c.

Their seasoning is often excessive.

SAUCISSES au VIN BLANC

First Method.—Put the sausages in a well-buttered saut£-pan; poach them gently in the oven, and dish them on thincrusts of bread fried in butter.

For twelve sausages, swill the sauté-pan with one-sixth pintof white wine; reduce this to half; add one-sixth pint of half-glaze sauce; boil for a few minutes, and finish, away from thefire, with one and one-half oz. of butter. Pour this sauce overthe sausages.

Second Method.—Stiffen the sausages in butter; add one-third pint of white wTine, and complete their poaching. Setthem on fried crusts; reduce the wine by two-thirds, and addthereto the yolk of one egg, a few drops of lemon juice, twotablespoonfuls of pale melted meat-glaze, and three oz. ofbutter. Pour the sauce over the sausages.

SAUCISSES de FRANCFORT et de STRASBOURG

Plunge the sausages into a saucepanful of boiling water, andthen poach them for no more than ten minutes; should theybe allowed to cook for a longer time, they would only lose theirquality.

They may be served with a hors-d’oeuvre dish of gratedhorse-radish, and an apple sauce separately; but their properadjunct is braised sauerkraut.

Ham.

However deservedly pork may be praised, it could neverhave been included among the preparations of first-class cookery(except subsidiarily) had it not been for the culinary value ofhams.

With the latter it triumphs, and, be they of Bayonne orYork, of Prague or Westphalia, no other joints enjoy morefavour than these as Relevés.

Though it is somewhat difficult to decide which one of thevarious kinds of ham should be adopted, in my opinion thatof Bohemia, known as Prague ham, is best for a warm dish, and that of York for a cold dish.

The latter is also excellent when served hot, but, even so, for this purpose it is inferior to the Prague kind, the delicacyof which is incomparable.

Still, York ham ranks first in the opinion of many, for itshould be remembered that England has no rival in the pre-paration of seasoned pork, and her famous bacon, the renownof which is enormous, constitutes one of the greatest discoveriesin the science of gastronomy.

HOT HAM—Its Preparation

York ham is the kind chiefly used.

After having soaked it in cold water for six hours, brushit and remove the pelvic bone; put it into a stewpan of coldwater, and set to boil. This done, keep the water just simmer-ing, that the ham may cook after the poaching method.

There is no need of any seasoning or aromatic garnish. Asoften as possible, leave the ham to cool in its cooking-liquor.If the ham is to be braised, take it out of the water thirtyminutes before it is cooked. Skin it; clear it of any superfluousfat, and put it in a braising-pan, just large enough to hold it, with two-thirds pint of some such wine as Madeira, Port, Xeres, Chypre, &c. Select the wine in accordance with thetitle of the dish on the menu.

Having thoroughly sealed down the lid of the pan, put itin the oven, and continue the cooking of the ham gently forone hour, turning it over from time to time during the opera-tion. If it have to reach the table whole, glaze it at the lastmoment.

Its usual adjunct is a light and highly seasoned half-glaze sauce, combined with some of the braising-liquor, cleared of all grease.

JAMBON à la CHANOINESSE

Having poached the ham as explained above, braise it inwhite wine, adding thereto three oz. of mushroom parings.

Dish and send separately a garnish of large, fresh noodles, cohered with butter and a Soubise purée, and completed witha julienne of truffles.

Serve separately a half-glaze sauce, combined with the brais-ing-liquor, cleared of all grease and reduced.

JAMBON à la CHOUCROClTE

Completely cook the ham by poaching; skin and trim it.

If served whole, send, separately, some braised sauerkrautand potatoes, freshly cooked a I’anglaise. Serve a half-glazesauce with Rhine wine at the same time.

If served already carved, arrange the slices in a circle on around dish; put the sauerkraut in their midst, and border withthe potatoes.

Serve, separately, the same sauce as before.

JAMBON à la MAILLOT

Poach the ham; braise it, and glaze it at the last moment.Set it on a long dish, and surround it with the followinggarnish, arranged in alternate heaps:—Carrots and turnips, cut to the shape of large, elongated olives, cooked separately inconsomm6, and glazed; small onions cooked in butter; braisedand trimmed half-lettuces; peas and French beans cohered withbutter separately. ,

Serve apart a thickened gravy combined with some of thebraising-liquor, cleared of all grease.

JAMBON à la PRAGUE SOUS la CENDRE

Poach the ham and drain it on a dish. Remove the skin andall the black, outside parts. Prepare a piece of patty pastelarge enough to enclose the ham. Besprinkle the surface of theham with powdered sugar; glaze quickly at the salamander, and place the ham (glazed side undermost) on the layer ofpaste.

Draw the ends of the paste towards each other; seal themtogether, with the help of a little moisture, in such wise as toenclose the ham completely; turn the latter over, and put it ona tray with the sealed side of the paste lying underneath. Gildand streak, make a slit in the middle of the paste for the escapeof steam, and put the joint in the oven.

Leave it there until the paste is dry and well coloured. Aftertaking the ham out of the oven, inject into it, through a pre-

II II

pared hole, a large wineglassful of Port wine or Sherry. Stopup the hole with a little pellet of paste; dish, and serve imme-diately.

Serve at the same time a garnish of Gnochi, spinach, orSouffle au Parmesan (№2295A).

The best adjunct to Prague ham is a very light glaze pre-pared with Port wine, and buttered at the last minute.

Jambon de Prague à la Metternich

Prepare a ham “sous la cendre” as described above.

Send to the table with it as many fine collops of foie-gras, tossed in butter and each covered with a nice slice of truffle, asthere are diners. Send also a timbale of asparagus-heads.

The waiter in charge then puts a slice of ham, a collop offoie-gras, and a tablespoonful of asparagus-heads on each plateand serves.

The sauce should be a Madeira flavoured with truffle essence.1419b—JAMBON de PRAGUE à la NORFOLK

Prepare a ham as in №1419. Serve each slice of it withone collop of braised veal sweetbread and one tablespoonful offresh peas a la paysanne.

Send as an adjunct the braising-liquor of the veal sweet-bread.

VARIOUS GARNISHES for BRAISED HAM

The garnishes best suited to ham relevés are: —

Spinach; new broad beans; braised lettuce; endives; fresh

peas a la paysanne.

Noodles; Spaghetti; various Macaronis; Gnochi; Purees offresh beans, broad beans.

The most usual accompanying sauce is half-glaze withMadeira.

JAMBON Soufflé

This is a variety of the ham souffles given hereafter. Thepreparation used is the same, and it may be made either fromraw or from cooked ham.

After having completely boned it, but for the end bone, which must be kept, cook the ham, and cool it.

Now cut it horizontally, one-half inch above its bone, fromthe extremity of the end bone to the head of the latter. At thelast-mentioned point, make a vertical incision meeting and end-ing at the first; remove the cushion of ham, which should bynow be quite separated from the rest of the joint, and put asidefor some future purpose.

All that remains of the ham, therefore, is a thick pieceadhering to the end-bone. Carefully trim this piece, and sur-round it with a strong band of buttered paper, tied on by meansof string, the purpose of which is to hold in the soufflé.

This done, put a sufficient quantity of soufflé de Jambon(described hereafter) on the remaining meat of the ham to recon-struct it entirely. Smooth the surface of the preparation withthe flat of a knife (dipped in cold water), and so finish off thecontour of the ham. Decorate according to fancy; place thedish containing the ham on a saucepanfu) of boiling water, andput the two in the oven with the view of obtaining the maximumamount of steam, which latter helps to poach the soufflé. Thissouffled ham may be poached just as well in a steamer.

When the preparation is properly poached, remove the bandof paper; dish the ham, and send one of the garnishes or saucesgiven for braised ham separately.

SOUFFLES au JAMBON

Ham souffles are prepared after two recipes; in the first, cooked ham is used, and in the second the ham is raw. Thislast procedure is derived from mousseline forcemeat, and, in-asmuch as the preparation resulting from it is less flimsy thanthat of the first, it is preferred when a large number of peoplehave to be served.

THE PREPARATION of THE Soufflé

with COOKED HAM

Finely pound one lb. of lean, cooked ham, and add thereto, one after the other, three tablespoonfuls of very cold Bechamelsauce. Rub through a fine sieve; put the resulting puffie into asauffipan, and finish with one-quarter pint of very creamy andboiling Bechamel sauce, flavoured with ham essence; four egg-yolks, and the whites of six eggs, beaten to a stiff froth.

This preparation may be combined with three oz. of gratedParmesan, and the two flavours will be found to blend veryagreeably.

Prepared in this way, it is particularly well suited to the“Jambon Soufflé,” the recipe whereof is given above(№1421).

THE PREPARATION of THE Soufflé

with RAW HAM

Following the quantities given under “Farce mousseline”(№195), make the soufflé preparation, and add thereto four

H H 2

tablespoonfuls of reduced and very cold Bechamel sauce perlb. of raw ham.

Keep the forcemeat somewhat stiff, and finish it with thewhites of four eggs, beaten to a stiff froth, per lb. of ham.

Soufflé de JAMBON ALEXANDRA

Make the soufflé preparation after one of the methods givenabove. Spread it in layers in a buttered timbale, alternatingthe layers of soufflé with others of asparagus-heads cohered withbutter. Smooth the surface to the shape of a dome; decoratewith a fine slice of truffle, and cook in a moderate oven, of atemperature suited to this kind of preparation. Serve thesouffle as soon as it is ready. If it be small, spread only onelayer of asparagus-heads in the middle of it.

If it be large, spread two or three layers of asparagus-heads.

Soufflé! de JAMBON CARMEN

Add to the selected one of the two soufflé preparations—either will do—for one lb. of ham, the purée of one-half lb.of pressed tomatoes, cooked in butter with one half-capsicum, rubbed through a sieve and very much reduced.

Dish the soufflé in a buttered timbale; sprinkle the surfacewith a pinch of red capsicum, cut in fine julienne fashion, andcook as described above.

Soufflé de JAMBON GASTRONOME

Dish the selected ham soufflé preparation in layers in abuttered timbale, and between each layer of it spread a litter ofnoodles, tossed in butter.

Sprinkle the surface with chopped truffles; set a ball oftruffle well in the centre of the soufflé, and cook in the usualway.

Soufflé de JAMBON MILANAISE

Dish the ham soufflé preparation in a buttered timbale, andspread it in alternate layers with a fine garnish & la Milanaise(№1258).

Deck the surface with small pieces of poached macaroni, fried in butter; sprinkle with grated cheese, and cook the soufflein a moderate oven.

Soufflé de JAMBON PERIGOURDINE

Dish the soufflé preparation in layers in a buttered timbale, and between each layer spread a litter of truffle slices. Be-sprinkle the surface with chopped truffles, and cook thesouffle in the usual way.

MOUSSES et MOUSSELINESCHAUDES de JAMBON

Mousses and Mousselines are made from the same prepara-tion as “Farce mousseline de jambon,” in pursuance of thegeneral principles given under №195.

The need of differentiating the terms arises from the factthat mousses are poached in a mould the contents of which aresufficient for a number of people, whereas mousselines are spoon-moulded quenelles, shaped like eggs.

In the preparation of “Farce mousseline de jambon” it isnecessary to allow, in the salt seasoning, for the amount ofsalting the ham has already received.

If the meat of the ham is not very red, the colour of theforcemeat may be intensified by means of a little vegetablered, in order that it may be of a distinct pink shade.

TREATMENT and ACCOMPANIMENT

of HAM Mousse

Put the forcemeat in a deep border-mould, somewhat like aCharlotte, and poach it under cover in a bain-marie.

That the poaching may be regular, keep in water at a con-stant temperature of 205° or 208° Fahrenheit, and allow forty-five minutes for the operation in the case of a mousse made ina quart mould.

The preparation is seen to be cooked when it swells andrises in the mould.

As soon as this occurs, withdraw the latter from the bain-marie; let it stand for five minutes, that its contents may settle;turn it upside-down on a dish, and wait two minutes beforeremoving the mould. In any case, do not take off the moulduntil the liquid which has drained from it, all round the dish, has been soaked up. Ham mousses are chiefly accompaniedby Supreme sauce, or Veloutés with curry or paprika; some-times, too, a highly-seasoned and buttered half-glaze sauce, with Madeira, Port, or Marsala may be used. The most suit-able garnishes for ham mousses are those I have already givenfor Ham.

Treatment and Poaching of Ham Mousselines

As I have already stated, moussclines, like quenelles, aremoulded with a spoon.

They may also be laid, by means of a piping-bag, on thebottom of the well-buttered sauté-pan in which they are to bepoached; they are shaped like meringues, even or grooved,

47°

and, in either case, they are decorated with lozenges, crescents, or discs, &c., of ham or truffle.

Having carried out the selected method of preparation, cover them with boiling water, salted to the extent of one-third oz. per quart, and poach them for from eighteen to twentyminutes, taking care to keep the water at a constant temperatureof 208°F. These mousselines may also be poached dry in asteamer or in a drying stove.

•433—MOUSSELINES de JAMBON ALEXANDRA

Decorate the mousselines, prepared according to one of thetwo methods above described, with one lozenge of ham andanother of truffle. Poach them; drain them well, and dishthem in the form of a crown. Cover them with an Allemandesauce, flavoured with ham essence, and combined with two oz.of grated Parmesan per pint of the sauce, and glaze quickly.

After taking the mousselines out of the oven, set in theirmidst a heap of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter.

MOUSSELINES de JAMBON à la FLORENTINE

Spread a layer of shredded spinach, fried in butter, on adish.

Upon it set the poached and well-drained mousselines; coverthem with the same sauce as that prescribed for the “Mousse-lines Alexandra,” and glaze them quickly.

•435—MOUSSELINES de JAMBON à la HONGROISE

Poach the mousselines, the forcemeat of which must beflavoured with paprika. Drain them; dish them in a circle;cover them with Ilongroise sauce, and glaze them quickly.

On withdrawing the dish from the oven, set a fine heap ofbaked cauliflowers with cheese in the middle of it.

MOUSSELINES de JAMBON aux PETITS POIS

Proceed exactly as described under №1433, but substitutefor the asparagus-heads a garnish of very small peas coheredwith butter.

Cold Ham.

•437—JAMBON FROID à la GELEE

When ham is to be dished cold, it should, if possible, beallowed to cool in its cooking-liquor, except when it has to beboned. In the latter case, take it out as soon as it is cooked;incise it underneath, following the edge of the cushion; detachand remove the bones.

Relevés and ENTREES

Now roll up the ham; bind it tightly in a piece of linen, andcool it under pressure.

Whether boned or unboned, skin it when it is cold; removesome of its fat, and sprinkle it wdth cold, melted aspic untilthe latter covers it evenly.

Dish it up; fix a frill to it, and surround it with fine aspicdice.

JAMBON Soufflé FROID

Proceed exactly as in №1421, but substitute for thesouffle preparation therein described the cold ham mousse below.

Mousse FROIDE de JAMBON

The Preparation of the Mousse.—Finely pound one lb. ofvery lean, cooked ham; add to it one-third pint of cold Velouffi, and rub through a fine sieve.

Put the resulting purée into a basin; season it; work it onice for a few minutes, and mix therewith, little by little, one-quarter pint of melted aspic. Finally combine two-thirds pintof half-beaten cream wdth it.

The mousse may be moulded, either in an aspic-clothedmould, decorated with truffles, as explained under №956, or insmall cassolettes, lined with a thin strip of paper inside theirbrims, after the manner of small, cold souffles.

As the dishing and serving of mousses are always the same, the reader is begged to refer to those recipes dealing with thequestion.

Mousse FROIDE de JAMBON A d’Alsacienne

Take a deep, square dish and garnish it, half-full, with fine, ham mousse. Even the surface of this layer of mousse, and, when it has set, arrange upon it some shells, raised by meansof a spoon dipped in hot water, from a foie-gras Parfait. Assoon as this is done, pour over the foie-gras shells, a sufficientquantity to cover them of half-melted succulent chicken aspicwith Madeira, and let this jelly set.

When about to serve, incrust the dish in a block of ice.

Mousse de JAMBON au BLANC de POULET

Garnish a deep, square dish with some ham mousse. Whenthe latter has set, arrange thereon the suprêmes of a very white, poached fowl. These suprêmes, cut into regular collops, shouldbe coated wdth a white chaud-froid sauce.

Cover with aspic, as directed under “Mousse hl’Alsacienne,” and serve.

N.B.—If desired, the collops need not be coated with chaud-froid sauce, but, in this case, they should be covered with aspic.

Chapter XVI Relevés and Entrées of Game and Poultry

—M0U5SELINES FROIDES de JAMBON

These mousselines are made from the same preparation asthat used for the mousse, and, but for the basic ingredient,which is not the same, they are treated after the manner de-scribed under “Petites Mousses de Homard” (No. 958). Toavoid needless repetition, therefore, the reader will kindly sub-stitute the word ham for lobster in the recipe just referred to.

r

CHAPTER XVI

POULTRY (VOLAILLE).

Although the term “poultry” (Fr. volaille), in its generalsense, implies Turkeys, Geese, Ducks and Pigeons, just as wellas Fowls, only the latter are meant, from the culinary stand-point, when the word “Volaille” appears on a menu.

Four qualities of fowl are recognised in cookery, and eachplays its part, has its uses, and is quite distinct from the otherthree. We have: —

(1) Pullets and capons; usually served whole, either asrelev^s or roasts.

(2) Chickens, so-called “h la Reine”; used for sautes andchiefly for roasts.

(3) Spring chickens; best suited to en cocotte or grilledpreparations.

(4) Chicks; served only en cocotte or grilled.

Supremes and ailerons of fowl, which are among the finestentries, are supplied by chickens h la Reine or by Springchickens.

Finally, there are the giblets, consisting of the pinions,necks, gizzards, and livers of fowl, which give rise to a numberof preparations, the recipes whereof I shall give briefly at theend of the series.

—PULLETS and CAPONS for RELEVES

Pullets and capons for relev^s and entries are poached orpoeled; sometimes, but more rarely, they are braised.

The birds to be treated by poaching are trussed with theclaw's "folded back and inserted into the belly; their fillets andlegs are rubbed with lemon, so as to keep them white, and theyare then covered with thin slices of larding bacon.

The ingredients for chicken poaching stock were given underNo. 249. The bird is known to be cooked when the bloodwhich issues from a prick on the leg is white or faintly pink.

These fowls are sometimes larded or studded. When this isto be done, dip the legs and belly of a trussed and lemon-

474

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

rubbed fowl into boiling white stock; this will be found tosufficiently harden the flesh to allow of its being treated in therequired way. The products used for studding and larding are,according to circumstances, ham or tongue, truffles or mush-rooms, and sometimes, the red part of a carrot for the larding.Only truffles, ham and tongue are used for studding.

Poeled fowls are trussed as above; they are covered withslices of bacon in order that the fillets may be protected duringthe first stages of the cooking; then they are cooked in butteron poeling-aromatics, under cover and in a deep, thick sauce-pan. When the piece is almost cooked, just moisten it a little,either with rich poultry-stock, with the cooking-liquor of trufflesor mushrooms, with Madeira, red or white wine, &c. Thismoistening serves in the basting of the fowl and must there-fore be renewed if it reduces too quickly. After having beencleared of all grease, it is always added to the sauce whichaccompanies the piece of poultry.

Braised fowls are always treated after the manner describedunder No. 248; they are not rubbed with lemon, but they arecovered with slices of bacon. The latter should only cover thebreast, but be thick, notwithstanding; for they protect the belly,which, without them, would shrivel by the time the legs cooked.

The covering of bacon is essential to all pieces of poultry,whether these be poached, poeled, braised or roasted.

—THE WAY TO 5ERVE POULTRY RELEVESQUICKLY and HOT

I feel bound to call the reader’s attention to this very im-portant point in culinary work

Owing to the difficulties involved in the carving of the fowland the placing and arranging of the pieces and their garnishupon the consumers’ plates—both of which operations requiredexterity and expertness, which those in charge very often donot possess, or thanks to the inefficiency of particular installa-tions, or wfflat not, I have noticed for some considerable time,that the method of serving large pieces of poultry is, in manycases, very far from being the right one.

For, indeed, how often does not the diner find himself pre-sented with a plate of fowl which is neither appetisingly daintynor yet sufficiently hot 1 It follows from this, that all the careand trouble devoted by a chef to the preparation of the dish areentirely wasted. Now, I have tried to improve this state ofaffairs, by planning a method of serving which would be atonce simple and expeditious, without necessarily being devoidof tastefulness and presentability.

475

In the first place, it is my practice to remove the fowl’s twosupremes, in the kitchen, and to keep them warm in a littlecooking-liquor until the last minute. Secondly, I remove allthe bones of the breast, and I reconstruct the fowl with agarnish in keeping with the dish, i.e., either a mousseline force-meat, pilaff rice combined with cream, foie gras and truffles,spaghetti, or noodles with cream.

Having properly smoothed and arranged the selected gar-nish, the fowl may now be placed, either at one end of any buta round dish, or on a low cushion of fried bread, on which itmay be set firmly.

It may also be entirely coated with Mornay sauce, sprinkledwith grated cheese, and speedily glazed.

When the body of the bird is dished, its garnish should beset round it in fine, tartlet crusts; its supremes, quickly sliced,should be distributed among the tartlets, and the dish sent tothe table with the sauce separately.

By this means, it reaches the table hot, it is served quicklyand cleanly; and every person gets a slice of meat, and notgarnish only, as was so often the case formerly.

Instead of tartlets, one may use thin croutons of bread, ofthe size of the slices of chicken, and fried in fresh butter.

Thus, for a “Poularde k la Derby,” after having stuffedthe pullet with rice, suppressed the bones of the breast, andremoved the supremes; all that is necessary is to properly shapethe rice, and to dish the fowl on a cushion.

This done, prepare as many croutons and slices of foie-gras, sautdd in butter, as there are diners, and arrange themround the pullet—the slices of foie-gras lying on the croutons.Now, quickly cut the supremes into slices; put one of theseon each slice of foie-gras, and on each of the latter put a sliceof truffle. Put the pullet, thus prepared, in the oven for a fewminutes; let it get very hot, and send it to the table with thesauce separately.

In the dining-room the Maitre-d’hotel quickly serves thegarnished croutons on hot plates, beside each crouton he putsa tablespoonful of the rice with which the pullet has been stuffed,and, finally, a tablespoonful of sauce.

In less than two minutes after its entrance into the dining-room, the pullet is thus served w^arm to each person.

Of course, the above measures refer to the fowl that has tobe dished whole and presented; but, when this is not required,the rice withdrawn from the cooked bird need only be setin the centre of. a deep, square entree dish (fitted with a cover),

476

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

and surrounded by the sliced supremes, with intercalated slicesof foie-gras and truffle. The sauce is also served separately inthis case. Cover the dish, so that it may stand and keep hota few minutes, if necessary, without spoiling.

The legs, which are rarely served at a well-ordered dinner,remain in the kitchen together with the carcass.

I cannot too strongly recommend the system just described,whenever the circumstances allow of its being put into practice.It is the only one that ensures an efficient service, calculatedto give entire satisfaction to all concerned.

— POULARDE ALBUFERA

Stuff the pullet with the rice prescribed under No. 2256, andpoach it. Dish it and coat with Albuffira sauce.

Surround with small tartlet crusts, garnished with trufflesraised by means of a spoon the size of a pea; quenelles of thesame shape; small button mushrooms, and cocks’ kidneys.Cohere this garnish with Albuffira sauce.

Between each tartlet, place a slice of salted tongue, cut tothe shape of a cock’s comb.

— POULARDE ALEXANDRA

Having larded the pullet with tongue and truffle, poach it.This done, remove the supremes, and replace them by mous-seline forcemeat; smooth this forcemeat, giving it the shape ofthe pullet in so doing, and set to poach in the front of the oven.

Now, coat the piece with Mornay sauce, and glaze quickly.Dish, and surround with tartlet-crusts garnished with asparagus-heads, cohered with butter; place a collop of the reservedsupremes (which should have been kept hot) on each tartlet,and border the dish with a thread of pale glaze.

— POULARDE AMBASSADRICE

Stud the pullet with truffles, cover it with a Matignon (No.227), wrap it in muslin, and braise it.

Remove the supremes; suppress the bones of the breast;fill the carcass with a garnish of asparagus-heads, cohered withbutter, and arrange this garnish as already described under No.1444.

Slice the supremes, and put them back on the garnish,in suchwise as to reconstruct the breast of the fowl. Coat thepiece with somewhat stiff and fine supreme sauce; dish it,and surround it with lamb sweet-breads, studded with truffles,

477

braised and glazed, and alternate the sweetbreads with littlefaggots of asparagus-heads.

—POULARDE ANDALOUSE

Poele the pullet. Dish it, and coat it with its poeling-liquor, combined with tomated half-glaze sauce. On eitherside of it set some capsicums, stuffed with rice, and someroundels of egg-plant, seasoned, dredged and tossed in butter;alternating the two products.

—POULARDE à l’ANGLAISE

Poach the pullet, and coat it with a Bechamel sauce fla-voured with chicken-essence.

Dish it and surround it with slices of salted tongue, laidtile-fashion on either side; and heaps of carrots and turnips(cut to the shape of balls) and peas and celery, at either end.All these vegetables should be cooked a I’anglaise; i.e., eitherin boiling water or in steam.

—POULARDE à l’AURORE

Poach the pullet without colouration; dish it, and coat itwith an “Aurore Sauce” (No. 60). Surround it with medium-sized, decorated quenelles; and trimmed oval slices of saltedtongue, arranged according to fancy.

—POULARDE à la BEAUFORT

Stuff the pullet with a fine foie-gras, stiffened in the ovenfor twenty minutes with a little Madeira, and cooled.

Fill up the pullet with a little, fine sausage-meat; stud itwith truffles, and braise it in short moistening.

Dish it on a low cushion, and surround it with braised,lambs’ tongues, alternated with artichoke-bottoms, garnishedwith a rosette of Soubise puree. As an adjunct, use thebraising-liquor, cleared of all grease.

—POULARDE BOUILLIE à l’ANGLAISE

Cook the pullet in light, white stock with one lb. of breastof bacon and a garnish of vegetables as for pot-au-feu. Dish,and surround with the bacon, cut into slices.

Serve, separately, an English parsley sauce, and a sauceboatof the pullet’s cooking-liquor.

M53—POULARDE aux CELERIS

Poele the pullet, and baste it towards the close of the opera-tion with strong veal stock.

Prepare a garnish of braised celery.

478

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Dish the pullet; surround it with the braised celery, andcover the latter with the poeling-Uquor.

— POULARDE aux CHAMPIGNONS A BRUN

Poele the pullet, and swill the saucepan with mushroomessence. Add this swilling-liquor (reduced) to one-quarter pintof half-glaze with Madeira.

Dish the pullet, and surround it with twenty grooved andcooked mushroom-heads. Serve separately the reduced half-glaze, to which add two oz. of fresh butter.

— POULARDE aux CHAMPIGNONS A BLANCPoach the pullet.

Dish it, and coat it with an Allemande sauce flavoured withmushroom essence.

Surround it with twenty grooved, cooked and very whitemushroom-heads.

— POULARDE CHANOINESSE

Prepare a “Poularde Souffle” after recipe No. 1518. Dishit, and surround it with small heaps of crayfishes’ tails, alter-nated with small croutons of fried bread, on each of which placea collop of the supremes. Finish off with a slice of truffle oneach collop of the supremes.

Serve a Mornay sauce, finished with crayfish butter, separ-ately.

— POULARDE CHATELAINE

Poele the pullet without letting it acquire too much colour.Dish it, and surround it with small artichoke-bottoms, stewedin butter and garnished with Soubise.

Alternate the artichoke-bottoms with small heaps of chestnutscooked in consommd and glazed.

Pour a little thickened poeling-liquor on the bottom of thedish, and serve what remains of it, separately, in a sauceboat.

— POULARDE CHEVALIERE

Remove the supremes, and the minion fillets. Lard theformer with two rows of truffles and two rows of tongue; trimthe minion fillets; make five or six slits in each; insert a thinslice of truffle half-way into each slit, and draw the respectiveends of the two fillets together in suchwise as to form two rings.Put the supremes and the minion fillets each into a butteredsaut6pan, and cover the latter.

Remove the pullet’s legs, keeping the skin as long as pos-sible; bone them to within one and one-third inches of the

POULTRY

479

joints, and cut off the claws, aslant, just below the same joints.Garnish the boned regions with godiveau prepared with creamclose the opening by means of a few stitches of strong cotton,and truss each leg in such a manner as to imitate a small duck.

Poach these stuffed legs in stock made from the pullet’scarcass.

Also poach the supremes and the minion fillets in good time,with a little mushroom cooking-liquor, and a few drops oflemon juice.

With a pinch of flour mixed with water, stick a fried crouton(the shape of a pyramid, three inches high and of twro inchbase) in the middle of a dish.

Around this pyramid, arrange the twro stuffed legs and thetwo supremes; putting each of them on a decorated quenellewith the view of slightly raising them. Set the minion filletson the legs, and, between the latter and the supremes, lay smallheaps of cocks’ combs and kidneys, and some very white mush-room-heads. Pierce the crouton with a liatelet garnished withone truffle, one fine cock’s comb, and a large mushroom.

Serve a supreme sauce separately.

N.B.—This dish is generally bordered, either with noodle-paste, white English paste, or with a chased silver border.

—POULARDE CHIMAY

Stuff the pullet with one-half lb. of half-poached noodles,tossed in butter, and combined with a little cream and threeoz. of foie-gras cut into large dice.

Poele it gently; dish it, and coat it with some of its poeling-liquor, thickened.

Distribute over the pullet a copious amount of raw noodles,sauted in clarified butter; and serve the remainder of the thick-ened poeling-liquor separately.

—POULARDE CHIPOLATA

Poele the pullet and put it into a terrine a pate with a gar-nish consisting of small, glazed onions; chipolata sausages,poached in butter; chestnuts cooked in consomm^; fried piecesof baco'n; and, if desired, some small glazed carrots.

Add the pullet’s cooking-liquor, and simmer for ten minutesbefore serving.

—POULARDE à la CHIVRY

Poach the pullet. Dish it and coat it with Chivry sauce(No. 78).

Serve a Macedoine of new vegetables* cohered with butteror cream, separately.

480

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— POULARDE CUSSY

Braise the pullet. Dish it and surround it with wholetruffles, cooked in Mirepoix with Madeira, and alternated withfine, grilled mushrooms, garnished with artichoke purée.

In front of the pullet set a small, silver shell, in which shapea pyramid of large cocks’ combs, heated in butter.

— POULARDE EN DEMI-DEUIL

Between the skin and the fillets of the fowl insert a few fineslices of raw truffle. Lard the pullet and poach it.

When it is ready, strain the cooking-liquor through a napkin ;reduce it, and add it to a very white supreme sauce, containingslices of truffle.

Dish the pullet; cook it with some of the sauce, and sendwhat remains, separately, in a sauceboat.

— POULARDE DEMIDOFF

Poele the pullet. When it is three-parts done, put it intoa cocotte and surround it with the following garnish, preparedin advance and stewed in butter; viz one-half lb. of carrotsand five oz. of turnips, cut into grooved crescents, one inch indiameter; five oz. of small onions cut into thin roundels, andfive oz. of celery.

Complete the cooking of the pullet with this garnish, andadd to it, when about to serve, three oz. of truffles, cut to theshape of crescents, and one-sixth pint of chicken stock.

Serve the preparation in the cocotte, after having cleared theliquor of all grease.

— POULARDE DERBY

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after recipe No. 2256;and poele it. Dish, and surround it with collops of foie-gras,tossed in butter (each set on a small, fried crouton), and alter-nate these with large, whole truffles, cooked in champagne.

As an adjunct, serve the pullet’s cooking-liquor, cleared ofall grease, combined with the cooking-liquor of the truffles andone-sixth pint of veal gravy. Reduce the whole to one-sixthpint and thicken with arrow-root.

— POULARDE DIVA

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after recipe No. 2256, andpoach it without colouration.

Dish it, and coat it with supreme sauce, flavoured withpaprika.

Send a garnish consisting of cepes with cream, separately.

N.B.—This dish was served for the first time to Mme.Adelina Patti, the great singer.

—POULARDE DEVONSHIRE

Bone the breast of a fine pullet; season it inside, and fill itwith a chicken forcemeat, prepared with cream and mixed withhalf its weight of very fine sausage-meat.

In the middle of the pullet set a nice salted and cookedcalf’s tongue, trimmed and cleared of all cartilage; and placeit so that its thin end lies in the region of the bird’s tail.

Sew up the pullet’s belly with thin string, allowing the skinsufficient play not to tear under the pressure of the forcemeat,which swells while cooking. Truss, cover the pullet with aslice of larding bacon, poach, and drain it.

When about to serve, make an incision around the breastwith the point of a knife; detach the stuffing with the bladeof a knife, passed horizontally on a level with the spine, andcut off, at a stroke, the piece consisting of the pullet’s breast,the stuffing, and the calf’s tongue.

Dish the carcass with the legs and wings still attached, ona low cushion. Cut the breast, lengthwise, into two; and, ifthe fowl has been properly stuffed, the tongue should then befound neatly bisected. Slice each half, and return them tothe carcass in suchwise as to reconstruct the bird and give itan untouched appearance.

Coat lightly with Allemande sauce, combined with very redtongue, cut into dice; and surround with a border of timbalesmade from a purée of fresh peas (No. 2196), each set on an arti-choke bottom. Serve a sauceboat of the same sauce as that withwhich the pullet was coated.

—POULARDE à l’ECOSSAISE

Stuff the pullet with pearl barley cooked in white consomm£,well drained, and combined, per lb., with an equal quantity offine sausage-meat (to which has been added a chopped onion,cooked in butter), and two tablespoonfuls of cream.

Poach the pullet in the usual way; dish it and coat it withEcossaise sauce, i.e., an Allemande sauce, combined with abrunoise of vegetables: carrots, onions, leeks, and celery, anda large part of the reduced pullet’s poaching-liquor.

Serve a garnish of French beans with cream, separately.

—POULARDE EDOUARD VII

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after recipe No. 2256,and poach it without colouration. Dish it, and coat it with a

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

482

curry sauce, combined with two oz. of red capsicums in dice,per pint of sauce.

Serve a garnish of cucumbers with cream, separately.

N.B.—This dish was originated at the Carlton Hotel onthe occasion of His Majesty King Edw’ard VII.’s Coronation.

— POULARDE EN ESTOUFFADE

HaU-poele the pullet in a saucepan.

Line the bottom and sides of an oval cocotte with thin slicesof ham. Put the haH-poeled pullet into this cocotte, togetherwith one lb. of carrots, onions, and celery, all three sliced, friedin butter and moderately seasoned with salt and pepper.

Swill the saucepan with one-third pint of strong veal stock;reduce to half; put this reduced stock into the cocotte; cover thelatter; seal down the lid with a thread of paste, and completethe cooking of the pullet in a somewhat hot oven for three-quarters of an hour.

— POULARDE à l’ESTRAGON

Poach the pullet, and add to the ordinary garnish a bunchconsisting of five or six sprigs of tarragon.

Dish, and decorate the pullet’s breast with a nice sprayof blanched tarragon leaves.

Reduce and strain the pullet’s cooking-liquor, and serveit separately.

— POULARDE à la FAVORITE

Stuff the pullet with one-half lb. of rice, prepared afterrecipe No. 2256.

Poach it; dish it, and coat with a supreme sauce.

Surround with a garnish of cocks’ combs and kidneys,and slices of truffle.

— POULARDE à la FERMIERE

Prepare the pullet as for No. 1470; but, instead of liningthe cocotte with slices of ham, cut the latter into dice and addthese to the garnish, together with four oz. of peas and fouroz. of French beans, cut into small lozenges.

— POULARDE à la FINANCIERE

Braise the pullet.

Dish it, and surround it with a garnish consisting of smallheaps of quenelles made from chicken, mousseline forcemeat;grooved, button-mushroom heads; cocks’ combs and kidneys;

POULTRY 483

slices of truffle, and blanched olives. Add a small quantity ofhalf-glaze sauce prepared with truffle essence.

Send a sauceboat of the same sauce separately.

M75—POULARDE à la GASTRONOMF

Stuff the pullet with one-half lb. of noodles, slightly tossedin butter, and poele it.

Swill the saucepan with one-quarter pint of champagne.Dish the pullet and surround it with medium-sized truffles,cooked in champagne, alternated with small heaps of cookedand glazed chestnuts, and place a cock’s kidney between eachheap.

Serve, separately, a half-glaze sauce, flavoured with truffleessence and combined with the reduced swilling-liquor.

—POULARDE à la GODARD

Braise the pullet brown.

Dish it and surround it with spoon-moulded quenelles offorcemeat, combined with chopped mushrooms and truffles;large oval quenelles, decorated with tongue and truffle; groovedbutton-mushroom heads; cocks’ combs and kidneys; glazedsmall lambs’ sweetbreads; and olive-shaped truffles.

Slightly coat this garnish with Godard sauce, combinedwith some reduced braising-liquor, and send what remains ofthe latter in a sauceboat.

—POULARDE à la GRAMMONT

Poach the pullet, and let it half-cool.

Now remove the supremes and the bones of the breast; fillup the cavity in the carcass with a garnish consisting of larks’fillets, sauted just before dishing; grooved button-mushroomheads; cocks’ combs and kidneys; and cohere the whole bymeans of Bechamel sauce, finished with truffle essence.

Slice the supremes, and return them to their place, setting aslice of truffle between each. Coat the pullet with a stiff Alle-mande sauce; sprinkle with grated Parmesan and melted butter;glaze quickly, and serve at once.

—POULARDE GRAND HOTEL

Cut up the fowl as for a saute dish, and cook it in butter,under cover. Then set the pieces in a very hot cocotte, anddistribute thereupon five ox. of raw truffles cut into thick slicesand slightly salted and peppered.

Swill the sautepan with a few tablespoonfuls of white wine;add a little chicken stock; pour this liquor into the cocottc;

l I 2

484

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

thoroughly close the latter, and put it in a very hot oven foreight or ten minutes with the view of cooking the truffles.

Serve the preparation as it stands in the cocotte.

N.B.—This dish was invented at the Grand Hotel at MonteCarlo, as a means of offering to those who could not wait forthe preparation of truffled pullets a substitute of a somewhatsimilar nature to the latter.

— POULARDE au GROS SEL

Poach the pullet, and add to it ten small olive-shaped carrotsand ten small onions.

Dish, and surround the bird with the carrots and the onions,arranged in small heaps.

Serve, separately, a sauceboat containing the pullet’s cook-ing-liquor, and a seller of kitchen salt.

— POULARDE à la GRECQUE

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after recipe No. 2253,and pocle it.

Dish it, and coat it with very strong reduced chicken stock,thickened by means of arrowroot.

— POULARDE à la HONGROISEPoele the pullet.

Dish it; coat it with Hongroise sauce, and surround it withtimbales of pilaff rice, combined with tomato pulp, cut intodice.

Send a Hongroise sauce separately.

— POULARDE aux HUiTRES

Boil the pullet gently in light, white stock, until it is wellcooked. With the cooking-liquor prepare a supreme sauce,and add thereto the almost entirely reduced poaching-liquor oftwenty-four oysters, one-half pint of cream, and the twenty-fouroysters (cleared of their beards).

Dish the pullet, and pour this sauce over it.

— POULARDE à l’INDIENNEPoach the pullet.

Dish it; coat with Indienne sauce, and serve a timbale ofrice h l’lndienne, prepared after recipe No. 2254, separately.

— POULARDE ISABELLE de FRANCE

Stuff the pullet with rizotto, combined with two oz. oftruffle slices and eighteen crayfishes’ tails, and poach it in whitestock containing one bottle of Chablis wine.

With the pullet’s cooking-liquor prepare a highly-seasoned

485

supreme sauce. Dish the bird on a small cushion; coat it withsauce, and surround it with fine black truffles, cooked in cham-pagne, and set each on a small, round, and slightly hollowedcrouton of fried bread.

Serve the remainder of the sauce separately.

—POULARDE à l’lVOIRE

Poach the pullet, keeping it very white. Dish it, and serveit plain.

Send, separately, an ivory sauce, a sauceboat of the pullet’scooking-liquor, and some kind of garnish, such as macaroni ornoodles with cream cepes, cucumber, &c.

i486—POULARDE LADY CURZON

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after recipe No. 2256,and poach it.

Dish it, and coat it with an Indienne sauce.

A garnish of cepes or cucumber with cream may be servedat the same time.

—POULARDE LOUISE D’ORLEANS

Insert a whole foie gras into the pullet, the former havingbeen studded with truffles, poached for fifteen minutes in somesucculent veal stock, and one glassful of old Madeira, and afterwards cooled.

Stiffen and colour the pullet for twenty minutes in the oven,sprinkling it with butter the while.

Cover it entirely with thick slices of truffles; cover thesewith slices of bacon, and envelop the whole in a layer of plaindough, which should be well sealed up. Set the pullet, pre-pared in this way, on a baking-tray; make a slit in the top ofthe paste for the escape of steam during the cooking process,and cook in a moderate oven for one and three-quarter hours.

This pullet is served as it stands, cold or hot.

— POULARDE à la LOUISIANE

Stuff the pullet with one lb. of maize with cream, combined

with one and one-half oz. of capsicums cut into dice, and poeleit. Dish it and border it, on either side, with timbales of riceand fried bananas, arranged alternately. At either end of thedish set a croustade of lining paste, garnished with maize “hI3. cr^mc#5*

— POULARDE à la LUCULLU5

Braise the pullet.

Dish it, and surround it with (1) fine truffles, cooked inchampagne, alternated with (2) large, round quenelles ofmousseline forcemeat. At either end of the dish, which should

486

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

be oval, set a small silver shell of the same height as thecushion on which the pullet lies.

Garnish these shells with very white, curled cocks’ combsand cocks’ kidneys. Add the reduced braising-liquor to a half-glaze sauce, flavoured with truffle essence; cover the bottom ofthe dish with some of this sauce, and send what remains,separately, in a sauceboat.

[490—POULARDE à la MANCIN1

Poach the pullet.

Remove the supremes; suppress the bones of the breastwithout touching either the pinions or the legs, and set thecarcass, thus prepared, on a very low cushion of bread or rice,so that it may be steady.

Fill the carcass with macaroni, cohered with cheese andcream, and combined with three oz. of foie gras in dice, andone-half oz. of a julienne of truffles.

Slice the supremes, and reconstruct them on the macaroni,placing a fine slice of truffle between each. Coat the pulletwith a stiff and unctuous cream sauce; sprinkle with gratedcheese, and glaze quickly at the salamander.

Serve separately a creamy supreme sauce.

— POULARDE MARGUERITE de SAVOIE

Fry quickly ten larks in butter, insert these info a finepullet, and braise the latter in veal stock and white Savoywine, in equal quantities. Prepare a milk polenta (No. 2294);spread it on a tray in layers one inch thick, and let it cool.Now stamp it with a round cutter one and one-half inches indiameter, and, a few minutes before serving, dredge theseroundels of polenta, and brown them in clarified butter.

Just before dishing up, sprinkle them with grated Parmesan,and glaze them quickly at the salamander.

Dish the pullet on a very low cushion of fried bread; sur-round it with the glazed roundels of polenta; pour a little of thefowl’s cooking-liquor, thickened, over the dish, and send whatremains of it in a sauceboat.

Serve at the same time a vegetable-dish of white Piedmonttruffles, slightly heated in a Tittle butter and some consomm£.

— POUI ARDE à la M^NAGfeRE

Poach the pullet in some rather gelatinous white stock.Slice six carrots, six new potatoes, six new onions; put thewhole into a saucepan, and cook gently in the fowl’s poaching-liquor, with the lid of the saucepan off. When the vegetables

POULTRY

487

are cooked, and the liquor is sufficiently reduced, set the pulletin a special oval cocotte, and cover it with the prepared vege-tables and their cooking-liquor.

—POULARDE MIREILLE

Poele the pullet.

Dish it; surround it with small timbales of rice with saffron,alternated with tartlet crusts, garnished with concassed tomatoescooked in butter, and set a fine, stoned olive on each tartlet.

Serve a tomato sauce separately.

—POULARDE à la MONTBAZON

Stud the pullet with truffles, and poach it.

Dish it; coat it with supreme sauce, and surround it withpoached lamb sweetbreads, spoon-moulded quenelles of mous-seline, chicken forcemeat, and grooved mushroom heads, ar-ranged alternately.

Serve a supreme sauce separately.

—POULARDE à la MONTE CARLO

Poach the pullet.

Dish it; coat it with supreme sauce, and surround it on theone side with quenelles of pink, mousseline, chicken forcemeat,and on the other with a border of fair-sized, very black truffles.

—POULARDE à la MONTMORENCY

Lard the pullet with truffles, and braise it in Madeira.

Set it on an oval dish, and, at either end of the latter, placea fine, decorated quenelle; on either side of the fowl arrangesome artichoke-bottoms, garnished with asparagus-heads,cohered with butter.

Serve separately a half-glaze sauce with Madeira, to whichthe braising-liquor of the pullet has been added.

—POULARDE à la NANTUA

Poach the pullet.

Dish it; coat it with a supreme sauce, finished with crayfishbutter, and surround it with small heaps of quenelles withcrayfish butter, crayfishes’ tails, and slices of truffle.

498—POULARDE à l’ORIENTALE

Stuff the pullet with one lb. of pilaff rice with saffron, andpoach it.

Remove its supremes; suppress the breast-bones by meansof scissors, without touching the rice, and coat the latter with

488

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Bechamel sauce coloured with tomato sauce and flavoured withsaffron.

Dish; reconstruct the sliced supremes on the rice, and setbetween each slice another of chow-chow stewed in butter.Cover the pullet with the same sauce as that indicated above,and surround it with quarters of chow-chow cooked in butter, orserve this garnish separately.

— POULARDE aux CEUFS D’or

Poele the pullet without letting it acquire overmuch colour.

Strain the poeling-liquor; clear it of all grease; add theretoa little tomato purée, and thicken it with arrowroot. Finishwith three oz. of butter, the juice of half a lemon, and a littlecayenne.

Dish the pullet; surround it with a border of egg-shapedcroquettes of egg with truffles, and send the sauce separately.

— POULARDE à la PARI5IENNE

Poach the pullet.

Dish it; cover it with Allemande sauce, and decorate it ontop with slices of truffles and salted tongue cut to the shape ofcocks’ combs.

Surround with spoon-moulded quenelles of chicken force-meat, half of which should have been combined with choppedtruffles, and the other half with chopped, salted ox-tongue.

Arrange the quenelles round the fowl, alternately, andborder the dish with a thread of pale glaze.

— POULARDE ADELINA PATTI

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after recipe No. 2256,and poach it in white, chicken stock. Dish it on a low cushion;cover it with a supreme sauce, flavoured with paprika, andsurround it with fair-sized artichoke-bottoms, each garnishedwith a fine truffle, coated with pale meat glaze.

Serve separately a sauceboat of the same sauce as thatalready used in coating the pullet.

— POULARDE à la PAYSANNE

Brown the pullet in butter, and put it into an oval cocotte.

Around it set a garnish consisting of four oz. of the red partof a carrot, three oz. of onion, and two oz. of celery, all threeminced somewhat finely. Complete the cooking of the pulletwith the vegetables, sprinkling it often the while with goodveal stock.

Serve the preparation as it stands in the cocotte.

489

— POULARDE à la PERIGORD

Stuff the pullet with one-half lb. of truffles in the shape of

large olives, cooked in two oz. of melted pork fat, and mixed,while hot, with one lb. of fresh, grated pork fat, rubbed througha sieve. String the piece, taking care to close all its openings,and poele it gently.

Dish it; coat it with a very fine half-glaze sauce, made fromthe ^oeh'wg-liquor and finished with truffle essence.

— POULARDE PETITE MARIEE

Poach the pullet in a little white stock, and surround it (when

setting it to cook) with six small new onions, six small carrots,six small new potatoes, and one-quarter pint of freshly-shelledpeas.

Set the pullet in a cocoite with the garnish of vegetables, andcoat it with its reduced cooking-liquor, combined with someexcellent supreme sauce.

*505—POULARDE à la PIEMONTAISE

Stuff the pullet with two-thirds lb. of rizotto combined withone-half lb. of white sliced truffles, and poele it in the usualway.

Dish it, and serve at the same time a thickened chickengravy to which has been added the reduced f oeling-Wquor.

—POULARDE à la PORTUGAISE

Stuff the pullet with three-quarters lb. of rice, combinedwith five oz. of peeled and concassed tomatoes, cooked in butter.

Poele the pullet. Dish it; coat it with a Portugaise sauce,combined with the poeling-liquor, and surround it with agarnish of medium-sized tomatoes, stuffed with rice “k laPortugaise.”

—POULARDE PRINCE5SE

Poach the pullet.

Dish it, and coat it with an Allemande sauce, flavoured withmushroom essence and finished with two oz. of asparagus-headbutter per pint of sauce. Surround it with croustades ofDuches.se potatoes, rolled in breadcrumbs and melted butter,fried, emptied, then garnished with asparagus-heads coheredwith butter, and each surmounted by a fine slice of truffle.Between each croustade set a faggot of very green asparagus-tiCcids*

—POULARDE PRINCESSE HELENEStuff the pullet with rice prepared after recipe (No. 2256),and poach it. Dish it; coat it with supreme sauce, and sur-round it with spinach subrics, cooked at the last moment; add

490

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

to this garnish some shavings of white truffles, barely heatedin butter, and set in a shell placed behind the fowl.

— POULARDE REGENCE

Stuff the pullet with one lb. of mousseline forcemeat ofchicken, combined with three oz. of crayfish pur£e, and poach it.

Dish it; coat it with Allemande sauce, flavoured with truffleessence, and surround it with the following garnish, arrangedin small heaps:—Spoon-moulded quenelles of mousseline,chicken forcemeat; white, curled, cocks’ combs; slices of rawfoie gras, stamped out with a round cutter, and tossed inbutter; small, grooved, cooked, and very white mushrooms;olive-shaped truffles, and one round quenelle decorated withtruffles at either end of the dish.

— POULARDE de LA REINE ANNE

Poele the pullet.

When it is ready, remove the supremes and the breast bones,and fill the carcass with a garnish of macaroni and cream, com-bined with foie gras and truffle dice. Cover the macaroni withMornay sauce; glaze quickly, and dish the pullet on a low-cushion.

Surround it with small tartlet crusts garnished with cocks’combs and kidneys, cohered with Allemande sauce, and set aslice of the supremes on each tartlet. Put a silver shell con-taining a pyramid of truffles behind the fowl.

Serve an Allemande sauce, flavoured with truffle essence,separately.

— POULARDE REINE MARGOT

Stuff the pullet with two-thirds lb. of mousseline forcemeatof chicken, combined with two oz. of almond purée, and poachit.

Dish it; coat it with supreme sauce, finished with a littlealmond milk, and surround it with quenelles prepared withpistachio butter and quenelles prepared with crayfish butter,arranged alternately.

— POULARDE REINE MARGUERITE

Poach the pullet.

Remove the supremes and the breast bone, without touchingeither the wings or the legs, and set the carcass, thus trimmed,on a low cushion of bread or rice. Finely slice the supremes;add as many slices of truffle as there are collops of supremes,and combine the whole with a souffle preparation with Par-mesan, which should not be too light.

491

Reconstruct the pullet with this preparation; smooth thesurface, and surround the base of the pullet with a band ofpaper, so that it may keep its form. Set some thin slices ofGruy^re cheese upon it; dish it, and cook it in a moderatelyhot oven.

—POULARDE au RIZ

Poach the pullet.

Dish it, and coat it with an Allemande sauce, flavoured withchicken essence. Surround it with a garnish of rice, cookedin the pullet’s poaching-liquor, and moulded in small, buttered,timbale moulds.

—POULARDE ROSSINI

Poele the pullet.

Remove the supremes; slice them, and dish them in theform of a crown upon a round dish, alternating them withcollops of foie gras, tossed in butter. Pour a very strongchicken stock finished with truffle essence in their midst.

Serve, separately, a timbale of noodles with butter coveredwith raw noodles tossed in butter.

—POULARDE SAINTE ALLIANCE

Heat in butter ten fine truffles seasoned with salt and pepper;sprinkle them with a glassful of excellent Madeira, and leavethem to cool thus in a thoroughly sealed utensil. Now putthese truffles into a fine pullet, and poele it just in time for itto be sent to the table.

When the pullet is ready, quickly cook as many ortolans,and toss in butter as many collops of foie gras as there arediners, and send them to the table at the same time as the pullet,together with the latter’s poeling-liquor, strained and in a sauce-boat.

The waiter in charge should be ready for it with three assist-ants at hand, and he should have a very hot chafer on the side-board. The moment it arrives he quickly removes the supremes,cuts them into slices, and sets each one of these upon a collopof foie gras, which assistant No. 1 has placed ready on a plate,together with one of the truffles inserted into the pullet at thestart.

Assistant No. 2, to whom the plate is handed forthwith, addsan ortolan and a little juice, and then assistant No. 3 straight-way places the plate before the diner.

The pullet is thus served very quickly, and in such wise asto render it a dish of very exceptional gastronomical quality.

N.B.—The name “Sainte Alliance” which I give to thisdish (a name that Brillat-Savarin employs in his “Physiology

492

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

of Taste” in order to identify a certain famous toast) struckme as an admirable title for a preparation in which four suchveritable gems of cookery are found united—the supremcs of afine pullet, foie gras, truffles, and ortolans.

This dish was originally served at the Carlton Hotel in 1905.

—POULARDE 5ANTA-LUCIA

Stuff the pullet with truffles, prepared as for No. 1515, andbraise it in Marsala. Dish it on a low cushion, and surroundit with small tartlets of Gnochi “h la Romaine,” alternated withcollops of foie gras, tossed in butter.

*5*7—POULARDE SICILIENNE

Poach the pullet.

Raise the fillets, leaving the wing-bones on the carcass;suppress the breast bones, and fill the resulting cavity withmacaroni, cohered with the strong liquor of braised beef “k laNapolitaine,” and combined with dice of truffles and foie gras,cocks’ combs and kidneys.

Envelop the piece in pig’s caul, giving the former its naturalshape; sprinkle with raspings and melted butter, and set inthe oven that the pig’s caul may cook and colour.

Dish on a low cushion, and coat with chicken glaze withbutter.

Surround with tartlet crusts, each garnished with a slice ofthe supremcs, covered with a slice of foie gras tossed in butter,and surmounted by a slice of truffle.

Send a chicken glaze with butter separately.

—POULARDE SOUFFLEE

Poach the pullet.

Raise the supremes, and cut them into thin slices; suppressthe breast-bones by means of scissors, and stuff the bird withone lb. two oz. of monsseline forcemeat of chicken, combinedwith one-third lb. of foie-gras purde. Spread this preparationin layers, and between each of the latter set alternate slices ofsupreme and truffle.

Reconstruct the bird exactly; smooth its surface; deck itwith bits of truffle, salted tongue, and boiled white of egg;place the dish on a deep tray containing a little boiling water,the steam of which assists the poaching of the preparation, andpoach in a moderate oven.

When about to serve, coat the pullet with Allemande sauceflavoured with truffle essence.

N.B.—The use of a bain-marie consisting of a deep pan

493

containing boiling water, wherein the dish which holds thepullet is placed, is highly recommended, but the ideal methodof poaching this sort of preparations is by means of a steamer.

—POULARDE STANLEY

Stuff the pullet with one-half lb. of rice, three oz. of mush-rooms, and three oz. of a julienne of truffles. Poach it withone lb. two oz. of sliced and blanched onions, seasoned witha pinch of curry. When the pullet is ready, rub the cooking-liquor and the onions through tammy. Add one-third pint ofVelout6 and one-third pint of cream to this cullis; reduce to astiff consistence; rub once more through tammy, and finish withone-sitfth pint of cream.

—POULARDE SOUVAROFF

Stuff the pullet with one-half lb. of foie gras and five oz. oftruffles cut into large dice, and three-parts poele it.

Now put it into a cocotte with ten fair-sized truffles stewedin Madeira for a few minutes in the same saucepan as thatin which the pullet wras poeled. Moisten with one-sixth pintof veal stock; close the cocotte; seal the cover with a thread ofpaste, and complete the cooking in a moderate oven for thirtyminutes.

Serve the fowl as it stands in the cocotte.

—POULARDE SYLVANA

Stuff the pullet with one lb. of mushrooms, tossed in brownbutter, and half-brown it in the oven.

Meanwhile put one pint of fresh peas into a saucepan, to-gether with ten small new onions, one small lettuce cut julienne-fashion, and a faggot consisting of parsley stalks, chervil, anda sprig of mint. Add salt, sugar, two oz. of butter, and mix thewhole up together.

Moisten with two small tablespoonfuls of water; cover andhalf-cook, taking care to toss from time to time during theoperation. When the pullet is half-cooked, put it into a cocottelined w-ith a thin layer of paste, overreaching the edges of thecocotte by about two incl es.

Surround it with a garnish of peas; cover it with a slice ofbacon, and close the cocotte with its cover. Draw the overlap-ping paste over the latter; seal it down with some white of egg,that it may be hermetically closed, and set in the oven for aboutforty-five minutes.

Serve the preparation as it stands in the cocotte. A sauce-boat of good chicken gravy may be served separately.

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

494

— POULARDE TALLEYRAND

Poele the pullet; raise the supremes, and cut these intolarge dice. Mix them with an equal quantity of macaroni, cutshort, and thickened with cream sauce combined with Parmesan,and add enough foie gras and truffles, cut into large dice, toequal half the weight of the supremes.

Suppress the breast-bones; fill the fowl with the above pre-paration, and cover the latter with a layer of mousseline force-meat, reconstructing the bird naturally in so doing. Deck thesurface with a crown of truffle slices; cover with buttered paper,and set in the oven (1) to poach the forcemeat, (2) to thoroughlyheat the preparation beneath.

Dish the pullet; pour a little half-glaze sauce, flavoured withtruffle essence and combined with slices of truffle, over the dish,and serve what remains of the sauce separately.

— POULARDE T05CA

Stuff the pullet with rice, prepared after No. 2256, and poeleit in short moistening. Dish it on a low cushion of fried bread,and surround it with a garnish of braised, tuberous fennel-roots.

Send the pullet’s poeling liquor separately, after havingreduced and finished it with butter.

— POULARDE TOULOUSAINE

Poach the pullet.

Dish it; coat it with Allemande sauce, flavoured with mush-room essence, and surround it with the following garnish, ar-ranged in heaps:—Quenelles of mousseline chicken forcemeat;slices of poached, veal sweetbreads; cocks’ combs and kidneys;cooked and very white button-mushroom heads, and slices oftruffle.

Serve an Allemande sauce, flavoured with mushroomessence, separately.

— POULARDE TRIANON

Poach the pullet.

Dish it, and surround it with quenelles of chicken force-meat, stuffed with foie-gras pur£e. Arrange these quenelles inheaps, and set a nice, whole truffle between each heap.

Pierce the pullet wdth a hatelet, garnished with one groovedmushroom, one fair-sized glazed truffle, and a quenelle decoratedwith salted tongue.

Serve a supreme sauce at the same time.

495

— POULARDE VALENCIENNE

Poele the pullet.

Dish it, and surround it with a garnish of rizotto, combinedwith ham dice. Set a crown of grilled slices of ham upon therizotto.

Serve a well-seasoned tomated supreme sauce separately.

— POULARDE au VERT-PRE

Poach the pullet.

Dish it; coat it with a supreme sauce, finished with prin-tanier butter (No. 157), in the proportion of two oz. per pintof sauce; and surround it with a garnish consisting of peas,French beans, and asparagus-heads, cohered with butter.

—POULARDE VICHY

Stuff the pullet wflth ordinary pilaff rice, and braise it white.Dish it, coat it with a supreme sauce, combined with the re-duced braising-liquor, and surround with small tartlet crusts,garnished with carrots h la Vichy.

—POULARDE VICTORIA

Stuff the pullet with truffles and foie gras, and three-partspoele it, exactly as directed under “Poularde Souvaroff.”

Put it into a cocotte with one lb. of potatoes, cut into largedice and tossed in butter, and complete its cooking and that ofthe potatoes in the oven.

—POULARDE WASHINGTON

Stuff the pullet with ten oz. of green maize, three-partscooked, and combined with one chopped onion cooked in butterand three oz. of good sausage-meat, fried in butter for onemoment with the onion. Braise the pullet, and glaze it at thelast minute.

Serve separately and at the same time a timbale of maizewith cream.

iS3»—CHAPON FIN aux PERLES DU PERIGORD

Stuff the capon with fine truffles, and envelop it in verythin slices of cushion of veal. Braise it with best liqueur-brandy.

Dish and serve separately (1) the braising liquor in a sauce-boat; (2) a timbale of cardoons with gravy.

—POULETS SAUTES

As I pointed out at the beginning of Part V. of this chapter,the chickens best suited to the saute treatment are those termed

496

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

“h la Reine”; they should be of medium size, very fleshy, andtender.

In an extreme case, small pullets or large chickens might beused, but neither of these are so eminently suited to the pro-cedure in question as chickens “h la Reine.”

The fowl which is to be sauted should be cut up thus: afterhaving emptied, singed, and thoroughly cleaned it; cut off itslegs—quite a simple matter, since all that is necessary is thedisjunction of the thigh-bones, after having cut the skin. Cutoff the claws just below the joint of the tibia, and pare thespurs. Now cut the tibia above the joint, and remove thethigh-bone.

Cutthe pinions at the first joint; remove the wings, afterhaving cut round a portion of the breast in such wise that eachwing holds one half of it; finally detach the centrepiece orbreast-bone, which should be left whole if the fowl be smalland cut into two if it be otherwise.

The carcass thus remains. Cut it into two, and trim eachpiece on both sides.

Before setting them to cook, moderately season the pieces offowl with salt and pepper. Whatever the demands of a par-ticular recipe may be, the preparatory principle of sautedchickens is always as follows :—

Take a sautepan just large enough to hold the pieces of fowl,and heat therein two oz. of clarified butter; or, according tocircumstances, half butter and half good oil. When the selectedfat is quite hot, insert the pieces of fowl; let them colour quickly,and turn them over from time to time, that they may do soevenly. Now cover the utensil, and put it in a sufficiently hotoven to ensure the complete cooking of the fowl. Some tenderpieces, such as the wings and the breast, should be withdrawnafter a few minutes have elapsed, and kept warm; but the legs,the meat of which is firmer and thicker, should cook seven oieight minutes more at least.

When all the pieces are cooked, withdraw them; drain awaytheir butter, and swill the sautepan with the prescribed liquor,which is either some kind of wine, mushroom cooking-liquor, orchicken stock, &c. This swilling forms, as I have alreadypointed out, an essential part of the procedure, inasmuch as itsobject is to dissolve those portions of solidified gravy whichadhere to the bottom of the sautepan.

Reduce the swilling-liquor to half, and add thereto the saucegiven in the recipe. Put the pieces of carcass, the claws, thepinions and the legs into this sauce, and simmer for a few

497

minutes. The other pieces, i.e., the wings and breast, arethen added, but when the sauce is sufficiently reduced, it muststop boiling. When the pieces are completely cooked, it isobviously unnecessary for the sauce to boil, since the formerwould only be hardened thereby.

A few minutes before serving, put the pieces into a deepentree dish (fitted with a cover) in the following order:—Thepieces of carcass, the claws and the pinions on the bottom ofthe dish, upon these the legs and the breast, and, last of all, thewings.

The sauce is then finished according to the directions of therecipe, and is poured over the pieces of fowl.

Some chickens are prepared without colouration—that is tosay, the pieces are merely stiffened in butter without browning,and their cooking is completed in the oven as above. In thiscase the swilling-liquor is invariably white, as also the supple-mentary sauces, and the latter are finished with cream.

—POULET SAUTE ARCHIDUC

Fry the pieces of fowl without colouration, i.e., merely stiffenthem. Add four oz. of onions, previously cooked in butter, andcomplete the cooking of the onions and the fowl together.

Withdraw the pieces; dish them; cover the dish, and keep ithot. Moisten the onions with a small glassful of liqueurbrandy; reduce the latter; add thereto one-sixth pint of creamand one-sixth pint of velout6, and rub through tammy.

Reduce this sauce to a stiff consistence; finish it, away fromthe fire, with one and one-half oz. of butter, the juice of thequarter of a lemon, and a tablespoonful of Madeira, and pourit over the fowl.

Set about ten slices of truffle on the latter, and serve.

—POULET SAUTE ARLESIENNE

Saute the chicken in oil, and withdraw the pieces.

Swill with one-quarter pint of white wine; add a piece ofcrushed garlic as large as a pea, one-sixth pint of tomated half-glaze sauce, and reduce by a third. Dish the chicken, andsurround with alternate heaps of onion and egg-plant roundels,seasoned, dredged, and fried in oil, and concassed tomatoescooked in butter.

—POULET SAUTE ARMAGNAC

Cook the pieces of chicken in butter without colouration; addthereto three and one-half oz. of raw slices of truffle, and dishin a shallow cocotte.

Swill with a small glassful of old liqueur brandy; add a few

K K

498 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

drops of lemon juice and one-sixth pint of cream; heat; finishthis sauce, away from the fire, with two oz. of crayfish butter,and pour it over the fowl.

Serve in the cocotte.

— POULET SAUTE D’ARTOIS

Saute the chicken in butter, and dish the pieces.

Swill with three tablespoonfuls of Madeira, and add one-seventh pint of light, pale meat glaze, four small quarteredartichoke-bottoms, tossed in butter, ten carrots shaped likeolives, cooked in consommd and glazed, and eight small onionscooked in butter.

Finish with one and one-half oz. of butter and a pinch ofchopped chives, and pour this sauce over the pieces of fowl.

— POULET SAUTE BEAULIEU

Saute the chicken in butter, and add to it five oz. of newpotatoes (the size of hazel-nuts) and the same quantity ofsmall quartered artichoke-bottoms, cooked in butter beforehandwith the potatoes.

Keep the whole in the oven, under cover, for ten minutes.

Set the pieces of fowl, the potatoes and the artichoke-bottoms in an earthenware saucepan, and add twelve blackolives.

Swill the saucepan with a few tablespoonfuls of white wineand a little lemon juice; complete with a tablespoonful of vealstock, and pour into the cocotte.

Simmer for five minutes, in the utensil, and serve the pre-paration as it stands.

— POULET SAUTE BORDELAISE

Saute the chicken in butter, and dish it. Surround it withsmall quartered artichoke-bottoms stewed in butter; slicedpotatoes cooked in butter, and roundels of fried onions, arrangedin small heaps, with a small tuft of fried parsley between eachheap.

Swill the saucepan with a few tablespoonfuls of chickengravy, and sprinkle the fowl with the latter.

— POULET SAUTE BOIVIN

Fry the chicken in butter and add twelve small onions; threequartered artichokes, small and very tender; twenty-four smallpotatoes of the size of hazel-nuts. Cover and cook the wholetogether, in the oven.

Dish the chicken with the onions and potatoes over it, andsurround it with the artichokes.

499

Swill the saucepan with two tablespoonfuls of consommd;add three tablespoonfuls of pale glaze, a few drops of lemonjuice, and one and one-half oz. of butter; and pour this sauceover the chicken.

—POULET SAUTE BRETONNEStiffen the pieces without colouring them, and add theretothree oz. of the white of a leek and the half of an onion,both sliced and stewed in butter beforehand. Cover and set inthe oven.

About five minutes before the fowl is quite cooked, addthree oz. of mushrooms, minced raw and tossed in butter.

Dish the pullet, add one-sixth pint of supreme sauce andas much cream to the vegetables; reduce to half, and pour thesauce and the vegetables over the chicken.

— POULET SAUT6 aux cEpesSautS the chicken in oil. When it is cooked, drain away

the oil, dish it; heat three chopped shallots in the sautdpan;swill with one-quarter pint of white wine; reduce, and completewith one and one-half oz. of butter.

Pour this sauce over the chicken, and surround the latterwith eight oz. of cepes, sauted k la Bordelaise.

Sprinkle a pinch of chopped parsley over the chicken.

— POULET SAUTls CHAMPEAUXSaute the chicken in butter; dish it, and surround it with

small onions and potatoes (the size of hazel-nuts), both cookedin butter beforehand. Swill with a little white wine; add one-sixth pint of veal gravy and one tablespoonful of meat glaze;reduce; finish with one and one-half oz. of butter; and pour thissauce over the chicken.

*543—POULET SAUTE CHASSEURSaute the chicken in equal quantities of butter and oil, anddish it. Swill the saucepan with a few tablespoonfuls of whitewine, and reduce; add one-quarter pint of Chasseur SauceEscoffier; heat; pour over the chicken, and sprinkle the latterwith a pinch of concassed parsley.

—POULET SAUTE CYNTHIASauti the chicken in butter and dish it.

Swill the saucepan with a glass of dry champagne; reduceto half; add one tablespoonful of light poultry glaze; finishwith two and one-half oz. of butter, the juice of half a lemon,and one tablespoonful of dry Curasao; pour this sauce overthe chicken.

K K 2

500

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Surround the latter with three oz. of grapes, cleared of allskin and pips, and ten sections of an orange, peeled in suchwisethat the pulp of the fruit is raw.

— POULET SAUTE DEMIDOFF

Colour the chicken in butter; add the vegetable garnish givenfor “Poularde & la Demidoff” (1464), and put the two to stewin the oven. About ten minutes before the cooking is com-pleted, add two oz. of truffles, cut to the shape of crescents likethe carrots and turnips, and three tablespoonfuls of good vealstock.

Dish the pieces of chicken, and cover them with the garnish.

— POULET SAUTE à la DORIA

Colour the pieces of chicken in oil and butter; add theretoone-half lb. of cucumber cut to the shape of garlic cloves; andcomplete the cooking by stewing in the oven.

Dish the chicken with the cucumber upon it. Swill thesaucepan with one tablespoonful of veal gravy and a few dropsof lemon juice; and sprinkle the chicken and its garnish withthis swilling-liquor, to which add one and one-half oz. of brownbutter.

— POULET SAUTE à la DURAND

Dredge the seasoned pieces of chicken, and toss them in oil.Dish them in the form of a crown; garnish their midst witha fine heap of roundels of fried onion; and, in the centre ofthe latter, set a cone, made from a very thin slice of ham andfilled with concassed tomatoes cooked in butter.

— POULET SAUTE à l’EGYPTIENNE

Colour the pieces of chicken in oil. Toss in oil,together, three oz. of onion, and two oz. of mushrooms, sliced;and six oz. of raw ham, cut into dice.

Set the pieces of chicken in a cocotte, alternating them withthe garnish, which should have been well-drained; cover withtwo tomatoes, cut into thick slices; cover the cocotte, and com-plete the cooking in the oven for twenty minutes.

When about to serve, sprinkle with a tablespoonful of vealstock.

i54Sr~POULET SAUTE à l’ESPAGNOLE

Saute the chicken in oil. Drain the latter away, and addone-half lb. of pilaff rice, combined with one and one-half oz.of capsicums in dice; three oz. of large green peas, cooked dI’anglaise, and two sliced and poached sausages.

Soi

Cover the saut^pan, and set the whole to stew in the ovenfor ten minutes.

Dish the chicken; cover it with the garnish, and surroundit with six small grilled tomatoes.

—POULET SAUTE à l’ESTRAGON

Toss the chicken in butter, and dish it.

Swill the saut^pan with one-sixth pint of white wine; reduceto half; add one-sixth pint of gravy in which tarragon has beeninfused, and thicken with arrowroot.

Pour this sauce over the chicken, and decorate its wingswith sprays of parboiled tarragon leaves.

*551— POULET SAUTE FEDORA

Saute the chicken in butter, without colouration, with fouroz. of raw, sliced truffles; and dish.

Swill with one-sixth pint of cream; add three tablespoonfulsof Bechamel sauce, and reduce to half. Finish, away from thefire, with one and one-half oz. of crayfish butter, a few dropsof lemon juice, and a little cayenne; add four oz. of parboiledasparagus-heads to this sauce, and pour it over the chicken.Or, after having cohered them with butter, the asparagus-headsmay be arranged in heaps round the fowl.

—POULET SAUTE au FENOU1L

Saute the chicken in butter, without colouration; swill withcream; add three quartered tuberose fennels, trimmed to theshape of garlic cloves and parboiled, and complete the cookingof the fennels and the chicken, together.

Set the pieces of fennel in the form of a crown on a specialearthenwarg dish, and put the chicken in their midst, placing thepieces side by side. Coat with Mornay sauce, flavoured withchicken essence, and set to glaze.

—POULET SAUTE à la FERMlfcRE

Slice three oz. of the red part of a carrot, the same quantityof turnip, two oz. of celery, and half an onion. Season witha little salt and sugar, and half-stew in butter.

Brown the pieces of chicken in butter; put them in thecocotte with the garnish of vegetables; add thereto two and one-half oz. of ham cut into dice, and complete the cooking of boththe chicken and the vegetables, in the oven.

When about to serve, sprinkle with four or five tablespoon-fuls of veal stock.

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

502

*554—POULET SAUTE aux FINES HERBES

Saute the chicken in butter, and two minutes before dishingit, sprinkle it with one-half oz. of chopped shallots. Swill thesaut^pan with one-sixth pint of white wine; reduce; add threetablespoonfuls of strong, veal gravy and as much half-glazesauce; and finish the sauce, away from the fire, with one andone-half oz. of butter and a coffeespoonful of chopped parsley,chervil, and tarragon. Pour it over the chicken.

*555—POULET SAUTE FORESTIERE

Sautd the chicken in butter; sprinkle it with a table-spoonful of chopped shallots; add five oz. of quartered morels;stew in the oven for ten minutes, and dish the chicken.

Swill with white wine; add one-sixth pint of veal stock;reduce, and pour over the chicken with the morels. Surroundwith four small heaps of potatoes, cut into large dice and tossedin butter; put a rectangle of frizzled bacon between each heap,and sprinkle a pinch of chopped parsley over the chicken.

—POULET SAUTE QABRIELLE

Saute the chicken in butter, without colouration, and dish it.Swill with one-eighth pint of mushroom cooking-liquor; addthree tablespoonfuls of Bdchamel sauce, and three tablespoonfulsof cream; reduce, and finish the sauce, away from the fire, withone and one-half oz. of butter.

Pour this sauce over the chicken; sprinkle on it some veryblack truffle, cut julienne-fashion, and surround it with littleleaves of puff-paste, baked white.

*557—POULET SAUT^ GEORGINA

Saute the pullet in butter with twelve small new onions anda small faggot, containing a sprig of fennel. Dish the chicken.

Swill with three tablespoonfuls of mushroom cooking-liquorand as much Rhine wine; add one-fifth pint of cream; twelvemushroom-heads, sliced; and reduce the cream to half.

Complete with a pinch of chopped chervil and tarragon, andpour over the chicken.

—POULET SAUTE! HONGROISE

Prepare a sufficient quantity of pilaff rice, combined withconcassed tomatoes, to make a border.

Saute the chicken in butter, without colouration, with achopped half-onion and a little paprika. When the onion isslightly coloured, add three peeled and quartered tomatoes, and

5°3

complete the cooking of the whole. Mould the rice to form aborder, and set the chicken in the middle.

Add one-sixth pint of cream to the tomatoes; reduce to half;rub through tammy; heat this sauce, and pour it over thechicken.

—POULET SAUT6 à l’INDIENNEOU CURRIE de POULET

Cut the chicken into small pieces, and fry them in oil witha sliced onion and a large pinch of curry. Swill with one-sixthpint of cocoanut milk or, failing this, almond milk; add one-third pint of velout6, and complete the cooking of the chickenwhile reducing the sauce to half. Set in a deep dish, and servea timbale of rice k l’lndienne separately.

—POULET SAUTE JAPONAISE

Fry the chicken in butter; add one lb. of cleaned and par-boiled stachys and complete the cooking of the whole, chickenand stachys, in the oven.

Dish the chicken with the stachys upon it. Swill with one-sixth pint of slightly thickened veal stock; complete, away fromthe fire, with one and one-half oz. of butter, and pour this overthe chicken.

—POULET SAUTE JURASSIENNE

Saute the chicken in butter and, when it is ready, add toit one-half lb. of blanched breast of fresh pork, cut into stripsand well fried in butter. Drain away three-quarters of thechicken’s grease; swill with one-sixth pint of light half-glazesauce, and dish the chicken.

Complete the sauce with a pinch of chopped chives, andpour it over the chicken with the strips of bacon.

—POULET SAUTE LATHUILE

Heat three oz. of butter in a saut^pan, just large enough tohold the chicken and its garnish. Set the pieces of chicken inthis butter, together with one-half lb. of potatoes and five oz.of raw artichoke-bottoms, both cut into fair-sized dice.

When the chicken and the vegetables are coloured under-neath, turn the whole over at one stroke and complete thecooking on the other side; sprinkle the chicken with threetablespoonfuls of meat glaze and a pinch of chopped parsleycontaining a mite of crushed garlic, and set the chicken and thegarnish on a dish, after the manner of “Pommes Anna.”

Pour two and one-half oz. of nut-brown butter over thewhole, and surround with roundels of seasoned onions, dredged

5°4

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

and fried in oil, and very green, fried parsley, arranged in alter-nate heaps.

— POULET SAUTE LYONNAISE

Saut6 the chicken in butter and, when it is half-cooked, addthree fair-sized onions, finely sliced, tossed in butter and slightlycoloured.

Complete the cooking of the chicken and the onions together,and dish the former. Swill with one-sixth pint of veal gravy;reduce; pour this liquor and the onions over the chicken, andsprinkle the whole with a pinch of chopped parsley.

— POULET SAUTE MARENGO

Saute the chicken in oil. Swill the sautdpan with white wine;add two peeled and concassed tomatoes, or one and one-halftablespoonfuls of tomato pur£e, a mite of crushed garlic, tensmall mushrooms, and ten slices of truffle.

Dish the chicken; cover it with sauce and garnish; surroundit with heart-shaped croutons, fried in butter; small, fried eggs,and trussed crayfish cooked in court-bouillon, and sprinkle thewhole with a pinch of concassed parsley.

— POULET SAUT6 MARYLAND

Season the pieces of chicken; dip them in butter; roll themin bread-crumbs, and cook them in clarified butter. Dish,placing a slice of grilled bacon between each piece of chicken;surround with small, fried galettes of maize flour, and friedslices of banana.

Serve a horse-radish sauce with cream, separately.

— POULET SAUTE MARSEILLAISE

Saute the chicken in oil, and, when it is half-cooked, addthereto two crushed cloves of garlic; three oz. of ciseled, greencapsicums, and the same weight of quartered tomatoes—all threetossed in oil.

When the chicken is cooked, drain away the oil; swill thepan with one-sixth pint of white wine and a few drops of lemonjuice, and reduce almost entirely.

Dish the chicken; cover it with the garnish, and sprinklewith a pinch of concassed parsley.

— POULET SAUTE MEXICAINE

Saute the chicken in oil; swill the saut^pan with a fewtablespoonfuls of white wine; reduce, and add one-sixth pintof tomat^d veal gravy.

POULTRY

505

Dish the chicken; pour the sauce over it, and surround itwith grilled capsicums and mushrooms, garnished with con-cassed tomatoes cooked in butter.

—POULET SAUT^ M1REILLE

Saute the chicken in oil and add to it, when half-cooked,one chopped onion, four concassed tomatoes, and one pimentocut into dice. Ten minutes before serving, flavour with a smallpiece of crushed garlic.

Dish the chicken; pour the juice of the tomatoes into thesaut^pan; reduce to half, and strain over the chicken.

Serve a timbale of rice, flavoured with saffron, separately.

—POULET SAUTE aux MORILLES

Colour the chicken in butter and three-parts cook it; addto it two-thirds lb. of morels, stewed in butter, and completethe cooking of the chicken, under cover, in the oven.

Dish the chicken with the morels upon it; swill the saut^panwith a tablespoonful of brandy; add thereto the juice of themorels, two tablespoonfuls of meat glaze, and one and one-half oz. of butter, and pour this sauce over the chicken.

—POULET SAUTE NORMANDE

Half-sautt the chicken in butter, and set the pieces in acocotte with one lb. of peeled and sliced russet apples. Swillwith a small glassful of liqueur cider; put this liquor in thecocotte; cover, and set in the oven, that the chicken may becompletely cooked and the apples as well.

Serve the preparation, as it stands, in the cocotte.

—POULET SAUTE PARMENTIER

Brown the chicken in butter, and add one lb. of potatoes,raised by means of an oval spoon-cutter, or cut into large dice,and already slightly frizzled in butter.

Complete the cooking in the oven, and dish the chicken withthe potatoes arranged in heaps all round. Swill with a fewtablespoonfuls of white wine; add to it a tablespoonful of vealgravy; pour this over the chicken, and sprinkle the latter witha pinch of chopped parsley.

—POULET SAUTE PIEMONTAISE

Saute the chicken in butter and dish it.

Swill with a few tablespoonfuls of white wine; add thereto atablespoonful of melted pale meat glaze, and pour this overthe chicken. Sprinkle it at the last moment with two oz. of

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

506

nut-brown butter, and finally with chopped parsley, and servea timbale of rizotto with white truffles separately.

•573—POULET SAUTE PORTUGAISE

Saute the chicken in butter and oil, and dish it. Drain awaya portion of the butter used in the cooking, add to the remaindera mite of crushed garlic and a chopped half-onion; and, whenthe latter is fried, add four oz. of peeled and concassed tomatoes,two oz. of sliced mushrooms, a few drops of white wine, anda pinch of concassed parsley.

Complete the cooking of the whole, taking care to reduceall moisture.

Cover the chicken with its garnish, and surround it with half-tomatoes or tomatoes stuffed with rice.

— POULET SAUTfi PROVEN^ALE

Saute the chicken in oil and dish it. Swill with white wineand add thereto a mite of crushed garlic, three oz. of con-cassed tomatoes, four anchovy fillets cut into dice, twelve blackolives stoned and parboiled, and a pinch of chopped sweet basil.

Leave the whole to simmer for five minutes, and cover thechicken with it.

— POULET SAUTE STANLEY

Colour the chicken in butter, and complete its cooking undercover with one-half lb. of minced onions. Dish it in a fiat,earthenware cocotte, setting a heap of mushrooms on either sideof it; add one-third pint of cream to the onions; simmer forten minutes; rub through tammy, and reduce.

Finish this sauce with one oz. of butter, a little curry, andpour it over the chicken.

Set ten slices of truffle on the latter.

— POULET SAUTE aux TRUFFES

Half-saute the chicken in butter; add six oz. of rawtruffles, cut into slices, and complete the cooking under cover.Dish; swill with a few tablespoonfuls of Madeira; reduce; addthree tablespoonfuls of half-glaze sauce; finish with one andone-half oz. of butter, and pour this sauce over the chicken.

•577—POULET SAUT^ VAN DYCK

Cook the chicken in butter without letting it brown; swillwith one-sixth pint of cream; add one-sixth pint of supremesauce, and reduce by a third.

Mix one-half lb. of young parboiled hop-sprouts to the

POULTRY 507

sauce; simmer for two minutes, and pour over the chicken, whichshould be dished in a cocotte.

— POULET SAUTE VICHY

Colour the chicken in butter; add one-half lb. of half-cookedcarrots a la Vichy (No. 2061) to it, and complete the cookingof the chicken and the carrots under cover in the oven.

Swill with a few tablespoonfuls of veal stock; dish thepullet, and cover it with the garnish of carrots.

— POULET SAUTE VERDI

Prepare a border of rizotto k la Piemontaise.

Saute the chicken in butter; set it in the centre of theborder, and on the latter arrange a crown of slices of foie gras,tossed in butter, alternated with slices of truffle, resting againstthe chicken.

Swill with Asti wine; reduce; add three tablespoonfuls ofveal stock and one and one-half oz. of butter, and pour thissauce over the pieces of chicken.

—FILETS. 1581—SUPREMES. 1582—COTELETTES

—AILERONS of CHICKEN

The terms “Fillet” and “Supreme” are synonymous, andeither one or the other may be used for variety to expressthe same thing on a menu. They are names given to thebreast of the fowl, divided into two along the sternum, andcleared of all skin. Each fillet or supreme comprises the largeand the minion fillets.

When suprernes are taken from a small chicken, the minionfillets are not removed; if the chicken be an ordinary one ora pullet, the minion fillets are removed, cleared of all tendons,and twisted into rings or crescents, after having been contisedwith slices of truffle that are half-inserted into the little incisions,made at regular intervals in the meat with the point of a knife.

Prepared in this way, these fillets are generally included inthe garnish of the supremes. Chicken ailerons and cutlets(the latter must not be mistaken for those prepared from cookedmeat and which are only a kind of croquette) are supremes towhich the humerus-bone of the wing is left adhering.

Cutlets are always cut from such fowls as chickens k laReine, or very fleshy, spring chickens. The same rule appliesto supremes: though, sometimes, the latter are cut from pullets.But, in that case, as they would be too large, they are cut intothree or four very regular pieces, which are slightly flattened,and trimmed to the shape of hearts or ovals; except when theyhave to be stuffed.

508

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

In the latter case, they are opened in the thickness, by meansof the point of a small knife, to form sacks; and, in theresulting interstice the selected stuffing is inserted, with thehelp of a piping-bag fitted with a little, even pipe, and in asufficient quantity to fill out the supremes well.

Supremes and cutlets are always cooked without liquor, oralmost so; for should any moistening liquid even approach theboil, it would immediately harden them. If they be desiredpoached, it would be best to cook the whole fowl, and cut themfrom the latter when it is cooked.

This is how they are prepared, according as to whether theybe required colourless or sauted; though the brown method ofpreparing them is applied more particularly to cutlets.

Cutlets or supremes sauted: Season them with salt; rollthem in flour; set them in a vegetable pan containing some veryhot clarified butter, and quickly gild them on both sides. Thesepieces of fowl are so tender that they are cooked and gilded atthe same moment of time.

Cutlets or supremes prepared without colouration: Seasonthem, and set them in a vegetable-pan, containing some fresh,melted, unclarified butter. Roll the supremes in this butter;add a few drops of lemon juice; thoroughly seal the vegetable-pan, and put it in a very hot oven.

A few minutes suffice for the poaching of the supremes,which are known to be ready when they seem resilient to thetouch, and are perfectly white.

Important Remarks: Chicken Supremes or cutlets shouldnever be allowed to wait, lest they harden. They should becooked quickly, at the last moment; dished and served imme-diately. The shortest wait is enough to spoil them, and to makean insipid and dry preparation of what should be an exquisitedish.

N.B.—The recipes given hereafter for supremes may ofcourse be applied to fillets, cutlets, ailerons, blanc de poulet,&c.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE AGNES SOREL

Line some oval buttered tartlet-moulds with mousselineforcemeat. Upon the latter, put some raw, sliced mushrooms,tossed in butter; cover with forcemeat so as to fill the mould,and poach in the bain-marie.

Turn out in a circle on a round dish; put a poached supremeon each tartlet; coat with Allemande sauce; deck with a trufflegirt by a ring of very red tongue, and surround the supremewith a thread of pale, meat glaze.

POULTRY

5° 9

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE ALEXANDRA

Poach the supremes dry. Dish them with a few slices oftruffle set upon them; coat them with Mornay sauce, flavouredwith chicken essence, and glaze quickly. Surround with smallheaps of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE AMBASSADRICE

Poach the supremes dry. Dish them; coat them withsupreme sauce, and surround them with lamb sweetbreads,studded with truffles and cooked without colouration, alternatedwith faggots of asparagus-heads.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE ARLESIENNE

Season and dredge the supremes, and toss them in clarifiedbutter.

Meanwhile, fry in oil some egg-plant roundels and someseasoned and dredged roundels of onion. Also prepare agarnish of tomatoes tossed in oil. Dish the egg-plant roundelsin a circle on a round dish; set the supremes thereon, and gar-nish the latter with the tossed tomatoes and the fried onions,set in small heaps upon them.

Serve a delicate, tomat^d half-glaze sauce separately.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE BOISTELLE

Cut the supremes into heart shapes, and stuff them withmousseline forcemeat combined with half its bulk of mashed rawmushrooms.

Put the supremes in a buttered vegetable-pan, with two-thirdslb. of peeled, minced, raw mushrooms; season with salt, whitepepper and lemon juice, and set to poach slowly in a moderateoven.

Dish in the form of a crown, in a timbale, with the mush-rooms in the centre.

Add to the liquor, which should only consist of the moistureof the mushrooms, two and one-half oz. of butter and a fewdrops of lemon juice; pour this sauce over the supremes, andcomplete with a pinch of chopped parsley.

—SUPREME5 de VOLAILLE AUXCHAMPIGNONS, A BLANC

Poach the supremes in a little mushroom cooking-liquor.

Dish them in the form of a crown, with some fine very whitecooked mushroom-heads. Coat them moderately with Alle-mande sauce, combined with the cooking-liquor of thesupremes.

Serve what remains of the sauce separately.

5io

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE AUXCHAMPIGNONS, A BRUN

Cook the supremes in clarified butter, as already described.Dish them; surround them with mushrooms, minced raw andtossed in butter, and coat them with a light mushroom sauce.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE CHIMAYCook the supremes in clarified butter.

Dish them; garnish them with tossed morels and asparagus-heads, cohered with butter, and surround with a thread of goodthickened gravy.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE CUSSY

Collop the supremes; slightly flatten each collop; trim themround, dredge them, and toss them in butter.

Set each collop of supreme upon an artichoke-bottom aboutequal in size to the former; put a thick slice of glazed truffleon each collop, and a very white cock’s kidney upon eachslice of truffle.

Serve a thickened gravy separately.

I593_SUPR£mES de VOLAILLE DORIA

Season and dredge the supremes, and toss them quickly inclarified butter. Dish them and surround them with piecesof cucumber, shaped like garlic cloves and cooked in butter.

When about to serve, sprinkle them with a little nut-brownbutter, and a few drops of lemon juice.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE DREUX

Make some incisions, at short intervals, in the supremes,and half-insert into these, alternate roundels of truffle and saltedtongue. Poach them dry. Dish; surround with a garnish ofcocks’ combs and kidneys, and slices of truffle, and pour amoderate quantity of Allemande sauce over this garnish.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE ECARLATE

Incise the supremes as above; but garnish them only withroundels of tongue. Poach them dry, and set them on oval,flat quenelles of mousseline forcemeat, sprinkled with very redchopped tongue.

Coat with clear supreme sauce, that the red of the tonguemay be seen.

— SUPREiMES de VOLAILLE ECOSSAISE

Poach the supremes.

Dish them; coat them with Ecossaise sauce, and surroundthem with small heaps of French beans, cohered with butter.

POULTRY 511

*597—SUPR&MES de VOLAILLE FAVORITE

Saute the supremes in clarified butter.

Dish them in a crown, on tossed slices of foie gras, withthree slices of truffle on each supreme.

In their midst set a heap of asparagus-heads, cohered withbutter, and serve, separately, a sauceboat of light meat-glaze,buttered.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE FINANClfeRE

Saute the supremes in clarified butter.

Dish them in the form of a crown, upon fried croutons ofthe same size; in their midst arrange a garnish k la financi&re(No. 1474), and coat the supremes and their garnish withfinanci&re sauce.

*599—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE aux FONDS

D’ARTICHAUTS

Saute the supremes in clarified butter.

Dish them with a garnish of raw artichoke-bottoms, sliced,tossed in butter, and sprinkled with fine herbs. Sprinkle afew drops of nut-brown butter over the supremes, and serve athickened gravy separately.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE GEORGETTE

Prepare ■ as many “pommes Georgette” as there aresupremes, and take care to choose potatoes of the same size asthe supremes.

Poach the supremes. Set one on each potato, with a fineslice of truffle in the middle, and arrange in the form of a crownon a round dish.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE HENRI IV.

Collop the supremes; slightly flatten the collops, and trimthem round. Season and dredge them; saute them in clarifiedbutter, and set each collop on an artichoke bottom, slightlygarnished with buttered meat-glaze.

Serve a B^arnaise sauce separately.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE HONGROISE

Prepare some pilaff rice, combined with concassed tomatoes,and dish it in a shallow timbale.

Season the supremes with Paprika; toss them in clarifiedbutter, and set them in a timbale, upon the pilaff rice.

Swill the vegetable-pan with a few tablespoonfuls of cream;add the necessary quantity of Hongroise sauce, and coat thesupremes with this sauce.

512

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE à l’INDIENNE

Saute the supremes in butter, and put them for a fewminutes in a curry sauce & l’lndienne, but without letting thelatter boil.

Dish the supremes in a timbale with the curry sauce.

Serve a timbale of rice k l’lndienne, separately.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE JARDINIERE

Saute the supremes in butter. Dish and surround with smallheaps of vegetables, arranged very neatly, as explained in thecase of the Jardiniere garnish.

Sprinkle the supremes with a few drops of nut-brownbutter, just before serving.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE JUDIC

Cut the supremes into heart shapes; season them, and poachthem dry.

Dish them in a crown, upon little braised lettuces; and seta slice of truffle and a cock’s kidney upon each heart of supreme.Coat slightly with thickened gravy.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE MARECHALE

It is the rule that all preparations termed “k la Mar^chale”should be treated with chopped truffle; that is to say that thelatter takes the place of the customary bread-crumbs.

For the sake of economy the a Vanglaise treatment (i.e., eggand bread-crumbs) is more commonly applied; so the readermay choose which of the two he prefers. In any case, sautethe supremes in butter; dish them in the form of a crown, witha fine slice of truffle on each, and set in their midst a garnishof asparagus-heads, cohered with butter.

N.B.—Formerly, these supremes, like all preparations “kla Mar^chale,” were gently grilled upon buttered paper.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE MARYLAND

Proceed exactly as directed under “Poulet saut6 & la Mary-land” (No. 1565).

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE M0NTPEN5IER

Roll the supremes in beaten egg and bread-crumbs, andsaute them in clarified butter. Dish them in a crown with aslice of truffle upon each, and surround with small heaps ofasparagus-heads, cohered with butter.

Sprinkle the supremes with a few drops of nut-brown butter.

513

—SUPREMES de VOLA1LLE ORLY

Take some supremes of chicken & la Reine, and set themon a dish with parsley stalks and finely sliced onions; sprinklewith a little oil and lemon juice, and set to marinade for anhour.

When about to prepare them, dry them by means of a pieceof linen; dip them into light batter, and put them in a veryhot frying fat that they may cook quickly.

Drain; dish on a napkin with bunches or a border of verygreen fried parsley, and serve a tomato sauce separately.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE à l’ORIENTALE

Saute the supremes in butter, and dish them each upon athick slice of chow-chow, cut to the same shape, parboiled, andstewed in butter beforehand. Coat with Supreme sauce, com-bined with a quarter of its bulk of tomato pur£e, and flavouredmoderately with saffron.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE EN PAPILLOTE

Cut out as many heart-shaped pieces of kitchen paper asthere are supremes, and either butter or oil them.

Quickly stiffen the supremes in butter. In the centre of eachpaper heart, set a slice of ham cut to the shape of a triangle;cover the ham with a tablespoonful of reduced Italienne sauce;set the supremes on the sauce, and cover it with the same sauceand another triangle of ham. Close the pieces of paper, andpleat their edges in such wise as to entirely enclose their con-tents; set the papillotes, thus prepared, on a tray; and put themin a sufficiently hot oven to allow of completing the cooking ofthe supremes and blowing out the papillotes.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE au PARMESAN

Season the supremes; dip them in beaten egg and roll them

in grated Parmesan. Saute them in butter, and dish them oncroutons of polenta (No. 2294), shaped somewhat like thesupremes and browned in clarified butter. When about toserve, sprinkle the supremes with nut-brown butter.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE à la POLIGNAC

Poach the supremes dry, and dish them.

Coat them with Supreme sauce, combined with a julienne oftruffles and mushrooms.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE à la POJARSKI

Mince the supremes, and, in so doing, combine with them,

firstt the quarter of their weight of bread-crumbs dipped in milk

L L

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

5H

and well squeezed, and the same weight of fresh butter; andthen an equal quantity of fresh cream, which should be addedlittle by little. Season with salt, pepper, and nutmeg.

Divide up this preparation into portions equal in size to thesupremes, and shape them exactly like the latter; in short,reconstruct the supremes exactly with this mince-meat.

Dredge; cook in clarified butter, and serve as soon asready.

There is no hard and fast rule for the garnishing of thesesupremes; the garnish is therefore optional.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE REGENCE

Cut the supremes into heart shapes; flatten them slightly,and poach them. Set each supreme on a quenelle of chickenforcemeat, prepared with crayfish butter, and dish in the formof a crown. Coat with Allemande sauce, flavoured with truffleessence, and, on each supreme, set an olive-shaped truffle anda cock’s kidney—the two separated by a cock’s comb.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE RICHELIEU

Treat the supremes a I’anglaise, and cook them in clarifiedbutter.

Dish them; coat them with half-melted butter h la Maitred’hdtel, and set four fine slices of truffle on each supreme.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE ROSSINI

Sautd the supremes in butter, and dish them on collopsof foie gras, arranged in the form of a crown and also tossedin butter. Coat with a stfong Madeira sauce, combined withslices of truffle.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE TALLEYRAND

Prepare :—(1) a croustade of lining paste, of a size in propor-tion to the garnish to be put inside it, just as the garnishshould be in proportion to the number of supremes:—(2) agarnish of macaroni with cream, combined with three oz. of foiegras and three oz. of truffles in dice, per one-half lb. ofmacaroni.

Cut the suprimes to the shape of hearts; stuff them withgodiveau with cream (No. 198), mixed with half its bulk of apur£e of foie gras, and poach them dry.

Put the macaroni in the croustade, shaping it like a domein so doing; coat the supremes with Allemande sauce, and setthem in a crown on the timbale and round the dome ofmacaroni.

Send a sauceboat of velout£ to the table separately.

SlS

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE VALEN^AY

Stuff the supremes with truffles, cut into small dice andcohered with very reduced Allemande sauce. Treat them &I’anglaise and cook them in butter.

Prepare some fried croutons, shaped like cocks’ combs, inthe proportion of two for each supreme; cover these with adome of fine truffled forcemeat, and put them in a moderate oventhat the forcemeat may poach.

Dish the supremes in the form of a crown; surround themwith the crofitons; and, in their midst, pour a pur£e of mush-rooms.

—SUPREMES de VOLAILLE à la VALOIS

Treat the supremes a I’anglaise, and cook them in clarifiedbutter.

Dish them with a garnish of small, stoned olives, stuffedand poached at the last moment.

Serve a Valois sauce separately.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE VERNEUIL

Marinade the supremes as for No. 1609; treat them d.

Vanglaise, and cook them in clarified butter. Dish them inthe form of a crown, and coat them with Colbert sauce.

Serve separately a pur£e of artichokes, combined with finely-minced truffles.

— SUPREMES de VOLAILLE VILLEROY

Poach the supremes without completely cooking them.

Dip them in a Villeroy sauce, in such wise that they may bewell coated with it. Leave them to cool; treat them a Vanglaise ;and, a few minutes before serving, put them in some very hotfrying fat. Dish them in the form of a crown, and serve aP^rigueux sauce separately.

—BLANC de POULET ELISABETH

Raise the supremes of two small chickens; poach them inbutter and lemon juice, and coat them with Supreme sauce.

Dish them around a low, very cold cushion of bread, placedon the dish at the last moment. Upon the cushion, quickly set a dozen shelled oysters, which should have been kept in icefor at least two hours before dishing.

Serve very quickly in order that the supremes may be veryhot and the oysters very cold. Send a Supreme sauce sepa-rately.

L l 2

516

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— TURBAN de FILETS de POULET

Take the required number of fillets, which is determinedby the size of the mould to be used. Flatten these fillets outsomewhat thinly, and trim them neatly on both sides.

With these fillets, line a buttered savarin-mould; setting arow of thin slices of truffle between each of the fillets, andallowing the latter to hang over the edge of the mould. Overthe fillets spread a layer of mousseline forcemeat, two-thirds in.thick.

Three-parts fill the remaining space with a large tongue,truffles and mushrooms salpicon, cohered by means of a reducedAllemande sauce.

Cover this salpicon with forcemeat, so as to fill the mould,and then draw the overlapping ends of the fillets across theforcemeat.

Set to poach in the bain-marie for about forty minutes; and,upon withdrawing the mould, let it stand for five minutes,that its contents may settle. Turn out upon a round dish; poura Toulousaine garnish (see Poularde No. 1524) in the middle,and surround the turban with a thread of Allemande sauce.

— MIGNONNETTES de POULET

Take the required number of small, minion fillets of pullet;trim them; make six incisions in each, and half-insert into eachof these incisions alternate thin roundels of truffle and tongue.

Set these minion fillets on a buttered dish, and shape themlike rings.

Trim and indent the edges of as many artichoke-bottoms asthere are minion fillets, and heat them in butter. Garnish theseartichoke-bottoms, dome-fashion, with a very white and some-what stiff chicken pur£e. Sprinkle the minion fillets with alittle mushroom cooking-liquor, and poach them in the ovenfor from five to six minutes.

Set the artichoke-bottoms in a circle on a round dish, andset a minion fillet upon each.

Serve a very delicate Supreme sauce, separately.

— NONNETTES de POULET AGNES SOREL

Truss twelve ortolans for entries, and stiffen them in butterfor a moment.

Raise the fillets of twelve spring chickens; trim them; flattenthem slightly and pair them off, putting the edges of one onthe other, that a larger surface may be obtained.

5i7

In the middle of these joined supremes of chicken, put anortolan; wrap it in them, and tie them round once or twicewith string, that they may keep the shape of a panpiette.

Set these paupiettes in a shallow saut^pan, and, five minutesbefore serving, sprinkle them with four oz. of boiling butter;salt moderately, and cook in a fierce oven.

After having removed the string, set each nonnette on asquare, hollowed crouton of bread-crumb, fried in butter, andcoated inside with foie-gras purée. Coat moderately with alight chicken glaze, finished with butter, and squeeze a dropof lemon juice on each nonnette.

—URSULINES de NANCY

Prepare some barquette crusts.

Mould some chicken forcemeat into large, round, regularquenelles, and poach them in some white consomm^, in timefor them to be ready when the Ursulines are being dished.

A few moments before serving, garnish the barquette crustswith foie-gras purée, thinned with a little good half-glaze,flavoured with port or sherry wine. In the middle of each gar-nished barquette, set a well-drained mousseline quenelle; deckeach quenelle with a thin and wide slice of truffle; set a smallheap of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter, at either end ofthe barquettes, that is to say, on either side of the quenelle; andslightly coat the latter with chicken glaze, finished with butter.

Serve, separately, a sauceboat containing some of the samechicken glaze with butter.

—FILETS de POULET à la SAINT-GERMAIN

Season the fillets, dip them in melted butter and roll themin bread-crumbs; grill them gently, each on a sheet of oiledpaper, and sprinkle with clarified butter during the operation.

Dish the grilled fillets, and serve at the same time :—(1) aB^arnaise sauce; (2) a timbale containing a puree of foie graswith cream.

—FILETS de POULET MIREILLE

Prepare a garnish as for No. 1365; i.e., sliced, raw potatoesand artichoke-bottoms, set in a small earthenware dish andcooked as “Pommes Anna.”

Saute the fillets in butter at the last moment; put them onthe garnish, and sprinkle them with nut-brown butter.

518

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

SPRING CHICKENS (POULETS de GRAINS)

Spring chickens are usually either grilled or prepared “encasserole” in accordance with one or another of the manyrecipes applicable to them.

— POULET de GRAINS à la BELLE-MEUNlERE

Stuff the chicken with four sliced chickens’ livers and threeoz. of raw, quartered mushrooms, slightly tossed in butter.Slip five or six fine slices of truffle under the skin of the breast;truss the chicken as for an entree, and brown it in butter.

This done, put it into an oval cocotte, with two oz. of butter,four rectangles of blanched breast of pork, and three oz. ofraw quartered mushrooms, quickly tossed in butter beforehand.

Cook in the oven, under cover, and add two tablespoonfulsof veal gravy, just before serving.

— POULET de GRAINS à la BERGERE

Fry in butter four oz. of blanched breast of pork, cutinto dice, and one-half lb. of small, whole mushrooms. Drain,and set to brown in the same butter, the chicken stuffed witha half-onion and three oz. of mushrooms, chopped and friedin butter, and mixed with three oz. of butter and a coffee-spoonful of chopped parsley.

When the chicken is well coloured or gilded, put the baconand the mushrooms round it; swill with one-sixth pint of whitewine; reduce by two-thirds; add four tablespoonfuls of vealgravy, and complete the cooking of the chicken in the oven.

Set it on a round dish; thicken the cooking-liquor with apiece of manied butter, the size of a hazel-nut, or a little arrow-root; pour the sauce and the garnish round the chicken, andsurround it with a border of freshly-fried straw potatoes.

— POULET de GRAINS BONNE FEMME

Fry in butter four oz. of breast of fresh or salted pork, cutinto slices and blanched. Drain; colour the chicken in the sametat, and put it in an oval cocotte with the slices of bacon.

With the same fat, fry in a frying-pan two-thirds lb. ofpotatoes cut to the shape of corks and divided into roundels;put these round the chicken, and set to cook in the oven, undercover.

When about to serve, sprinkle the fowl with a few table-spoonfuls of veal gravy.

Serve the preparation in the cocotte.

5J9

—POULET de GRAINS EN CASSEROLE

Poele the chicken with butter in an earthenware saucepan,and baste it often the while. When about to serve, clear of allgrease, and add a tablespoonful of veal gravy.

This chicken is served plain, without any garnish.

—POULET de GRAINS EN COCOTTE

Brown the chicken in butter, in a cocotte, and under cover.

When it is half-done, surround it with two oz. of frizzledpieces of fresh or salted pork cut in dice, twelve small onionspartly cooked in butter, and twenty small potatoes, the size andshape of olives.

Complete the cooking of the whole together, and, whenabout to serve, sprinkle with a little veal gravy.

—POULET de GRAINS CLAMART

Brown the chicken in butter; half-cook it, and put it in acocotte with one-half pint of half-cooked peas h la Fran^aise(No. 2193), the cooking-liquor of which should be very short.Complete the cooking of the whole, together, and serve the pre-paration as it stands, without cohering the peas.

—POULET de GRAINS GRILLE DIABLE

Truss the chicken as for an entree; split it open lengthwisealong the middle of the back; flatten it with a butcher’s beater,and remove as many bones as possible. Season it; sprinkleit with melted butter, and half-cook it in the oven.

This done, coat it thoroughly with mustard strengthened bymeans of cayenne; sprinkle copiously with bread-crumbs; pressupon the latter with the flat of a knife, that they may adhereto the mustard; sprinkle a little melted butter over the bird, andcomplete the latter’s cooking gently on the grill.

Set on a round dish, bordered with thin slices of lemon, andserve a Devilled Sauce EscofRer separately.

—POULET de GRAINS, GRILLE à l’ANGLAISE

(Spatchcock)

Split the chicken open, laterally, proceeding from the ex-tremity of the belly to the wing-joints. Open it without separat-ing the two halves, flatten it so as to break the joints and thebones, and remove the fragments of the latter with great care.

Fix the wings by means of a skewer; sprinkle the chickenwith melted butter, season it, and half-cook it in the oven.

This done, sprinkle it with bread-crumbs and melted butter,and complete its cooking on the grill. Set it on a round dish,bordered with gherkins, and serve it as it stands.

520

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— POULET de GRAINS aux FONDS D’ARTICHAUTS

Brown the chicken in butter, and put it in a cocotte withfive fair-sized artichoke-bottoms, sliced while raw, and tossedin butter.

Complete its cooking gently in the oven, and, when aboutto serve, add a tablespoonful of veal gravy and a few drops oflemon juice.

— POULET de GRAINS à l’HOTFLIERE

Bone the chicken’s breast; stuff it with one-half lb. of goodsausage-meat, and truss it as for an entree. Brown it withbutter in an earthenware saucepan, and put it in the oven.

When it is twfo-thirds done, add to it four oz. of quarteredmushrooms, sauted in butter, complete its cooking, and, whenabout to serve, finish it writh three tablespoonfuls of veal gravy.

— POULET de GRAINS à la KATOFF

Split the chicken open along the back, and half-cook it inthe oven as in No. 1636. This done, complete its cooking onthe grill.

Meanwhile, mould on a round, buttered dish a sort of galetteof Duchesse potatoes (No. 2212), one inch thick. Gild, andcolour in the oven.

Dish the grilled chicken on this galette, and surround thelatter with a thread of strong veal gravy.

— POULET de GRAINS à la LIMOUSINE

Stuff the chicken with one-half lb. of good sausage-meat,combined with two oz. of chopped mushrooms fried in butter.Put the chicken in a cocotte with one oz. of butter and sixrectangles of blanched breast of bacon, and cook gently in theoven.

When about to serve, add two or three tablespoonfuls ofveal gravy.

Send, separately, six fine chestnuts cooked in consommd.

— POULET de GRAINS MASCOTTE

Brown the chicken in butter, and cook it “en casserole”with four oz. of potatoes the size and shape of olives and tossedin butter.

When the chicken is almost cooked, put it in a cocotte withthe potatoes all round, two tablespoonfuls of veal gravy, andtwo oz. of sliced truffles set upon it.

Cover the cocotte; put the chicken in the front of the ovenfor ten minutes, and serve it as it stands.

521

—POULET de GRAINS aux MGRILLES

Prepare this chicken like the one “en casserole,” and sur-round it with one-half lb. of morels, tossed in butter for amoment. Complete the cooking under cover, and, when aboutto serve, finish with one tablespoonful of veal gravy.

—POULET de GRAINS SOUVAROFFProceed exactly as explained under No. 1520, but reducethe garnish by half.

—POULET de GRAINS TARTAREProceed as for No. 1636, but serve a Tartare sauce at thesame time.

CHICKS (POUSSINS)

The most perfect example of this class would be the Ham-burg chick, were it not for the fact that it is too often kept inconfinement and fed on fish, which gives a disagreeable flavourto the young bird.

When it is bred rationally, however, this chick is a greatdelicacy.

—POUSSINS CENDRILLONOpen the chicks along the back, and brown them in butter,This done, season them with salt and cayenne, and put thembetween twTo layers of pork forcemeat. Wrap them in very softpig’s caul. Dip them in melted butter; roll them in bread-crumbs, and grill them gently for twenty or twenty-five minutes.Dish, and serve a P^rigueux sauce separately.

—POUSSINS à la PIEMONTAISEStuff each chick with one and one-half oz. of white Pied-mont truffles, pounded with an equal weight of very fresh porkfat. Now truss them as for an entree; string them and fry themin butter over a fierce fire. At the end of ten minutes putthem in a cocotte; partly surround and cover them writh rizotto& la Pi^montaise, and complete the cooking in the oven withlid off.

A few minutes before serving, sprinkle the rizotto with gratedParmesan; glaze; and, at the last minute, sprinkle with nut-brown butter.

—POUSSINS à la POLONAISEStuff each chick with one and one-half oz. of gratin force-meat, two-thirds oz. of soaked and pressed bread-crumbs, one-third oz. of butter, and a pinch of chopped parsley. Truss asfor entries; string; quickly fry the chicks in butter in a very

522 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

hot oven; put them in a cocotte, and complete their cooking inthe oven.

At the last moment sprinkle them with a few drops oflemon juice and nut-brown butter, combined with one oz. ofbread-crumbs per four oz. of butter.

— POUSSINS à la TARTARS

Proceed exactly as for “Poulet a la Tartare.”

— TOURTE de POUSSINS à la PAYSANNE

Prepare a round layer of short paste, ten inches in diameter.Upon this paste spread two-thirds lb. of sausage-meat, com-bined with five oz. of dry Duxelles, taking care to leave a margintwo inches wide of bare paste all round.

Upon this coating of forcemeat set ten half-chicks, stiffenedin butter; sprinkle two-thirds lb. of chopped mushrooms, sautedin butter, over them; spread a second coating of sausage-meatand Duxelles over the whole; cover with a very thin slice ofbacon, and close the whole with a layer of paste a little largerthan the underlying one, the edges of which should have beenmoistened. Seal the two edges, and pleat regularly; gild;streak; make a slit in the top, and bake in a moderate oven forabout forty minutes.

When taking the tourte out of the oven, pour into it, throughthe slit in its cover, a few tablespoonfuls of half-glaze sauce.

— POUSSINS à la VIENNOISE

Cut the chicks each into four pieces; season them; dredgethem; dip them in beaten egg, and roll them in bread-crumbs.

A few minutes before serving, put them in hot fat; drainthem, and dish them in pyramid form on a folded napkin.Surround with fried parsley and sections of lemon, and servevery hot.

Various Preparations of Fowl

— ABATIS aux NAVETS

Fry one-half lb. of blanched breast of pork, cut into dice, inbutter. Drain, and fry in the same'saut^pan three lbs. of giblets,cut into pieces (all except the livers, which are only added one-quarter hour before dishing). Sprinkle with two and one-half oz. of flour; mix the latter with the pieces, and cook it inthe oven for seven or eight minutes; moisten with three pintsof white stock. Season with a pinch of pepper; add afaggot and a crushed, garlic clove; set to boil, stirring thewhile; cover, and place in a somewhat hot oven, that the pre-paration may boil gently.

523

At the end of thirty-five minutes transfer the pieces to an-other saucepan; put back the bacon; add twenty-four smallonions, tossed in butter, one lb. of turnips shaped like elongatedolives and glazed, and strain the sauce over the whole.

Complete the cooking gently, and serve in a timbale.

N.B.—With the same procedure, the giblets may be pre-pared with peas; with mixed, new vegetables; k la chipolata, &c.

—GIBLET PIE

Fry the giblets, cut into pieces, in butter; sprinkle themmoderately with, flour; cook the latter, and moisten with justsufficient consomm^ to make a clear sauce which will just coverthe pieces. Three-parts cook, and leave to cool.

This done, pour the whole into a pie-dish; cover with a layerof puff-paste, which should be sealed down to a strip of paste,stuck to the edge of the dish; gild; streak, and bake in a mode-rately warm oven for from twenty-five to thirty minutes.

—BALLOTINES ET JAMBONNEAUX

These preparations are useful for disposing of any odd legsof fowls, the other parts of which have been already used. Thelegs are boned and stuffed, and the skin, which should be pur-posely left long if this preparation be contemplated, is thensewn up. The stuffing used varies according to the kind of dishin preparation, but good sausage-meat is most commonly used.

Ballotines or Jambonneaux are braised, and they may beaccompanied by any garnish suited to fowl.

If they be prepared for serving cold, coat them with jelly, orcover them with brown or white chaud-froid sauce, and garnishthem according to fancy.

Boudins et Quenelles de Volaille

—BOUDINS de VOLAILLE à la RICHELIEU

Take the required amount of chicken forcemeat, preparedwith panada and cream, and divide it into three-oz. portions.Roll these portions into sausage-form, and open them so as tostuff them with some white chicken-meat, truffle and mushroomsalpicon, cohered with reduced Allemande sauce. Thesequenelles may also be moulded in little, rectangular cases, usedin biscuit-making, as follows:—Line the bottom and sides ofthe moulds, which should be well buttered, with a thickness ofone-third inch of forcemeat; garnish the centre with salpicon;cover with forcemeat up to the edges, and smooth with theblade of a small knife dipped in tepid water.

524

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Whichever way they are made, however, the boudins arepoached like quenelles, and are afterwards drained on a piece oflinen. They are then dipped in beaten egg and rolled in bread-crumbs, and, finally, gently coloured in clarified butter, thattheir inside may get heated at the same time.

Dish them in a circle on a folded napkin, and serve a P£ri-gueux sauce separately.

—BOUDINS de VOLAILLE SOUBISE

Prepare the boudins with some forcemeat as above, butreplace the salpicon inside by a very reduced .and cold truffledSoubise pur£e.

Poach, dip in beaten egg, and roll in bread-crumbs, andcolour as before in clarified butter.

Serve a clear Soubise separately.

*657—QUENELLES de VOLAILLE MORLAND

Mould some portions of somewhat firm chicken mousselineforcemeat into the shape of oval quenelles, three oz. in weight.Dip them in beaten egg; roll them in finely minced truffle, andpress lightly on the latter with the blade of a knife, in orderthat it may combine with the egg.

Poach gently in clarified butter, tinder cover, that the force-meat may be well cooked.

Dish in a circle, and in the middle pour a mushroom purée.

— QUENELLES de VOLAILLE D’UZES

Line the bottom and sides of some oval buttered quenellemoulds with chicken forcemeat prepared with panada and cream.Garnish the middle with a mince of the white of chicken meatcohered with reduced Allemande sauce, and cover with force-meat.

Poach the quenelles in good time; drain them on a piece oflinen; set them in a circle on a round dish, and coat withAurore sauce. Garnish the centre of the circle with a fineJulienne of truffles.

— CAPILOTADE de VOLAILLE

Prepare an Italienne sauce, combined with cooked, slicedmushrooms. Add to this sauce some thin slices of cold fowlremains, and heat without allowing to boil at all.

Dish in a timbale, and sprinkle a little chopped parsley overthe preparation.

— CHICKEN PIE

Cut a fowl into pieces as for a fricassee; season the pieces,and sprinkle them with three finely-chopped onions, one and

5*5

one-half oz. of chopped mushrooms cooked in butter, and apinch of chopped parsley.

Line the bottom and sides of a pie-dish with thin slices ofveal; set the pieces of fowl inside, putting the legs undermost:add five oz. of thin slices of bacon; the yolks of four hard-boiled eggs cut into two; and moisten sufficiently to three-partscover with chicken consomm£. Cover with a layer of puff-paste, which should be sealed down to a strip of paste stuck tothe edges of the pie-dish; gild; streak; make a slit in the middleof the paste, and bake in a moderate oven for one and one-halfhours.

When taking the pie out of the oven, pour a few table-spoonfuls of strong gravy into it.

—CRATES ET ROGNONS de COQ

In order to prepare cocks’ combs and kidneys, they shouldbe first set to soak in cold water for a few hours.

If they are fresh, they should be put in a saucepan of coldwater; the latter should be made lukewarm, and they shouldthen be drained and rubbed in a towel that their skins may beremoved. This done, they are trimmed, and kept in fresh water,which ought to be frequently changed until they are quite white.

They may then be cooked in a very light Blanc (No. 167).

The kidneys are merely soaked in cold water for a few hours,and put to cook with the combs a few minutes before the latterare ready.

Cocks’ combs and kidneys are mostly used as garnish;nevertheless, they also serve in the preparation of special dishes,for which I shall now give a few recipes.

—CRETES ET ROGNONS de COQ à la GRECQUE

About twenty-five minutes before serving, prepare a pintof pilaff rice, combined with one half-capsicum cut into dice,and a very little saffron.

Also prepare ten roundels of egg-plant, seasoned, dredged,and fried in oil just before dishing. The moment the riceis cooked, add thereto twenty-four very fresh cocks’ kidneys,frizzled in butter, and twelve fine blanched cocks’ combs, poeledafter the manner of lambs’ sweetbreads.

Set the whole in a silver saucepan, arrange the egg-plantroundels in a circle on the rice, and serve instantly.

-DESIRS de MASCOTTE

Put three oz. of butter in a vegetable-pan, and fry it nut-brown.

526

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Add to this butter twenty-four fine cocks’ kidneys (it isessential that these should be fresh); season them with salt,pepper, and a little red pepper, and cook them for from fiveto six minutes, which should prove sufficient.

Meanwhile, prepare twelve croutons of bread-crumbs, one-third inch thick, stamped out with a round cutter two-thirdsinch in diameter. Fry these croutons in butter at the lastminute.

Put four fine, very black truffles, cut into somewhat thickslices, into the required quantity of reduced half-glaze sauce;add the kidneys, drained of their butter, as well as the friedcrusts, one and one-half oz. of very best butter, and a few dropsof lemon juice, and roll the saucepan gently, that the butter maythoroughly combine with the sauce.

Dish immediately in a very hot, silver timbale, and serveinstantly.

—ROQNONS de COQ FARCIS pour ENTREESFROIDES, GARNITURES, ETC.

Choose some fine, cooked kidneys, and cut them into twolengthwise. Trim them slightly underneath, that they may liesteady.

Stuff them by means of a piping-bag with a highly seasonedpur6e of foie gras, or of ham, of the white of a chicken andtruffles, combined with an equal weight of fresh butter.

Coat them with a pink or white chaud-froid sauce, accordingto the requirements; set them in a low timbale, and cover themwith light jelly.

They may also be put into petits-fours moulds, surroundedwith jelly, and used as a garnish for cold fowls.

a—CHICKEN CROQUETTES and CUTLETS

The croquettes and cutlets with which we are now concernedare made up of exactly the same constituents, and only differin the matter of shape, the croquettes, as a rule, being shapedeither like corks or rectangles; sometimes, too, like quoits;whereas the cutlets, as their name implies, are made in cutlet-shaped moulds.

The preparation from which they are made is as follows: —One lb. of the meat of a poached or roast fowl, thoroughlycleared of all skin, cartilage, and bones, and cut into smallregular dice1; six oz. of cooked mushrooms; an equal amountof salted ox-tongue or York ham, and four oz. of truffles. Cut

1 When prepared as directed above, all meats, whether of poultry, game,fish, Crustacea or mollusca, &c., may serve in the preparation of croquettes orcutlets.

527

these various products like the chicken, and mix them there-with; then add one-half pint of very reduced and finished Alle-mande sauce to the whole; set the preparation to dry for a fewminutes over an open fire; this done, remove it from the latter,and thicken it with the yolks of four raw eggs, which shouldbe quickly mixed with it. Now pour the preparation into avery clean, buttered tray, and butter its surface, lest a crustform thereon during the cooling.

When the preparation is quite cold, transfer it, by means ofa spoon, in pieces weighing about two oz., to a flour-dustedmixing board. Make the croquettes and cutlets about thedesired shape; dip them into an anglaise, and roll them infine bread-crumbs. Definitely shape them; plunge them intovery hot fat; keep them therein till they have acquired a finegolden colour; drain them, and dish them in a crown on a nap-kin, with a heap of fried parsley in the middle.

Croquettes and cutlets may be garnished as fancy sug-gests, but the accompaniment should always be served sepa-rately. Tomato and P6rigueux sauces are the most commonlyused, and the best garnishes for the purpose are all the purges,peas, French beans, and jardinieres.

Chickens’ Livers (Foies de Volaille)

—BROCHETTES de FOIES de VOLAILLECollop the livers; quickly stiffen them in butter, and thentreat them exactly as explained under “Brochettes deRognons” (No. 1343).

—FOIES de VOLAILLE ET ROGNONSSAUTES au VIN ROUGEProceed according to the recipe given under “RognonsSautes au Champagne” (No. 1333), using sliced chickens’livers and cocks’ kidneys in equal quantities, and substitutingexcellent red wine for the Champagne.

N.B.—Chickens’ livers are also prepared sautes chasseur;sautes fines herbes, au gratin; en coquilles; en pilaw, &c. Referto sheeps’ kidneys for these preparations.

—FRICASSEE de POULET à l’ANCIENNEFor a fricassee cut up the chicken as for a saute, but dividethe legs into two. The procedure is exactly that of “Fricasseede Veau” (No. 1276)—that is to say, the chicken is cooked inthe sauce.

About ten minutes before serving, add ten small onions,

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

528

cooked in white consomm^, and ten small grooved mushroom-heads. Finish at the last moment with a pinch of choppedparsley and chives. Thicken the sauce at the last moment withthe yolks of two eggs, four tablespoonfuls of cream, and one oz.of best butter.

Dish in a timbale, and surround the fricassee with littleflowerets of puff-paste, baked without colouration.

— FRICASSEE de POULET aux ECREVISSES

Prepare the fricassee as above, and add thereto as garnishten small, cooked mushrooms, and the shelled tails of twelvecrayfish, cooked as for bisque. When about to serve, finishthe fricassee with two and one-half oz. of crayfish butter, madefrom the crayfishes’ carcasses and their cooking-liquor rubbedthrough linen.

Dish in a timbale.

— FRITOT OU MARINADE de VOLAILLE

Cut some boiled or roast fowl into slices, and marinade thesein a few drops of oil, lemon juice, and some chopped herbs forone-quarter hour. Boiled fowl is preferable, in that the greaterporousness of its meat facilitates the percolation of the marinadethrough it.

A few minutes before serving, dip the slices into very lightbatter, and put them into very hot fat. Drain, the moment thebatter is well gilded; dish on a napkin with fried parsley, andserve a tomato sauce separately.

N.B.—Nowadays Fritot and Marinade of fowl are identicallythe same dish, but formerly they differed in this, namely, thatthe Fritot was prepared from cooked fowl, and the Marinadefrom pieces of uncooked fowl which were marinaded before-hand.

— M0US5ES ET MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE

Both these preparations have for basic ingredient the mous-seline forcemeat of No. 195. They differ in that the“Mousses” are prepared singly for one service, i.e., for severalpeople at once, and that the “Mousselines,” which are vir-tually special quenelles, are prepared in the proportion of oneor two for each person.

In different parts of this work, especially under No. 797, thesubject has already been exhaustively treated; there is no neednow, therefore, to go over the ground again.

POULTRY

529

—MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE ALEXANDRA

Mould and poach the Mousselines. Drain them, and setthem in a circle on a round dish; place on each a fine slice ofcooked fowl, and upon the latter a slice of truffle. Coat withMornay sauce, glaze quickly, and, in the middle of the mous-selines, set a heap of asparagus-heads or small peas, coheredwith butter.

—MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE à l’INDIENNE

Prepare the mousselines as above; set them in a circle on around dish; coat with Indienne sauce, and serve a timbale ofrice & l’lndienne separately.

— MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE au PAPRIKA

When the mousselines are poached and dished, set uponeach a fine collop of supreme, and coat with supreme sauce withpaprika. Surround them with small timbales of pilaff rice com-bined with concassed tomatoes cooked in butter.

— MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE à la PATTI

Proceed as for “Mousselines Alexandra,” but coat them

with supreme sauce, finished with crayfish butter. In theirmidst set a heap of asparagus-heads, cohered with butter, andupon these lay some fine slices of glazed truffles.

—MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE à la SICILIENNE

Prepare the mousselines as above, and set them, each on anoval tartlet, garnished with macaroni & la Napolitaine. Coatthem with supreme sauce; besprinkle with grated Parmesan,and glaze quickly.

—SYLPHIDES de VOLAILLE

Prepare and poach the mousselines in the usual way.Garnish the bottom of some barquettes with Mornay sauce,and put a mousseline into each barquette.

Set a collop of fowl on each mousseline, and cover them witha somewhat stiff preparation of souff!6 au Parmesan (No. 2295a),applied ornamentally by means of a piping-bag fitted with aneven pipe. Put the sylphides in the oven, in order to cook thesouffle, and serve instantly.

—MOUSSELINES de VOLAILLE à la FLORENTINE

Proceed as for the sylphides; taking note only of this differ-ence, viz., that the bottom of the barquettes must be garnishedwith shredded spinach stewed in butter. For the other detailsof the operation the procedure is the same.

M M

530

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— PILAW de VOLAILLE

Pilaff, which is the national dish of Orientals, gives riseto an endless number of recipes. The various curries ofveal, lamb, and fowl are “pilaffs,” and all except the one “k laParisienne,” which I give below, follow the same method ofpreparation—namely, that of curry; but for a change in thecondiments and the treatment of the rice, which is not the sameas that of “Riz & l’lndienne.”

— PILAW de VOLAILLE à la GRECQUE

Cut the fowl into small pieces, and fry it in mutton fat withthree oz. of chopped onions. Sprinkle with one oz. of flour;moisten with one pint of white consomm^; add twTo-thirds of acapsicum, cut into dice, and one and one-half oz. of currantsand sultanas, and cook gently.

Dish in a timbale, and serve some pilaw rice separately.

— PILAW de VOLAILLE à l’ORIENTALE

Prepare the fowl as above, only flavour it with a littlepowdered ginger, and add three green braised and quarteredcapsicums to the sauce.

Serve a timbale of pilaff rice at the same time.

— PILAW de VOLAILLE à la PARISIENNE

Cut up the fowl as for a fricassde; season it; fry it in butter,and add thereto three and one-half oz. of rice, browned inbutter, with one chopped onion, a leaf of bay, and two peeledand concassed tomatoes. Moisten with enough white brothto more than cover, and cook in a very hot oven for twTenty-fiveminutes. At the end of this time the fowl and rice are cooked,and the rice should be quite dry.

Sprinkle then with one-sixth pint of veal stock; mix thelatter with the pilaff by means of a fork, and dish with care ina timbale.

Serve a sauceboat of tomato sauce separately.

— PILAW de VOLAILLE à la TURQUE

Prepare the fowl as for “Pilaw k la Parisienne,” and flavourwith a little cayenne and another of saffron. Dish in a tim-bale.

N.B.—Pilaff may also be prepared with cooked fowl, cutinto slices which are heated in butter. In this case, garnish thebottoms and sides of a timbale with tomated pilaff rice; put theslices of fowl in the middle; cover with rice, and turn out thetimbale on the dish.

Surround the timbale with a thread of tomato sauce.

53*

—SOUFFLES de VOLAILLE

For dinners on a large scale, it is in every way preferableto use raw chicken-meat. For small services, cooked chicken-meat suits perfectly.

N.B.—The time allowed for cooking chicken souffles withcooked chicken-meat is comparatively long, and it is better tocook them a little too much than not enough.

For a souffle made in a quart timbale, and cooked in amoderate oven as directed, allow from about twenty-five tothirty minutes.

—SOUFFLE de VOLAILLE with RAW MEAT

Prepare two lbs. of mousseline forcemeat of chicken, accord-ing to recipe No. 195; add to this the whites of fpur eggs beatento a stiff froth.

Dish in buttered timbales, and cook in a moderate oven.

—SOUFFLE de VOLAILLE with COOKED MEAT

Finely pound one lb. of the white of cooked chicken-meat;add thereto six tablespoonfuls of cold, reduced, Bdchamel sauce.Rub through tammy.

Heat this preparation in a saucepan, without allowing it toboil, and add to it one and one-half oz. of butter, the yolks offive eggs, and the whites of six, beaten to a stiff froth.

Dish in a buttered timbale, and cook in a moderate oven.

Supreme sauce and the other derivatives of Allemande sauceform the best accompaniments to chicken souffles.

—SOUFFLE de VOLAILLE à la PERIGORD

This may be made from either one of the two above-men*tioned preparations, but there must be added to it three and one-half oz. of chopped truffles. The preparation is then spread inlayers separated by slices of truffle, which should weigh aboutthree and one-half oz. in all, in order to be in proportion to thequantities already given.

Cold Preparations of Fowl.

—POULARDE à la CARMELITE

Poach the pullet; raise the supremes and remove their skin;slice them; coat them with white chaud-froid sauce, and de-corate them soberly with pieces of truffle. Trim the carcass:coat it outside with white chaud-froid sauce, and fill it with afine crayfish mousse, reconstructing it exactly in so doing.

Cause a mousse to set in a refrigerator; place the collops of

MM2

53*

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

supreme neatly upon it, in two rows, and between each row laya dozen fine crayfish tails shelled and trimmed.

Coat the whole with half-melted aspic jelly; set in a deepdish; incrust the latter in a block of ice, and pour enough verygood, melting aspic jelly (No. 159) over the pullet to half-immerse it.

— POULARDE au CHAMPAGNE

Stuff a pullet two days beforehand with a whole foie grasstudded with truffles and stiffened in butter for twenty minutes.Poele it in champagne; put it in a cocotte; cover it with itspoeling-Yiquor, containing a sufficient addition of succulentjelly, and leave it to cool.

On the morrow remove, by means of a spoon, the greasethat has settled on the jelly, and scald the latter twice or thricewith boiling water, in order to remove the last traces of grease.

Serve this pullet very cold, in the same cocotte in which ithas cooled.

— POULARDE EN CHAUD = FROID

Poach the pullet; let it cool in its cooking-liquor; cut it up,and clear the pieces of all skin. Dip the pieces in chaud-froidsauce, already prepared from the pullet’s cooking-liquor ifpossible, and arrange them on a tray. Decorate each piece witha fine slice of truffle; glaze with cold, melted jelly; leave toset, and trim the edges of the pieces, just before dishingthem.

Old method of dishing: Formerly, chaud-froids were dishedon a cushion of bread or rice, placed in the middle of aborder of jelly; and, between each piece, cocks’ combs andmushrooms, covered with chaud-froid sauce or jelly, were set.

They were also dished on stearine tazzas, made in specialmoulds; but these methods, however much they may have beenhonoured by old cookery, are generally scouted at the presentday.

The method of dishing detailed hereafter is steadily oustingthem; it allows of serving much more delicate and more agree-able chaud-froids in the simplest possible way, and wasinaugurated at my suggestion at the Savoy Hotel.

Modern method of dishing: Set the decorated pieces, coatedwith chaud-froid sauce, side by side on a layer of excellent aspicjelly, lying on the bottom of a deep square dish. Cover themwith the same aspic, which should be half melted, and leaveto set. When about to serve, incrust the dish in a block ofcarved ice, or surround it with the latter fragmented.

533

This procedure allows of using less gelatinous products inthe preparation of the aspic, and the latter is therefore muchmore delicate, mellow, and melting.

i69o_POULARDE EN CHAUD-FROID à l’ECOSSAISE

Having poached and cooled the pullets, raise the supremes,and cut each into three or four collops. Garnish these collops,dome-fashion, with a salpicon consisting of the meat cut fromthe carcass, combined with an equal quantity of salted tongueand truffle, and cohered with reduced chicken jelly.

Coat these collops with white chaud-froid sauce; sprinklethem immediately with very red tongue, truffle, gherkins, andhard-boiled white of egg; all chopped, mixed, and glazed with

jelly. .

Now set the collops in a deep, square silver dish, alternatingthem with oval slices of salted tongue.

Garnish their midst with a salad of French beans, cutlozenge-form and cohered with aspic.

—CHAUD-FROID FELIX FAURE

Raise the supremes of a fine pullet; cut them in two inthe thick part, without separating them, and slightly flattenthem. Lay them on a piece of linen; season them; and, on oneof their halves, spread a layer of foie-gras purde thickened witha little chicken forcemeat. Upon this layer set some rectanglesof raw foie gras, one-third in. thick; cover with purde, set someslices of truffle upon the latter; coat again with purde; moistenwith white of egg, and over the whole press the other half ofthe supreme. Wrap each supreme, prepared in this way, in apiece of muslin; poach them in a moderate oven, after havingmoistened them to within half their height with chicken stock;and leave them to cool in their cooking-liquor under slightpressure.

This done, take off the muslin, and cut each supreme intoten or twelve medallions. Envelop each medallion in a mousseof chicken made with the meat of the poached eggs, and leaveto set. Then coat each medallion with white chaud-froid sauce,and deck each with a fine slice of truffle.

Clothe a dome-mould with a fine chicken jelly, and decorateit with slices of truffle; put the medallions inside, proceeding asfor an aspic, and leave to set.

When about to serve, turn out on a serviette.

—CHAUD-FROID de POULARDE à la GOUNOD

Raise the supremes of a poached pullet, and cool them underpressure.

534

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Then cut them into rectangles of equal sizes; and, if neces-sary, bisect them in the thickness.

Prepare a slab of mousse (made from the legs and thetrimmings), twice as thick as the rectangles. Smoothen thismousse neatly, and put it in the refrigerator that it mayget firm. This done, cut it into pieces exactly equal in sizeto the supremes; to do this, all that is necessary is to stickthe latter on the mousse by means of jelly.

Now coat each supreme garnished with mousse with whitechaud-froid sauce, and decorate with a bar of notes, imitatedwith truffles.

Set in a square, deep silver dish; cover with limpid andmelting chicken jelly; leave to set, and serve the dish incrustedin a block of ice.

,693—CHAUD-FROID de POULARDE à la ROSSINI

Prepare the pieces as for ordinary chaud-froid, and coat themwith chaud-froid sauce combined with a quarter of its bulk ofvery smooth foie-gras pur£e. Decorate each piece with a lyrecomposed of truffle stamped out with a “lyre” fancy-cutter, setthem on a deep, square dish, and cover with chicken jelly asabove.

694—POULARDE à la DAMPIERRE

Completely bone the pullet’s breast, and stuff it with apreparation of chicken forcemeat (No. 200). Sew up the piece,truss it as for an entrde, and poach it in a chicken stock.

When it is cold, trim it, and coat it with a white chaud-froidsauce, combined with a little almond milk. Glaze with aspicjelly, and set it, without decorating it, on a low cushion lying ona long dish.

Surround it with six small, ham mousses and six small,chicken uiousses, moulded in deep dariolc-moulds, and arrangedalternately.

Border the dish with croutons of jelly, cut very neatly.

—POULETS à l’ECARLATE

Bone the breasts of three fair-sized chickens; stuff and poachthem as explained above. When they are quite cold, cover themwith white chaud-froid sauce; decorate with pieces of truffle;glaze with aspic jelly, and leave to set.

This done, set them upright on a dish, letting them leanone against the other. Between each chicken set a salted calf’stongue, upright, with the tip of the tongue pointing upwards;and, on either side of the tongues, a large glazed truffle.

535

Border the dish with fine crotitons of jelly, and serve amayonnaise sauce at the same time.

—POULARDE à la LAMBERTYEPoach the pullet and let it cool thoroughly.

Raise the supremes, suppress the bones of the breast andgarnish the cavity with a cold chicken mousse, combined witha quarter of its volume of foie-gras purée, shaping the latter insuch wise as to reconstruct the bird.

Cut the supremes into thin, long slices; coat them withwhite chaud-froid sauce, and place them on the mousse,pressing them lightly one upon the other. Deck with piecesof truffle; glaze with chicken jelly; set in a square, entree dish,and surround with melted jelly.

When about to serve, incrust the dish in a block of ice.

—POULARDE à la NEVAStuff the pullet with chicken forcemeat (No. 200), combinedwith foie gras and truffles, cut into dice; poach it in chickenstock and let it cool. This done, coat the piece with whitechaud-froid sauce, decorate with jelly, and leave to set.

Set the pullet on a cushion of rice, lying on a long dish.Behind the bird, arrange a fine, vegetable salad in a shell ofcarVed rice, or in a large, silver shell.

Border the dish with neatly-cut croutons of pale jelly.

—POULARDE ROSE de MAIPoach the pullet and, when it is quite cold, raise its supremesand remove the bones of the breast. Coat the carcass with awhite chaud-froid sauce; decorate as fancy may dictate; garnishwith a mousse of tomatoes (No. 814), and arrange the latter insuch wise as to reconstruct the bird.

Slice the supremes-, coat them with white chaud-froid sauce;decorate with truffles, and glaze with chicken jelly. Garnishwith the same mousse as that already used for the pullet, asmany small, barquette-moulds as there are chaud-froid-coatedslices, and leave to set.

Put the pullets on a low cushion of rice, placed on a longdish; surround it with the barquettes of mousse, turned out atthe last moment; set a chaud-froid-coated slice on each bar-quette, and distribute crotitons of jelly over the dish.

—POULARDE ROSE MARIEHaving poached and cooled the pullet, raise its supremes;cut these into collops, and coat them with white chaud-froidsauce. Trim the carcass, leaving the wings attached; garnish

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

536

it with very smooth and pink, ham mousse, giving the latter theshape of the pullet, and put to set in the refrigerator.

Mould in small, oval moulds, as many barquettes of the sameham mousse as there are collops.

When the mousse in the fowl has properly set, coat it withchaud-froid sauce, prepared with paprika of a fine, tender, pinkshade; decorate according to fancy, and glaze with chicken jelly.

Set the pullet on a low cushion of rice, placed on a dish;place the barquettes of ham mousse around it; set a collop oneach mousse and a fine slice of truffle on each collop, andborder the dish with croutons of aspic.

— POULARDE à la SAINT-CYR

Poele the pullet in white wine, and leave it to cool in itscooking-liquor. This done, raise the fillets; cut them intoregular slices; coat them with white chaud-froid sauce anddecorate.

Meanwhile, saute fifteen larks in a mirepoix; remove thefillets of six of them; glaze them with brown, chaud-froid sauce,and decorate them with bits of hard-boiled white of egg.

With the remainder of the larks and five oz. of foie gras,prepare a mousse, and use the latter for reconstructing thepullet as explained in the preceding recipes. When the moussehas set properly, coat it with brown, chaud-froid sauce.Arrange the chicken fillets, coated with white, chaud-froid sauce,on either side of the mousse; in the middle put the larks’ fillets,coated with brown, chaud-froid sauce, and let them slightlyoverlap one another.

Set the pullet in a deep, square dish; surround it with melted,chicken jelly; let the latter set, and serve the dish incrustedin a block of ice.

— POULARDE EN TERR1NE à la QELEE

Bone the pullet all but the legs, and stuff it with a forcemeatconsisting of: three and one-half oz. of veal; three and one-halfoz. of fresh pork fat; three and one-half oz. of gratin forcemeat,prepared from fowls’ livers; two tablespoonfuls of brandy; twotablespoonfuls of truffle essence, and the yolk of an egg.

In the midst of the stuffing, set half of a raw foie gras andone raw, quartered truffle on each side. Reconstruct the pullet;truss it as for an entree; cover it with slices of bacon, and poelein Madeira for one and one-half hours.

Leave to half-cool in the cooking-liquor; withdraw the pullet;remove the slices of bacon, and put it in a terrine just largeenough to hold it.

537

Add a little chicken jelly to the bird’s cooking-liquor, whichshould not have been cleared of grease, but merely strainedthrough a napkin; and pour this sauce over the pullet.

Do not serve until twenty-four hours have elapsed, and clearof grease as directed under “Poularde au Champagne” (No.1688).

Serve the terrine in a block of ice, or on a dish with brokenice all round.

—TERRINE de POULARDE EN CONSERVE

Prepare the pullet as explained above, and put it in a boxjust large enough to hold it. Seal up the box; mark the topwith a bit of tin; put it in a stewpan with enough water to coverit, and boil for two hours.

This done, withdraw the box and cool it, placing it upsidedown, that the grease may be at the bottom and the breastcoated with jelly.

—AILERONS de POULET à la CARMELITE

Poach a chicken & la Reine; let it cool; raise its supremesand leave the humerus bones attached, after having duly clearedthem of all meat; skin the supremes, and coat them with a littlejelly.

Garnish a timbale, just large enough to hold the two wings,half-way up with crayfish mousse. Upon this mousse, set thetwo supremes, opposite one another, and between them set arow of shelled and trimmed crayfishes’ tails, cooked as forbisque. Cover the whole with a succulent half-set chicken jelly,and place in the refrigerator for two hours.

—AILERONS de POULET LADY WILMER

Poach three fleshy, spring chickens, taking care to have thesupremes just cooked. Leave to cool, and raise the wings asin the preceding recipe, trim them and coat them with jelly.

With the meat of three legs, prepare a chicken mousse, andmould it in a dome-mould. When the mousse is set, turn itout on a dish, and place the wings all round, fixing them on themousse, with their points upwards, by means of a little half-setjelly.

Cover the mousse on top, and the gaps between the pointsof the supremes with chopped truffle and chopped tongue, laidalternately. In the middle of the viousse, set a fine, glazedtruffle, pierced by a small hatclet.

—ASPIC de POULET à l’lTALIENNE

Clothe a border mould with aspic jelly, in accordance withthe procedure described under “Aspic de Homard” (No. 954),

538

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

and decorate it with large slices of truffles. Fill the mould witha coarse julienne of chicken fillets, salted tongue and truffles,spread in successive layers and besprinkled with cold, meltedaspic.

When about to serve, turn out the aspic on a very colddish; set a salad “k l’ltalienne” in its midst, and serve aR^moulade sauce separately.

— ASPIC de POULET à la GAULOISE

Clothe an ornamented mould with jelly, and decorate itsbottom and sides with truffles. Fill it with successive andalternate layers of: aspic jelly, collops of chicken fillets, cocks’combs coated with brown, chaud-froid sauce, fine cocks’ kidneys,coated with white chaud-froid sauce, and slices of saltedtongue cut into oval shapes.

When about to serve, turn out, and surround with finecroutons of aspic.

— MEDAILLONS de VOLAILLE RACHEL

Prepare some chicken supremes as explained under “Chaud-froid F61ix Faure” (No. 1671), and cut them into collops. Trimthese collops with a round, even cutter, and coat them withaspic.

Prepare a mousse from the meat of the legs. Spread thismousse on a tray in a layer one-third in. thick and leave itto set. When it is quite firm, stamp it out with a round, evencutter, dipped in hot water, and a little larger than the oneused in trimming the collops.

Set a medallion on each roundel of mousse, fixing it thereby means of a little half-set jelly, and arrange the medallionprepared in this way on a square dish.

In their midst set a fine faggot of asparagus-heads; fill thegaps betwen the medallions with a garnish consisting of a saladof asparagus-heads with cream.

Serve on a block of ice or surround the dish with ice.

— GALANTINE de VOLAILLE

For galantines, fowls may be used which are a little tootough to be roasted, but old fowls should be discarded. Thelatter invariably yield a dry forcemeat, whatever measures onemay take in the preparation.

The fowl should be cleaned but not emptied, and it shouldbe carefully boned; the process beginning from an incision downthe skin of the back, from the head to the tail.

This done, carefully remove the meat with the point of a

539

small, sharp knife, until the carcass is quite bare. Cut off thewings and the legs, flush with the articulations of the trunk;remove all the meat that the skin may be quite clean, and spreadthe skin on a clean piece of linen. Trim the meat of thebreast, cut it into pieces one-third inch square, and put theresulting trimmings aside.

Season these pieces and marinade them in a few drops ofbrandy; prepare other pieces of the same size and length fromfour oz. of truffles; six oz. of salted, fat pork; four oz.of cooked ham, and four oz. of salted and cooked ox-tongue.Then clear the meat of the legs of all tendons; add to it thetrimmings cut from the breast, as much very white veal andtwice as much very fat, fresh pork; season these meats withsalt, pepper and nutmeg; chop them up very finely; poundthem, and rub them through a sieve. Add the brandy in whichthe fillets were marinaded.

Spread a layer, three in. wide, of this forcemeat along thewhole of the middle of the chicken’s skin; upon this layer offorcemeat set the strips of bacon, fowl, truffle, ham, and tongue,arranging them alternately and regularly; upon them spreadanother layer of forcemeat, equal to the first; then another layerof the various pieces, and finally cover and envelop the wholein what remains of the forcemeat.

Draw the skin of the fowl over the whole and completelywrap the former round the latter. Carefully sew up the edgesof the skin, and roll the galantine in a napkin, either end ofwhich should be tightly strung.

With six lbs. of shin of veal, one-half lb. of fresh blanchedpork rind, and the fowl’s carcass, prepare a white veal stock(No. io). When this stock has cooked for about five hours,add the galantine to it, and gently cook the latter for aboutone and one-quarter hours.

At the end of this time take the galantine off the fire; drainit on a dish, and let it cool for ten minutes; remove the napkinin which it has cooked, and roll it in another one which shouldbe similarly tied at both ends. This done, put the galantine tocool under a weight not exceeding five or six lbs.

The cooking-liquor, once it has been cleared of grease andclarified as for an aspic (No. 158), constitutes a jelly whichaccompanies the galantine. When the latter is quite cold,remove the napkin covering it, trim it neatly at either end; coatit with half-melted jelly, and dish it on a low cushion of carvedrice. Finally, decorate it as fancy may dictate with pieces ofjelly.

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

540

— PAIN de VOLAILLE FROID

Poele a very tender chicken; do not colour it and have itonly just done. Withdraw it and leave it to cool. Add twotablespoonfuls of strong veal stock and one tablespoonful ofburned brandy to the foeling-liquor.

Simmer for ten minutes. Strain this stock through asieve, and slightly press the vegetables in so doing, that alltheir juices may be expressed.

Clear of grease, and reduce until the liquor does not measuremore than two tablespoonfuls. Put it on the side of the fire,add the yolks of three eggs, stirring briskly the while, and add,little by little, six oz. of very good, fresh butter, just as for aHollandaise sauce. Finally, add one and one-half leaves ofgelatine, dissolved in two tablespoonfuls of boiling water, andrub the whole through tammy.

Meanwhile, raise the chicken’s fillets and cut them into wideand thin collops, after having cleared them of skin. Cover eachcollop with a slice of truffle dipped in good, half-melted jelly,and with them line the bottom and sides of a timbale-mould,already clothed with jelly and incrusted in ice.

Then completely bone the chicken; finely pound theremainder of its meat as well as the skin; rub the whole througha fine sieve, and add the resulting purée to the prepared sauce.Mix the whole well, and fill the mould with it. Allow to setwell, and turn out on a cushion of rice surrounded by finecroutons of jelly.

N.B.—By substituting young ducks, young pigeons, or somekind of game such as pheasant, woodcock, &c., for thechicken, this recipe may be applied to any piece of poultry orgame.

— SUPREME de VOLAILLE JEANNETTE

Poach a fowl; let it cool; raise its supremes, and cut eachinto four collops, trimmed to the shape of ovals. Coat thesecollops with white chaud-froid sauce, and decorate them withtarragon leaves, blanched, cooled, well-drained and very green.

Let a layer of aspic jelly one-half in. thick set on the bottomof a timbale or a square dish; upon this layer set some slicesof foie-gras Parfait, cut to the shape of the collops, and placeone of the latter on each slice of the Parfait. This done, coverwith fine half-melted chicken jelly.

When about to serve, incrust the dish or the timbale in ablock of carved ice.

541

—MOUSSE de VOLAILLE FROIDE

The carefully boned and skinned meat of a poached fowlmay be used in the preparation of this mousse, but a freshly-roasted fowl, scarcely cooled, is preferable; the latter’s flavourbeing more delicate and more distinct.

The quantities and the mode of procedure for cold fowlmousse are those given under “mousse de tomates” (No. 814).

The various mousse recipes which I gave for trout (Nos.813 and 815) may be applied to cold fillets of fowl. In this case,the latter may be coated with some kind of chaud-froid sauce,or simply glazed with jelly, and soberly decorated.

These mousses constitute excellent dishes for suppers, andfrom a very long list of them I may quote: —

Mousse de jambon au blanc de poulet.

Mousse de foie gras au blanc de poulet

Mousse de langue au blanc de poulet.

Mousse de tomates au blanc de poulet.

Mousse d’dcrevisses au blanc de poulet.

Mousse d’airelles ou de canneberges au blanc de poulet.

Mousse de physalis au blanc de poulet.

—MAYONNAISE de VOLAILLE

Garnish the bottom of a salad-bowl with ciseled lettuce,arranging it in the shape of a dome. Season with a little saltand a few drops of vinegar. Upon this salad arrange the coldcollops of boiled or roast fowl, carefully cleared of all skin.

Cover with mayonnaise sauce; smooth the latter and decoratewith capers; small stoned olives; anchovy fillets; quarteredhard-boiled eggs; small quartered or whole lettuce hearts.

Arrange these decorating constituents according to fancy,as no hard and fast rule can be given.

When about to serve, mix as for a S^Iad.

—CHICKEN SALAD

This dish consists of the same ingredients as the precedingone, except for the mayonnaise, which is replaced by anordinary seasoning added just before mixing and serving.

—PATE de POULET

Line a raised-pie mould with patty paste (No. 2359), takingcare to leave a fine crest.

Bone a fowl weighing about four or five lbs. Set thesupremes (each cut into three collops) to marinade in a glass

542

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

of brandy, salt, pepper, nutmeg, and five medium-sized peeledtruffles, each cut into four or five thick slices.

With what remains of the fowl’s meat, as much lean porkand veal (mixed in equal quantities) and twice as much fresh,pork fat (i.e., a quantity equal in weight to all the othermeats put together), prepare a very smooth forcemeat; choppingthe whole first, then pounding it and rubbing it through asieve. Add to this forcemeat a little truffle essence; themarinade of the fillets; one raw egg, and the necessary sea-soning, to wit: salt, pepper, and nutmeg.

Line the bottom and sides of the pie with this forcemeat;on this first layer of forcemeat lay a thin slice of bacon andthick slices of tongue, beef, or ham. Place thereon anotherslice of bacon, followed by a thin layer of forcemeat, a layerof truffle slices, another layer of forcemeat, the collops of fowl,another layer of forcemeat, one more layer of truffles, onemore layer of forcemeat, one more layer of tongue or ham(between two thin slices of bacon); and finally cover the wholewith what remains of the forcemeat and a slice of lardingbacon superposed by a bay-leaf. Now close the pie with acover of the same paste as that already used, carefully sealdown the cover to the crest of the underlying paste, trim andpinch the crest, and deck this cover of paste with imitation-leaves of the same paste.

Make a slit in the top of the pie, for the escape of steam;carefully gild the cover and the crest, and bake in a moderateoven for about one and one-quarter hours. On withdrawingthe pie from the oven, let it half cool, and fill it with asucculent, chicken jelly. Allow this dish to cool for at leasttwenty-four hours before serving.

N.B.—With this recipe as model, and by substitutinganother piece of poultry or game for the fowl, raised pies maybe prepared from every kind of game or poultry, except water-game, which only yields mediocre results.

In the case of game pies, the forcemeat is combined withone-sixth of its weight of gratin forcemeat (No. 202) and anequal quantity of fat bacon is suppressed. The chicken jellyis also replaced by a jelly prepared from the carcasses of thebirds under treatment.

Dish these raised pies plainly, on napkins, and very cold.

a—CHICKEN PIE

See No. 1660.

543

—DINDONNEAU (Young Turkey)

Young turkeys, served as relevds or entries, admit of allthe recipes given for pullets; therefore, in order to avoidunnecessary repetition, the reader is begged to refer to thoserecipes.

Those most generally applied to young turkeys are the onestermed “k l’Anglaise”—with celery, & la Financffire, k laGodard, and k la Jardiniere.

In addition to these preparations, there are others whichare better suited and are more proper to young turkeys, andthese I give below.

—DINDONNEAU FARCI aux MARRONS

Cut open the shells of two and one-quarter lbs. of chest-nuts; immerse them for a few seconds in smoking fat; peelthem, and almost completely cook them in consommd. Thenmix them with two lbs. of very finely-chopped pork, rubbedthrough tammy. Fill the bird with this preparation; trussit, and roast it on the spit or in the oven, basting frequentlythe while.

Serve with the gravy separately. The latter should besomewhat fat.

—DINDONNEAU à la CATALANE

Cut up the young turkey as for a fricassee, and fry thepieces in three oz. of butter. When the pieces are nicelybrowned, swill the utensil with one pint of white wine; seasonwith salt and pepper; add a piece, the size of a pea, ofcrushed garlic, and completely reduce. Then moisten withsufficient tomato purée and equal quantities of Espagnole andbrown stock to just cover the pieces.

Cook in the oven for forty minutes; transfer the pieces toanother dish after having trimmed them, and add one-halflb. of raw, quartered mushrooms, sauted in butter; twentychestnuts cooked in consomnffi; twenty small, glazed onions;five quartered tomatoes, and ten sausages.

Strain the sauce over the pieces of turkey; complete thecooking for twenty-five minutes, and dish in a timbale.

—DINDONNEAU CHIPOLATA

This may be prepared in two ways, according as to whetherit be intended for lunch or for dinner.

(1) Cut up the young turkey and fry the pieces in butteras above. Swill with one glassful of white wine; add a suffi-cient quantity of tomated half-glaze sauce, just to cover thepieces, and cook in the oven for forty minutes.

544

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

This done, transfer the pieces to another stewpan and addthereto twenty small, glazed onions, twenty chestnuts cookedin consomme, ten chipolata sausages, one-third lb. of frizzledpieces of fresh pork cut into dice, and twenty olive-shaped andglazed carrots. Strain the sauce over the whole, complete thecooking and dish in a timbale.

(2) Braise the young turkey; glaze it at the last moment,and set on a long dish. Surround it with the garnish givenabove, combined with the reduced braising-liquor.

— DINDONNEAU EN DAUBE

Bone the young turkey’s breast, and stuff it, arranging itsmeat as for a galantine, with very good sausage-meat com-bined with a glassful of liqueur brandy per two lbs. of theformer; bacon, truffles; and a very small and red ox-tongue,covered with slices of bacon and set in the centre of thegarnish.

Reconstruct the young turkey; sew it; truss it, and putit in a terrine just large enough to hold it and its moistening.

With the bones and the trimmings of the young turkey,two slices of veal, two lbs. of frizzled beef, aromatics, one pintof white wine, and two quarts of water, prepare a brown stockafter recipe No. 9. Reduce this stock to one and one-halfquarts; put it into the terrine; cover and thoroughly close upthe latter with a strip of paste, and cook in a hot oven fortwo and one-half hours.

Leave to cool in the terrine, and, when about to serve,slightly heat the latter in order to turn out the daube.

— BLANC de DINDONNEAU à la DAMPIERRE

Remove and bone the young turkey’s legs. With the meat,carefully cleared of all tendons, prepare a mousseline forcemeat;spread the latter on a tray in a layer one-third in. thick, andpoach it. Stamp it out with an even, oval fancy-cutter, aboutthree in. by two in.

Braise or poele the young turkey’s breast with the greatestcare, keeping it underdone. This done, raise the two supremes,skin them, and cut them into collops of a size that will allowof their being trimmed with the fancy-cutter already used.With a little raw forcemeat, stick a collop to each oval ofpoached forcemeat; then, by means of a piping-bag fittedwith an even pipe, garnish the borders of the collops with thesame forcemeat combined with twice its bulk of chopped saltedtongue. Set the medallions thus prepared on a covered tray,and put them in the steamer that the forcemeat may poach.

545

When about to serve, take the piping-bag and make 3fine rosette of a puree of peas in the centre of each medallion.Set these medallions in a circle on a round dish, around alittle bowl of carved, fried bread, garnished with the samepurée of peas.

Serve separately a velout£ prepared from the bones of thedindonneau.

—BLANC de DINDONNEAU à la T0UL0U5AINE

Poele the young turkey. When it is cooked, raise itssupremes, skin them, and cut them into somewhat thick collops.

Dish these collops in a circle, and set a collop of foie gras,sauted in butter, between each.

Pour a Toulousaine garnish in their midst, and surroundwith a thread of light glaze.

—AILERONS de DINDONNEAU DOR^SA LA Purée de MARRONS

The pinions referred to in this recipe are pinions properlyso called; that is to say, they consist of the two last joints ofthe wing. When they are properly prepared, they constituteone of the most savoury luncheon entries that can be served.

The pinions of large pullets may be treated in this way.

Clear and singe the pinions, and set them in a butteredsaut^pan, just large enough to hold them. Colour gently onboth sides and drain.

In the same butter, gently brown a sliced carrot and onion,to which add a few parsley stalks and a little thyme and bay.Set the pinions on these aromatics; season moderately with saltand pepper; cover the saut^pan, and continue cooking gentlyin a very slow oven, basting often the while.

The dish will be all the better for having been cooked slowlyand regularly. Do not moisten, if possible, or, at the most,only do so with a few drops of water, in order to keep thebutter from clarifying—not an unusual occurrence when theheat is too fierce.

When the pinions are cooked, dish them radially, and coverthem that they may keep warm. Add a few tablespoonfuls oflight stock or some water to the cooking butter, and set toboil gently for fifteen minutes. When this stock is sufficientlyreduced to only half-immerse the pinions, pass it through afine strainer and clear of some of the grease if necessary;remember, however, that this stock should be somewhat fat.

Pour it over the pinions, and serve a timbale of a fine pur£eof marrons separately.

:N N

a—DINDONNEAU FROID

All the recipes given for cold pullets may be applied tothis bird.

Goose (Oie)

The principal value of the goose from the culinary point ofview lies in the fact that it supplies the best, most delicateand firmest foie gras.

Apart from this property, the preciousness of which is trulyinestimable, goose is really only served at bourgeois or familytables.

b—OISON à l’ALLEMANDE

Completely bone the gosling’s breast; season it inside, andstuff it with quartered, peeled and cored apples, half-cookedin butter.

Sew up the openings, and braise gently, basting with fatthe while.

When the gosling is cooked, dish it and surround it withpeeled apples, cored by means of the tube-cutter, cooked inbutter, and garnished with red-currant jelly. Drain away three-quarters of the grease; swill the braising-pan with the requiredquantity of good gravy for roasts; strain this gravy, and serveit separately.

c—OISON à l’ALSACIENNE

Stuff the gosling with very good sausage-meat; truss; colourin butter and focle. Dish and surround with sauerkraut braisedin goose grease, and rectangles of lean bacon, cooked writh thesauerkraut.

— OISON à l’ANGLAISE

Cook one lb. of unpeeled onions in the oven. Whenthey are cold, peel them; chop them, and add to them anequal weight of soaked and pressed bread, one oz. of fresh orchopped sage, salt, pepper and nutmeg.

Stuff the gosling with this preparation; truss it, and roastit on the spit or in the oven.

Dish it; surround it with the gravy, which should be some-what fat, and serve a sauceboat of slightly-sugared, stewedapples, separately.

— OISON EN CIVET

When killing the gosling, carefully collect its blood. Addthe juice of a lemon and beat it, so as to prevent coagulation,until it is quite cold.

547

Cut the gosling into pieces and proceed exactly as for “Civetde Li&vre” (No. 1821).

—OISON au RAIFORT

Braise the gosling.

Dish it and surround it, either with noodles with butter, orrice au gras (No. 2252). Besprinkle the garnish with the re-duced braising-liquor, and serve a horse-radish sauce with cream(No. 138), separately.

N.B.—Besides these various recipes, goslings may also beprepared like young turkeys, i.e., with chestnuts, h la Chip-olata, en Daube; or with turnips, peas, and “en Salmis,”like Duck.

—FOIE GRAS

Foies gras are supplied either by geese or ducks. Goose’sliver is larger, firmer and less readily melted than that of theduck. As a rule the former should be selected in preference,more particularly in the matter of hot dishes. Nevertheless,failing goose’s liver, duck’s liver may be used and with verygood results when its quality is good.

Foies gras are used in the preparation of terrines, raisedpies, parfaits and mousses, which are among the most delicateand richest of cold dishes.

They may also be used as a garnishing ingredient, in theform of collops or mousseline quenelles. Finally, they mayalso be served as hot entries.

When a whole foie gras is to be served hot, it must first betrimmed, studded with raw truffles which have been previouslypeeled, quartered, seasoned with salt and pepper, stiffened ina glassful of brandy, together with a bay-leaf, and cooledin a thoroughly closed terrine.

When the foie gras has been studded with truffles, wrap itin thin slices of bacon or a piece of pig’s caul, and set it ina thoroughly-sealed terrine before cooking it.

The best way to cook foie gras, when it is to be servedwhole and hot, is to bake it in a crust of paste that canabsorb the excess of grease produced by the melting of theliver. For this purpose prepare two layers of patty paste, alittle larger than the liver.

On one of these layers, set the liver wrapped in slices ofbacon; and, if possible, surround it with whole fair-sizedtruffles, peeled. Set half a bay-leaf on the liver; moisten theedges of the paste; cover the whole with the other layer ofpaste; seal it down with the thumb, and fold over the edgesof the paste to form a regular, ornamented border which, besides

N N 2

finishing off the preparation, also increases the strength of thewelding.

Gild the top; streak; make a slit in the top for the escapeof the steam; and, in the case of a medium-sized liver, cook ina good, moderate oven for from forty to forty-five minutes.

Serve this crust as it stands, and send the garnish separately.

In the dining-room, the waiter in charge removes the topof the crust, cuts out the liver with a spoon, setting a pieceon each plate, and arranges around each piece the garnishmentioned on the menu.

I am not partial to the cooking of foie gras in a terrinewhen it is to be served hot. In any case the method describedabove strikes me as being much the best, whatever be thegarnish that is served with the liver.

I particularly recommend a garnish of noodles, macaroni,lazagnes, spaghetti and even rice, with hot foie gras.

These pastes should simply be cooked in water and finishedwith cream.

This accompaniment makes the foie gras much moredigestible and palatable. The best garnishes for hot foie gras,besides those given above, are truffles, whole or in slices,or a Financi&re. In the matter of brown sauces, a Madeirasauce suits admirably, provided it be of great delicacy and notovercharged with Madeira; but a very light* buttered, veal orchicken glaze, combined with a little old Sherry or old Port,is even superior. A Hongroise sauce with paprika or an excel-lent supreme sauce may also be served when the garnish admitsof it.

—FOIE GRAS CUIT DANS UNE BRIOCHE

For this dish the foie gras is cooked differently; the resultis almost the same as that yielded by the crust prescribedabove, except that it is much more delicate. This method,moreover, allows of obtaining a foie gras clear of all grease(the latter being completely absorbed by the paste), and istherefore best suited to cold dishing.

After having studded the foie gras with truffles and placedit in a closed terrine as above, wrap it in slices of bacon, set itto poach in a moderate oven for twenty minutes, and leave it tocool.

Line a buttered timbale-mould, of a size in proportion tothat of the liver, with a thick layer of ordinary unsugaredbrioche paste (No. 2370).

Put the foie gras upright in the mould, which it shouldalmost fill; close the timbale with a cover of the same paste;

POULTRY

549

make a slit in the top; surround the top of the mould with aband of strong, buttered paper, that the paste may be preventedfrom running over, and let it rest for about thirty minutes ina temperature of 86° F. to allow the paste to work.

Bake in a rather hot oven, until a needle inserted throughthe centre withdraws quite clean.

Serve the dish as it stands with one of the ordinary foie-gras garnishes.

—E5CAL0PES de FOIE GRAS à la PERIGUEUX

Cut some slices two and one-half oz. in weight from a rawfoie gras. Season them with salt and pepper; dip in beatenegg; roll in finely-chopped truffle, and saute in clarified butter.

Dish in a circle, and, in the middle, pour a Madeira sauceflavoured with truffle essence.

—ESCALOPES de FOIE GRAS à la RAVIGNAN

From a layer of unsugared brioche paste, one-third in.thick, cut twenty roundels two and one-half in. in diameter. Onten of these roundels, spread a coating of chicken forcemeat,leaving a margin one-third in. wide of bare paste on eachroundel.

Set a slice of truffle in the middle, a thick roundel of rawfoie gras on the truffle, another slice of truffle upon that, a coatof forcemeat over the whole; and cover with the ten remainingroundels, after having slightly moistened the latter, that thetwo edges of paste may be sealed. Press with the back of around cutter; gild, and cook in a hot oven for fifteen minutes.

Dish in a circle, and serve a P^rigueux sauce at the sametime.

—ESCALOPES de FOIE GRAS à la TALLEYRAND

Prepare: (1) a crust made in a flawn-mould, six in. in dia-meter; (2) a garnish of blanched macaroni, cut into lengths ofone in., cohered with four oz. of grated Gruy&re and Parmesancheese per lb. of macaroni, and combined with two oz. ofbutter, four oz. of a julienne of truffles and four oz. of foie grascut into large dice.

Dish in a circle in the crust ten collops of foie gras sautedin butter, alternating them with fine slices of truffle. Putthe macaroni in the middle, shaping it like a dome, sprinklewith grated cheese and glaze quickly.

Dish on a napkin, and serve separately a clear chickenglaze, flavoured with truffles and well buttered.

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

55°

— SOUFFLE de FOIE GRAS

Rub two-thirds lb. of foie gras and three and one-half oz.of raw truffles through a fine sieve. Mix the two purges in abasin, and add two-thirds lb. of raw chicken-meat, poundedwith the whites of four eggs, and rubbed through a finesieve. Season; work the preparation on ice, and add to it,little by little, one-half pint of rich, thick, and very fresh cream,then the well-stiffened whites of four eggs.

Dish in a buttered souffle saucepan, and poach under coverin the bain-uiarie for from thirty to thirty-five minutes.

Serve a Madeira sauce, flavoured with truffle essence,separately.

— TIMBALE de FOIE GRAS à l’ALSACIENNE

Prepare an ordinary timbale crust. When about to serve,

fill it with layers of noodles with cream, separated by alternatelayers of foie-gras collops, sauted in butter, and slices of truffles.Complete with some raw noodles, tossed in butter and dis-tributed over the last layer of cohered noodles.

Cover the timbale, and serve a supreme sauce, flavouredwith truffle essence, separately.

— TIMBALE de FOIE GRAS CAMBACERFS

Line a buttered dome-mould with rings of large poachedmacaroni.

These rings should be one-fifth inch thick, and should begarnished inside with very black truffle purde, cohered bymeans of a little forcemeat.

When the mould is lined, coat it inside with a layer ofchicken forcemeat combined with truffle purde. Put the mouldfor a few minutes in a moderate oven, that the forcemeat maypoach.

Reduce one-third pint of Bechamel sauce, combined withfour to five tablespoonfuls of truffle and chicken essence, tohalf; mix therewith one-half lb. of poached macaroni, cut intolengths of one inch, and four tablespoonfuls of foie-gras andtruffle pur£e, made from trimmings. Mix the whole thoroughly.

Garnish the timbale with this macaroni, spreading it inlayers, separated by other alternate layers of foie-gras collops,poached in Madeira, and slices of truffle. Cover the garnishwith a layer of forcemeat, and poach in the bain-marie, allow-ing forty-five minutes for a quart-mould.

Let the mould stand for a few minutes before emptying it;turn ou» the timbale upon a round dish; surround it with a

border of P^rigueux sauce, and serve a sauceboat of P^rigueuxsauce separately.

—TIMBALE de FOIE GRAS MONTESQUIEU

Spread a very even layer, one-third inch thick, of chickenforcemeat upon a sheet of buttered paper. Moisten the surfacewith some white of egg; sprinkle with chopped truffle, andpress on the latter by means of the flat of a knife.

Set to poach gently; cool, and then stamp out with a round,even cutter, one inch in diameter. With the resultingroundels, garnish the bottom and sides of a Charlotte mould,placing their truffled sides against the mould. Then, with theview of binding these roundels together, as they are to con-stitute the outside of the timbale, coat the whole of the mouldinside with some fairly firm chicken forcemeat, combined with aquarter of its bulk of foie-gras puree.

Fill the mould with a foie-gras Parfait with truffles cut intovery large dice and cohered by means of mousseline chickenforcemeat.

Cover the whole with a layer of the same forcemeat as thatused for the purpose of binding the roundels, and set to poachunder cover.

Turn out, following the same precautions as above; sur-round the timbale with a border of nice, pink, Hungarian saucewith paprika, and send a sauceboat of this sauce to the tableat the same time.

Foie Gras Froid

—ASPIC de FOIE GRAS

Clothe an even or ornamented mould (fitted with a centraltube) with aspic, and decorate it with poached white of egg andtruffle. Fill it with rows of well-trimmed foie-gras rectangles,or shells raised by means of a spoon dipped in hot water,separating each row with a coat of aspic.

Except for its principal ingredient, which may vary, thepreparation of aspic is always the same as that described under“Aspic de Homard” (No. 954).

For the turning out and dishing, proceed in exactly thesame way.

—FOIE gras gastronome

Take a plain foie-gras Parfait, i.e., one without a crust;trim it neatly to the shape of an egg, and completely cover itwith a chaud-froid sauce with paprika. Decorate it accordingto fancy, and glaze it with cold melted jelly.

Cut out a crust, proportionate in size to the egg, and shape

55*

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

it like a cushion. Coat it with a chaud-froid sauce of a differentcolour; deck it with softened butter, applied by means of apiping-bag fitted with a narrow, grooved pipe; set it on thedish, and place the foie-gras egg upon it.

Surround the cushion with fine fair-sized truffles, glazedwith aspic jelly.

'737—FOIE GRAS au PAPRIKA

Trim a fine, fresh foie gras; salt it; sprinkle it with acoffeespoonful of paprika; put it into a saucepan with a largesliced Spanish onion and a bay-leaf, and cook in the oven forthirty minutes.

This done, set it instantly in an oval terrine, after havingcarefully removed every bit of onion; cover it wdth its owngrease; fill up the terrine with jelly, and leave to cool.

Keep in the cool until ready for serving.

N.B.—In Vienna, where this dish is usually served as ahors-d’oeuvre, with baked potatoes, the onion is not removed.The foie gras is left to cool in the terrine in which it has cooked,with all its grease, and it is served thus, very cold.

This piece of information was kindly given to me byMadame Katinka.

—ESCALOPES de FOIE GRAS MARECHALE

From a terrine of very firm foie gras cut the required numberof collops, giving them an oval shape. Make a preparation of“pain de foie gras” (No. 1741) with the remains of the terrine,and cover the collops with the preparation, shaping the latterin a dome upon them. Coat these garnished collops withcream chaud-froid sauce; decorate with a slice of truffle, andglaze with aspic.

With some foie-gras purée prepare some balls (of the shapeof bigaroons); in the centre of each place a little ball oftruffle in imitation of the stone of the fruit, and coat them witha reddish-brown, chaud-froid sauce. This done, glaze them withjelly.

Dish the collops round a circular cushion, set upon a verycold dish; arrange the bigaroons in a pyramid on the cushion,and border the dish with fine, jelly croutons.

*739—MOUSSE de FOIE GRA5

For the preparation of the mousse, see No. 814. The pro-cedure and the quantities are always the same, and only theprincipal ingredient changes. The moulding is also effectedin the same way in a jelly-clothed and decorated mould, gene-

rally just large enough to hold the requisite amount for oneservice, or in a silver timbale, incrusted in ice.

—MOUSSELINES de FOIE GRAS

I have oftentimes explained that the substance is the samefrom which mousses and mousselines are prepared, and I havepointed out wherein the difference between them lies.

Just like the other mousselines, those of foie gras are madein egg- or quenelle-moulds, or others of the same kind. Foie-gras mousselines are, according to circumstances, either simplyglazed with aspic, or coated with chaud-froid sauce and dishedin a timbale with jelly. They may also be moulded in littlepaper cases.

—PAIN de FOIE GRAS

From a cold foie gras, braised in Madeira, cut a few collopsand put them aside. Clear the cooking-liquor of all grease,reduce to half, and add the yolks of four eggs and one-half lb.of butter, proceeding as for a Hollandaise sauce. Completewith a grilled, crushed, hazel-nut, two leaves of dissolved gela-tine, and, when the preparation is only lukewarm, mix there-with (without working the whole overmuch) what remains ofthe foie gras, rubbed through a sieve.

Spread this preparation in layers in an aspic-clothed anddecorated mould, separating each layer with other alternatelayers consisting of the reserved collops and some slices oftruffle.

Cover the last layer with aspic, and set the mould in a re-frigerator for a few hours.

When about to serve, turn out, and border the dish withfine, aspic jelly croutons.

—PARFAIT de FOIE GRAS

Fresh foies gras do not bear transport very well, and, whensent from a distance, often reach their destination tainted. It is,therefore, difficult, whatever care may have been bestowed ontheir preparation, to obtain the results which are achieved bymanufacturers who are renowned for this kind of produce. Con-sequently, it is preferable to buy the Parfait of foie gras ready-made from a good firm rather than to try to make it oneself.

—PAVE de FOIE GRAS LUCULLUS

Let a coat of aspic, one-half inch thick, set on the bottomof a square timbale, and lay thereon a few slices of truffle. Uponthis jelly spread a layer, two-thirds inch thick, of foie-graspur£e, thinned by means of a little melted jelly. When thispur£e has set, lay on it a few foie-gras collops and slices of

554

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

truffle; cover with aspic, and continue thus with alternatelayers of pur£e, collops, and aspic. Fill up the mould witha layer of aspic jelly; put it in the refrigerator for a few hours,and dish on a block of ice, cut to the shape of a flagstone.

—TIMBALE de FOIE GRAS TZARINE

Line a timbale-mould with ordinary patty paste, and coverthe inside all over with slices of larding bacon. Just in themiddle set a fresh foie gras, seasoned with salt, pepper, andallspice; surround it with quails stuffed with a piece of truffle,and set upright with their breasts against the slices of bacon.Fill up the mould with whole, raw, and peeled truffles; coverthe whole with a round slice of the same bacon; cover thetimbale with a layer of paste, well sealed down round theedges; make a slit in the top for the escape of steam, and bakein a good, moderate oven for one and one-quarter hours.

On withdrawing the timbale from the oven, pour into itsome succulent veal stock, flavoured with Madeira, and suffi-ciently gelatinous to form a nice jelly.

Keep the timbale in the cool for one or two days beforeserving it.

Ducks and Ducklings (Canards et Canetons)

Three varieties of the duck family are recognised in cookery,viz., the Nantes duck, the Rouen duck, and the different kindsof wild duck. The latter are generally used for roasts and insalmis.

The Rouen duck is also served more often as a roast thanas an entrde. The characteristic trait of its preparation liesin its being kept very underdone, and it is very rarely braised.It is killed by suffocation, and not by bleeding, which is theusual mode of killing other birds.

The Nantes duck, which is similar to the Aylesbury one, isnot so fleshy as the Rouen duck, and may be roasted, poeled,or braised.

'745—CANETON NANTAIS à la CHOUCROOTE

Take a piece of manicd butter the size of an egg, and insertit into the duckling with chopped parsley and shallots. Trussthe bird as for an entree; brown it in the oven, and put it ina stewpan already lined for braising.

Moisten, just enough to cover, with white veal stock andRhine wine (in the proportion of two-thirds of the former toone-third of the latter), or ordinary good white wine, andbraise slowly until cooking is completed.

POULTRY 5 5 5

Meanwhile, braise in the usual way two lbs. of sauerkrautwith one-half lb. of salted breast of pork.

When it is three-parts done, drain it, and complete itscooking with one-third pint of veal gravy and one-sixth pintof white wine, until this moistening is completely reduced.

Set the sauerkraut in a border round a dish, and surroundit with the pork cut into small rectangles. Place the carvedduck in the centre, and coat it moderately with half-glaze saucecombined with the reduced braising-liquor. Send the remainsof this sauce separately.

—CANETON D’AYLESBURY POfiL& à la MENTHE

Stuff the duckling with one oz. of butter combined with apinch of chopped mint, and poele it. Dish it; sw'ill the stew-pan with one-sixth pint of clear, veal gravy and a little lemonjuice; strain, add a pinch of chopped mint, and pour this sauceover the duckling.

—CANETON MOLIERE

Bone the duckling, and stuff it with one lb. of gratin foie-gras forcemeat, combined with two-thirds lb. of good sausage-meat. Set two rows of truffles in the middle of the thickest partof the forcemeat, lengthwise, along the duckling. Reconstruct;sew up the skin, wrap in a serviette, after the manner of agalantine, and poach in a stock made from the carcass.

Glaze the duckling with some of this stock, strained, clearedof all grease, and reduced. With what remains prepare aMadeira sauce, and add thereto two oz. of sliced truffles.

Dish the duckling, after having removed all stitches fromit, and coat it with this sauce.

—CANETON BRAISE aux NAVETS

Brown the duckling well in butter, and withdraw it fromthe saucepan.

Drain away the butter; swill with a little white wine; addtwo-thirds pint of brown stock, as much Espagnole, and afaggot; return the duck to this sauce, and braise gently.

With the reserved butter brown one lb. of turnips, shapedlike elongated garlic-cloves, and sprinkle them with a largepinch of powdered sugar, that they may be glazed to a nice,light brown colour. Also have ready twenty small onions,which should have been gently cooked in butter.

When the duckling is half cooked, transfer it to anothersaucepan; put the turnips and the onions round it; strain thesauce over the whole, and complete the cooking gently.

556 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Dish with the garnish of turnips and onions, arranged roundthe bird.

— CANETON aux OLIVES

Prepare the duckling as above, and keep the sauce short andsucculent. A few minutes before serving, add one-half lb. ofstoned and blanched olives. Glaze the duckling at the lastmoment, and dish it surrounded with the olives and the sauce.

— CANETON BRAISE à l’ORANQE

This braised duckling must not be confused with roast duck-ling, which is also served “a l’orange,” for the two dishes arequite distinct.

As in the case of the roast, this duckling may be preparedwith Seville oranges; but, in this case, the sections of orangemust not appear as garnish, owing to their bitterness, and onlythe juice is used for the sauce.

Braise the duckling in one-third pint of brown stock andtwo-thirds pint of Espagnole sauce, and cook it sufficiently toallow of its being cut with a spoon.

Clear the sauce of grease; reduce it to a stiff consistence;rub it through tammy, and add the juice of two oranges andone half-lemon to it, which should bring the sauce back to itsoriginal consistence.

Now add a julienne of the blanched yellow part only of therind of a half-orange and a half-lemon, but remember that theaddition of the juice and rind of the orange and the half-lemononly takes place at the last moment, after which the sauce mustnot boil again. Glaze the duckling, dish it, coat it slightlywith sauce, and surround it with sections of orange, skinnedraw.

Serve what remains of the sauce separately.

— CANETON aux PETITS POIS

Brown in butter six oz. of salted breast of pork, cut intolarge dice and blanched, and fifteen small onions. Drain thepork and the onions, and set the duckling to fry in the samebutter. When it is well coloured, remove the butter; swillwith a little brown stock, and add one-half pint of thin, half-glaze sauce, one and one-half pints of fresh peas, one faggot,the pork dice and the onions, and complete the cooking of thewhole gently.

Dish the duckling, and cover it with the garnish and thesauce, after having withdrawn the faggot therefrom and re-duced the sauce so that it only just covers the garnish.

SSI

— pAte chaud de caneton

Roast the duckling, keeping it somewhat underdone, andcut the whole of the breast into long collops or very thin slices.Line a buttered Charlotte mould with short paste, and coverthe whole of the inside with a layer of gratin forcemeat(No. 202), combined with four tablespoonfuls of very reducedhalf-glaze sauce per one and two-thirds lb. of forcemeat—thenecessary quantity for this pie.

On the layer of forcemeat arrange a litter of the slices ofbreast; sliced, cooked mushrooms, and slices of truffle; andfill the mould in this way, taking care to alternate the layersof forcemeat, slices of breast, &c. Complete with a coat offorcemeat, upon which sprinkle a pinch of powdered thymeand bay-leaf; close the mould with a thin layer of paste, sealeddown round the edges; make a slit in the top; gild, and bakein a moderate oven for one hour.

When taking the pie out of the oven, turn it upside-downon a dish; detach the base; cut the latter into triangles, andset these triangles round the pie. Cover the forcemeat, thusbared, with a few tablespoonfuls of Madeira sauce; set a large,grooved, cooked mushroom just in the middle, and surround itwith a crown of sliced truffle.

Serve a Madeira sauce separately.

— BALL0TINE5 de CANETON

Bone the duckling, and completely clear the bones of all

meat.

Remove all tendons from the latter, and chop it, togetherwith half its weight of veal, as much fresh pork fat, a third asmuch panada (No. 190), the yolks of four eggs, one-half oz. ofsalt, and a little pepper and nutmeg. Pound; rub through asieve, and mix with this forcemeat, three oz. of gratin foie-grasforcemeat and three oz. of chopped mushrooms, sauted in butter.Divide up into portions weighing two oz.; wrap each portionin a piece of the duckling’s skin; envelop in muslin, and poachin a stock prepared from the duckling’s carcass. At the lastmoment, remove the pieces of muslin and glaze the ballotines.

Dish in a circle, and set the selected garnish, which may beturnips, peas, olives, or sauerkraut, &c., in the middle.

—CANETON ROUENNAIS

Except for the one case when they are served cold “h.la cuiller,” Rouen ducklings are not braised: they are roastedand always kept underdone. When they have to be stuffed,the forcemeat is prepared as follows:—Fry four oz. of larding

558

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

bacon, cut into dice, with one oz. of chopped onion, and addone-half lb. of sliced ducks’ livers, a pinch of chopped parsley,salt, pepper, and a little spice.

Keep the livers underdone, merely stiffened; let the wholehalf-cool; pound, and rub through a fine sieve.

— A1GUILLETTE5 de R0UENNAI5 à la BIGARRADEPoele the duckling and only just cook it, bearing in mind

that twenty minutes is the time allowed for cooking a fair-sizedbird. Remove the fillets lengthwise, each in ten slices, andset the latter on a lukewarm dish.

Add a few tablespoonfuls of veal gravy to the poeling-Uquor;set to boil for a few minutes; strain clear of grease, and finishas directed under sauce Bigarrade claire (No 31).

Cover the slices of breast with some of the sauce, and servethe remainder separately. “Aiguillettes” (or thin slices ofbreast cut lengthwise) k l’orange are prepared in the sameway, except that they are surrounded with sections of orange,skinned raw.

— AIGUILLETTES de ROUENNAIS aux CERISESPrepare the duckling as above, but add a little Madeira to

the braising-liquor. Clear the latter of grease; thicken witharrowroot; strain through muslin, and add one-half lb. ofstoned morello cherries, at the last moment. Set the cherriesround the aiguillettes; coat the latter thinly with sauce, andserve what remains of the latter, separately.

— AIGUILLETTES de ROUENNAIS aux TRUFFESPoele the duckling, and only just cook it.

Add one-sixth pint of Chambertin wine to the poeling-Uquor,and cook therein five medium-sized, peeled truffles. This done,reduce the liquor, clear of grease, strain it, and add it to asomewhat light Rouennaise sauce.

Raise the duckling’s aiguillettes, slice the truffles, and set ona lukewarm dish, alternating the aiguillettes with the slicesof truffle.

Coat thinly with sauce, and send what remains of the latterseparately.

— CANETON ROUENNAIS au CHAMPAGNEPoele the duckling as above.

Add one-half pint of dry Saint Marceaux champagne to thepoeling-Uquor; reduce, and complete with one-sixth pint ofthickened, veal stock.

559

Strain this sauce through muslin; clear it of grease, andsend it in a sauceboat at the same time as the duckling.

—CANETON ROUENNAIS EN CHEMISE

Stuff the duckling with the preparation given under No.1754; truss it as for an entree; insert it into a well-soakedbladder, and string the end of the latter close to the bird’s tail.Wrap the bladder in a napkin, also strung, and poach gentlyfor about forty-five minutes in a very strong brown stock.When about to serve, remove the napkin, and leave the duck-ling in the bladder.

Serve a Rouennaise sauce as an accompaniment.

—CANETON ROUENNAIS au PORTO

Roast the duckling “en casserole,” keeping it only justdone.

Swill with one-fifth pint of port wine; reduce to half, andadd this reduced swilling-liquor to one-half pint of ducklinggravy, thickened with arrowroot.

— CANETON ROUENNAIS à la PRESSE

Roast the duckling for twenty minutes, and send it instantlyto the table, where it should be treated as follows :—Remove thelegs, which are not served; carve the fillets into fine slices, laidone against the other on a lukewarm dish.

Chop up the carcass and press it, sprinkling it the whilewith a glassful of good red wine. Collect the gravy; addthereto a few drops of brandy, and with this liquor sprinklethe slices of breast, which should have been well seasoned.

Put the dish on a chafer, and thoroughly heat without allow-ing to boil.

Serve instantly.

— CANETON FARCI à la ROUENNAISE

Stuff the duckling with the forcemeat given under No. 1754,

and roast it before a fierce fire for from twenty-five to thirtyminutes, according to its size.

Send a Rouennaise sauce to the table with it.

If it be served carved, remove the legs, cisel them inside,season them well with salt and pepper, and grill them.

Cut the fillets into thin slices, set these on either side of along dish, and, in the middle, place the forcemeat withdrawnfrom the inside.

Set the grilled legs at either end of the dish.

Roughly chop up the carcass and press it, sprinkling it

560

the while with a glass of liqueur-brandy and a few drops oflemon juice. Add the collected gravy to the Rouennaise sauce;coat the slices of breast thinly with sauce, and serve whatremains of the sauce separately.

— SALMIS de CANETON à la ROUENNAISE

After having suppressed the clavicle, truss the duckling.

Put it in a red oven, where it should only stay eight minutes,

i.e., four minutes each side.

If possible, let it cool for a few minutes, that it may be moreeasily carved. Take care, also, to wipe it, for, as a rule, thefierceness of the oven blackens it. Remove the legs; ciselthem inside; season and grill them.

Sprinkle a long, buttered dish with chopped shallots, kitchensalt not too finely powdered, freshly-ground pepper, nutmeg,and allspice.

Cut the fillets into very thin slices lengthwise, fifteen fromeach fillet, and set them one against the other on the dish.Sprinkle them with the same seasoning as that lying on the dish,except for the shallots.

Remove the remaining stumps of the wings, as also thesmall, remaining skin of the breast; season both, and set themto grill by the side of the legs. Roughly chop up the carcass;press it while sprinkling it with half a glassful of red wine,and sprinkle the slices of breast with the collected gravy.

When about to serve, set a few small pieces of butter onthe slices of breast; heat for a moment on the stove, and putthe dish in a very hot oven, or at the salamander, that theglazing may be instantaneous.

Withdraw the dish the moment the edges of the aiguillettesbegin to curl, set the grilled legs at either end of the dish, thetwo wing-stumps, with the skin of the breast, in the middle, andserve immediately.

— SOUFFL6 de CANETON ROUENNAIS

Poele the duckling, and only just cook it.

Raise the supremes, and keep them hot, and cut the bonesfrom the carcass in such a way as to imitate a case, as I describedin a number of pullet recipes. With the duckling’s liver, theraw meat of another half-duckling, the white of an egg, andthree oz. of raw foie gras, prepare a mousseline forcemeat.

Fill the carcass with this forcemeat, shaping it so as to re-construct the bird. Surround it with a band of strong, butteredpaper, so as to avoid loss of shape, and poach gently, undercover, for twenty minutes.

561

With some reserved forcemeat, combined with an equalweight of foie-gras purée, garnish some tartlet crusts, and poachthem at the same time as the souffle.

Dish the piece; surround it with the tartlets; set a collop ofsupreme on each of the latter, and serve a Rouennaise sauceseparately.

Canetons Froids

—CAN ETON à la CUILLER

Braise the duckling with Madeira, and cook it well.

Put into a terrine just large enough to hold it; cover withthe braising-liquor, strained through a napkin, and combinedwith enough aspic jelly to completely coat the duckling. Leaveto cool.

When about to serve, clear the surface of grease, first bymeans of a spoon, then with boiling water, and dish on anapkin.

—CANETON GLAC6 aux MANDARINES

Poele the duckling, and let it cool in its liquor.

When it is quite cold, set it on its back; glaze it with aspicjelly, and place it on a low rice or carved-bread cushion lyingon a long dish.

Surround it with emptied tangerines, filled with cold moussemade from ducklings’ livers and foie gras. Alternate the tan-gerines with small timbales of aspic, combined with the poeling-liquor and the juice squeezed from the sections of thetangerines.

—CANETON GLACS aux CERISES

Roast the duckling, and keep it underdone.

When it is quite cold, remove the breast, and remove thebones in such wise as to form a case with the carcass. Cuteach fillet into eight thin slices; coat them with a brown chaud-froid sauce, and decorate with truffles. Fill the carcass witha mousse made from the remains of the meat, the duckling’sliver, and some foie gras, and shape it so as to imitate the con-vex breast of the bird.

Glaze with aspic, and set in the refrigerator, that the moussemay harden. When the latter is firm, lay the chaud-froid-coated collops upon it, and set the piece in a deep, square dish.Surround with cold, stoned, morello cherries, poached inBordeaux wine, and cover these with an aspic jelly flavouredwith duckling essence.

o o

— AIQUILLETTES de CANETONS à l’^CARLATEPoele a Rouen duckling until it is just cooked, and let it

cool in its liquor. Raise the fillets; skin them, and cut themeach into eight thin slices. Coat them with a brown chaud-froid sauce, and decorate with truffles. Prepare an equalnumber of slices of tongue the size and shape of the slices ofduckling, and coat them with aspic.

With the remains and the meat of the legs, prepare amousse, and pour it into a square or oval silver dish; let it cool,and then set the aiguillettes of duckling and the slices of tongueupon it, alternating them in so doing, and cover the moussewith aspic.

— MOUSSE ET MOUSSELINESDE CANETON ROUENNAIS

These are prepared with the same quantities as the chickenmousses and mousselines, but they allow of no other sauce thanthe Rouennaise or the Bigarrade, nor of any other garnishesthan sections of orange, cherries, vegetable purges, or creams.

— MOUSSE de CANETON ROUENNAIS

With the exception of the nature of the principal ingredient,the preparation, quantities, and moulding of this mousse arethe same as for chicken mousse. The reader is, therefore,begged to refer to No. 1670, which may be applied perfectlywell to Rouen duckling.

— SOUFFL6 FROID de CANETON à l’ORANGEProceed as for the “Caneton aux cerises,” but with this

difference, that the duckling is used entirely for the mousse.

Serve, similarly, in a square dish, and surround with sec-tions of oranges skinned raw. Cover with an aspic jellyflavoured with the juice of Seville oranges, and combined witha liqueur-glassful of Curasao per pint of jelly.

— TERRINE de CANETON ROUENNAIS à la GELI2EFirst prepare the following forcemeat:—Heat three oz. of

fat bacon, cut into small dice, and three oz. of butter in afrying-pan. Throw six fine ducks’ livers (seasoned with saltand pepper, and sprinkled with a pinch of powdered thyme,bay-leaf, and half an onion chopped) into this fat. Toss themover a fierce fire, just long enough to heat them; leave themto cool, and rub them through a sieve.

Bone the breast of a Rouen duckling and its back as faras the region of the legs, and suppress the tail. Stuff it withthe preparation given above; truss as for an entree, and put

POULTRY

563

it in a terrine just large enough to hold it. Sprinkle it witha glassful of brandy; cover with a slice of bacon, and cook itin the bain-marie, in the oven, and under cover for fortyminutes.

With the carcass and some strong veal stock, prepare two-thirds pint of excellent aspic, and, when withdrawing theduckling from the oven, cover it with this aspic, and let it cool.When about to serve, remove all grease, first by means of aspoon, and then by means,of boiling water, and set the terrineon a napkin lying on a long dish.

—TIMBALE de caneton a la voisinRoast a Rouen duckling, and keep it underdone; let it cool,and raise its fillets. With the carcass prepare a Salmis sauce,and thicken it with aspic as for a chaud-froid sauce.

Cut the fillets into slices, coat them with Salmis sauce, andleave this to set. Let a thickness of sauce set on the bottom ofa timbale.

Upon this sauce lay some of the coated slices, alternatingthem with slices of truffle, and cover with a thin layer of aspicjelly. Lay another row of slices of fillet and of truffles, followedas before by a layer of aspic, and continue thus in the sameorder. Complete with a somewhat thick layer of aspic, andkeep in the cool until ready for serving.

N.B.—This old and excellent cold entree is really only acold salmis. The procedure may be applied to all game suitedto the salmis method of preparation. It is the simplest andcertainly the best way of serving them cold.

—PINTADES (GUINEA FOWL)The guinea-fowl is not equal to the pheasant from the gas-tronomical standpoint, though it often takes the place of thelatter among the roasts after the shooting season. But, thoughit has neither the fine flavour nor the delicate meat of thepheasant, it does good service notwithstanding. The majorityof pheasant recipes may be applied to it, especially k laBoh^mienne, k la creme, en Chartreuse, en salmis, k la chou-crofite, &c.

—PIGEONS and SQUABS (PIGEONS ET PIGEONNEAUX)Young pigeons are not very highly esteemed by Englishgourmets, and this is more particularly to be regretted, since,when the birds are of excellent quality, they are worthy thebest tables.

—PIGEONNEAUX à la BORDELAISOpen the squabs down the back; season them; slightlyflatten them, and toss them in butter. They may just as

002

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

564

well be halved as left whole. Dish, and surround with thegarnish given under “Poulet & la Bordelaise” (No. 1538).

— PIGEONNEAUX EN CASSEROLE à la PAYSANNE

Cook the squabs in the oven in an earthenware saucepan.

When they are two-thirds done, surround them with one andone-half oz. of salted breast of pork, cut into small dice andblanched, and two oz. of sliced and sauted potatoes for eachpigeon. Complete the cooking of the whole gently, and, whenabout to serve, add a little good gravy.

— PIGEONNEAUX EN CHARTREUSE

Prepare the Chartreuse in a Charlotte mould, as explainedunder No. 1182. Line the bottom and sides with a layer ofbraised, drained, and pressed cabbages; in the centre set thesquabs, cooked “a la casserole” and cut into two lengthwise,and alternate them with small rectangles of blanched, saltedbreast of pork, and sausage roundels. Cover with cabbages,and steam in a bain-marie for thirty minutes.

Let the Chartreuse stand for five minutes after withdrawingfrom the bain-marie; turn out on a round dish, and surroundwith a few tablespoonfuls of half-glaze sauce.

— PIGEONNEAUX EN CRAPAUDINE

Cut the young pigeons horizontally in two, from the apexof the breast to the wings. Open them; flatten them slightly;season them; dip them in melted butter, roll them in bread-crumbs, and grill them gently.

Serve a devilled sauce at the same time.

— PIGEONNEAUX EN COMPOTE

Fry in butter two oz. of blanched, salted breast of pork andtwo oz. of raw mushrooms, peeled and quartered. Drain thebacon and the mushrooms, and set the squabs, trussed as foran entree, to fry in the same butter.

Withdraw them when they are brown; drain them of butter;swill with half a glassful of white wine; reduce the latter, andadd sufficient brown stock and half-glaze sauce (tomated), inequal quantities, to cover the birds. Plunge them into thissauce, with a faggot, and simmer until they are cooked andthe sauce is reduced to half.

This done, transfer the squabs to another saucepan; addthe pieces of bacon, the mushrooms, and six small onions,glazed with butter, for each bird; strain the sauce over the

POULTRY 565

whole through a fine sieve; simmer for ten minutes more, andserve very hot.

—PIGEON PIE

Line the bottom and sides of a pie-dish with very thin,flattened collops of lean beef, seasoned with salt and pepper,and sprinkled with chopped shallots.

Set the quartered pigeons inside the dish, and separate themwith a halved hard-boiled egg-yolk for each pigeon. Moistenhalf-way up with good gravy; cover with a layer of puff paste;gild; streak; make a slit in the top, and bake for about one andone-half hours in a good, moderate oven.

—VOL au VENT de PIGEONNEAUX

Suppress the feet and the pinions; poele the squabs, andonly just cook them.

Cut each bird into four, and mix them with a garnish “& laFinanci&re” (No. 1474) combined with the poeling-liquor.Pour the whole into a vol-au-vent crust, and dish on a napkin.

—C6TELETTE5 de PIGEONNEAU à la NE5LE5

Cut them in two, and reserve the claw, which serves as thebone of the cutlet. Flatten them slightly; season, and fry themin butter on one side only. Cool them under slight pressure;coat their fried side, dome-fashion, with some godiveau withcream, combined with a third of its bulk of gratin forcemeatand chopped truffles. Set them on a tray, and place in amoderate oven to complete the cooking, and poach the force-meat. Dish in a circle, and separate the cutlets with collopsof veal sweetbreads, dipped in beaten eggs, rolled in bread-crumbs, and tossed in butter. Garnish their midst with mush-rooms and sliced fowls’ livers, tossed in butter and coheredwith a few tablespoonfuls of Madeira sauce.

—COTELETTES de PIGEONNEAUX EN PAPILLOTES

Cut the pigeons in two, as above; stiffen them in butter, andenclose them in papillotes as explained under “Cotelettes deVeau en Papillotes” (No. 1259).

—C6TELETTES de PIGEONNEAUX à la SEVIGNE

Saute the half-pigeons in butter, and leave them to coolunder slight pressure. Garnish their cut sides dome-fashionwith a salpicon of white chicken-meat, mushrooms, andtruffles, the whole cohered by means of a cold Allemande sauce.

Dip them in beaten egg, roll them in bread-crumbs, andcook them gently in clarified butter.

566

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Dish them in a circle; garnish their midst with asparagus-heads cohered with butter, and serve a light, Madeira sauceseparately.

— SUPREMES de PIGEONNEAUX à la DIPLOMATERaise the fillets and slightly flatten them; stiffen them in

butter, and leave them to cool under slight pressure. Thisdone, dip them in a Villeroy sauce, combined with choppedherbs and mushrooms, and cool them. Dip each fillet in beatenegg; roll them in bread-crumbs, and fry just before serving.

Dish in a circle, and in their midst set a heap of friedparsley. Send separately a garnish of pigeon quenelles, mush-rooms, and small, olive-shaped truffles, to which a half-glazesauce flavoured with pigeon essence has been added.

— SUPREMES de PIGEONNEAUX à la SAINT-CLAIR

With the meat of the legs prepare a mousseline forcemeat,and, with the latter, make some quenelles the size of smallolives, and set them to poach. Poele the breasts, withoutcolouration, on a thick litter of sliced onions, and keep themunderdone. Add a little velout6 to the onions; rub themthrough tammy, and put the quenelles in this sauce.

In the middle of a shallow croustade, set a pyramid of cepestossed in butter. Raise the fillets; skin them, and set them onthe cepes; coat them with the prepared sauce; surround with &thread of meat glaze, and place the quenelles all round.

— SUPREMES de PIGEONNEAUX à la MARIGNYCut off the legs, and, with their meat, prepare a forcemeat.

Poach the latter on a tray, and stamp it out with an oval cutterinto pieces the size of the supremes.

Cover the breasts with slices of bacon, and poele them,taking care to only just cook them.

Quickly raise the supremes, skin them, and set each uponan oval of forcemeat, sticking them on by means of a littlegratin forcemeat.

Put the supremes in the oven for a moment, that thisforcemeat may poach. Dish the supremes round a pyramidconsisting of a smooth pur4e of peas, and coat with a velout6sauce, finished with an essence prepared from the remains andthe poeling-Mquor of the breasts.

— SUPREMES de PIGEONNEAUX aux TRUFFESRaise the supremes, flatten them slightly; toss them in

clarified butter, and set them on a border of smooth forcemeat,

GAME 567

laid on a dish by means of a piping-bag, and poached in thefront of the oven.

Swill the vegetable-pan with Madeira; add four fine slicesof truffle for each supreme, and a little pale melted meat glaze,and finish with a moderate amount of butter.

Coat the supremes with this sauce, and set the slices oftruffle upon it.

—MOUSSELINES de PIQEONNEAUX

à l’EPICURIENNE

Prepare and poach these mousselines like the chicken ones,but make them a little smaller. Dish them in the form of acrown; set thereon a young pigeon’s fillet roasted, and in theirmidst arrange a garnish of peas with lettuce. Coat with afumet prepared from the carcasses and cohered with a few table-spoonfuls of velout6.

N.B.—Pigeons and squabs may also be prepared after therecipes given for chicks.

Relev6s and EntriesGAME

VENISON and GROUND GAME

The stag (Fr. Cerf) and the fallow deer (Fr. Daim) supplythe only venison that is consumed in England, where the roe-buck (Fr. Chevreuil) is not held in very high esteem. True, thelatter’s flesh is very often mediocre in quality, and saddles andlegs of roebuck often have to be imported from the Continentwhen they are to appear on an important menu.

On the other hand, venison derived from the stag or red deerand the fallow deer proper is generally of superior quality. Theformer has perhaps more flavour, but the latter, which is sup-plied by animals bred in herds on large private estates, has noequal as far as delicacy and tenderness are concerned, while itis covered with white and scented fat, which is greatly appre-ciated by English connoisseurs.

Although these two kinds of venison are generally servedas relev^s, they belong more properly to the roasts, and I shallgive their recipes a little later on. In any case, only half ofthe hind-quarters (that is to say, the leg together with thatpart of the saddle which reaches from it to the floating ribs)is served at high-class tables.

I shall now, therefore, only give the various recipes dealingwith roebuck, it being understood that these, if desired, maybe applied to corresponding joints of the stag or deer.

568 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— SELLE de CHEVREUIL ET CUISSOT

Saddles and legs of roebuck may be prepared after the samerecipes, and allow of the same garnishes. The recipes forsaddle which I give hereafter may therefore be applied equallywell to legs.

Whichever joint be selected, it must first be cleared of alltendons and then larded with larding bacon. The last opera-tion is no more essential than is the marinading which inFrance has become customary with such pieces. It might evenbe said with justice that marinading is not only useless, butharmful, more particularly in the case of young animals whosemeat has been well hung.

Unlike many other specimens of game, roebuck has to beeaten fresh; it does not suit it to be in the least tainted. Ishould like to point out here that game shot in ambush isbest, owing to the fact that animals killed after a chase decom-pose very quickly, and thereby lose a large proportion of theirflavour.

The saddle of the roebuck generally consists of the whole ofthe latter’s back, from the withers to the tail, in which casethe bones of the ribs are cut very short, that the joint may liesteady at all points.

At the croup-end, cut the joint on either side diagonally,from the point of the haunch to the root of the tail. Sometimes,however, the saddle only consists of the lumbar portion of theback, and, in this case, the ribs are cut up to be cooked ascutlets.

— SELLE de CHEVREUIL à l’ALLEMANDE

Marinade the saddle for two or three days in raw marinadeNo. 169, and roast it, on a narrow baking-tray, upon the vege-tables of the marinade.

As soon as the joint is cooked, withdraw it; swill the traywith a little marinade, and almost entirely reduce. Clear ofgrease; add two-thirds pint of cream and one powdered juniperberry; reduce by a third; complete with a few drops of meltedglaze, and rub through tammy.

Serve this sauce at the same time as the saddle, which seton a long dish.

— SELLE de CHEVREUIL à la BADEN-BADEN

The saddle should be marinaded and well dried before beingset to cook.

Poele it on the vegetables of the marinade.

When it is cooked, put it on a long dish, and, at either end

569

of it, set a garnish of stewed pears, unsugared, but flavouredwith cinnamon and lemon-rind. Pour one-third pint of gamestock into the tray in which the joint was cooked; cook for tenminutes; strain; clear of grease, and thicken with arrowroot.

Serve this thickened stock separately, and send some red-currant jelly to the table at the same time.

—SELLE de CHEVREUIL aux CERISES

Keep the saddle for twelve hours in marinade (No. 169)made from verjuice instead of vinegar. Roast it on the spit,basting it with the marinade, and keep it slightly underdone.

At the same time, serve a cherry sauce consisting of equalquantities of poivrade sauce and red-currant jelly, to each pintof which add three oz. of semi-candied cherries, set to soak inhot water thirty minutes beforehand.

N.B.—This saddle need not be marinaded if it be desiredplain.

—SELLE de CHEVREUIL à la CUMBERLAND

Roast it like a haunch of venison, without marinading it.Send it to the table with a timbale of French beans, coheredwith butter, and serve a Cumberland sauce (No. 134) separately.

—SELLE de CHEVREUIL à la CREOLE

Marinade it for a few hours only, and roast it on the spit,basting it the while with the marinade.

Set it on a long dish, and surround it with bananas tossedin butter.

At the same time serve a Roberts sauce, combined with athird of its bulk of Poivrade sauce, and one oz. of fresh butterper pint.

—SELLE de CHEVREUIL à la BEAUJEU

Lard and roast it. Set it on a long dish, and surround itwith artichoke-bottoms, garnished with lentil purée, and alter-nated with chestnuts cooked in a small quantity of consomm^and glazed.

Serve a venison sauce separately.

—SELLE de CHEVREUIL au GENIEVRE

Lard the saddle, and roast it. Swill the baking-tray witha small glassful of burned gin; add one powdered juniper berryand one-sixth pint of double cream. Reduce the cream to half;complete with a few tablespoonfuls of poivrade sauce and a fewdrops of lemon juice. Serve this sauce with the saddle, andsend separately some. hot stewed apples, very slightlysugared.

570

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— 5ELLE de CHEVREUIL AVEC SAUCES DIVERSESSaddle of roebuck may also be served with the following

sauces:—Poivrade, Venison, Grand-Veneur, Moscovite,Roberts, &c. The selected accompaniment determines the titleof the dish.

— NOISETTES ET C6TELETTES de CHEVREUIL

The same recipes may be applied to both. Trim them afterthe manner of lamb noisettes or cutlets. They may be mode-rately marinaded, but they may also be used fresh. In thelatter case, fry them in butter over a somewhat fierce fire, likethe lamb noisettes.

If they have been marinaded, it is better to toss them veryquickly in very hot oil, and then to dry them before dishingthem.

It is in the dishing only that the noisettes and the cutletsdiffer; for, whereas the latter are always dished in a crown,one overlapping the other, or each separated from the rest bycroutons of bread-crumb fried in butter, the noisettes are alwaysdished in a circle on small, oval croutons fried in butte^ or ontartlet crusts containing some kind of garnish.

— COTELETTES de CHEVREUIL CONTI

Saute the cutlets in very hot oil; dry them; dish themin a crown, and separate them by similarly-shaped collopsof salted tongue.

Swill the saucepan with a little white wine; add this liquorto a Poivrade sauce, and coat the cutlets with it.

Serve a light, buttered pur£e of lentils at the same time.

— C6TELETTES de CHEVREUIL DIANE

Spread an even layer, one-third inch thick, of mousselinegame forcemeat on a tray. Poach this forcemeat in a steameror in a very moderate oven, and cut it into triangles equal insize to the cutlets.

Toss the latter as already explained; dish them in a crown,and separate them by croutons of forcemeat already prepared.

Coat the whole with poivrade sauce, thinned by means ofa little beaten cream, and garnished with crescents of truffleand hard-boiled white of egg, and serve a purde of chestnutsat the same time.

— NOISETTES de CHEVREUIL au GENIEVRE

Cook the noisettes in smoking oil. Dry them, dish them,

GAME

57i

and coat them with the same sauce as that given under “Selleau Geni&vre” (No. 1798).

Serve some stewed apples at the same time.

—NOISETTES de CHEVREUIL ROMANOFFCook the noisettes; set them on stuffed sections of cucumber,prepared after No. 2124a, and place a slice of truffle on eachnoisette. Coat with a Poivrade sauce with cream, and servea mushroom pur£e separately.

—NOISETTES de CHEVREUIL VALENCIACook the noisettes, and dish them in a circle, each on around crouton of brioche fried in butter, and coat lightly withbigarrade sauce.

Serve a sauceboat of bigarrade sauce and an orange saladat the same time.

—NOISETTES de CHEVREUIL VILLENEUVECarefully clear the meat of the roebuck of all tendons, andchop it up with a knife, combining with it the while the thirdof its weight of fresh butter, as much bread-crumb, soaked inmilk, and pressed, and one-third pint of fresh cream per lb. ofmeat. Season, divide into portions weighing two oz., mouldto a nice round shape, wrap in pig’s caul, cook quickly at thelast moment, and dish in the form of a crown.

Coat with Chasseur sauce, and send a timbale of celerypur6e separately.

—NOISETTES de CHEVREUIL WALKYRIE

Saute the noisettes in the usual way, and dish them in theform of a crown, each on a small quoit of “Pommes Berny”(No. 2184). On each noisette lay a fine, grilled mushroom,garnished with a rosette of Soubise pur£e, made by means ofa piping-bag fitted with a grooved pipe. Pour a little venisonsauce over the dish, and send a sauceboat of it separately.

N.B.—Roebuck noisettes and cutlets are still served withpurges of chestnuts or celery, with truffles, cepes, mushrooms,&c.

The sauces best suited to them are Poivrade sauce and itsderivatives, such as Venison sauce, Grand-Veneur sauce,Romaine sauce, &c., also Roberts sauce Escoffier.

—CIVET de CHEVREUILFor “Civet de Chevreuil” the shoulders, the neck, and thebreast are used, and these pieces are cut up and set to marinadesix hours beforehand with the aromatics and the same red wineas that with which the civet will be moistened.

572

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

When about to prepare the civet, drain and dry these pieces,and proceed exactly as for “Civet de Li&vre” (No. 1821),except for the thickening by means of blood, which the diffi-culty of obtaining the blood of the roebuck perforce precludes.

This civet, which should be classed among dishes for thehome, is usually served in the form of a stew; for, inasmuchas the final thickening with blood is lacking, it can only bean imitation of the civet. When, therefore, hare’s blood isavailable, it should always be used in finishing this dish exactlyafter the manner of No. 1821—that is to say, the preparationshould be given the characteristic stamp of civet by means ofa final thickening with blood.

— BOAR and YOUNG BOAR (5ANGLIER ETMARCASSIN)

When the wild boar is over two years of age, it is no morefit to be served as food. Between one and two years it shouldbe used with caution, and the various roebuck recipes maythen be applied to it. But only the young boar less than twelvemonths old should be prepared in decent kitchens.

The hams of a young boar, salted and smoked, supply avery passable relev£, which allows of varying the ordinarymenu. They are treated exactly like pork hams.

The saddle and the cushions may be prepared after therecipes given for saddle of roebuck, and the same holds goodwith the cutlets and the noisettes.

Finally, the saddle may be served cold, in a daube, when itis prepared after No. 1173.

As the various parts of the young boar are covered withfat, it is understood that they are not larded, nor do theyneed it.

— HARE and LEVERET (LlEVRE ET LEVRAUT)

As a result of one of those freaks of taste, of which I havealready pointed out some few examples, hare is not nearly sohighly esteemed as it deserves in England; and the fact seemsall the more strange when one remembers that in many of hercounties excellent specimens of the species are to be found.

Whatever be the purpose for which it is required, alwaysselect a young hare, five or six lbs. in weight. The age maybe ascertained as follows :—Grasp one ear close to its extremitywith both hands, and pull in opposite directions; if the eartear, the beast is young; if it resist the strain, the hare isold, and should be set aside for soups and the preparation offumets and forcemeats.

GAME 573

—LIEVRE FARCI à la PERIQOURDINE

Take care to collect all the blood when emptying the hare;break the bones of the legs, that they may be easily trussed;clear the legs and the fillets of all tendons, and lard them.Chop up the liver, the lungs, the heart, and four fowls’ livers,together with five oz. of fat bacon.

Add to this mincemeat five oz. of soaked and pressed bread-crumbs, the blood, two oz. of chopped onion, cooked in butterand cold; a pinch of chopped parsley,'a piece of crushed garlicthe size of a pea, and three oz. of raw truffle parings. Mixthe whole up well; fill the hare with this stuffing; sew up theskin of the belly; truss the animal, and braise it in white winefor about two and one-half hours, basting it often the while.Glaze at the last moment. Serve the hare on a long dish.

Add two-thirds pint of half-glaze game sauce to the braising-liquor; reduce; clear of grease; strain, and add three oz. ofchopped truffles to this sauce.

Pour a little sauce over the dish on which the hare has beenset, and serve what remains of the sauce separately.

—RABLE de LIEVRE

The French term “rable” means the whole of the back ofthe hare, from the root of the neck to the tail, with the ribscut very short.

Often, however, that piece which corresponds with thesaddle in butchers’ meat alone is taken, i.e., the piece reachingfrom the croup to the floating ribs. Whatever be the particularcut, the piece should be well cleared of all tendons, and finelylarded before being set to marinade; and this last operation mayeven be dispensed wflth when the “r&ble” is derived from ayoung hare.

Marinading would only become necessary if the piece hadto be kept some considerable time.

—RABLE de LlEVRE à l’ALLEMANDE

Set the table well dried on the vegetables of the marinade,which should be laid on the bottom of a long, narrow dishWhen it is nearly cooked, remove the vegetables, pour one-quarter pint of cream into the dish, and complete the cookingof the rable, basting it the while with that cream.

Finish at the last minute with a few drops of lemon juice.

Dish the rable, and surround it with the cream stock,strained through a fine strainer.

574

— rAble de lievre au geni'evre

Roast it, as above, on the vegetables of the marinade.

Swill the dish with a small glassful of gin and two or threetablespoonfuls of marinade, and reduce to half. Add one-sixthpint of cream, two tablespoonfuls of poivrade sauce, and fourpowdered juniper berries.

Strain and serve this sauce separately at the same time asthe Table.

— CUISSES de LIfeVRE

Use the legs of young hares only; those of old animals maybe used for the “civet” and forcemeat alone. After havingcleared them of tendons and larded them with very thin stripsof bacon, treat them like the rable.

— FILETS de LEVRAUT à la DAMPIERRE

Take five leverets’ fillets; contise them with slices of truffle,after the manner directed for “Supr£mes de Volaille k laChevali&re” (No. 1458); shape them like crescents, and setthem on a buttered dish.

Lard the minion fillets with a rosette consisting of stripsof salted tongue, and set them also on a buttered dish.

With what remains of the meat of the leverets, prepare amousseline forcemeat, and add thereto some truffle essence andsome chopped truffles.

Dish this forcemeat, shaping it like a truncated cone twoand one-half inches high, the radius of which should be thelength of a leveret’s fillet.

Set this forcemeat to poach in the front of the oven.

Sprinkle the fillets and the minion fillets with a little brandyand melted butter; cover them, and poach them likewise inthe front of the oven. This done, arrange them radially onthe cone of forcemeat, alternating the fillets and the minionfillets. Place a fine, glazed truffle in the middle of the rosette,and surround the base with mushrooms, separated by chestnutscooked in consomm£ and glazed, and small onions cooked inbutter.

Serve a poivrade sauce at the same time, combined with thefillets’ cooking-liquor.

— FILETS de LEVRAUT à la MORNAY(Recipe of the Freres Provei^aux)

Trim two leverets’ fillets, and cut them into collops, oneinch in diameter and one-third inch thick. Prepare (1) the

575

same number of bread-crumb croutons as there are collops, andmake them of the same size as the latter, though half as thick;(2) the same number of thick slices of truffle, cooked at the lastminute in a little Madeira.

Toss the collops of fillet quickly in clarified butter; colourthe croutons in butter at the same time, and mix the latter withthe collops and the truffles in a saucepan.

Swill the saut^pan with the Madeira in which the truffleshave cooked; add a little succulent pale glaze; reduce suffi-ciently; strain the sauce through a sieve; finish it liberallywith butter; add it to the sauted collops, and serve the latterin a very hot timbale.

N.B.—This recipe was given by the Comte de Mornay him-self to the proprietors of the famous Parisian restaurant, andfor a long while the dish was one of the specialities of a houseno longer extant.

—FILETS de LEVRAUT à la VENDOME

After having contised the leveret’s fillets, roll them round abuttered tin mould, and fasten them with a string, that theymay form rings.

Set to poach. Meanwhile, spread on a buttered tray a layerone-half inch thick of game forcemeat; poach the latter; stampit out by means of an even cutter into roundels of the samesize as the rings, and set one of these on each of the force-meat roundels, fixing it by means of a little raw forcemeat.

Cut the minion fillets into collops, and quickly toss themin butter with an equal quantity of mushrooms and five oz. ofraw, sliced truffles.

Swill the saucepan with a little brandy and the poaching-liquor of the fillet-rings; add a little poivrade sauce; finish thissauce with butter, and plunge therein the collops of fillet, themushrooms, and the truffles.

Set the rings in a circle on a dish, and fill them with thisgarnish. Serve separately a sauceboat of poivrade sauce anda timbale of chestnut purée.

—MOUSSES ET MOUSSELINES de LlEVRE

Proceed exactly as for all other mousses and mousselines,except, of course, in regard to the basic ingredient, which inthis case is the meat of a hare.

—SOUFFLE de LlEVRE

With one lb. of the meat of a hare, prepare a light mous-seline forcemeat; add thereto the whites of two eggs,

576 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

whisked to a stiff froth; poach the mousseline in a souffle sauce-pan.

Cut the hare’s minion fillets into collops, and toss them inbutter at the last moment.

Cook the souffle in a moderate oven; coat the top lightlywith half-glaze sauce flavoured with hare fumet, and surroundit with the minion-fillet collops, alternated with slices oftruffles.

The minion-fillet collops and the slices of truffles may beadded to the sauce, and this garnish is served separately inanother timbale.

18ai— CIVET de LIEVRE

Skin and clean the hare, taking care to collect all the bloodin so doing. Put the liver aside, after having carefully freedit from the gall-bladder, as also from those portions touchingthe latter.

Cut up the hare, and put the pieces in a basin with a fewtablespoonfuls of brandy and an equal quantity of olive oil,salt, pepper, and an onion cut into thin roundels. Cover andleave to marinade for a few hours in the very red wine usedfor the moistening. Fry one-half lb. of lean bacon, cut intolarge dice, in butter, and drain it as soon as it is brown. Inthe same butter brown two fair-sized, quartered onions; addtwo tablespoonfuls of flour, and cook this roux gently untilit acquires a golden tinge. Put the pieces of hare into thisroux, after having well dried them, and stiffen them.

Moisten with the wine used for the marinade. Add a largefaggot, in which place a garlic clove; cover, and leave to cookgently on the side of the stove.

A few minutes before serving, thicken the civet with thereserved blood, which should be gradually heated, and mixtherewith a few tablespoonfuls of sauce. Then transfer thepieces of hare, one by one, to another saucepan with the friedpieces of bacon, twenty small, glazed onions, and twenty cookedmushrooms.

Strain the sauce over the whole through a strainer.

Dish in a warm timbale, and surround with heart-shapedcroMons fried in butter at the last moment.

Cold Preparations of Hare1823—liEvre en daube

Take a fresh hare, and bone it from the back without empty-ing it, that the skin of the belly may be untouched.

Detach the shoulders and the legs; do not touch the head;

GAME

577

season with salt and pepper; sprinkle with a few drops ofbrandy, and leave to marinade. With the hare’s liver, somefat bacon, and some truffle parings, prepare a gratin force-meat. Prepare another forcemeat with the meat of the shouldersand the legs, an equal weight of fat bacon, one egg, a pinch ofwild thyme, salt, pepper, spices, and the brandy of the marin-ade. Rub this forcemeat through a sieve, and add to it thegratin forcemeat, one-half lb. of fat bacon, and five oz. oftruffles cut into dice.

Fill the boned hare with this preparation; sew it up, andtie the head to the back in such wise as to give the piece theappearance of the animal at rest.

Wrap it in slices of bacon, and set it in a terrine lined withthe latter; sprinkle with a glassful of brandy, and place inthe oven for thirty minutes with lid off.

Then pour into the terrine a fumet prepared with red winefrom the hare’s bones; cover, and then cook in the oven gentlyfor three hours.

Leave to half-cool; drain away the cooking-liquor, andcarefully remove the slices of bacon. Strain the cooking-liquorthrough muslin; return it to the terrine, and fill up the latterwith savoury jelly.

Keep in the cool for two hours before serving.

—PAIN de LlfeVRE

This u Pain” is prepared according to No. 1689, and it maybe served in “Belle-vue,” after the manner described for coldpieces prepared in this way.

—PATE de LIEVRE

Clear the fillets, the minion fillets, and the legs of alltendons; moderately lard them; season them; set them in adish with an equal quantity of truffles and fat bacon strips;sprinkle with some brandy, and leave to marinade for onehour. With what remains of the meat, some fillets of vealand pork, in the proportion of six oz. per lb. of hare; fresh,fat bacon in the proportion of one and one-half lbs. per lb. ofhare; and spiced salt, prepare a forcemeat, and finish it withone egg and three tablespoonfuls of brandy per lb. of force-meat.

Rub through tammy, and add a portion of the hare’s blood.

Line a round or oval buttered mould with raised-pie paste,and completely cover the paste with slices of bacon. Then coatinside with forcemeat, and fill up the mould with alternate layersof forcemeat, hares’ fillets, truffle, and fat bacon strips.

p P

578

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Finish with a layer of forcemeat; cover with a slice ofbacon; sprinkle a pinch of powdered thyme and bay over thelatter; close the pie with a layer of paste, which should besealed down round the moistened edges; pinch the crest insideand out, and finish off the pie by means of imitation leavesmade from paste.

Gild; bake in a moderate oven, and, when the pie is almostcold, pour some jelly flavoured with hare fumet into it.

—TERRINE de LIEVRE

A “Terrine” or Patty is only a pie without a crust, and itallows of the same forcemeat and of the same garnish of baconstrips as the latter. The terrine should first be lined withslices of bacon, whereupon it is garnished like the pie withalternate layers of forcemeat, bacon strips, hares’ fillets, andtruffles.

Cover with a slice of bacon; sprinkle the centre of thelatter with a little powdered thyme and bay, and a little spice.Put the lid on the terrine, place it in a saucepan containing alittle water, and set it to cook in the oven.

The time allowed for cooking is naturally subject to thesize of the terrine. It is known to be quite cooked when thegrease which rises to the surface is quite clear.

As long as this grease is turbid, raw juices are still issuingfrom the forcemeat and the garnish inside. Another methodof telling is by the -insertion of a needle. If the latter with-draws evenly heated throughout its length, the terrine is cooked.

If the patty is to be served immediately, add some aspic toit when it is just tepid, and set it to cool under slight pressure.When quite cold, clear it of grease; trim its surface, and cutit up in the utensil.

If it is to be served whole and presented, set it to cool undergreater pressure; turn it out, and trim it all round. This done,cause a layer of jelly to set on the bottom of the terrine; returnthe trimmed patty to the latter, and surround it with meltedaspic jelly.

When about to serve, turn it out after the manner of anaspic; set it on a long dish, and border the latter with jellycroutons.

If it have to be kept some time, proceed as above, but uselard instead of aspic, and keep it well covered and in the cool.

—YOUNG WILD RABBIT (LAPEREAUX)

Use the w’ild rather than the tame young rabbit, and testits age after the manner described in regard to the hare, and

GAME 579

also by means of a little lentil-shaped bone, which is to befound in the region of the patella.

As the wild rabbit ages, this bone shrinks and finally com-bines with the other bones of the articulation.

When the wild rabbit is old, it is tough, and can only beused for stock or forcemeats.

All the recipes given for “Poulet Saut6,” and those givenfor hare, may be applied to wild rabbit; the reader is, therefore,begged to refer to these.

—FEATHERED GAME

Feathered game comprises all esculent birds that live infreedom.

The number of species involved, therefore, is considerable,but from the culinary standpoint they may be grouped intoten principal classes, which are :—

1. The various pheasants, grey and red partridges, the Te-tras Californias.

2. The hazel-hen, grouse, prairie fowls, ganga, sand-grouse,

3. The various wild ducks and teals.

4. The woodcocks and snipes.

5. The various plovers, lapwings, sandpipers, water-rails,water-hens.

6. The quails, land-rails, Virginia quails.

7. The various thrushes, Corsican blackbirds.

8. The various larks.

9. The warblers.

10. The ortolans.

The birds of Classes 1 and 4 are better high—that is tosay, they should be hung for a few days, before being plucked,in a moderate draught, that they may begin to decompose, andthat the particular flavour of their flesh may be accentuated, aprocess which increases their culinary value. Whateveropinion may be held in regard to the gaminess of these birds,one thing is quite certain—namely, that the meat of a freshpheasant and that of a high one are two totally different things.When fresh, the meat is flavourless, whereas when it is reason-ably high it is tender, full of taste, and of an incomparableflavour.

Formerly, it was the custom to lard the birds of Class t,especially when they were to be roasted. But this practiceshould be resolutely discarded, for, if the bird be young, itcan only impair the latter’s flavour, and, if it be old, it cannotpossibly restore those qualities to it which it has already lost.

p p 2

580

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Besides, an old bird should never be served; it ought onlyto be used in the preparation of game stock or forcemeats.

The birds belonging to the remaining classes are preparedfresh; or, if it be thought necessary to let them hang for afew days, at least they should not be allowed to get high, moreparticularly the aquatic ones, because gaminess is, if anything,deleterious to the flavour of their flesh.

— PHEASANT (FAISAN)

When this bird is young, its legs are grey and the ventralend of the sternum is tender and flexible. But with pheasants,as with partridges, an infallible sign of youth may be discoveredat the extremity of the last large feather in the wing. If thisfeather be pointed, the bird is young; if it be round, the reverseis the case.

— FAISAN à la MODE D’ALCANTARA

This recipe comes from the famous Alcantara convent. His-tory tells us that at the beginning of the Portuguese campaignin 1807 the convent’s library was pillaged by Junot’s soldiers,and its precious manuscripts were used in the making of cart-ridges.

Now it happened that an officer of the commissariat whowas witnessing the event found, among a collection of recipesselected by the monks, the particular one now under our notice,which was applied only to partridges.

It struck him as interesting, and after trying it when he re-turned to France in the following year, he surrendered it tothe Duchess of Abrant&s, who noted it in her memoirs.

It represents, perhaps, the only good thing the Frenchderived from that unfortunate campaign, and it would tend toprove that foie gras and truffles, which had been known forso long in Languedoc and Gascony, were also known in Estre-madura, where, even at the present day, tolerably good trufflesare to be found.

The procedure is as follows :—

Empty the pheasant from the front; bone its breast, and stuffit with fine ducks’ foies gras, mixed with quartered truffles,cooked in port wine.

Marinade the pheasant for three days in port wine, takingcare that it be well covered therewith. This done, cook it “encasserole” (the original recipe says on the spit, but the sauce-pan is more suitable). Reduce the port wine of the marinade;add to it a dozen medium-sized truffles; set the pheasant onthese truffles, and heat for a further ten minutes.

GAME

581

N.B.—This last part of the recipe may be advantageouslyreplaced by the la Souvaroff” treatment—that is to say,having placed the pheasant and the truffles in a terrine, sprinklethem with the reduced port combined with slightly butteredgame glaze; then hermetically seal down the lid of the terrine,and complete the cooking in the oven.

—FAISAN à l’ANGOUMOISE

Stuff the pheasant with a preparation consisting of two-thirds lb. of very fresh pork fat, rubbed through a sieve; fouroz. of raw, peeled, and quartered truffles, and four oz. of finechestnuts, cooked in consomm£.

This preparation, which should be seasoned as for theordinary truffling (No. 1956), ought to be quite cold wheninserted into the pheasant.

Wrap the bird in slices of bacon; roast it gently for three-quarters of an hour, and take care to remove the slices of baconseven or eight minutes before the cooking is completed, thatthe outside of the piece may be coloured.

Set on a long dish, and serve a P^rigueux sauce at the sametime.

—FAISAN à la BOHEMIENNE

Season a small foie gras with salt and paprika; stud it withraw quartered truffles, and poach it in Madeira for twentyminutes.

When it is cold, insert it into the pheasant, which shouldbe high. Truss the bird, and cook it in butter in a sauce-pan or a cocotte for forty-five minutes. When about to serve,remove some of the butter used in cooking; sprinkle thepheasant with a glassful of burnt brandy, and add a few table-spoonfuls of reduced game gravy to the cooking-liquor.

Serve the pheasant in its cooking utensil.

—FAISAN EN CASSEROLE

Truss the pheasant as for an entr4e, and poele it in butteronly. This done, swill the saucepan with a few drops of brandyand a tablespoonful of game gravy.

Cover the utensil, and serve the dish burning hot.

—FAISAN EN COCOTTE

Proceed exactly as for pheasant “en casserole,” and, whenthe cooking is two-thirds done, surround it with a garnish ofsmall onions cooked in butter; small, cooked mushroom-headsand olive-shaped truffles, the latter taking the place of the

582

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

potatoes, which are one of the garnishing ingredients of fowls“en cocotte.”

— FAISAN EN CHARTREUSE

Parboil a fine, round-headed, quartered cabbage, and braiseit as directed under No. 2100, adding thereto an old, oven-browned pheasant.

The chartreuse may be made with the pheasant kept wholeor cut into pieces, but in any case, roasted or poeled, it shouldbe very tender and only just cooked. The old pheasant put inwith the cabbage only serves in imparting its flavour to thelatter, but it must not and cannot be used for the chartreuse.

If the chartreuse be made with a cut-up pheasant, proceedas in the case of No. 1778. If whole, line an oval mouldchartreuse-fashion; coat the inside with a portion of the braisedcabbage, which should be slightly pressed; set the pheasant,breast undermost, in the mould; cover it with what remainsof the cabbage, and then turn it out on a dish.

Send a sauceboat of excellent half-glaze, flavoured withpheasant fumet, separately.

— FAISAN à la CHOCCROUTE

Prepare the sauerkraut after No. 2097, and bear in mindthat when it is specially prepared to accompany a pheasant, itis considerably improved by being braised with foie-gras fat.

Poele a very tender pheasant, and only just cook it. Laythe well-drained sauerkraut on a long dish; set the pheasantupon it, and surround it with a border consisting of rectanglesof bacon, cooked in the sauerkraut.

Serve separately the poeling-liquor combined with a littlegame fumet, strained, and kept somewhat greasy.

— FAISAN à la CREME

Cook the pheasant in butter, in a saucepan, with a medium-sized, quartered onion. When the cooking is three-parts done,sprinkle the bird with one-quarter pint of cream (sour if pos-sible), or with ordinary cream, acidulated by means of a fewdrops of lemon juice.

Finish the cooking, basting the piece the while with creamand serve in the saucepan.

— FAISAN DEMIDOFF

Proceed exactly as directed under “Poulet h la Demidoff”(No. 1464).

GAME 583

—FAISAN à la GEORGIENNE

Truss the pheasant as for an entree, and put it into a sauce-pan with thirty fresh, halved, and well-peeled walnuts; the juiceof two lbs. of grapes and of four oranges, pressed on a sieve;a wineglassful of Malmsey wine; a glassful of strong, greentea; one and one-half oz. of butter, and the necessary seasoning.

Poach the pheasant in this preparation for about thirtyminutes, and colour it when it is almost cooked.

When about to serve, dish it and surround it with freshwalnuts.

Strain the cooking-liquor through a napkin; add theretoone-third pint of game Espagnole, and reduce to half.

Slightly coat the pheasant and its garnish with the sauce,and serve what remains of the latter separately.

—FAISAN GRILLE DIABLE

For this preparation only young pheasants are used;although, provided they be tender, adult pheasants will answerthe purpose. The procedure is precisely the same as that de-scribed under “Poulet Grille” (No. 1636).

—FAISAN KOTSCHOUBEY

Cook the pheasant “en casserole,” and add to it, when itis almost done, two oz. of fine, raw truffle slices, and a littleexcellent game glaze, clear and well buttered.

Serve the following garnish separately :—Fry in butter fouroz. of blanched, fresh breast of bacon, cut into dice. Whenthe pieces are properly frizzled, add to them one lb. of freshly-cooked, well-drained, uncooled, and roughly-chopped Brusselssprouts. Add two oz. of fresh butter, a little pepper and gratednutmeg, and stew gently for one-half hour, that the garnish mayjust be ready in time for dishing.

—FAISAN à la NORMANDE

Colour the pheasant in butter.

Meanwhile quarter, peel, mince, and slightly toss in buttersix medium-sized apples.

Garnish the bottom of a terrine with a layer of these apples;set the browned pheasant thereon; surround it with whatremains of the apples; sprinkle it with a few tablespoonfulsof fresh cream; cover the terrine, and cook in the oven for fromtwenty to twenty-eight minutes.

Serve the preparation in the terrine,

— FAISAN à la PERIGUEUX

Stuff the pheasant with truffles, proceeding as for ordinarytruffling (No. 1956). Poele it in Madeira; dish, and surroundit with a border of quenelles consisting of truffled game force-meat, moulded by means of a coffeespoon, and poached at thelast moment.

Serve separately a P^rigueux sauce combined with thereduced poeling-liquor, cleared of all grease.

— FAISAN à la REGENCE

Poele the pheasant, and dish it on a low crodton, carvedfrom a sandwich-loaf and fried in butter.

Surround it with small, decorated, round game quenelles;large, grooved, cooked mushrooms; and cocks’ kidneys; allthree arranged alternately.

Serve separately a Salmis sauce, flavoured with truffleessence, and combined with the strained and reduced poeling-liquor, cleared of all grease.

— FAISAN à la SAINTE-ALLIANCE

Bone two woodcocks, and put their livers and intestinesaside.

Chop up their meat, together with a quarter of its weightof poached and cooled beef-marrow, and as much fresh, fatbacon; salt, pepper, and herbs. Add to this hash six oz. ofraw, peeled, and quartered truffles, slightly cooked in butter.

Stuff the pheasant with this preparation; truss it; wrap itin slices of bacon, and keep it in the cool for twenty-four hours,that the aroma of the truffles may be concentrated.

Roast the pheasant on the spit, or, if in the oven, set it ona somewhat high stand in a baking-pan. Cut a large croutonfrom a sandwich-loaf, and fry it in clarified butter.

Pound the woodcocks’ livers and intestines with an equalweight of grated fresh fat bacon, the well-washed fillets ofan anchovy, one oz. of butter, and one-half oz. of raw truffle.When this forcemeat is very smooth and all its ingredientsthoroughly mixed, spread it over the fried croutons.

When the pheasant is two-thirds cooked, set this coatedcrodton under the bird in such wise as to allow the juices escap-ing from the latter to drop upon the crouton. Complete thecooking, and dish the pheasant on the crodton. Surround withslices of bitter orange, and send the gravy separately.

When serving, accompany each piece of pheasant with aslice of orange and a small slice of the coated crouton.

GAME

585

—FAISAN SOUVAROFF

Cook six fair-sized truffles for five minutes in a glassful ofMadeira and an equal quantity of light meat glaze. Withdrawthe truffles and put them in the terrine in which the pheasantwill complete its cooking.

Cut one-half lb. of foie gras into large dice; stiffen thesein the truffles’ cooking-liquor, and stuff the pheasant therewith.Truss the latter; wrap it in slices of bacon, and two-thirdspoele it.

This done, put it into the terrine containing the truffles; addthe poeling-liquor, a small glassful of Madeira, and the samequantity of game gravy; hermetically close the terrine, andcontinue cooking for about a quarter of an hour.

Serve the preparation as it stands.

—SUPREMES, C6TELETTES ET FILETS de FAISAN

Pheasant Supremes, Cutlets and Fillets, allow of the samegarnishes as those of fowl. But, whereas in the case of thelatter, they are raised raw, and then poached, my advice inregard to pheasant is, that it should be previously roasted orpoeled, (keeping it just underdone) and that the supremes beonly raised at the last moment.

By this means, a much better result is obtained than bythe poaching of raw fillets; which, once cooked, are gene-rally dry if they have to wait but a few seconds.

I also advise, when the garnish consists only of foie-grascollops and truffles (as in the case of the Rossini garnish), thesending separately of a small timbale of noodles with cream.

—SALMIS de FAISAN

Salmis is perhaps the most delicate and most perfect ofthe game preparations bequeathed to us by old-fashionedcookery. If it be less highly esteemed nowadays, it is owingto the fact that this recipe has been literally spoiled by thehaphazard fashion in which it has been applied right and leftto game already cooked, and cooked again for the purpose.

But the Salmis given above may always be included in anymenu, however sumptuous. It is applied more particularly togame of the 1st and 2nd classes, which should be somewhathigh when treated.

The recipe I give may be applied to all the birds in the twoclasses referred to.

Roast the pheasant, keeping it moderately underdone.Quickly cut it into eight pieces, thus: two legs, two wings(separated from the pinions), and the breast cut into four length-

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

586

wise. Skin the pieces; trim them neatly, and keep them at atemperate heat in a covered vegetable-pan, with a few drops ofburnt brandy and a little clear melted meat glaze.

Pound the carcass and the trimmings, and add to them halfa bottleful of red wine (almost entirely reduced), three choppedshallots and a few mignonette pepper. Add one-quarter pintof good game Espagnole sauce; cook for ten minutes; rubthrough a sieve, pressing well the while, and then strain througha strainer.

Reduce this sauce to about one-third, and despumate it;strain it once more through a close strainer; add a small quan-tity of butter, and pour it over the pieces of pheasant, to whichadd a fine, sliced truffle and six grooved mushroom-heads.

I advise the discarding of the old method of dishing upona cushion of bread fried in butter, as also of the triangularcroutons fried in butter and coated with gratin forcemeat, whichusually accompanied the Salmis.

A speedy preparation and a simple method of dishing, whichfacilitate the service and allow of the Salmis being eaten hot,are the only necessary conditions. Moreover, the goodness ofthe preparation is such as to be independent of a fantasticmethod of dishing.

— SAUTE de FAISAN

Unless it be prepared with the greatest care, sauted pheasantis always dry. I therefore do not recommend it; but, shouldit be necessary to make a dish of it, care should be observed inselecting a young, plump bird. It should be cut up like afowl, cooked in butter on a moderate fire and kept somewhatunderdone.

Dish it after the manner of a “poulet sauffl , v and cover it.Swill the saufflpan and prepare a sauce after the recipe incommon use.

This sauce must always be short, and it should be pouredover the pheasant just before serving it.

— PATE CHAUD de FAISAN

The preparation of hot, raised pheasant pies is the same asusual; the ingredients alone changing. The reader will, there-fore, kindly refer to “Pat6 chaud de Canard” (No. 1752), andduly note the following modifications: —

(1) Use a gratin forcemeat (No. 202) prepared from gamelivers and meat.

(2) Roast the pheasant, keeping it underdone, and mix thepieces of cooked mushroom with the sliced truffles.

(3) Accompany the pie by a Salmis sauce, prepared fromthe pheasant’s carcass and remains.

—MOUSSES ET MOUSSELINES de FAISAN

As already stated in various parts of this work, the con-stituents and their quantities are the same for mousses andmousselines, and but for the basic ingredient, which is pheasantin this case, the procedure does not differ from that alreadydescribed.

The base of the sauces served with these mousses and mous-selines is a fumet made from the carcasses and remains.

—SOUFFLE de FAISAN

Prepare a very light, mousseline forcemeat of pheasant.

Set in a buttered souffle saucepan, and cook in a moderateoven.

Send a fine, half-glaze sauce, flavoured with game essence,at the same time.

Cold Pheasant

—FAISAN à la BOH^MIENNE

Proceed as for “Faisan k la Boh^mienne” hot (No. 1831).Cook it in an earthenware terrine, and add thereto, at the sametime as the prescribed brandy, enough succulent, savoury jellyto fill up the terrine.

Leave to cool for a day or two, and, when about to serve,remove the grease that has settled on the surface, by means ofa spoon. Remove the last vestiges of grease by repeatedscaldings; carefully wipe the terrine, and serve it incrusted in ablock of ice.

—CHAUD = FROID de FAISAN

Proceed exactly as for “Chaud-froid de Volaille” (No. 1689),and use a brown chaud-froid sauce, flavoured with pheasantfumet.

In regard to the decoration, dishing, &c., follow the recipealready referred to.

—CHAUD-FROID de FAISAN à la BULOZ

Poele a pheasant, keeping it underdone; raise its supremes,and cut these into thin collops.

With a fumet prepared from the carcass and the poeling-liquor, prepare a brown chaud-froid sauce. Coat the collopswith this sauce, and also coat ten cooked and grooved mush-rooms with a white chaud-froid sauce.

588

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Clothe a dome-mould with clear aspic jelly, and deck it withtruffles.

Set the collops of pheasant and the chaud-froid-coated truf-fles inside, alternating the two in so doing; fill up the mouldwith the same jelly, and let it set on ice. When about to serve,turn out after the manner of an aspic, on a low cushion ofrice or semolina, lying on a round dish.

Border with neatly-cut croutons of very clear aspic.

,855—FAI5AN à la CROIX de BERNY

Roast the pheasant and keep it underdone. When it isquite cold, raise its fillets and leave the legs and the wingsattached to the carcass.

By means of scissors, completely bone the carcass; garnishits inside with a truffled foie-gras Parfait, and cover it with athin coat of foie-gras Mousse.

Replace the fillets upon this Mousse, after having slicedthem, and fill any gaps that may exist between the slices withsome of the same Mousse: thus reconstructing the bird.

Let the Mousse set thoroughly, and glaze with aspic jelly.Meanwhile, coat eight boned, stuffed, poached and cold larkswith brown chaud-froid sauce. Decorate them with pieces oftruffle and salted tongue, and glaze them with aspic jelly

Dish the pheasant on a low cushion; surround it with thelarks, and garnish the gaps between the latter with choppedand very clear aspic.

—FAISAN EN DAUBE

Proceed as for “Terrine de Poularde k la gel£e” (No. 1701),making due allowance, in the cooking, for the differencebetween the sizes of the two birds.

, 857—COTELETTES de FAISAN

Proceed as for “Cotelettes froides de Volaille.”

— GALANTINE de FAISAN

See “Galantine de Volaille” (No. 1708).

— MOUSSE de FAISAN

Prepare the Mousse according to the usual procedure, andmould it after the manner of “Mousse de Volaille” (No. 1711).

— PAIN de FAISAN EN BELLE-VUE

The procedure follows that of No. 1709, but for the differencein the basic ingredient, which in this case is pheasant.

GAME 589

—suprPmes de FA 15an chatelaine

Raise the supremes and prepare them exactly like thesupremes of fowl in “Chaud-froid F^lix Faure” (No. 1691).Poach them; cool them, and cut them into medallions asexplained.

Cover half of these medallions with chicken Mousse, and theother half with pheasant Mousse. Keep on ice for some timethat the Mousse may set. This done, coat the first lot withbrown chaud-froid sauce and the second lot with white chaud-froid sauce. Deck each medallion with small pieces of truffle.Set them in a deep, square dish (alternating the two colours),and cover with very clear, succulent aspic jelly. Leave to setand serve on a block of ice.

—SUPREMES de FAISAN GASTRONOME

Poele the pheasant in Madeira and let it cool. Raise thefillets; cut them into thin, regular slices; coat them with brownchaud-froid sauce, and decorate according to fancy. With thetrimmings and the meat of the legs, prepare a pheasant Mousseafter the manner described under No. 1711, and mould it in aParfait mould which should have the depth of the chaud-froid-coated slices.

When this Mousse has set, turn it out on a dish and placethe slices all round, standing them upright and letting themlean one against the other.

Surround with a crown of fine, fair-sized, peeled truffles,cooked in Champagne, and set one of them on the top of theMousse, fixing it there by means of a hatelet.

Border the dish with fine croutons of aspic.

—TERRINE de FAISAN

Prepare it after the manner of the “Terrine de Li£vre” (No.1825), and take care to make due allowance, in the cooking, forthe difference, in the matter of tenderness, between the twomeats. But the explanations already given on this subjectought to suffice for ascertaining whether or not the patty havecooked sufficiently.

PARTRIDGE (PERDRIX ET PERDREAUX)

Three kinds of partridges are used in Cookery :—the GreyPartridge, which is commonest in flat country, and which isalso the most highly esteemed; the Red Partridge, which is to befound in hilly and wooded country; and the Bartavelle (perdixvertevella), which is a somewhat larger species than the twoformer. To these three kinds may be added the American

59o

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

Colin (Ortix Virginianus), an excellent bird sometimes seen inEnglish markets.

All the recipes given for pheasants may be applied to par-tridge, and below, I shall only give those which are proper tothe latter.

— PERDREAU à la BOURGUIGNONNE

Truss the partridge as for an entree; three-parts poele it, andplace it in a terrine with six small glazed onions and as manysmall, cooked mushroom heads. Swill the saucepan with aglassful of red wine; reduce it two-thirds, and add a table-spoonful of game half-glaze. Strain; clear of grease; pour thissauce over the partridge, and complete the latter’s cooking forseven or eight minutes.

— PERDREAU EN DEMNDEUIL

Bone the breast and fill the partridge with truffled partridgeforcemeat, prepared with panada or butter. Between the skinand the fillets, slip a few slices of very black truffle; truss asfor an entree; wrap the piece in muslin, and poach it for thirtyminutes in a game fumet.

When about to serve, remove the muslin; take the stringoff, and dish the partridge. Reduce the fumet in which thepartridge has poached; strain it; add thereto a liqueur-glassfulof burnt liqueur-brandy, and send this reduced fumet sepa-rately.

— PERDREAU EN ESTOUFFADE

Brown the partridge in the oven and set in a terrine justlarge enough to hold it, with a tablespoonful of Matignon (No.227) and one crushed juniper berry, on top and beneath.

Add one-half oz. of butter, a liqueur-glassful of burntbrandy, and twice that amount of game fumet. Close theterrine; seal down the lid with a strip of paste; bake in a hotoven for twenty-five minutes and serve the dish as it stands.

— PERDREAU à la LAUTREC

Select a young partridge; open its back; slightly flatten itwith a butcher’s beater; pierce it through with a skewer; seasonit with salt, pepper and melted butter, and gently grill.

At the same time grill six small mushroom-heads.

Dish the partridge; on either side of it set the mushrooms,each of which should be garnished with a coffeespoonful ofMaitre-d’hotel butter; surround the mushrooms with a thread ofmelted meat glaze and sprinkle the partridge with a few dropsof lemon juice.

59i

—PERDREAU LADY CLIFFORD

Cook the partridge in butter in a saucepan. When it isthree-parts done, surround it with two oz. of fine slices ofraw truffle; add a liqueur-glassful of burnt brandy and onetablespoonful of clear melted meat glaze.

Serve a Soubise sauce at the same time and separately.

—PERDREAU aux CHOUX

Prepare a garnish of braised cabbages as explained under No.2100, and add thereto an old partridge, browned in the ovenor on the spit. Meanwhile, roast or poele a very tender youngpartridge and keep it underdone.

Dish the cabbages, which should be well drained; set theyoung partridge upon them, and surround with small rectanglesof very lean bacon, cooked with the cabbages, and a thread ofhalf-glaze sauce, flavoured with game jumet.

N.B.—This dish may be given a more decorative appearanceby means of a sort of Chartreuse, which is prepared as fol-lows:—Line a large bowl or a buttered, round-bottomed tim-bale with roundels of sausages; roundels of carrots arranged insuperposed rows, separated by a line of French beans or peas;and small rectangles of bacon, laid side by side.

Line the inside of the timbale with a thick layer of cab-bages, and put the young partridge, breast undermost, in themiddle (the partridge may also be carved up). Cover the cab-bages and press the latter with a fork; turn the timbale out on adish and tilt the latter that all the grease may fall before with-drawing the timbale, which answers the purpose of a mould.

Surround w’ith a thread of half-glaze sauce, flavoured withgame fumet.

—CREPINETTES de PERDREAUX

After substituting the meat of a young partridge, cleared ofall tendons, for the veal sweetbreads, and fresh bacon for calf’sudder, proceed exactly as directed (as regards quantities andother particulars) under “Cr^pinettes de ris de Veau” (No.1222), taking care to add three oz. of chopped truffles per lb.of the forcemeat.

Divide up the forcemeat into portions one and one-half oz.to two oz. in weight; wrap them in pig’s caul; roll them firstin melted butter and then in bread-crumbs, and grill themgently.

The usual accompaniment to these cr^pinettes is a lightchestnut or lentil puree.

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

592

— EPIGRAMMES de PERDREAU

Raise the young partridge’s fillets, leaving the wing-boneattached to the carcass, and put them aside. From the minionfillets and the meat of the legs, prepare a mousseline forcemeat;mould the latter in very small buttered cutlet moulds, and set topoach.

Roll the fillets in melted butter and bread-crumbs, and grillthem gently. Dip the cutlets in beaten egg; roll them in finely-chopped truffles; press upon the latter with the flat of a knife,that they may combine with the egg; adjust the shape of thecutlets, and toss them in butter.

Dish in the form of a circle, alternating the fillets and thecutlets; pour in their midst a cullis prepared from the par-tridge’s carcasses, and serve a chestnut pur£e separately.

— TIMBALE de PERDREAU DIANE

Line a liberally-buttered, shallow mould with crescents oftruffle arranged in superposed rows, and then completely coverthe bottom and sides of the mould with a layer, two-thirds in.thick, of raw partridge forcemeat.

Place the mould in the front of the oven that the forcemeatmay be poached; and then spread another layer of gratin force-meat of game.

Fill the utensil with a garnish of small quenelles consistingof truffled partridge forcemeat, mushrooms and slices of truf-fles, cohered with a reduced Madeira sauce. Cover the garnishwith a small coat of forcemeat, and poach in the bain-mariefor from thirty to thirty-five minutes.

When about to serve, turn out on a dish, and deck the tim-bale with a crown of partridges’ supremes, raised from birdsfresh from the spit or the oven. Surround the base of thetimbale with a thread of Diane sauce, and send a sauceboat ofthe latter separately.

— PERDREAUX FROIDS

The various recipes given for cold pheasant also suit coldpartridge; it is only necessary therefore to replace the word“pheasant” by “partridge” in the formulae referred to.

— WOODCOCK and SNIPE(BECASSEET BECASSINES)

If grouse, which can only be thoroughly appreciated inits native country, wyere extinct, woodcock would be the leadingfeathered game. But the latter have this advantage over theformer, namely: that their fumet is not so fugitive, and thatthey may be kept much longer. Woodcock does not yield itsfull quality unless it be moderately high.

593

—BECASSE de CAREME

Sprinkle the woodcock with a few drops of oil, and roastit, keeping it underdone. As soon as it is cooked, divide itinto two lengthwise, and cut each half of the breast into twocollops. Mix half a coffeespoonful of French mustard in asmall vegetable-pan, with a few drops of lemon juice. Roll thepieces of woodcock in this mustard, and keep them hot.

Chop up the carcass and the intestines; sprinkle with aglassful of burnt liqueur brandy; reduce; add a tablespoonfulof game fumet, and cook for five minutes.

Strain through a strainer, pressing on the pieces of wood-cock in so doing, and rock the saucepan, that the pieces maybe coated with the cullis. Dish in a hot timbale, and, uponthe pieces, set the woodcock’s head.

N.B.—Becasse a la fine Champagne is prepared in the sameway, but without mustard. Cut it into six pieces: wings, legsand two halves of the breast, and put these pieces into a roundcocotte. Swill the saucepan with burnt liqueur brandy; add thechopped intestines, mixed with the juices of the pressed carcass;add a tablespoonful of fumet, a little lemon juice, and a littlecayenne, and pour this cullis (heated but not boiled) over thepieces.

Becasse a la Riche is prepared in the same way, but:—(1)the pieces are dished on a crouton of fried bread, coated withgratin forcemeat of game; (2) the sauce is thickened with alittle foie-gras pur£e and one oz. of butter, and then strainedover the pieces through a coarse strainer, during which processthe operator should press with a spoon or a whisk.

—BECASSE à la FAVART

Proceed as for “Caneton rouennais Souffle” (No. 1764),and remember to add the woodcock’s intestines to the force-meat.

When the carcass is garnished, set the sliced supremes onthe forcemeat, with a row of sliced truffles in the middle. Theforcemeat should poach for about twenty minutes.

Serve at the same time a half-glaze sauce, flavoured withwoodcock fumet.

—SALMIS de BECASSE

Under the article “Pheasant,” I gave the generic recipe forSalmis, which may be applied to all feathered game. In regardto the Woodcock Salmis, the operator should remember to addthe bird’s intestines to the sauce, and to keep the meat ratherunder- than overdone.

Q Q

594

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— BECASSE SOUVAROFF

Proceed exactly as for “Faisan k la Souvaroff” (No. 1845),after making due allowance for the size of the bird in regardto the quantity of truffles and foie gras.

— MOUSSES ET MOUSSELINES de BECASSE

Proceed as indicated in No. 1850.

— TIMBALE de BECASSE.METTERNICH

Prepare a somewhat shallow, decorated timbale crust.

Roast the woodcocks and keep them underdone.

Raise the supremes and put them in the timbale, separatingthem by collops of fresh foie gras, sauted at the last moment.

Pound the remains of the woodcocks, including their car-casses; thin the purée with truffle essence; rub it through asieve, pressing heavily the while, and then rub it throughtammy.

Heat the cullis thus obtained, without letting it boil; finishit with a little lemon juice, liqueur-brandy and butter, and pourit into the timbale over the pieces of woodcock and the foie grascollops.

Dish the timbale on a folded napkin, lying on a round dish.

— TIMBALE de BECASSE NESSELRODE

Poele the wroodcocks and keep them underdone.

As soon as they are cooked, raise their fillets and put theseaside.

Bone the remains, and pound the meat thus obtained, to-gether with a quarter of its weight of raw foie gras.

Rub through a sieve, and add an equal weight of gameforcemeat, prepared with panada and butter. Add the choppedcarcasses and a glassful of liqueur brandy to the poeling-liquor;cook for a few minutes; strain, and in this stock poach five oz.of olive-shaped truffles (for an ordinary timbale).

Line a buttered Charlotte-mould with short paste; cover itsbottom and sides with the prepared forcemeat, and against thisforcemeat set the woodcock’s supremes, cut into collops.Garnish the centre with the truffles, and cover these with a fewtablespoonfuls of Espagnole, reduced with some of the fumet.Close the timbale with a layer of paste, as explained in thevarious preceding timbale recipes, and bake in a good, moderateoven for about forty-five minutes.

When about to serve, turn out the timbale on a dish; pourinto the former some half-glaze sauce combined with whatremains of the fumet, and send a sauceboat of the same sauceseparately.

595

N.B.—This “Timbale Nesselrode'’ may be prepared afterthe same recipe, from Pheasant, Partridge, Woodcock or Hazel-Hen, but the name of the selected bird should, of course, appearon the menu.

—BECASSES ET BECASSINES FROIDES

All the recipes given for cold pheasant and partridge may beapplied to woodcocks and snipes.

—QUAILS

Quails should always be chosen plump, and their fat shouldbe white and very firm. Besides the spit, which should alwaysbe used in preference to the oven for roasting, they allow oftwo other methods of cooking: they may be cooked in butter,in a saucepan; or they may be poached in excellent strong andgelatinous veal stock.

This last mode of procedure greatly enhances the quail’squality and is frequently used.

—CAILLES EN CASSEROLE

Cook them in butter, in the saucepan in which they will beserved.

Swill with a few drops of brandy; add a little game fumet;cover, and serve very hot.

—CAILLES aux CERISES

For four quails :—Truss them as for an entree and cook themwith butter in a saucepan. Swill with a little brandy and aglass of port, in which a piece of orange rind should havesoaked.

Add three tablespoonfuls of excellent veal stock, three table-spoonfuls of red-currant jelly and about forty cherries, pre-viously poached in a boiling syrup of about 180 (Saccharometer)and cooled in the syrup.

Drain them before adding them to the quail, and, if thesauce be too insipid, sharpen it with a few drops of lemon juice.

—CAILLES à la DAUPHINE

Wrap each quail in a buttered vine-leaf and a thin, squareslice of bacon, and roast them for ten minutes.

Meanwhile, prepare a well-seasoned purée of fresh peas withlettuce, and reduce it to a somewhat stiff consistence.

Line the bottom and sides of a deep dish with very thinslices of ham; pour the puree into it; smooth the surface, andhalf-plunge the quails into this puree.

Place in the oven for ten minutes, and this done, send thedish to the table immediately.

Q Q 2

— CAILLES FIGARO

Insert a piece of truffle into each quail, and wrap them eachin a piece of gut together with a bit of pale veal glaze, thesize of a pigeon’s egg. String the pieces of gut at two pointsone in. from either extremity of the quails, that the envelopemay not burst while cooking. Poach the quails in good vealstock, that they may not be washed as they would be if thegut happened to burst in a poaching-liquor consisting of saltedwater.

Serve the quails as they leave their cooking-liquor.

— CAILLES à la GRECQUE

Cook the quails in a saucepan, and set them in a timbale,half-garnished with “Riz h la Grecque.” Swill the saucepanwith a few tablespoonfuls of game fumct, and pour this swilling-liquor over the quails, without clearing it of grease.

— CAILLES JULIETTE

Divide the quails into two along the back and do not separatethe two halves; season them; sprinkle them with melted butterand finely-chopped truffle. Wrap each quail in a piece of pig’scaul; sprinkle again with melted butter and fine raspings, andgrill gently.

Dish the quails and sprinkle them with a few drops of ver-juice.

— CAILLES JUDIC

Poele the quails.

Dish them in the form of a crown, each on a small, braisedlettuce, with a cock’s kidney on either side and a truffle ontop. Coat with a half-glaze sauce prepared with quail fumet.

— CAILLES LUCULLUS

Cook the quails in butter. Dish them in a circle on around dish, each on an oval or rectangular fried crouton, andbetween each set a fine truffle cooked in Champagne and chickenglaze.

— CAILLES à la NORMANDE

Peel, mince and toss some apples in butter, as explainedunder “Faisan k la Normande.” Allow half an apple per quail.Garnish the bottom of a cocotte with some of these apples; uponthem set the quails, browned in butter; add what remains ofthe apples; sprinkle with a few tablespoonfuls of cream, andcomplete the cooking in the oven.

597

—CAILLES aux PETITS POIS à la ROMAINE

Cook the quails in butter. At the same time, fry in butterone small new onion and two-thirds oz. of raw, chopped ham,for each quail. Add some peas, shelled at the last moment, andcook without any moistening whatsoever.

The moisture contained in the ham and peas is sufficient forthe cooking. The peas should be ready simultaneously withthe quails.

Serve the quails and the peas separately, in little, closed tim-bales. The diner mixes them.

—CAILLES aux RAISINS

Cook the quails in butter. Swill the utensil with a few dropsof dry, white wine and a little verjuice; add half a tablespoonfulof strong game fumet for each quail; and dish in a very hotcocotte with about one oz. of fresh peeled grapes for each quail.

—CAILLES RICHELIEU

Select some fresh and plump quails; remove their gizzards;season them inside with a grain of salt and a few drops ofbrandy; insert a piece of raw truffle into each bird, and trussthem as for an entrde. Set them in a sautepan, snugly pressedone against the other, and season them with salt. Cover themwith a coarse julienne of carrots, onions and celery, cooked inbutter, and prepared as far as possible from new vegetables.

Moisten, just enough to cover, with some succulent amber-coloured veal stock, gelatinous and fine; cover, boil, and thenpoach gently for twelve minutes.

This done, add a julienne of truffles (raw if possible) whichshould equal only half of the vegetable julienne, and poach fora further two minutes, that the truffles may cook and the quailsbe done.

Dish in a timbale, clear of grease, and pour the cooking-liquor and the julienne over the quails.

Pilaff rice is often served with quails prepared in this way.

—RIZOTTO de CAILLES

Into each quail insert a piece of fresh, pounded pork fat,the size of a hazel nut, combined with an equal quantity ofwhite truffle; and cook them in a saucepan with butter.

Add their fat to a previously-prepared Rizotto. Dish thisrizotto in a timbale, and hollow it out so as to make a nest forthe quails.

Sprinkle the latter with the saucepan-swillings, consistingof game fumet; and send the dish to the table at once.

598 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— CAILLES SOUS LA CENDRE

Stuff the quails with a little smooth truffled game force-meat, and wrap them each in a buttered vine-leaf, followedby a slice of bacon, and finally by two sheets of buttered paper.

Place them on the hearth-stone; cover them with very hotcinders, and cook thus for thirty-five minutes, taking care torenew the hot cinders from time to time.

When about to serve them, remove the outside covering ofpaper which is charred, but leave the other coverings.

N.B.—A log fire is essential for this recipe.

— CAILLES SOUVAROFF

Prepare these as described under “Faisan & la Souvaroff”(No. 1845).

— CAILLES à la TURQUE

Truss the quails as for an entree; brown them in butter, andcomplete their cooking in pilaff rice, combined with a quarterof its weight of cooked and chopped egg-plant pulp.

Set the rice in a pyramid on a dish; place the quails allround (upright against the rice), and surround with a thread ofquail fumet.

,900—TIMBALE de CAILLES ALEXANDRA

Coat a well-buttered timbale mould with patty paste, andline it with slices of bacon so as to completely cover the paste.The slices of bacon in this case are there to prevent the mois-tening of the timbale from reaching the paste. Insert a pieceof foie gras into each quail; stiffen them in butter, and setthem against the sides of the timbale in successive tiers.

Completely garnish the middle with small, peeled truffles;add one-quarter pint of excellent stock with Madeira (per sixquails), and a few bits of bay-leaf. Close the timbale witha layer of paste and cook in a moderately hot oven for one andone-quarter hours.

Turn out upon withdrawing from the oven, and serve thedish as it stands.

N.B.—(1) The shell of paste merely serves to hold in thequails and their garnish, and ought not to be eaten

(2) The same timbale may be prepared with ortolans, except•ifiat these need only forty-five minutes’ cooking.

599

Cold Quails

—CHAUD-FROID de CAILLES EN BELLE-VUE

The quails should be boned for a chaud-froid, and stuffed withgratin forcemeat of game with a rod of foie gras and anotherof truffle set in the middle. This done, reshape them; wrapthem each in a square of muslin; poach them for twentyminutes in an excellent veal stock, and let them cool therein.

When they are quite cold, dry them; and dip them, so as toveneer them all over, in a good brown chaud-froid sauce (No.34), prepared with quail fumet. Decorate the breast of eachquail elegantly with bits of truffle and poached white of egg;sprinkle with cold melted savoury jelly, so as to fix the decora-tion; and leave to set.

Remove the excess of sauce from around the quails; setthem in a square, deep dish; cover them with very good limpidsavoury jelly, and place them in a refrigerator until they arerequired.

—CAILLES EN CAISSES

Prepare the quails as for a chaud-froid, as above; but seteach in an oval, pleated case of delicate porcelain or paper.Border with a thin thread of chopped jelly, and on each quailset a head, the eyes of which may be imitated by means of aring of white of egg and a central spot of truffle.

—CAILLES GLACEES au GRANITE

I shall only give a few recipes of this class; for the series isa long one, and I recommend them more particularly on accountof their quaintness. These dishes, wherein a sugary and glazedpreparation is introduced, are highly esteemed in summer; butthey really belong to the culinary repertory of hot countries.

—CAILLES GLACfiES CERISETTE. Prepare the quailsas for an entree and poach them for 12 minutes in a strong vealstock, with Champagne. This done, put them each into a small,oval mould; fill up these moulds with cooking-liquor, cleared of allgrease and strained, and leave them to set on ice.

This preliminary procedure applies to all quail dishes in thisseries.

Now prepare a Granitd with cherry juice (see No. 2930).

Set this Granit6 in a pyramid on a dish incrusted in ice. Turnout the quails and place them round the Granite; fill up thegaps between them with small heaps of stoned cherries, poachedin syrup for a few minutes and quite cold.

6oo

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

*905—CAILLES GLACEES CARMEN. Prepare the quails asabove, and place them round a rock of Granite made frompomegranates.

— CAILLES GLACEES MARYLAND. Set them round

a rock of Granite made with pineapple.

— CAILLES GLACEES REINE AMELIE. Prepare thequails in the usual way, and lay them round a rock of Graniteprepared with tomatoes.

— CAILLES GLACEES au ROMANEE. Poach the quailsin stock combined with Romance wine, and set them round a rockof Granite made with verjuice.

— FILETS de CAILLES aux POMMES D’or. Raisethe quails’ suprimes, after having poached and cooled them. Setthese supremes in the rinds of small oranges or tangerines, and fillup the rinds with jelly prepared with Port. When about to serve,deck each orange or tangerine, by means of the piping-bag, witha small ornament of Granite, prepared with the juice of thefruit used.

— CAILLES CECILIA

Roast the quails, keeping them juicy, and leave them to cool.

This done, raise their fillets and skin these; then, with theremains of the meat and an equal quantity of foie gras, preparea pur£e.

Set each fillet of quail on a similarly-shaped slice of liver,causing it to adhere by means of the prepared pur£e, and coatwith brown chaud-froid sauce.

When the sauce has quite set, place these fillets in an evenborder-mould, clothed with very limpid aspic, and decoratedwith truffles. Fill up the mould with the same aspic jelly,and let the latter set.

When about to serve, turn out on a napkin, after the mannerof an aspic.

— CAILLES au CHATEAU-YQUEM

Prepare the quails like those “k la Richelieu” (No. 1895).After having added the julienne, sprinkle them with Chateau-Yquem; cover; reduce, and complete their cooking as directed.

When they are poached, transfer them to another saucepan;add ten slices of truffle per quail; strain their cooking-liquor,through muslin, over them, and poach them for a further twominutes.

This done, place the quails in a timbale; cover them with thecooking-liquor cleared of all grease; leave it to set, and serve ona block of ice.

GAME

601

—MANDARINES de CAILLES

Slice the tangerine rinds at their stem-ends with an evenround cutter; remove the sections; put them to dry, and skinthem raw.

Three-parts garnish the tangerine rinds with a quail Mousse,combined with foie gras, cut into dice; set a roasted quail’sfillet on the Mousse; coat with brown chaud-froid sauce, andcover with the sections of tangerine, glazed with aspic jelly.Keep in the cool for some time and dish on a napkin.

—CAILLES NILLSON

Proceed as for “Cailles au Chateau-Yquem,” and set eachquail in a small, silver cassolette. Cover with the cooking-liquor, cleared of grease and strained, and surround each quailwith four small very white cocks’ kidneys.

—CAILLES RICHELIEU FROIDES

Prepare these like the “Hot Cailles Richelieu”; placethem in a square, deep dish; cover with the cooking-liquor andthe garnish and let them cool until the cooking-liquor sets.Then clear the dish of all grease and serve on a block of ice.

—TIMBALE de CAILLES TZARINE

Line a round pie-dish with ordinary paste, and coat it insidewith slices of bacon. In the middle, place a fresh foie grasseasoned with salt, pepper and allspice, and surround it withquails, stuffed with quarters of truffles, set upright with theirbreasts against the bacon.

Fill up the timbale with whole raw and peeled truffles;cover with a round slice of bacon; close the timbale with a layerof paste sealed down round the edges; make a slit in the top,and bake in a hot oven for one and one-quarter hours.

When withdrawing the timbale from the oven, pour intoit some veal stock flavoured with Madeira, and let it be suffi-ciently gelatinous to set like a jelly.

Keep the timbale in the cool for one or two days beforeserving it.

—CAILLES à la VENDANGEUSE

Roast the quails; let them cool, and set them, each in alittle dosser of dry paste, resting against a cushion lying on around dish. On top of the cushion plant a leafy vine-shootbearing grapes. Surround the quails with white and blackgrapes (peeled and pipped) and cover with a slightly gelatinousaspic jelly, prepared with liqueur brandy.

602

GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

-MOUSSES de CAILLES

See the various remarks made concerning this subject, underPheasant, Partridge and Woodcock.

— LAND RAIL, ROI de CAILLESOU RALE de GENETS

The Land Rail, which must not be confused with the WaterRail, is most often served roasted, but all the quail recipes,hot or cold (except those in which Granite forms an accompani-ment) may be applied to it.

— HAZEL-HENS 1920-BLACK GAME

—PRAIRIE-HENS 1922—PTARMIGAN

—GROUSE *924—GANGAS

These birds, one or two of which, such as grouse and thehazel-hen, are of incomparable delicacy and high culinary value,are mostly served roasted.

Mousses, Mousselines and Salmis are also prepared fromthem, after the directions already given. But I must remindthe reader that when they serve in the preparation of a salmis,their skins and legs, which are bitter, must be discarded.

All these birds must be treated while still very fresh.

— GRIVES ET MERLES de CORSE(Thrushes and Corsican Blackbirds)

The greater part of the quail recipes, more particularly the“en casserole” and “sous la cendre” ones, may be appliedto these excellent birds.

The two following recipes are proper to them.

— GRIVES OU MERLES à la BONNE-FEMME

Cook the birds in butter, with one oz. of very small dice ofsalted breast of bacon to each bird. Put them into a hot cocottewith two-thirds oz. of butter per bird; heat; add some squarecroutons fried in butter; sprinkle with the saucepan-swillings,which should be a few drops of brandy; cover, and serve veryhot immediately.

— GRIVES OU MERLES à la LIEGEOISE

Cook the birds in butter on the stove, in an uncoveredearthenware saucepan. When they are nearly done, sprinklethem with two finely-chopped juniper berries per bird; addsome round croutons of bread-crumb fried in butter; cover, andserve very hot.

This procedure particularly suits thrushes, more especiallywhen these come from the Ardennes.

GAME 603

—GRIVES ET MERLES FROIDS

The various, cold preparations of quails, except those com-prising a Granite, may be applied to thrushes.

Alouettes ou Mauviettes (Larks)

These birds are generally served to the number of two orthree for each person.

—MAUVIETTES à la BONNE-FEMME

Proceed exactly as directed for the thrushes.

!930—MAUVIETTES à la M&RE MARIANNE

Slice some peeled and cored russet apples, and three-partscook them in butter. Spread this stew in thick layers on abuttered dish.

Simply stiffen the seasoned larks in nut-brown butter, andplace them upon the stewed apples, pressing them slightly intothe latter. Sprinkle with very fine bread-crumbs and meltedbutter, and set to glaze in the oven or at the Salamander, justlong enough to complete the cooking of the larks.

—ALOUETTES DU PERE PHILIPPE

Clean some fine, medium-sized potatoes, allowing one toeach lark; and cut a cover from each, which thin down until itis only one-sixth inch thick. With a root-spoon, hollow out thepotatoes in such wise as to allow of their each enclosing a lark.

Stiffen the larks in butter, and add thereto some salted breastof bacon, cut into small dice and blanched, and in the propor-tion of one-third oz. per lark. Place a lark in each potato,together with a few bacon dice and some of the cooking-fat;return cover of each potato to its place; fix it there by meansof cotton, and wrap each potato in oiled paper.

Lay them on the hearth, cover them with hot cinders, andcook for about forty minutes, taking care to renew the cindersfrom time to time.

—MAUVIETTES FROIDES

When cold, larks may be prepared in plain chaud-froidfashion, in cases, in Belle-vue, in Aspic, as Mousses, &c., inpursuance of the directions given under these various recipes.

—ORTOLANS

Serve ortolans as plainly as possible; but the best methodof preparing them is roasting. However, for the sake of variety,they may be prepared as follows: —

604 GUIDE TO MODERN COOKERY

— SYLPHIDES D’ORTOLANS

Butter some very small porcelain or silver cassolettes, andgarnish them half-full with mousseline forcemeat of ortolansprepared with truffle essence.

Set these cassolettes in the front of the oven, that the force-meat may poach. Cook in butter, for three minutes only, asmany ortolans as there are garnished cassolettes, and proceedso as to have them just ready when the forcemeat is poached.

Place an ortolan in each cassolette, and sprinkle them withnut-brown butter, combined with a little pale melted glaze andpineapple juice.

— BECS-FIGUES ET BEGUINETTES(Fig Peckers)

These birds are not met with in English markets; it istherefore useless to give the recipes concerning them. I willonly say that they may be prepared like the larks.

,936—CANARDS SAUVAGES (Wild Duck)

— SARCELLES (Teal)

— PI LETS (Pintails and Widgeons)

Birds of this class are mostly served roasted.

They may, however, be used in preparing excellent Salmis,which may be made after “Salmis de Faisan” (No. 1847) orafter “Salmis & la Rouennaise” (No. 1763).

They may also be prepared after all the recipes of “Canetonh la Rouennaise.”

— PLUVIERS DOR^S (Golden Plover)

— VANNEAUX (Lapwings)

— CHEVALIERS DIVERS (Various Sandpipers)

These various birds are generally served roasted.

They may also be served “en Salmis,” but in that case theskin must be discarded in the preparation of the cullis.

They only appear on very ordinary menus, and could not beserved at an important dinner.